<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.97402625" page_id="56264843"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
A C 1S7
b XVicultural
MAGAZINE
2001
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990772" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264844" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991526142857143" page_id="56264844"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in freedom and captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2001 as for 2000: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.551217" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264844" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.72716" page_id="56264844"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Subscription, changes of address, orders for back numbers etc. should be
sent to:
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, c /o BRISTOL ZOOLOGICAL GARDENS, CLIFTON,
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.900506333333333" page_id="56264844"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
BRISTOL BS8 3HA, ENGLAND.
Enquiries regarding membership should be sent to:
THE MEMBERSHIP SECRETARY, Stewart Pyper, 21, Primrose Hill,
Nunney, Frome, Somerset BA11 4NP.
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.996264666666667" page_id="56264844"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998437" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264844" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.9972025">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8195235" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264845" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.379555" page_id="56264845"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 107 - No. 1 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2001
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.994735" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264845" page_num="" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE BLUE-BELLIED ROLLER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996218935483871" page_id="56264845"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by R. C. J. Sawyer
The Blue-bellied Roller Coracias cyanogaster is found in Africa from
Senegal and The Gambia in the west to Sudan in the east. Including its
forked tail, this roller is about 35cm (15in) in length. It is a very beautiful
species which has the head, upper mantle and chest different shades of cream.
The wings, rump and breast to the under tail-coverts are deep blue, with the
under wing-coverts and the tail pale blue. The bill is greenish black and the
legs and feet are olive green. The sexes look alike. There is a small but
accurate illustration of this species in Mackworth-Praed and Grant's Birds
of West Central and Western Africa, Vol. 1 (Longmans, 1973), and a large
picture of it in J. M. Forshaw and W. T. Cooper's Kingfishers and Related
Birds, Part 2, Vol. 2 (Lansdowne Editions).
This roller was mentioned in the Avicultural Magazine in 1920, 1925
and 1927, when there was a colour frontispiece of it from the painting by
Roland Green to illustrate the article by David Seth-Smith. Unfortunately,
I do not have these issues, so have been unable to refer to them. My great
friend, our late President, Jean Delacour, writing in Aviculture, Vol. II, 1931,
referred to a Blue-bellied Roller received by London Zoo which was the
one mentioned in our magazine. I cannot recall having seen this species
prior to being fortunate enough to secure a living example in 1993. This
bird lived at first in the range of six flights for tropical birds and later was
put out in the original main flight next to the Toco Toucans Ramphastos
toco. In this flight it caught insects on the wing and was a great attraction
with visitors, who admired its delightful combination of colours. When it
died suddenly, I wondered if I would ever have another!
To my great delight, in 1996 I acquired two from Colin Surtees, the
dealer on Tyneside. These were placed in the Cock of the Rock aviary, in
which they have lived alongside birds such as African Pygmy Geese Nettapus
auritus, Black-necked Stilts Himantopus mexicanus. Splendid Lamprotornis
splendidus, Emerald L. iris and Amethyst Starlings Cinnyricinclus
leucogaster, various sunbirds, Fischer's Touracos Tauracofischeri and Red-
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.904803" page_id="56264846"  page_num="2" year="" vol="">
2
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.867448" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264846" page_num="2" year="" vol="">
SAWYER - BLUE-BELLIED ROLLER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996222642857143" page_id="56264846"  page_num="2" year="" vol="">
billed Oxpeckers Buphagus erythrorhynchus. The rollers were not surgically
sexed, but I believed them to be a true pair, on account of one being slightly
larger, with more blue on the belly. This has proved to be the male. They
are fed an insectivorous mixture to which is added minced (ground) beef
and minced ox heart plus livefood in the form of mealworms and wax worms.
I am sure they would also take pinkies if they were offered them. They
seldom bathe but during light showers of rain enjoy sitting with their wings
outstretched. They mix well and do not trouble smaller birds.
It was in July that they nested in the right-hand shelter at the rear of the
aviary. They nested in a sloping nest-box of the type provided in most of
the aviaries for larger birds. No nesting material was added to the bark
chippings in the bottom of the box. I believe that four white eggs were laid
and incubated for approximately 18 days. Three hatched and the young
fledged at 18 days. Whilst breeding the rollers consumed vast quantities of
mealworms, waxworms and minced beef. The pair became very aggressive
towards the keepers and dive-bombed them and made it too difficult for
them to look inside the nest-box. I was very pleased that they did not attack
any of the other birds in the aviary.
The proud parents would perch with their three youngsters, which were
paler versions of themselves without forked tails. They soon acquired adult
plumage and within six months could be distinguished from their parents
only because their tails were still not fully grown. They wintered well,
which is always helped if the birds roost inside at night as all five did,
remaining together as a group.
In March 1999 they nested again and reared just a single chick. The
1998 birds were perhaps nervous when their parents nested. However, I
decided not to separate them as some of the Coraciiformes, e.g. bee-eaters,
live together in family groups, and this proved to be the case with the Blue-
bellied Rollers. No aggression was shown by the parents but the group was
split up when the pair nested again.
In April 1997 several Blue-bellied Rollers were imported and after
studying them carefully I selected what I believed to be a true pair. This
second pair was put in the waterfall aviary. Amongst their neighbours were
Avocets Recurvirostris avosetta, sunbirds, ja#anas, Barbary Shrikes or
Yellow-crowned Gonoleks Laniarius barbarus, Golden-breasted or Royal
Starlings Cosmopsarus regius, White-throated Bee-eaters Merops albicollis
and a Giant Hummingbird Patagona gigas. Again I was fortunate to have
selected a true pair. The pair nested and hatched young only to lose them
the first time. However, in 1999 this pair raised two young. I suspect that in
the wild this species uses a cavity in a tree or a burrow perhaps in which to
nest. As with the first pair, this pair was offered a varied diet but proved to
be principally meat eaters. I also saw this pair catch insects on the wing.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.533229" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264847" page_num="3" year="" vol="">
SAWYER - BLUE-BELLIED ROLLER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.939723" page_id="56264847"  page_num="3" year="" vol="">
3
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99969864" page_id="56264847"  page_num="3" year="" vol="">
This species has a sharp call which can be likened to an 'ah', sometimes
uttered several times, otherwise this roller cannot be said to be very vocal.
This pair is also sensible enough to roost inside at night, unlike some of the
other occupants which now include a group of Pink-necked Fruit Doves
Ptilinopus porphyrea which exhibit all the stupidity of doves by remaining
outside at night and getting wet when it rains and causing me considerable
heartache and worry over their well being.
In 2000 only one pair nested and raised a single youngster. This pair
consists of a 1999-bred male and the female of the second pair, the male of
that pair having died during the winter. It shows that this species is capable
of breeding in its first season. This year I hope to establish the precise
lengths of the incubation and fledging periods and perhaps measure the eggs.
This species seems to adapt well to aviary life. I have heard that other
collections have had it go to nest but the birds have not succeeded in raising
young. The Racquet-tailed Roller C. spatulata has also been kept here and
the Lilac-breasted C. caudata has been bred successfully here at Cobham.
My friend and fellow member Roger Cattermole bred the Racquet-tailed
Roller and was awarded the society's medal for the first breeding in Britain
and Ireland. The breeding of the Blue-bellied Roller here at Cobham seems
to be the first breeding of this species in the UK, and if this proves to be true
it will be the 17th first breeding at Cobham.
As described above, the Blue-bellied Roller Coracias cyanogaster, has
been bred by R. C. J. Sawyer. This is probably the first successful breeding
of this species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who knows of a previous
breeding is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.914717" page_id="56264848"  page_num="4" year="" vol="">
4
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993754" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264848" page_num="4" year="" vol="">
AN EXAMINATION OF POTENTIAL REASONS FOR
VARIATION IN EGG-LAYING CYCLES OF WATTLED
CRANES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.564979" page_id="56264848"  page_num="4" year="" vol="">
by Nicole R. Bohlman
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.951293" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264848" page_num="4" year="" vol="">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989800428571428" page_id="56264848"  page_num="4" year="" vol="">
This study was conducted to examine possible reasons for the variations
in laying cycles of captive Wattled Cranes Bugeranus carunculatus . Egg-
laying records were collected from the International Crane Foundation, North
Carolina Zoological Park, Baltimore Zoo, Miami Metrozoo, Oklahoma City
Zoological Park, White Oak Conservation Center and St Catherines Wildlife
Survival Center. Correlation tests were run with the egg-laying data and a
significant relationship was found between the location of the breeding
facility with both the start and end dates of the breeding season. Strong
patterns were seen when correlation tests were run against the 'number of
eggs laid per season'. 'Season length' and 'number of eggs laid per season'
were also strongly correlated. Finally 'number of eggs laid' positively
correlated with 'latitude' and with inland sites, and negatively with coastal
localities. The results indicate that captive breeding centers in the USA that
are located further east have later starting dates (and later end dates) for
egg-laying cycles and coastal locations as compared to inland locations also
have later starting dates.
Introduction
The Wattled Crane is the largest and rarest of the six crane species that
occur in Africa. The total population remained at an estimated 13,000-15,000
during the 1990s, but the trend is towards a general decline due to the loss
and degradation of wetland habitats and human disturbance (Burke in Meine
&amp; Archibald, 1996). Because of this, captive propagation has become more
widespread with about 218 Wattled Cranes in captivity in 1997 (Beall, 1998).
Wattled Cranes have extreme variation in laying cycles both in the wild
and in captivity (Urban &amp; Davenport, 1993; Balzano, 1988). It is important
for captive breeding facilities to understand this variation for several reasons.
They have been known to lay all months of the year in the wild in Malawi,
South Africa, Zambia and Zimbabwe. In captivity, their egg-laying season
occurs at opposite times of the year when compared with other crane species.
For instance, while most cranes' breeding seasons are in spring and summer,
Wattled Cranes start laying eggs in October, November and December. It is
much more difficult for institutions located in temperate zones to breed in
the winter, therefore, it would be beneficial to understand these laying cycles
and develop better breeding techniques (S. Swengel pers. comm.).
In captivity, this species is relatively difficult to breed and fertility rates
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.641737" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264849" page_num="5" year="" vol="">
BOHLMAN - WATTLED CRANES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.886594" page_id="56264849"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
5
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997318666666667" page_id="56264849"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
are low compared to other crane species (Burke in Meine &amp; Archibald, 1996).
They also have the smallest clutch size of the world's cranes (Johnsgard
1983). Many of the Wattled Cranes in zoos and other institutions are older
birds that have difficulty copulating because of their pinioned wings. For
these reasons, artificial insemination (AI) is required. In order for AI to be
worthwhile or successful there must also be some predictability in egg-laying
patterns. Finding factors that stimulate captive breeding may help to
understand both wild and captive Wattled Crane breeding (S. Swengel pers.
comm.).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.726815">
Methods
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.976177064516129" page_id="56264849"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
Records for this analysis were received from the International Crane
Foundation, North Carolina Zoological Park, Baltimore Zoo, Miami
Metrozoo, Oklahoma City Zoological Park, White Oak Conservation Center
and St Catherines Wildlife Survival Center. Included in these records was
the date of the first egg laid per female for every year she laid eggs, the last
egg that was laid of the season, the season length and the number of eggs
laid per season. These were the dependent variables run in correlation tests.
Independent variables in the correlation tests included latitude and
longitude of each facility that participated in the study, total annual
precipitation and season length for each crane's breeding season. Finally,
each institution that participated in the study was assigned a (inland vs coastal)
code of one if it was a coastal area and two if it was an inland area. North
Carolina Zoological Park was counted as inland because it is far enough
from the coast to mitigate most of the effects of a maritime climate. The
latitude and longitude were retrieved from the Rand McNally Road Atlas,
and the precipitation data was retrieved from the website for the Southern
Regional Climate Center.
Data were collected for 21 female Wattled Cranes during the years from
1977-1999. There was a sample size of 96 when correlation tests involved
the 'number of eggs laid per season'. With all other correlations the sample
size was 112 (for 16 females x egg seasons, data on total eggs laid was not
received). Statistical analyses including linear single regression and linear
multiple regression were performed on dependent variables vs independent
variables.
Averages from each breeding facility were taken for every variable and
correlation tests were run. Included in these tests were the average monthly
precipitation and temperature (taken for the 30 year period 1961-1990 from
the 1998 World Almanac and Book of Facts) that corresponded with the
average start date of egg-laying at each facility. Systat version 7.0 was used
for all statistical analyses. Only tests with P&lt;.05 were considered statistically
significant and tests with P&lt;. 1 were considered nearly significant.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.971371" page_id="56264850"  page_num="6" year="" vol="">
6
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.701484" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264850" page_num="6" year="" vol="">
BOHLMAN - WATTLED CRANES
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.848188">
Results
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994144463414634" page_id="56264850"  page_num="6" year="" vol="">
Averages of each variable from the individual locations that data was
collected from were calculated, and correlation tests were conducted. All
the P-values were &gt;.l, so none of them were statistically significant.
There were repeated patterns that showed a negative correlation between
longitude and both the start and end dates. When 'season length' was tested
with the independent variables there were no correlations that showed a
P&lt;. 1. When 'number of eggs laid per season' was tested with the independent
variables there were very strong, significant patterns. These patterns showed
correlations between 'number of eggs laid per season' with 'season length',
'latitude', 'longitude' and 'inland vs. coastal' (Table 1).
There were two variables that had significant effects (Pc.05) on the first
egg laying dates. 'Longitude' was the most important variable and had a
negative correlation with a P-value of .014 in the single regression. In the
multiple regression (which included the variables 'latitude', 'longitude' and
'annual total precipitation') 'longitude' also had a negative correlation and
a P-value of .023. In this same regression there was an overall P-value of
.103, making it nearly significant. The second important variable that
correlated with start date was 'inland vs. coastal'. This also had a negative
correlation in the single as well as multiple regressions. There was a P-
value of .022 in the single regression and in the multiple regression there
was a P-value of .038 (Table 1).
'Longitude' repeatedly had a negative correlation when tested with the
end date. In the single regression there was a P-value of .025. In the first
multiple regression, the end date was tested with 'latitude', 'longitude', 'total
annual precipitation' and 'inland vs. coastal'. 'Longitude' had a negative
correlation and a P-value of .016 and 'inland vs. coastal' had a positive
correlation and a P-value of. 1 52. Since these numbers (longitude vs. inland/
coastal) oppose each other, two more multiple regressions were tested. One
of these included only 'latitude', 'longitude' and 'total annual precipitation',
and the other included only 'latitude', 'total annual precipitation' and 'inland
vs. coastal'. In the multiple regression including 'longitude', there was a
negative correlation and a P-value of .029 (Table 1).
There were repeated patterns in correlation tests involving the 'number
of eggs laid per season'. 'Season length' was the strongest variable having
a P-value of 0.00 and a positive correlation. This P-value was the same
throughout all of the regressions with 'number of eggs laid'. The overall P-
value that was given in the multiple regressions was .00 for every regression.
'Latitude' was a relatively strong variable when tested with the 'number of
eggs laid'. When tested in a single regression it had a positive correlation
and a P-value of .078, making it nearly significant. When tested in a multiple
regression with 'season length', 'longitude' and 'total annual precipitation',
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.61136" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264851" page_num="7" year="" vol="">
BOHLMAN - WATTLED CRANES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.985889" page_id="56264851"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
7
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999721166666667" page_id="56264851"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
'latitude" was given a P-value of .032. 'Longitude' was given a P-value of
0.00 when tested with 'season length', 'latitude', 'longitude', 'total annual
precipitation' and 'inland vs. coastal' . In this same regression, 'longitude'
had a positive correlation and 'inland vs. coastal' had a negative correlation
and both variables had a P-value of 0.00. Because these variables have
opposing effects, two more multiple regressions were conducted. These
additional regressions contained 'season length', 'latitude', 'total annual
precipitation' and either 'longitude' or 'inland vs. coastal' in each regression.
This resulted in both variables having a positive correlation, but only the
multiple regression with the 'inland vs coastal' variable was considered
statistically significant because it had a P-value of 0.00. When 'inland vs.
coastal' was tested in a single regression there was a P-value of .002 (Table 1).
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.828933">
Discussion
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.95449847826087" page_id="56264851"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
Start date
Results suggest that Wattled Crane breeding facilities located further
east should expect their cranes to lay their first eggs later than facilities
located in the west. Similarly, coastal centres that breed Wattled Cranes
should expect their cranes to start laying eggs later than those inland breeding
Wattled Cranes.
End date
There is a lot of evidence suggesting that facilities located farther east
will have Wattled Cranes with breeding seasons that not only begin later,
but will also end later than in breeding centres that are located in the west.
However, there is nothing that suggests a later ending date in centres located
on the coast rather than inland.
Number of eggs laid per season
This study indicates that more eggs will be laid if there is a longer breeding
season. It also indicates that breeding facilities that are located in the north
will yield more eggs per season than facilities in the south. There is strong
evidence that also suggests that breeding facilities located inland as opposed
to coastal will have Wattled Cranes that lay more eggs. The very same
regression suggested that the farther east a breeding facility is located, the
more likely the Wattled Cranes will lay more eggs. Because these statements
are somewhat contradictory, more regressions were conducted. These
regressions resulted in the former of the two statements being found to be
true and significant.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.726808">
Table 1. Results of regressions testing a correlation between egg-laying data of female Wattled Cranes in North American zoos
and external and environmental factors with significant values in bold type.
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.381458" page_id="56264852"  page_num="8" year="" vol="">
BOHLMAN - WATTLED CRANES
Averages from each facility were calculated for every variable. Included in these tests were the average monthly precipitation and temperature that corresponded
with the average start date of egg-laying at each facility. All of these tests had a p-value &gt;.l and are not significant.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.619125" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264853" page_num="9" year="" vol="">
BOHLMAN - WATTLED CRANES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.904945" page_id="56264853"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
9
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.491406" genericHeader="conclusions" page_id="56264853" page_num="9" year="" vol="">
Conclusion
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9987365" page_id="56264853"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
Since the results demonstrate that location of breeding facilities of captive
Wattled Cranes influence the beginning, ending and number of eggs laid
per breeding season, this is valuable data for breeders of captive Wattled
Cranes. While this is useful, this research could be expanded significantly.
It would be beneficial to analyse precipitation (preceding the first egg of the
season for Wattled Cranes) in a different way than was analysed in this
study, and to include temperature in this analysis. It would also be beneficial
to conduct an analysis similar to this on a larger scale that would include
data taken from every region of the USA and possibly from international
captive breeding facilities.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.889461" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56264853" page_num="9" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9195315" page_id="56264853"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
I would like to thank the facilities that participated in the study and
answered my requests for Wattled Crane egg-laying data, specifically: the
International Crane Foundation, St. Catherines Wildlife Survival Center,
White Oak Conservation Center, Oklahoma City Zoological Park, Miami
Metrozoo, Baltimore Zoo and the North Carolina Zoological Park. I am
also grateful to Scott Swengel for his assistance with many facets of this
project including statistical analysis and interpretation of the data, and Sara
Zimorski for her proofreading skills.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.962908" genericHeader="references" page_id="56264853" page_num="9" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.988907434782609">
Balzano, S. 1988. Climatic influences in crane production. Unpublished report from the 1988
North American Crane Workshop.
Beall, F. 31 December, 1998. Wattled crane studbook, Bugeranus carunculatus. American
Zoo Association, Bethesda, Maryland.
Burke, A. 1996. Wattled Crane. The Cranes: Status survey and conservation action plan.
Meine, C.D. and Archibald G.W. (eds). International Union for Conservation of Nature and
Natural Resources, Gland, Switzerland and Cambridge, U K.
Famighetti, R. (ed) 1998. The world almanac and book of facts. K-III Reference Corporation,
Mahwah, New Jersey.
Johnsgard, RA. 1983. Cranes of the world. Indiana University Press, Bloomington, Indiana.
Swengel, S. 2000. Personal communication.
Urban, E.K. &amp; Davenport, L.B. 1993. Time of nesting in wild and captive wattled cranes.
Wamble, R.B. 24 May, 1999. Monthly data lister request. Southern Regional Climate Center
(LSU), Baton Rouge, Louisiana. Retrieved from www:http://maestro.srcc.lsu.edu/ucan.net/
3220req.html
National Climatic Data Center. Aug. 15, 2000. Weather station lookup and data. National
Climatic Data Center, Asheville, North Carolina. Retrieved from wwwihttp://
www4.ncdc.noaa.gov/
Nicole R. Bohlman undertook the above research while an Avicultural
Intern at the International Crane Foundation, E-11376 Shady Lane Road,
PO. Box 447, Baraboo, WI 53913-0447, USA (E-mail: cranes@
savingcranes.org). Her present address is:- 234 NW 21st., Apt. 3, Corvallis,
OR 97330, USA.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.99037" page_id="56264854"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
10
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99715" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264854" page_num="10" year="" vol="">
NOTES ON BEHAVIOUR AND ECOLOGICAL
REQUIREMENTS OF THE ROTHSCHILD'S MYNAH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.977557083333333" page_id="56264854"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
Leucopsar rothschildi
Dedicated to Prof. Dr Jurgen Nicolai on the occasion of his 75th
birthday
by Walter A. Sontag Jr.
A wealth of literature has been published on this magnificent bird,
especially on maintenance and breeding in captivity by aviculturists and
zoo staff (e.g. Taynton &amp; Jeggo, 1988; West &amp; Pugh, 1986). Most aspects
of its biology, however, in particular its ecology and behaviour in the field,
have been dealt with rather poorly (cf. Feare &amp; Craig, 1998). While the
Rothschild's Mynah is almost extinct in its natural habitat, which has
drastically shrunk, there is presently a well-established captive population
including five breeding projects worldwide (those in North America and
Great Britain started in 1984, in Europe and Japan in 1992, and in Indonesia
in 1993) with currently c. 1,200 individuals (cf. Pagel, 1999). Despite
remarkable efforts to reintroduce captive-raised individuals into the last free-
living population in the Bali Barat National Park (Pagel, 1999), the re-
stocking programme, has generally speaking, failed up to now. In 1999 the
situation worsened, when the breeding and pre-release centre in the Bali
Barat National Park was attacked twice and four and then 39 (out of 81)
individuals were stolen ( Gefiederte Welt 124:111 (2000)).
Surprisingly, the Rothschild's Mynah, which inhabits dry woodland
(Pagel, 1999), is most closely related to a group of typical open habitat
starlings comprising some 25 species grouped around the genera Sturnus
and Acridotheres, and including Leucopsar (Sontag, 1992). Probably almost
all of them perform open-bill probing (see Beecher, 1978 and others), and
most of them are found in Asia. Feare &amp; Craig (1998) characterize Leucopsar
habitat as open woodland with a grass understorey, but detailed studies on
space and habitat requirements are largely lacking. Since this species faces
extinction in the wild and bearing in mind the purpose of future re-stocking
or reintroduction, those working with this species are strongly recommended
to offer captive conditions that contain environmental structures and
properties characteristic or even necessary for Leucopsar. Therefore, I will
first report on research dealing with space and habitat aspects in a spacious
aviary. The focus is on the (relative) importance of various habitat levels,
i.e. ground and higher strata, in an artificial environment that is as natural as
possible. Almost nothing is known about potential adaptations of Leucopsar
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.387367" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264855" page_num="11" year="" vol="">
SONTAG - ROTHSCHILD'S MYNAH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999285" page_id="56264855"  page_num="11" year="" vol="">
11
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.945068375" page_id="56264855"  page_num="11" year="" vol="">
to its natural habitat, e.g. the grade of dependence on living in the woodland,
particularly native forest types. Although the present aviary habitat clearly
did not represent the full space (strata) spectrum of the natural habitat, the
available strata can be considered sufficient for preferential tests: the subjects
were able to choose between a number of alternatives at different heights
(viz. horizontal aviary areas). I also present notes on particularities in
breeding behaviour and deal with intraspecific aggression, a big problem in
captive Rothschild's Mynahs.
In order to assess specific habitat requirements, another species belonging
to the same group of stumids was chosen for comparison and kept together
with Rothschild's Mynahs, i.e. exposed to the same environment.
Species for comparison
The Black-collared Starling Gracupica nigricollis was the species chosen
for comparison. Its distribution ranges from west and central Thailand across
Burma and Laos, to southern China (Feare &amp; Craig, 1998); this is
geographically and climatically relatively similar to that of Leucopsar. Its
size is comparable with Leucopsar (28cm vs 25crn( 11 in vs 9 3 /4n)). I recorded
the Black-collared Starling on open farmland, in wet rice-fields (see p.17),
along the roads, in rural or open settlements, but also in farm plantations
and trees in a grove in Thailand. I saw this species in association with other
stumids including the Asian Pied Starling Sturnus contra , a species that was
reported to roost together with Black-winged Starlings A. melanopterus and
Rothschild's Mynahs in Bali (Ash, 1984). Accordingly, both species under
investigation would easily mix with other starlings under natural conditions
and housing them together in an aviary appeared appropriate. Aviary size
and the small number of individuals kept together provided good conditions
for a low level of aggressive interactions. During the course of the study,
severe aggression was not observed between species, although Leucopsar
is known for showing very strong intraspecific aggression (see below).
Housing
The starlings studied were kept in a partly roofed, spacious, richly
structured aviary (see p.12) situated in a wooded area at the Institute for
Comparative Ethology of the Austrian Academy of Sciences in Vienna. The
enclosure was provided with living vegetation and a lot of branchwork.
There were ledges along the wire mesh a short distance above the ground.
The aviary was subdivided into a larger (5.25m x 4.2m x 2.06m-2.51m
(approx. 17ft Sin x 13ft 9in x 6ft 9in-8ft Sin)) and smaller section (5.25m x
2.1m-2.9m x 2.06m-2.51m (approx. 17ft Sin x 6ft llin - 9ft 6in x 6ft 9in -
8ft Sin)) by wire mesh interrupted by an open door, a central fly-through
opening and two small openings (each 25cm (approx. lOin) wide) at floor
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.982037" page_id="56264856"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
12
</page>
<equation confidence="0.4507155" page_id="56264856"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
SONTAG - ROTHSCHILD&apos;S MYNAH
DG1 = small opening 1, DG2 = small opening 2
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.97557275" page_id="56264856"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
level. The two small openings were some distance from the feeding sites in
order to ensure that their use was not skewed by the food presented. Food
was offered on the floor and on a shelf in the roofed part of the aviary. The
structural variety provided and abundance of environmental conditions in
the aviary were intended to reduce aggression.
In this aviary, once a Black-collared Starling nest was built in a
branchwork site, and the Rothschild's Mynahs used the nest-box provided,
hatching and rearing two offspring from a clutch of three eggs.
Individuals and groups
Three mixed species groups were studied in the following uninterrupted
chronological order in 1987: Group 1 consisted of an adult pair of
Rothschild's Mynahs and an adult pair of Black-collared Starlings (four
individuals in total, excluding the Rothschild's Mynah hatchlings); Group 2
consisted of the same individuals supplemented by the two fledgling offspring
of the Rothschild's Mynahs (six individuals in total); Group 3 consisted of
the same Black-collared Starlings and the two young (subadult) Rothschild's
Mynah offspring (four individuals in total).
The left foot of the old female Rothschild's Mynah was crippled.
Surprisingly, this did not appear to affect breeding behaviour and even general
utilization of the aviary by this individual. The clutch size of three eggs was
in line with the data given and discussed in West &amp; Pugh (1986). However,
one egg did not produce a nestling. The two chicks that hatched differed
markedly in size (shortly after hatching). This also fits in well with the broad-
based findings from the Jersey Wildlife Preservation Trust presented by West
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.424738" page_id="56264856"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
&amp; Pugh ( loc . cit. on average only one young fledged). The same pair of
Rothschild's Mynahs also reared two offspring from a brood the year before.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.387332" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264857" page_num="13" year="" vol="">
SONTAG - ROTHSCHILD'S MYNAH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99937" page_id="56264857"  page_num="13" year="" vol="">
13
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.994630720930232" page_id="56264857"  page_num="13" year="" vol="">
Total ground utilization and complementary aspects
In total, both species spent more time above the ground than on it.
However, the Black-collared Starlings generally spent more time on the
ground than both the adult and juvenile Rothschild's Mynahs. For instance,
in Group 1 the Black-collared Starlings spent more than 40% of an
observation-session on the ground in five of 20 sessions while the old
Rothschild's Mynahs did so only once. However, remarkable variation in
the interspecific ground use difference was found between the three groups,
depending on the circumstances (cf. Sontag, 2001). Thus, for example, the
adult Rothschild's Mynahs did not spend significantly less time on the aviary
floor than the Black-collared Starlings in Group 1 (including the stage when
the Rothschild's Mynahs fed their nestlings). The old Rothschild's Mynahs
clearly visited the floor and the feeding sites on it to a greater extent when
rearing their offspring (19.6% in Group 1 vs. 15.9% in Group 2), while the
Black-collared Starlings spent an average of 28.6% of their time-budget on
the ground in all groups. Shortly after fledging, the total time spent by the
juvenile Rothschild's Mynahs on the ground was between the values of their
parents and the interspecific cohabitants, and was not statistically different
from either of them (U test). This suggests an increased level of exploratory
behaviour by the young Rothschild's Mynahs at this stage.
Moving through the small openings on the aviary floor may better reflect
the attractiveness of the bottom part than mere time-budgets on ground use.
In fact, a large and stable interspecific difference was established: in all
groups both the adult and juvenile Rothschild's Mynahs made use of these
passages much less frequently than the Black-collared Starlings (Sontag in
prep.), e.g. two (ad. Rothschild's Mynahs) vs. eight (juv. Rothschild's
Mynahs) vs. 99 (Black-collared) in Group 2.
Both species were observed to walk on the ground. However, the Black-
collared Starling's locomotion tended to be slow and deliberate, somehow
resembling that of a chicken. This appears concordant with the above
findings, although the frequency of ground-passage use by the Black-collared
Starlings showed much variation (e.g. 0-28 times per observation-session
in Group 1). This species often rested on the ground or stayed at locations
c. 50cm - 70cm (approx. 19 3 /4in - 27V2in) or c. 90cm (approx. 35V2in) above
the floor for longer. Moreover, their stays on the ledges near the aviary
floor lasted longer than those of the Rothschild's Mynahs (e.g. maximum
duration 98 seconds in Black-collared vs. 20 seconds in ad. Rothschild's
Mynahs, and 305 seconds in Black-collared vs. 11 seconds in juv.
Rothschild's Mynahs; cf. Sontag, 1991). On the other hand, the Rothschild's
Mynahs used the upper space of the aviary relatively intensely. The adult
male was often observed clinging upside down on the wire of the aviary
roof (which was not seen in the slightly handicapped female). This behaviour
was never recorded in the Black-collared Starlings.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998494" page_id="56264858"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
14
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.6049215">
SONTAG - ROTHSCHILD'S MYNAH
Table 1. Ground stay duration medians (seconds) of different chronological
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.911926666666667" page_id="56264858"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
stages in mixed Rothschild's Mynah/Black-collared Starling groups (see
text for details). Stage 1...3: breeding season of Rothschild's Mynahs up to
the late nestling period (i.e. Stage 3).
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.952667677419355" page_id="56264858"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
Group
I
II
III
Stage
1
2
3
4
5
6
Adult R. M.
58
56.6
43.1
72.5
83.4
-
Juvenile R. M.
-
-
-
70.5
93
65.5
Black-collared S.
258.1
458
125.5
173.5
519.7
</figure>
<page confidence="0.93392" page_id="56264858"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
390.5
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.995823193548387" page_id="56264858"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
Frequency of ground visits and cumulative ground use
As shown above, the total time spent on the ground is not the only relevant
measure for ground use. Passing through the small openings may better
account for the attractiveness of this habitat segment; this approach may be
even more powerful when put into relation to the time spent on the ground.
Another aspect, the portioning of the ground stays, may shed light on the
role of this habitat component for Leucopsar. For instance, Leucopsar may
on occasion take food items from the bottom level or forage in low stratum
parts in its natural 'woodland habitat'. Though limited in duration, ground
visits may be important for this species, and, if so, should be taken into
account for captive individuals.
In fact, the average individual stays of the Rothschild's Mynahs were
short compared to those of the Black-collared Starlings. This was true for
both the adult and juvenile Rothschild's Mynahs in all three groups studied
(cf. Sontag, 1992). Moreover, the duration of the individual ground stays of
the Rothschild's Mynahs differed only slightly between the observation-
stages and groups as well as between the adults and juveniles (Table 1). As
the time-totals on the ground varied widely for this species, a distinct
correlation should exist between visiting frequency and overall time spent
on the ground. This assumption is correct: a clear correlation is documented
in all groups (p. 15 graphs A, B, C, D: each point represents the respective
pairs of individuals, i.e., adult, young Rothdchild's Mynahs, surveyed per
observation-session). Conversely, the correlation between ground visit
frequency and cumulative time spent on the ground was much weaker in the
Black-collared Starlings: based on the limited data, in Groups 2 and 3 a
definite connection was even lacking in this sturnid (Group 1: R 2 = 0.249, p
= 0.0295, 19 'sessions'; Group 2: R 2 = 0.317, p = 0.057, 12 'sessions';
Group 3: R 2 = 0.256, p = 0.093, 12 'sessions'). Hence, its individual ground
stays varied considerably in duration.
The present findings allow the following conclusions to be drawn:
Rothschild's Mynahs (1) do use the floor habitat regularly, but (2) obviously
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.995921827586207" page_id="56264859"  page_num="15" year="" vol="">
SONTAG - ROTHSCHILD'S MYNAH
15
(%) sieioi -auiji Aeis punoj6
c 5
2
O
&lt;n
s
TJ # .S
3 ^
g .s
Sm -w
OX) ^
a 9
S a
O 0)
" &gt;&gt;
J s
** C/3
4&gt;
.\0x25BA 2
&lt;U
ox) cu
S T3
3 (c)
(R) S&apos; _
o 11
SS &lt;"
\0x25A0gj*
"f S
&lt;u F &quot;-C
-- S 3
_ST s #
" &quot;a "i "
\0x25A0 2 a c"
3 &quot;(c) *(c)
-os(c)
(c) (c)
C/3
^ .h
w eo
S3 a,
W cy
. \0x25BA
C/3 tS
(c)X) y
*J a
03 &lt;u
T3 -C
-- y
3 C/3
If
3 #
&amp; c
(c) 8
I B
J a
M
</figure>
<page confidence="0.996506" page_id="56264860"  page_num="16" year="" vol="">
16
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.776878" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264860" page_num="16" year="" vol="">
SONTAG - ROTHSCHILD'S MYNAH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990747878048781" page_id="56264860"  page_num="16" year="" vol="">
this is substantially dependent on the situation (e.g. care of nestlings); (3)
their individual ground visits are short but relatively frequent, for instance,
both the adult Rothschild's Mynahs and the Black-collared Starlings spent
nearly the same amount of time on the ground in 'session 10' of Group 1
(69.4% vs. 67.6%), but the individual ground visits of the former
outnumbered those of the Black-collared Starlings by far (31 vs. 5). The
above conclusions would fit with the insectivorous diet of Leucopsar, which
is known to feed on insects such as ants, termites, dragonflies, crickets and
grasshoppers (de Iongh, 1983).
Based on the total time and temporal organization of ground use,
Leucopsar should be regarded as a species that at least moderately uses the
ground section of its environment. Therefore aviculturists should offer this
species various, well-designed structural strata, including sufficient floor
space.
Some notes on breeding behaviour and aggression
What strategies does this largely white species employ to survive in more
or less open woodland? How do inexperienced young individuals behave
after leaving the nest cavity? My observations on the brood of the adult
Rothschild's Mynahs in Group 1 yielded crucial clues to potential specific
anti-predator adaptations. As such behaviour by Leucopsar appears
unreported in the literature, it may represent a special aberrant breeding-
case. However, the 'natural-like' way of keeping the birds, the uneventful
course of rearing the offspring, and the array and orderly impression of the
observations suggest normal behaviour and point to potentially widespread
anti-predator techniques. Judging from the limited observations, and in
agreement with Marshall (1981) and Schmidt et al. (1976), the female spent
more time than the male with the juveniles in the nest-box (Sontag in prep.).
The breeding took place in summer. The second chick hatched only two
or three days after the first one. On the 26th day after the hatching of the
first chick (i.e. the 27th day including the hatching date), one of the chicks
was observed outside the nest-box for the first time; one day later both of
them were seen outside the nest. Hughes &amp; Turner (1975) gave 23.4 days
as the mean nestling period based on six clutches of one pair and one clutch
of another pair (variation 21 -26 days). Even this mean value can be regarded
as a rather long nestling period compared to other sturnids of the
aforementioned complex (i.e. Sturnus-Acridother-es sensu ) Sontag (see
Feare &amp; Craig, 1998) and might represent a strategy against predators.
Most surprisingly, after leaving the nest for the first time the juveniles
regularly returned to the nest-box, i.e. they moved between the nest-box
and the aviary 'habitat' up to the 31st day after the hatching of the first
nestling (32nd day including hatching date). To my knowledge, no such
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.384437" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264861" page_num="17" year="" vol="">
SONTAG - ROTHSCHILD'S MYNAH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.990853" page_id="56264861"  page_num="17" year="" vol="">
17
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.774953" page_id="56264861"  page_num="17" year="" vol="">
Photo Walter A. Sontag Jr
A Black-collared Starling with three Common Mynahs Acridotheres tristis (arrowed) in
the Bang Pra area (Sri Racha, S.E. Thailand) in December 1988
Note: on the complete negative two Black-collared Starlings, three Common Mynahs, one
White-vented Mynah Acridotheres javanicus sensu (Lekagul &amp; Round, 1991) and an
indetermined mynah Acridotheres sp. can be distinguished.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.835203">
Photo Walter A. Sontag Jr
Four Black-collared Starlings in a wet rice-field habitat (Bang Pra area,
S.E. Thailand) in December 1988
</reference>
<page confidence="0.997664" page_id="56264862"  page_num="18" year="" vol="">
18
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.783522" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264862" page_num="18" year="" vol="">
SONTAG - ROTHSCHILD'S MYNAH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999189093023256" page_id="56264862"  page_num="18" year="" vol="">
behaviour has been mentioned in the Leucopsar literature. On the 32nd day
after the hatching of the first chick (the 33rd day including the hatching
date), nest return by the offspring was recorded only in the evening. As
Rothschild's Mynahs are conspicuous because of their largely white plumage
and juveniles additionally are less experienced, juvenile nest return may be
considered as a specific adaptation for predator avoidance. Moreover,
fledglings were fed in silence outside the nest-box and apparently begged
for food with open bill and raised wings in a silent manner, both of which
support the predator avoidance hypothesis.
Morphologically, a dark tinge on the white wing area of juvenile/subadult
Rothschild's Mynahs (pers. obs.) may also have a certain protective function
against visually orientated predators. In the tropics, white plumage may
withstand selective pressure in forest better than in other habitats, and the
above mentioned traits may support the plumage's adaptive function. H.
Winkler (pers. comm.) stresses that the occurrence of birds with white
plumage is more likely in the canopy than in the lower stratum. The findings
on ground use (i.e. restricted overall time and activity spent on the ground,
short - though frequent - ground stays) appear to be consistent with this
explanation.
Aggression is a big problem with captive Rothschild's Mynahs (e.g.
Pagel, 1990; Schmidt et al. 1976; pers. obs.), both between adult individuals
and against offspring. For example, the female of the pair living in a big,
richly planted aviary at Vienna Zoo was found drowned recently probably
as a result of aggression by the male (D. Schratter pers. comm.). My own
experiences strongly suggest (Sontag, 1996) that the removal of the nest-
box diminishes and/or puts off aggressive actions of adult individuals. In
order to be on the safe side, this measure was chosen with Group 2, when it
was certain that the young Rothschild's Mynahs were no longer returning to
the nest-box. It may provide a certain time-gain in protecting the progeny
from fatal injuries. Moreover, as long as social contact is maintained, the
possibility of learning from adult conspecifics (supposedly of great
importance for this stumid with respect to song-learning and social behaviour)
remains. Nonetheless, the adult pair was finally removed from Group 2
because the aggressive potential could not be judged reliably.
A means to lower or control Rothschild's Mynah aggression in the aviary
is apparently the combination of (a) sufficient overall space; (b) subdivision
of the enclosure into compartments with a number of connecting (closable)
openings; (c) the availability of numerous different structural elements at
various heights; and (d) the provision of vegetation which provides sight-
protection and cover. Moreover, (e) various feeding sites have to be provided
well apart from each other and away from the shallow basin for bathing in.
After negative experiences with Rothschild's Mynahs in traditional cages
and aviaries at the Institute for Comparative Ethology (J. Sieber pers. comm.),
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.387284" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264863" page_num="19" year="" vol="">
SONTAG - ROTHSCHILD'S MYNAH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998975" page_id="56264863"  page_num="19" year="" vol="">
19
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.992620655172414" page_id="56264863"  page_num="19" year="" vol="">
the aviary used in the above study was installed to incorporate the housing
conditions outlined above, and in fact no fatal aggression occurred.
Summary
Some aspects of space use by Rothschild's Mynahs were studied. For
this purpose Rothschild's Mynahs were compared with another south Asian
stumid, the related Black-collared Starling, with the birds being kept together
in different groups under captive conditions. The spacious aviary consisted
of two sections connected by various openings. Despite much variation in
the overall ground stay time (between observation sessions) the Rothschild's
Mynahs generally spend less time on the ground than the other species with
which they were compared. Much more strikingly, however, the small
openings on the ground (connecting the aviary sections) were passed through
far fewer times by the Rothschild's Mynahs, indicating that this species
uses the floor less than other starling species. Also, the individual ground
stays of both adult and juvenile Rothschild's Mynahs were clearly shorter
than those of the Black-collared Starlings. Contrasting with the latter, in all
observation groups the ground visit frequency and overall time spent on the
ground were clearly correlated positively in (both adult and juvenile)
Rothschild's Mynahs: i.e. the more visits, the more total time on the ground.
This experimental study clearly supports the assumption that Rothschild's
Mynahs are, to a high degree, adapted to living in woodlands or forests.
Nevertheless, the findings show that Rothschild's Mynahs use the floor
habitat regularly, although this is strongly influenced by the situation (Sontag,
2001). Their individual ground stays are short but frequent.
Some remarkable observations on breeding behaviour are also presented.
Surprisingly, after leaving the nest for the first time the juvenile Rothschild's
Mynahs of Group 2 regularly returned to the nest-box. Silent feeding outside
the nest-box is reported. In addition, strategies to avoid aggressive behaviour
under captive conditions are discussed.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.869214" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56264863" page_num="19" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998609875" page_id="56264863"  page_num="19" year="" vol="">
I am grateful to Dr H. Hoi (Konrad Lorenz Institute for Comparative
Ethology, Vienna) for critically reading the manuscript. I also thank Dr M.
Stachowitsch (Institute of Ecology and Conservation Biology, University
of Vienna) for numerous useful suggestions on the manuscript and improving
its English. I am deeply indebted to A. Seidel for help in statistical and
software matters. Thanks are also due to Prof. Dr W. M. Schleidt for drawing
the sketch of the aviary. Finally, I would like to thank the Hon. Editor for
his patience.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.971079" genericHeader="references" page_id="56264863" page_num="19" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.621246">
Ash, J. S. 1984. Bird observations on Bali. Bull. Br. Orn. Club 104: 24-35.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.995321" page_id="56264864"  page_num="20" year="" vol="">
20
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.978516885714286" page_id="56264864"  page_num="20" year="" vol="">
Beecher, W. J. 1978. Feeding adaptations and evolution in the starlings. Bull. Chicago Acad.
Sci. 11: 269-298.
de Iongh, H. 1983. Is there still hope for the Bali Mynah? Tigerpaper 10: 28-32. (cited in
Pagel, 1999.)
Feare, C. &amp; Craig, A. 1998. Starlings and mynas. Christopher Helm Ltd, A &amp; C Black Ltd,
London.
Hughes, A. &amp; Turner, C. G. 1975. Breeding and behaviour of Rothschild's Mynah Leucopsar
rothschildi at the National Zoological Park, Washington. Int. Zoo Yearb. 15: 116-120.
Marshall, A. P. 1981. Courtship and reproduction in the Bali Mynah Leucopsar rothschildi
(Aves: Stumidae). M.Sc. Thesis presented to the University of Pacific, (cited in West &amp; Pugh,
1986.)
Pagel, T. 1990. Balistar - fast ausgestorben?! Gefiederte Welt 114, 7: 198-201 &amp; 114, 8: 231 -
234.
Pagel, T. 1999. Der Balistar: Seine Heimat, Biologie, Haltung und Zucht sowie die BemUhungen
um seine Erhaltung. Z. Koln. Zoo 42, 2: 55-78.
Schmidt, D. , Risser jr., A. C, Lint, K. C. &amp; Scollay, P. 1976. The beautiful Bali Mynahs.
Zoonooz (San Diego) 49, 3: 4-8.
Sontag Jr., W. A. 1991. Zur Habitatnutzung beim Balistar ( Leucopsar rothschildi ): Vergleich
mit einer nahverwandten Referenzart. Seevogel (Hamburg) 12, Sonderheft 1: 111-113.
Sontag Jr., W. A. 1992. On habitat utilization in various South Asian starlings (Stumidae). Mitt.
Zool. Mus. Berl. 68 Suppl.: Ann. Om. 16: 115-123.
Sontag Jr., W. A. 1996. Zu Systematik, Charakteristika, Biologie und Haltung des Balistars
(Leucopsar rothschildi) - Teil 1 und 2. AZ-Nachrichten 43, 7: 481-488 &amp; 43, 8: 583-588.
Sontag Jr., W. A. 2001. Cues for specific ethological adaptions of the Rothschild's Mynah
(Leucopsar rothschildi) to the natural environment. UFZ-Bericht 2/2001 (Naturschutz und
Verhalten): 39-44. Umweltforschungszentrum Leipzig-Halle, Leipzig.
Taynton, K. &amp; Jeggo, D. 1988. Factors affecting breeding success of Rothschild's Mynah
Leucopsar rothschildi at the Jersey Wildlife Preservation Trust. Dodo 25: 66-76.
West, C. C. &amp; Pugh, P. B. 1986. Breeding and behaviour of Rothschild's Mynah Leucopsar
rothschildi at Jersey Wildlife Preservation Trust. Dodo 22: 84-97.
Dr Walter A. Sontag Jr is a zoologist living in Vienna. He has studied
the biology of the sturnids (starlings) for more than 25 years, working in
part co-operation with the Konrad Lorenz Institute for Comparative Ethology
in Vienna. He can be contacted at:- Trubelgasse 19/24, A-1030 Vienna,
Austria. E-mail:seidel@pflaphy.pph. univie. ac.at
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997686" page_id="56264865"  page_num="21" year="" vol="">
21
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.966151" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264865" page_num="21" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE GREY-WINGED TRUMPETER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8416986" page_id="56264865"  page_num="21" year="" vol="">
Psophia crepitans
by Rosemary Low
The Grey-winged Trumpeter Psophia crepitans is a curiously named
bird. Both parts of its scientific name refer to the deep, ventriloquial booming
sound which it makes. It belongs to the order Gruiformes, a group which
contains a seemingly odd assortment of birds: cranes, rails, the Limpkin
Aramus guarauna, Sunbittem Eurypyga helias, seriemas, bustards and the
fascinating Kagu Rhynochetos jubatus of New Caledonia. The main factor
which they have in common is that they are primarily ground-living birds,
some of which have lost the habit of flying.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.697978">
Rosemary Low
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989586714285714" page_id="56264865"  page_num="21" year="" vol="">
Adult sunbathing. The sexes look alike
There are three species of trumpeters. The Grey-winged is the best known
in aviculture. The Green-winged P. viridis and the White-winged P
leucoptera are rare in captivity. They originate in the Amazon region with
the species having long been separated by the great rivers, the Amazon and
the Madeira. The Grey-winged inhabits an area north of the Amazon and
the Rio Negro in Brazil, Venezuela, the Guianas, Colombia and Peru.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995423" page_id="56264866"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
22
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.57742" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264866" page_num="22" year="" vol="">
LOW - GREY-WINGED TRUMPETER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999375404761905" page_id="56264866"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
Trumpeters are readily recognisable by their small heads and hunched
bodies perched on pale green long legs. They have glossy, velvety black
bodies. Some of the feathers on the front of the neck have a broad band of
purple/green iridescence. The wing colour varies according to the species.
They weigh in the region of 1.1kg (21bs 6ozs).
These birds are known mainly as attractive zoo exhibits. Few private
aviculturists keep them. Trumpeters can become extraordinarily tame and
enjoy having their heads and necks scratched. They are inquisitive and
seem to enjoy interacting with people, thus they make excellent zoo birds.
They can even be allowed to roam free in suitable locations. However, this
can be fraught with danger as their lack of fear may result in them being
involved in accidents. Zoos have had limited success breeding trumpeters.
They can be quite aggressive birds. If more than one adult male is kept
together the subordinate bird may be attacked. The best combination seems
to be two females and one male. They can also be aggressive towards much
larger birds.
In the wild trumpeters live in groups of up to six individuals. They are
said to nest in spacious tree hollows. Although they spend much of their
time on the ground, they will jump or fly up into trees when alarmed. Nesting
on the ground would make the eggs and chicks too vulnerable to predators.
However, in captivity they may nest low down, even if a nest-box is available.
The clutch usually consists of three white eggs, laid at intervals of two days.
They are incubated by the male and female for 27-28 days.
If more than one chick hatches, sibling aggression might be apparent at
a very early age. One zoo overcame this problem by presenting one of the
two chicks to two males in another enclosure, which reared it as effectively
as a true pair would have done. This was probably because they live in
social groups in the wild, even when breeding, and adults other than the
parents might at times be allowed to look after the young. An alternative to
fostering, when the two chicks are small, is to place one on each side of a
low fence over which the adults can hop with ease.
When I was Curator of the breeding centre at Palmitos Park, Gran Canaria,
I had the opportunity to get to know trumpeters quite well. The adult birds
were in the park, at least one at liberty and a trio in an aviary. They were
always alert and active except when engaged in one of their favourite pursuits
- sun-bathing. Then they could be seen resting with their wings fully
outstretched, revealing the large grey area shown in my photo (p. 21).
Young were never reared in the park. Perhaps the close proximity of the
public was a disturbing influence when they were incubating. Therefore,
the eggs were placed in an incubator in the breeding centre. I discovered
that the humidity needs to be kept high or chicks will die just prior to hatching.
When the chicks emerged from the eggs (with eyes open and ready to run,
</bodyText>
<address confidence="0.229568">
LOW - GREY-WINGED TRUMPETER
</address>
<page confidence="0.998878" page_id="56264867"  page_num="23" year="" vol="">
23
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999246333333333" page_id="56264867"  page_num="23" year="" vol="">
as with all precocial species), I placed them in a brooder in a small paper-
lined box to dry for a few hours. When they were dry and strong enough to
run about, I would give them a drink of water by holding their beaks in a
small shallow container, usually the lid of a coffee jar. They soon learned to
drink from this. Their yolk sac nourishes them until then.
The chicks have thick down and do not seem to require a lot of heat after
the first few days (the temperature of the room in which they were kept was
usually about 27*C (80.6*F)). They are mottled grey, brown and black,
with the neck black. The beak is also black and the legs are grey. One
newly hatched chick in my care weighed 48g on the day of hatching. Two
at the National Zoo in Washington, USA, weighed 4lg and 43g on the second
day.
As soon as the chicks were up and running I started to feed them, although
their parents do not perhaps feed them until the day after hatching. On day
one the chicks would feed on small mealworms, small crickets, papaya and
egg yolk taken from forceps. I would offer food about every 45 minutes
during the day; they were not fed at night. By day four, feeds were given
every hour. There was less interest in egg yolk and papaya and more interest
in live insects.
In the brooder was a dish containing hard-boiled egg, ripe banana, grapes
and papaya, all finely chopped. Also there was a homemade rearing food,
consisting of wholegrain bread, raw carrot, hard-boiled egg and low fat cheese
finely mixed to a crumbly consistency in a food mixer.
Initially food is pecked from one's fingers or taken from the forceps.
After about four days though chicks will pick up food dropped in front of
them. From the age of about two days they become wildly excited when
offered livefood or meat. Cooked chicken liver or raw minced liver was
relished. They pecked furiously at these foods, as so they could not devour
them quickly enough.
The first chick I reared was offered freshly killed mice chopped into
large pieces. It became wildly excited at the sight of mouse on the menu.
The young trumpeters were also known to eat slugs and freshly dead geckos
- these lovely little creatures were never killed intentionally but sometimes
died if accidentally trapped in a door or window or if caught by my dog.
The young trumpeters were even known to eat cockroaches. Fortunately
but strangely, the reaction to a piece of cuttlefish bone held in a hand was
also one of excitement and vicious pecking. This was good because although
a calcium supplement was sprinkled on the food, one could observe this
source of calcium being consumed.
The young trumpeter, whose weights are shown on p.24, hatched in
February 1994. On the morning after it hatched it was lethargic, lying down
and refusing to feed. I have no doubt this was because it became overheated
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.993513" page_id="56264868"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
24
</page>
<table confidence="0.376710333333333" page_id="56264868"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
LOW - GREY-WINGED TRUMPETER
Newly hatched chick weighing 45g
Rosemary Low
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.999221428571428" page_id="56264868"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
during the night. By the afternoon it was active, vocal and feeding well,
taking crickets, papaya and egg yolk from a pair of forceps. On the sixth
day it was removed from the brooder to the floor, with a red lamp. By the
following day it was making a loud ' chirruping ' call. It ate a small quantity
of banana but 95% of its food consisted of insects: crickets, mealworms and
a large earthworm. On the 10th day the heat was discontinued during the
day. In the rearing room the temperature was 25 *C (77*F).
</bodyText>
<address confidence="0.209924">
LOW - GREY-WINGED TRUMPETER
</address>
<page confidence="0.904739" page_id="56264869"  page_num="25" year="" vol="">
25
</page>
<table confidence="0.553078333333333" page_id="56264869"  page_num="25" year="" vol="">
Rosemary Low
Eight days old and weighing 116g
Aged about three weeks
</table>
<page confidence="0.990325" page_id="56264870"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
26
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.577931" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264870" page_num="26" year="" vol="">
LOW - GREY-WINGED TRUMPETER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999019466666667" page_id="56264870"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
By the 13th day, when it was also eating eggfood and finely chopped
soaked figs, it would clean its beak vigorously on a towel after eating fruit.
By the next day it would pick up food dropped in front of it but ate very
little when I was not present. On the 15th day it ' chirped ' loudly with
excitement at the sight of crickets. A few days later chopped mice were
greeted with the same enthusiasm. The first flight feathers were erupting
and were about 50mm (2in) long. On the 20th day black contour feathers
were apparent through the down. On the 22nd day it was starting to hold the
wings open, like an adult. At this stage livefood was in short supply but
chicken liver and hard-boiled egg yolks were readily accepted. Eggshells
were taken with great enthusiasm. A potential problem in rearing young
trumpeters is their readiness to sample anything that might or might not be
edible. One chick puzzled me because blood was seen in its faeces on three
occasions over a period of four days. On the fourth day I discovered the
reason when I saw it pecking at the screen door and apparently swallowing
small pieces of wire. The problem was solved by covering the lower part of
the door.
By the age of about 25 days the soft grey plumes on the wings clearly
indicate the identity of the species. The overall appearance is otherwise
black. By the age of five months, young trumpeters look very like adults,
even having iridescent feathers on the neck. The only feature which
distinguishes them as being young birds is the leg colour which is pale but
not yet greenish. At this age they also vocalise like adults.
Hand-rearing trumpeters is quite time consuming, especially during the
early stages. If it is carried out only to avoid sibling aggression, a better
option would be to separate the parents and let each rear one chick or, as
mentioned earlier, foster them to other trumpeters. If hand-rearing is carried
out because the parents fail to incubate and rear them, consideration should
be given to moving them to a larger enclosure with a nesting area which is
screened from public view.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.965589" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264871" page_num="27" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE MALI OR KULIKORO FIREFINCH
</sectionHeader>
<keyword confidence="0.27955">
Lagonosticta virata
</keyword>
<page confidence="0.989918" page_id="56264871"  page_num="27" year="" vol="">
27
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.987337421052632" page_id="56264871"  page_num="27" year="" vol="">
by Ian Hinze
The e-mail message of July 16th 2000 read: 'Clive Barlow has found
some Mali Firefinches Lagonosticta virata in the UK and suggests you would
like to breed them. Clive plans to return to Gambia next month and has no
way to keep birds in the UK on a long term basis. A dealer has them and
Clive has examined them; we are working on the vocabulary and Clive has
an edited tape of their songs and calls which he can let you have. We have
tapes of an indigobird that mimics the calls and songs and would like to get
begging calls of the firefinch chick to compare with those of the male
indigobird.'
The message had come from Prof. Robert Payne of the University of
Michigan and the Clive Barlow in question was none other than the co-
author of Birds of The Gambia and Senegal. At the time I was making
sound recordings of Dybowski's Twinspot Euschistospiza dybowskii
nestlings for Prof. Payne, undoubtedly the world's leading authority on
indigobirds and their parasitisation and mimicry of estrildid finches.
Clive Barlow was in England for a month to visit his mother and record
the songs and calls of birds in dealers' establishments up and down the
country. While visiting one such dealer in Swindon he came upon a cageful
of African or Blue-billed Firefinches L. rubricata - and was more than a
little interested to spot a number of Mali Firefinches amongst them. The
male African Firefinch of the race L. r. polionota is almost identical to the
Mali Firefinch, but the two can be separated beyond any doubt by comparing
the outer primaries of the wings. The second outermost primary of L. r.
polionota is emarginated or blade-like while that of L. virata is broad. The
proprietor, Neil Eatwell, allowed Clive to separate the Mali Firefinches,
seven altogether, and these were placed in a cage of their own.
Knowing how rare this species is in captivity, and knowing of my success
with a number of waxbill species and the work I was doing for Prof. Payne,
Clive suggested that I be contacted to prevent the birds being dispersed and
in order for research to be carried out. Fortunately, I have known the Eatwell
family for about 15 years and so Neil needed little persuasion.
So it was that I drove to Swindon from Manchester, and arrived back
home with seven of the rarest firefinches available to aviculturists and a
sackful of Verse Laga Prestige tropical finch seed, which consists of very
small millet on which the birds were being fed. At the time I acquired these
Mali Firefinches there were less than 10 skins of this species in all of the
world's museums - five of these at Tring. I knew I could not afford to waste
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994473" page_id="56264872"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
28
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.696888" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264872" page_num="28" year="" vol="">
HINZE - MALI FIREFINCH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.914444730769231" page_id="56264872"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
L. rubricata L. virata
After Robin Restall
such a golden opportunity - an opportunity that might never occur again!
The Mali Firefinch, known also as the Kulikoro Firefinch, is endemic to
Mali. Prof. Payne (pers. comm.) states that it is found in the west of the
country, 15*N on Mts Mandingues (Kita, Boucle de Baoule), Bamako,
Kulikoro and Fiko near the Bandiagara Escarpment. Reports of the African
Firefinch in southern Mali may, in fact, be L. virata and it is thought it may
occur also in south-east Senegal and northern Guinea. In September 2000,
when the Mali Firefinch was breeding, Prof Payne did field work in Mali
and recorded the daytime temperature at 32*C (90*F) and the night-time
temperature at 26*C (80*F). He also informed me that the temperature is
much hotter in December. The temperature in my birdroom, which is heated
by electric tubular heaters during the day averages 23*C (74*F) and at night
15*C (60*F).
Description
The Mali Firefinch is about 10cm (4in) in length and the sexes differ
slightly: the crown is brownish grey, the back and wings are grey brown, the
outer primaries are broad and not emarginated, the rump is deep scarlet and
the tail is black with the outer margins of the feathers red. The lores are
scarlet, the cheeks and underparts from the throat to the belly are, in the
male, deep strawberry red and, in the female, pinkish red; the sides of the
breast and upper flanks have some very small dull white spots, the centre of
the belly is grey, the lower belly and under tail-coverts are black and the
thighs are dark grey. The upper mandible is blackish and most of the lower
mandible is light blue. The eyes are dark brown and the eye-ring is pink
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.467076" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264873" page_num="29" year="" vol="">
HINZE - MALI FIREFINCH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997931" page_id="56264873"  page_num="29" year="" vol="">
29
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999072923076923" page_id="56264873"  page_num="29" year="" vol="">
but, from a short distance away, may appear to be light yellow in some
individuals (a trick of the light perhaps? : see also plate 43 of Finches and
sparrows (Clement et al. 1993)). The legs and feet are bluish grey.
The juvenile is grey with, compared to the adults, duller red on the rump
and tail. One to two day old nestlings have dark grey to black skin, a little
whitish down on the crown of the head, a black bill and greyish-white gape
flanges. The mouth markings consist of five black lines on a slightly pink
and greyish palate.
In the field the Mali Firefinch appears as a very small bird with red and
dark greyish plumage. It can be distinguished from the Red-billed Firefinch
L. senegala . the only sympatric firefinch, through both L. senegala sexes
having red bills and the L. senegala female and juvenile having
predominantly light brown plumage (Goodwin, 1982).
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.479139">
Status
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.992909925925926" page_id="56264873"  page_num="29" year="" vol="">
Prof. Payne (pers. comm.) found L. virata to be the most common species
in the area in which he was conducting studies, which was a scrubby area of
about 40sq miles (lOOsq km). Because of the difficulty of getting around
the region one cannot say for sure how many other sites are as good or what
is the size of the global population. In the study area it is estimated there are
about 40 pairs per square mile (per 2.58sq km), and because comparable
habitat is widespread Prof. Payne believes there could be at least 100,000
individuals of this species in Mali. It is also suspected that, based on satellite
photographs that show similar habitat and topography, a comparable large
number may be found in eastern Senegal.
The species is not considered to be endangered or threatened, as it occurs
over a wide area and is common within that area. About 100 were spotted at
two bird dealers, and Clive Barlow had managed to acquire about 50 from
another dealer in Senegal only 12 months earlier and took them back to his
home in The Gambia. Both sites apparently export a lot but the birds are
mislabelled as L. rubricata and to compound matters, Senegal also exports
the real L. rubricata.
Voice
Goodwin (1982) reported that the alarm call is a rattling trill, like that of
Jameson's Firefinch L. rhodopareia but louder, deeper-pitched and harsher,
and sometimes with a suggestion of a 'ch' sound 'welling up' in the middle
of a trill, i.e. ' chrrrrrrrr, choorrrrrrr, choorrrr, (ch)rrrrrrr(ch)rrrr-rrrr and
variants. Harrison (in Goodwin, 1982) noted that the pitch of his males
became higher with the intensity of the calling. Burkard (in Goodwin, 1982)
described the alarm call of his pair as a sparrow-like ' tsheld repeated at
short intervals.
The contact calls of both sexes are subject to much minor variation,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99562" page_id="56264874"  page_num="30" year="" vol="">
30
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.778758" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264874" page_num="30" year="" vol="">
HINZE - MALI FIREFINCH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993214341463415" page_id="56264874"  page_num="30" year="" vol="">
such as 'kyew, kyah, kew, ztew ' (pers. obs.) and can be low-pitched, nasal,
slightly harsh and harsh. One of Goodwin's (1982) captive females uttered
a long, plaintive 4 feeeeeeeeeeeeee and, less frequently, a two-syllabled
4 feeee-eeeee ' as distance contact calls, both of which I have heard uttered
from my own females, as well as just a short 'feeee ' in reply to the call of a
solitary male and which were very similar to the homologous calls of the
female L. rubricata. Harrison (in Goodwin, 1982) described the nest call of
the male as a faint, persistent, clucking note. Goodwin (1982) also heard a
soft 'chew'or 'teu that resembled that of a male Jameson's Firefinch he had
observed and which was uttered in similar threat or defiance contexts.
Harrison (in Goodwin, 1982) reported two differing songs from two
different males - one 'a long drawn toneless trill' and the other a melodious,
high-pitched song of short, loud phrases that were frequently repeated. I
have noticed variation in the songs of different males, one emitting sounds
not unlike the familiar tinklings of our native Robin Erithacus rubecula. A
transliteration of the song of the breeding male under review given on
occasion would be a fast 4 pertipper-tipper-tipper-tip-teeu-teeu-teeu-teeu '
or similar. The song appears only to be given with any regularity, when the
male is on its own. Paired-up males very rarely sing. A second male in the
company of a female gave a long ' tchrrrrrrrf call which was answered
with a short 4 tchtrr ' from a solitary male. On other occasions a solitary
male gave more melodious 4 pseup-pseup-pseup ' calls.
Habitat, general behaviour and feeding
It is found in rocky sandstone areas with bushes, scrub and grass, and in
most habits it is reported to be very similar to other firefinches, particularly
Jameson's and the African Firefinch to which it is closely related (Clement
et al. 1993; Goodwin, 1982). It feeds on grass seeds and most likely small
insects, especially termites (Barlow pers. comm.). My captive birds also
love to chew growing grass and the leaves of plants. Compost, in which I
breed whiteworm, was rummaged through with the bill and regularly flicked
away to get at any hidden worms. Often, birds would take a small clump of
the compost in their bills and hastily carry it behind cover. Here they would
rummage through it and extricate any worms. I have only yet seen one pair
(the breeding pair) perform this behaviour, but it could well be typical of the
species in the wild in its pursuit of insects.
Courtship display
The majority of times I observed the courtship display it started with the
male flying up to a perch with a piece of dried grass or coconut fibre carried
by one end in his bill. The male would then stretch his body almost upright
and begin to bob up and down. I never once heard him sing during this
display, after which he would jump to the ground and repeat the process
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.467034" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264875" page_num="31" year="" vol="">
HINZE - MALI FIREFINCH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999758" page_id="56264875"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
31
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999441463414634" page_id="56264875"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
there under cover. The female, if receptive, would squat down and vibrate
her tail. Copulation would then take place. Less frequently, I have also
observed copulation, which I have timed at taking 16-20 seconds, take place
on a perch and, more recently, once on the edge of a water dish. In the main,
however, no display at all is given prior to copulation. The male merely
follows the female around uttering a regular soft 'tu-tu-tu-tu-tu call. The
female, after allowing a short chase, generally squats down and copulation
follows immediately. On one occasion a female performed the courtship
display to the male, complete with nesting symbol in her bill, but without
copulation following.
Nesting and captive observations
There is no information on the wild nest. My successful breeding pair
used an old nest which had been constructed out of hay and coconut fibres
by a male Black-faced or Vinaceous Firefinch L. larvata vinacea. It was a
small globular affair with a side entrance, which I placed on top of the base
of an old nest of the Dybowski's Twinspots that had been built in a Boston
Fern. I placed the Boston Fern, complete with the twinspot's nest, in the
Mali Firefinches' cage before adding the old nest built by the male Black-
faced or Vinaceous Firefinch. The male Mali Firefinch merely lined this
with short pieces of tom newspaper, which it had obtained by tearing strips
from that lining the cage floor, and any feathers it could find.
The female laid an egg on consecutive days until the clutch, which
numbered three eggs, was complete (it is believed clutches usually number
three to four eggs in the wild). Incubation did not begin until the last egg
was laid, whereupon the male and female shared the responsibility for 10-
11 days (it is believed incubation averages 11-13 days in the wild), whereafter
two nestlings hatched. These were brooded by both parents but, sadly, six
days after hatching one of the nestlings was found dead on the cage floor.
During the brooding of the remaining nestling the parents copulated daily
and the female proceeded to lay a further four eggs - her second clutch -
alongside the nestling. After fearing for the well-being of the nestling, offering
prayers to Jehovah and more than a week of sleepless nights, on entering
the birdroom for the second time on the morning of November 14th, I was
overjoyed to find a tiny, grey-looking, fledgling sitting contentedly on the
cage floor. It was 19-20 days old.
All my own-designed wooden cages are approximately 4ft long x 2ft sq
(approx. 1.2m long x 61cm sq). Instead of solid roofs, I use all-wire ones.
The reason for this is to enable me to place 3ft (91.5cm) long Arcadia bird
lamps (specially designed full spectrum fluorescents) over each cage to
guarantee a minimum of 15 hours 'natural' sunlight per day. Under this
lighting the natural colours of birds are enhanced, and in the case of the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995386" page_id="56264876"  page_num="32" year="" vol="">
32
</page>
<table confidence="0.3722864" page_id="56264876"  page_num="32" year="" vol="">
HINZE - MALI FIREFINCH
R. B. Payne
Mali Firefinch captured in the field
R. B. Payne
Rocky habitat of the Mali Firefinch in Tienfala, Mali
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.46707" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264877" page_num="33" year="" vol="">
HINZE - MALI FIREFINCH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999208" page_id="56264877"  page_num="33" year="" vol="">
33
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997468142857143" page_id="56264877"  page_num="33" year="" vol="">
fledgling Mali Firefinch its all grey plumage actually contained a very slight
suffusion of earth brown or rusty red. The base of the stubby tail was a
clearly noticeable rusty red, with the remainder being grey. The legs and
feet were grey, the bill black and there was a tuft of greyish-white down still
remaining on the crown, which was otherwise covered in tiny pin feathers.
The gape marks were creamy white with four papillae, two on each side
with one on the top and one on the bottom. They were not directly in line,
i.e. one on top of the other, but at more of a 45* angle to each other, the
bottom one being more forward than the top. The papillae looked strobe
blue with a tiny white dot in the middle. In the comer of the mouth there
was also a small rusty brown tubercle.
At 25-26 days of age the youngster was getting about the cage with ease
and starting to pick up seeds primarily from the cage floor, although its
father also continued to feed it. From the day of its fledging I never once
saw the female feed the youngster, she was more concerned with laying a
second clutch. Indeed, on one occasion the fledgling accidentally landed
on her back while she was perching and was promptly, but gently, scolded.
This brought about an immediate response from the male which appeared
to pacify his mate with some gentle calls and bill-fencing. He also tightened
his feathers, went into a crouched posture and fanned his tail. The following
day it became obvious by his occasional stem reluctance to feed the youngster
that he was encouraging it to start to fend more for itself. However, the
youngster was not truly independent until it was 36-37 days old, at which
stage it was still completely grey and had a very short tail.
The parents reared the youngster on whiteworms, defrosted bloodworms
offered in shallow water and soaked seed, which consisted of the Verse
Laga mentioned earlier and larger mixed millets and canary seed. I have
never known any other waxbill take so much soaked seed. I also provided
crushed oystershell, limestone and crushed, baked poultry egg shells. This
mixture was avidly taken by the female, especially, no doubt to aid her own
egg shell production.
To further enhance the health and condition of the birds, and particularly
for the benefit of the laying female, I added the Bird Care Company's Daily
Essential 2 multivitamins to the drinking water each day, as well as Vydex's
Calsure (a calcium supplement) and Entrodex (a probiotic). As nesting birds
are particularly prone to mites, I sprayed the entire cage and nest prior to the
birds breeding, using Zodiac a spray available from the Bird Care Company.
As well as eradicating fleas and mites, it also destroys their eggs and offers
protection for up to seven months!
During the writing of this account, the breeding pairs' well-worn nest
came apart (though I managed to save the five eggs, which it then contained)
and a new nest was built of coconut fibre and hay. The male collected the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997977" page_id="56264878"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
34
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.777415" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264878" page_num="34" year="" vol="">
HINZE - MALI FIREFINCH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9858163125" page_id="56264878"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
material and passed it to his mate, which did virtually all of the building
after which egg laying started again. At the same time, in a cage alongside,
a second pair also constructed a nest of coconut fibre and hay. I then had
two pairs incubating eggs.
I was able to measure six eggs (one from the first clutch and five from
the second). The first measured 15mm x 12mm. Of the five eggs from the
second clutch, which was abandoned, one measured 15mm x 12mm, one
15mm x 11mm, one 16mm x 11mm and two 14mm x 11mm.
It is too early to say whether or not the Mali Firefinch has tremendous
domestication possibilities, but I have certainly found it eager to start breeding.
Housing more than one pair or putting two males together is definitely not
recommended. Males will viciously attack and undoubtedly kill other males
(I rescued one, left almost scalped and motionless, in the nick of time) and
observed a paired-up female attack a single male. I would also strongly advise
against housing this species with other red coloured small birds, and in
particular other species of firefinch, especially at breeding time.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.282059" page_id="56264878"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
Postscript
On December 21 st three fledglings appeared followed by, on December
</table>
<listItem confidence="0.830937" page_id="56264878"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
24th, three from the second pair. This made a total of seven young (including
the single youngster from the first brood). At the time of writing (January
2nd) both pairs are nesting again, with the first pair having already laid
another three eggs.
</listItem>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.887577" genericHeader="references" page_id="56264878" page_num="34" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.914395" page_id="56264878"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
Clement, R, Harris, A. &amp; Davis, J. 1993. Finches and sparrows. Christopher Helm/A. &amp; C.
Black, London.
Goodwin, D. 1982. Estrildid finches of the world. British Museum (Natural History), London.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.873356" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56264878" page_num="34" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998277454545455" page_id="56264878"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
I would like to thank first and foremost my wife, Claire, and our four
children for their priceless patience and understanding while I virtually lived
with the Mali Firefinches throughout their breeding; also, Derek Goodwin
and Robin Restall for their friendship, support and encouragement and Prof.
Robert Payne and Clive Barlow, for not only their friendship but also their
having the faith in my abilities as an aviculturist to present me with this
wonderfully unique opportunity.
As described above, the Mali or Kulikoro Firefinch Lagonosticta virata ,
has been bred by Ian Hinze. This is probably the first successful breeding of
this species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who knows of a previous
breeding is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997072" page_id="56264879"  page_num="35" year="" vol="">
35
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7609615" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264879" page_num="35" year="" vol="">
THE SPRING SOCIAL MEETING
by Stewart Pyper
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.984595105263158" page_id="56264879"  page_num="35" year="" vol="">
The 60 members and guests who accepted the kind invitation of Michel
and Diane Klat to view their extensive collection at the Old House Bird
Garden, Hare Hatch, near Reading, Berkshire, on Sunday March 12th last
year, were indeed fortunate to view such a fine collection on what was a
lovely, warm and sunny early spring day.
The visit, which was arranged by Raymond Sawyer, showed that an
outing to a private collection can result in a good turn-out of members,
some of whom had travelled long distances to be present. None more so
than Mark Sproule, a Canadian member, who that morning had travelled
from Nottingham (quite a journey by train on a Sunday), where he was
working on the council's computer system.
Michel and Diane Klat's collection consists mainly of pheasants,
curassows and touracos. A further 40 or so pairs of curassows and touracos
are on loan to Birdworld, near Famham, Surrey.
Within the beautiful gardens, most of the pheasants are housed in
extremely well constructed aviaries built around four sides of an enclosed
fox-proof area. The aviaries, some of which are glass-fronted, to protect the
inhabitants during inclement weather, have been designed with the practical
aspects of feeding, maintenance and breeding very much to the fore. Most
are thickly planted to provide seclusion for the birds, with black bamboo
being widely used. All have a covered shelter and most floors are covered
with a layer of sand, which is easily raked over.
Two large comer aviaries about 12ft high x 40ft sq (approx. 3.6m high x
12m sq), one of which was being refurbished, house pairs of Great Blue
Touracos, the first UK breeding of which took place at the Old House Bird
Garden in 1999. The pair were in lovely condition and obviously benefited
from the quality of the accommodation, which must have contributed to the
successful breeding. It is planned to include zosterops in the refurbished
aviary to help control unwanted insects and because it has a water supply,
some waders will also be included.
A range of rearing pens for young pheasants are located at the rear of a
large paddock, which houses rheas and has a small lake with waterfowl.
The original aviaries are situated in what was once a vegetable garden. Many,
some of which were being rebuilt, are octagonal in shape.
It was the first UK collection to breed the Vietnamese Pheasant, Berlioz's,
Lewis's and Jones's Silver Pheasants, Bornean Crestless Fireback, several
subspecies of the Ring-necked Pheasant and was also first to breed the
Yellow-knobbed Curassow. The collection includes many rarely seen
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995049" page_id="56264880"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
36
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.768446" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264880" page_num="36" year="" vol="">
PYPER - SOCIAL MEETINGS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994331818181818" page_id="56264880"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
pheasant subspecies and also wild-caught Lady Amherst Pheasants. We
also saw Satyr, Temminck's, Cabot's and Blyth's Tragopans, and junglefowl.
A large aviary along the perimeter wall also housed a pair of Great Blue
Touracos, this pair sitting on a clutch of eggs which it was intended to remove
and artificially incubate in the large, scrupulously clean, incubating unit, in
which hygiene is paramount.
We were privileged to see a 24-hour old Great Blue Touraco being fed. I
had never before seen so many Great Blue and Ross's Touracos. I could
imagine the incubation room at the height of the breeding season being an
incredible sight. Other touracos in the collection are the White-crested,
Black-billed, Livingstone's, Red-crested and Fischer's.
Two Moluccan Cockatoos and two pairs of Keas complete the collection.
The latter can be very helpful at night in raising the alarm if a fox manages
to get into the garden.
Steve Bishop, the Curator, and a staff of two look after this magnificent
collection. They have certainly achieved excellent results and we wish them
well in the future. Perhaps Steve will find time to report about the collection
in our magazine.
On behalf of all the members and guests who so enjoyed the visit to the
Old House Bird Garden, I would like to thank Michel and Diane Klat for
their kind hospitality, which concluded with a wonderful tea in the nearby
village hall.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.799216" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264880" page_num="36" year="" vol="">
THE PRESIDENT'S GARDEN PARTY 2000
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.50032">
by Stewart Pyper
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.988329066666667" page_id="56264880"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
The President's Garden Party was held on Sunday July 16th, again by
kind invitation of our President Miss Ruth Ezra and Vice President Raymond
Sawyer. In what was not a very good summer, the day was notable for the
warm and sunny weather, which provided the 70 members and their guests
with ideal conditions to view the birds and garden on what is the social
highlight of the society's year. It was the 25th garden party to be held at
Chestnut Lodge, the first having been held in 1976.
Various birds had bred including Avocets, Black-necked Stilts, Masked
Plovers, Blue-faced Honeyeaters, Blue-bellied Rollers and Green Wood
Hoopoes. The breeding of a McClelland's or Rufous-vented Laughing Thrush
Garrulax gularis - like a larger version of the Yellow-throated species - is
probably a UK first breeding. There are two pairs in adjoining aviaries with
the pair in the waterfall aviary having fledged a single youngster. Raymond
has promised to write a report about this breeding.
A pair of Toco Toucans now share the aviary at the back of the left-hand
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.397757" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264881" page_num="37" year="" vol="">
PYPER - SOCIAL MEETINGS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998067" page_id="56264881"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
37
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999111605263158" page_id="56264881"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
side of the original complex. To enable the two to get to know each better,
they were housed first in adjoining aviaries and later the dividing wire was
removed and replaced later when they had settled down together in the first
aviary. Regrettably, one of the Keel-billed Toucans had died a few days
before our visit.
A few more South American birds have been available recently and
Raymond has obtained what he hopes are some Striped Manakins. They
were fit but rather sticky to handle when first obtained but in a short time
cleaned up nicely. They are what I would call a murky light green and
Raymond has found traces of red on the crown, but it could be two or three
years before they moult into adult plumage and he knows for sure that they
are Striped Manakins. This is a species I had not seen before. He also has
three male Red-capped and a pair of Blue-backed Manakins.
The Garnet Pitta looked lovely as did the various Hooded Pittas. I saw
four species of bee-eaters, including the Carmine and White-throated and
counted at least three male and two female Spangled Cotingas. The pair in
the Tropical House had attempted to build a nest but chose a rather awkward
place. Hopefully, next time they will choose a more suitable site. Another
pair are in the aviary which used to house the Toco Toucans and share it
with a Chestnut-collared Kingfisher, another species I had not seen before.
It has a large range which includes Borneo, Sumatra and the Malay Peninsula.
Raymond told us the tale of how the male Beautiful Sunbird had escaped
and somehow managed to survive for over three months from February to
April before it was recaptured. How it survived is unknown. Perhaps in the
summer it could have survived by getting nectar from the wonderful flowers
at Cobham, but there were few if any flowers during these months and surely
someone would have spotted it! How it survived is quite a mystery to
Raymond but he is delighted to have it back safe and sound.
We also admired the tortoises, wallabies and Red Squirrels, as well as
the impressive collection of Bonsai and many other beautiful plants, including
the large collection of succulents.
During tea Prof. J. R. (Bob) Hodges, an Avicultural Society Vice
President, thanked Ruth and Raymond for their wonderful hospitality. He
then presented the society's Certificate of Merit to Laura Gardner,
representing the Leeds Castle collection, for the first breeding in the UK of
the Crowned Hornbill Tockus alboterminatus (in 1998). The proceeds of
the ticket sales for the garden party which amounted to over #500 (roughly
US$750), were generously donated to the society's funds by our President.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998162" page_id="56264882"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
38
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.743293666666667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264882" page_num="38" year="" vol="">
PYPER - SOCIAL MEETINGS
THE SOCIETY'S AUTUMN SOCIAL MEETING
by Stewart Pyper
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995115368421052" page_id="56264882"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
Despite the fuel crisis during the week prior to the Autumn Social
Meeting, about 30 members and their guests visited Twycross Zoo in
Warwickshire on Sunday, September 17th, where we were welcomed by
Molly Badham, the zoo's owner and co-founder.
Famous for its collection of primates, the zoo also exhibits a variety of
other mammals and birds, and in the future intends to expand its bird
collection. The present collection includes Scarlet, Blue &amp; Gold and Red-
fronted Macaws, Moluccan Cockatoos and two pairs of Thick-billed Parrots,
the latter believed to have been obtained from Ken Dolton, an Avicultural
Society Vice President. Twycross is one of only four zoos which exhibit
this species.
Grey and Palawan Peacock Pheasants, Pink Pigeons, Kookaburras,
White-cheeked Touracos, Sulawesi Magpies and Bali Starlings are housed
in spacious planted aviaries. There are two enclosures, one housing Emus
and the other Double-wattled Cassowaries. Various species of waterfowl
are kept, Straw-necked and Scarlet Ibis and a flock of flamingos.
At lunch we were joined by Molly Badham and John Ray the Zoo
Manager, who at his home keeps a small collection of cockatoos and other
parrots.
In the afternoon the party made its way to Netherseal, to view the private
collection owned by Andrew and Audrey Perkins. Touracos are much in
evidence and include: Schalow's, Livingstone's, Red-crested, Hartlaub's,
White-cheeked, Purple-crested, Fischer's, Green-crested T. persa persa,
Buffon's T. p. buffoni , White-bellied Go-away Bird and Western Plantain-
eater.
Other birds in the collection include Satyr and Temminck's Tragopans,
Monal Pheasants, a young Green Peafowl, Eagle Owl, Spreo Starlings, Black-
breasted Thrush, Greater Hill Mynah, Crowned and Demoiselle Cranes, Red-
breasted Geese, Grey and Red-billed Hornbills, Spotted Laughing Thrushes,
a Fairy Bluebird and a Sulphur-breasted Toucan that is adept at catching
table tennis balls.
Andrew and Audrey Perkins have a superb colony of Ring- tailed Lemurs,
as well as Black and White Ruffed, White-faced and Red-faced Brown
Lemurs, which were enjoying their afternoon meal at the time we saw them.
In the newly built Safari Lodge, in which childrens' parties are held, the fine
collection of reptiles and tarantulas were admired.
Our hosts kindly provided us with tea and sandwiches before we set off
for home.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998442" page_id="56264883"  page_num="39" year="" vol="">
39
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993649" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264883" page_num="39" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
THREATENED BIRDS OF THE WORLD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999689" page_id="56264883"  page_num="39" year="" vol="">
The realisation that more than 1,800 of the world's bird species are now
regarded as threatened is a depressing thought. Even more shocking is that
182 of them are critically endangered with the prospect they may be extinct
in 10 years. These are facts presented in the recently published
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909075" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264883" page_num="39" year="" vol="">
THREATENED BIRDS OF THE WORLD.
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99936103030303" page_id="56264883"  page_num="39" year="" vol="">
This A4 hardback volume is weighty in every sense of the word. The
subject occupies and merits well over 800 pages, 1,000 of the world's leading
experts have contributed to it and each of the 1,186 species is illustrated in
colour with maps showing locations and ranges for each of them.
A short introduction to each species' account provides an explanation
(wherever possible for in some instances information is scanty) of the reasons
for its classification as either critical, endangered or vulnerable. This is
followed by a brief but detailed description of the bird, together with a short
note about similar species as an aid to correct identification. For many
there are brief hints - mainly about how and where they are likely to be seen
in the wild, how to imitate calls, etc. The main texts for individual species
is presented under five headings: Range and Population, Ecology, Threats,
Conservation and Targets. References are numbered in the text and in most
instances given in full in the reference list.
Books of this calibre are obviously costly to publish and in this case it is
interesting to note that many species' accounts have been sponsored by
individuals, charitable institutions or companies. Launched in 1999, the
sponsorship scheme was very successful and raised more than US$385,700
(approx. #257,130) from people and organisations around the world.
Among six forewords which in different ways, highlight the book's
message, the one contributed by writer and broadcaster, Sir David
Attenborough spells out in a few words the task, facing all who are interested
in confronting the problem but points out that losses (of species) need not
continue.
He writes: 'Birds are beautiful and fascinating creatures. They have
managed to reach, flourish and even breed in some of the coldest, the hottest,
the driest and the highest of environments - places that human beings have
only reached within recent times and where we can only survive at all with
the help of artificial support systems.
'Yet, as this volume shows us so vividly, despite these remarkable abilities,
one in eight species of bird are at risk of global extinction. The threat to the
diversity and richness of life has been brought about by the changes that we
have made to the face of the earth. Such losses need not continue. We now
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.990269" page_id="56264884"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
40
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.970787" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264884" page_num="40" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970456722222222" page_id="56264884"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
have the knowledge to maintain the wonderfully rich and varied bird life
that still exists.
'The challenge facing us now is to use this knowledge and apply our
skills, our imagination and our resources to dealing with these problems
before it is too late. I invite all readers of this volume to join us in our
efforts to conserve the world&apos;s birds and other wildlife'.
Habitat loss and degradation are cited as the major causes of
endangerment in birds, threatening 1,008 species (85%), of which 74% are
affected by recent losses of tropical forests. Indeed, unsustainable selective
logging is the most significant factor, affecting 367 species. Arable and
livestock farming, grazing, human settlement, mining, drainage and filling-
in of wetlands are among other common causes. Excessive hunting and
trapping have also played their part. It may still surprise some aviculturists
to learn that both the Java Sparrow Padda oryzivora and Timor Sparrow P.
fuscata are now classified as vulnerable. The introduction to the former
species reads: ' The popularity of this finch as a cage-bird has resulted (and
unless stringent action is taken, will continue to result) in a rapid decline in
its population and range as a consequence of intense trapping activity, such
that it qualifies as vulnerable&apos;.
Indeed, trapping for the cage-bird trade - particularly of passerine species
- is a cause listed all too frequently for the comfort of the more responsible
elements in aviculture. Among some of the species thus identified, and
taken at random are: Yellow (or Green) Cardinal Gubernatrix cristata (E),
Red Siskin Carduelis cucullata (E), Green Avadavat Amandava formosa
(V), Straw-headed Bulbul Pycnonotus zeylanicus (V), Red and Blue Lory
Eos histrio (E), Black-winged Lory E. cyanogenia (V), Chattering Lory
Lorius garrulus (E), Lesser Sulphur-crested Cockatoo Cacatua sulphurea
(C) and Philippine Cockatoo C. haematuropygia (C). There are many more.
After emphasising the part the human race has played in the creation of
this catastrophic situation ('People drive this extinction crisis...'), the book's
opening chapter The Extinction Risk and Opportunities For Action discusses
potential solutions including which areas and habitats should be conserved,
which issues should be addressed and opportunities for building solutions
for birds, biodiversity and people.
This is an important and thought provoking book. It is comprehensive,
well designed and of excellent quality.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.955271" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264884" page_num="40" year="" vol="">
THREATENED BIRDS OF THE WORLD is published by Lynx Edicions
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.813539333333333">
in association with BirdLife International, Passeig de Gracia 12, E-08007
Barcelona, Spain. Tel: +34-93 301 0777/Fax: +34-93 302 1475/Intemet:
www.hbw.com/ E-mail: lynx@hbw.com Normal price #70.00, special
launch price #59.50. Available from Lynx Edicions (postage and packing
free) or from good booksellers.
Frank Woolham
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909922" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264885" page_num="41" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994654" page_id="56264885"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
41
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.969969" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264885" page_num="41" year="" vol="">
WILDLIFE GUIDE TO HAWAII
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994239485714286" page_id="56264885"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
More than 400 pages of information, advice, descriptions, identification
aids and field guide illustrations of as many species of flora and fauna make
this one of the latest Ecotravellers' Wildlife Guides, a sure-fire must-have
for any visitor to Hawaii who has more than sun, sand and surf in mind.
Every bird species occurring on the main Hawaiian islands on the Midway
Atoll is included.
Stylistically, the guide is a strange blend of the serious and scientific,
and popularism. This is no doubt aimed at the diverse and largely American
market. For example, the author seems to have a problem with amphibians:
he describes one species as 'ugly' and another as 'odd-looking'. It is a mix
of essays on conservation, hints and guides, do's and dont's, personal
statements and visitor information. The bird chapter is treated
straightforwardly, the following one on mammals and the culminating
Environmental Close-up essay, less so.
It took me a while to find my way around the book and the key to the
illustrations (surely most people's first requirement). Following five
introductory chapters, it was finally tracked down to Chapter 6, which is
headed How to use this book! Unhelpfully, the species pictured on any one
plate are not necessarily to scale. There might be a good reason for this,
(which does not immediately occur to me) but it can be a problem, especially
when almost every short description begins with 'Large', 'Mid-sized' or
'Small'. A bit unnecessary as length is given in centimetres and inches.
The illustrations are a mix of colour photos and high quality paintings
which, with the odd exception, are pretty much as good as you will see
anywhere. Whenever confronted by a task like this, I always go to the
species I know best, to see if they 'sit right' on the page. For me, this is
waterfowl (plates 28-30 within 34 plates of birds and mammals by H. Douglas
Pratt). I reckon that a common fault in illustrations finds birds with a
disproportionately large head (or small body, depending on which way you
look at it) and, in truth, this applies here too, for example the Garganey.
With the exception of a curiously mincing Mallard, postures are fine. Flicking
through the other plates and groups of birds which I know quite well, the
large majority seem in proportion with accurate colours. The plates of
seabirds in flight are high class.
The Ecotravellers ' Wildlife Guide to Hawaii by Les Beletsky is published
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.8645012">
by Academic Press, Harcourt Place, 32 Jamestown Road, London NW1
7BY and Academic Press, 525 B Street, Suite 1900, San Diego, California
92101-4495, USA (website:www.academicpress.com). It is priced #19.95
in the UK , US$27.95 in the USA and $38.95 in Canada.
Dr Richard Meyer
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998114" page_id="56264886"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
42
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9797225" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264886" page_num="42" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
FIVE SPECIES BRED FOR THE FIRST TIME
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.556437846153846" page_id="56264886"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
The White-collared Kingfisher Halcyon chloris , Black-necked Stilt
Himantopus mexicanus. Trumpeter Homnbill Bycanistes bucinator, Orange-
winged Amazon Amazona amazonica and Black-headed Caique Pionites
melanocephala are five species which were bred last year for the first time
at Paradise Park, Hayle, Cornwall. The breeding of the White-collared
Kingfisher is almost certainly also a UK first breeding. Of the two chicks
hatched in April, one died and the other was revived in an incubator and
reared by Dale Jackson. For the first time in many years there two pairs of
Bali Starlings Leucopsar rothschildi reared their own young. Three were
raised and are living now in the Tropical House. In his Curator's report in
the Paradise Park Newsletter , Winter 2000, David Woolcock also records
the passing of the park's breeding female St Vincent Parrot A. guildingii,
which was already an adult when she arrived in 1983.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.484141111111111" page_id="56264886"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
* * *
GUINATE CURATOR
A. Paul Ockenden has written to point but that he now holds the position
of Curator at Guinate Tropical Park on Lanzarote in the Canary Islands,
Andres Marin and Ana Matesanz having vacated the post one and a half
years ago. The latter wrote about the park's Piping Hornbills Ceratogymna
or Bycanistes fistulator {Avicultural Magazine, Vol. 105, No. 3, pp.97-102).
The pair remain in the collection but to date has still not attempted to breed.
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.952019" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264886" page_num="42" year="" vol="">
SLIDING TOWARDS EXTINCTION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999300272727273" page_id="56264886"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
One in five Australian bird species is sliding towards extinction, with
land clearance being the main threat to their survival. This is among the
preliminary findings of a survey for Birds Australia, revealed recently as
clearing continues in Queensland and New South Wales. Bird Australia's
Conservation Manager, Michael Fendley said: 'the natural environment is
tilting away from diversity and health towards dispair, and our birds are
sliding away with it'. He said: 'land clearance kills about 7.5 million birds
a year'. Other threats come from overgrazing by sheep and cattle, other
agricultural activities, changes in fire patterns, introduced predators and the
growing loss of remnant vegetation in cleared areas. Queensland is
responsible for about 90 percent of all of Australia's land clearance.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999852" page_id="56264887"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.662342" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264887" page_num="43" year="" vol="">
A GOOD YEAR
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.984986625" page_id="56264887"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
Last year was a good year for John Harvey, despite it being a rather
indifferent summer. Two Blue-breasted Waxbills Uraeginthus angolensis
were reared. Three, fledged, but one disappeared. The breeding male was
at least four years old, having been given to him by his friend Brian
Humphries. Ten Indian Silverbills Lonchura malabarica were bred, his
best result yet with this species. A pair of Red-faced Pytilias Pytilia
hypogrammica (also known as Yellow-winged Pytilias or Red-faced Aurora
Finches), consisting of a 1998-bred male and an imported female, nested
three times in a 12ft x 6ft x 6ft high (approx. 3.6m x 1.8m x 1.8m high)
aviary with access to a small indoor flight. The first nest, in a finch box,
produced two young which on moulting proved to be a male and female.
The second nest was a failure but the third, in a wicker nest basket, produced
three young. Other occupants of the aviary were pairs of Blue-billed
Mannikins L. bicolor , Indian Silverbills, Black-faced Firefinches
Lagonosticta larvata vinacea and Jameson's Firefinches L. rhodopareia. A
second pair of pytilias abandoned their young after 13 days. His pair of
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.356170666666667" page_id="56264887"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
Chinese Painted Quail Excalfactoria chinensis which reared young in 1999,
were unsuccessful last year.
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.769362" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264887" page_num="43" year="" vol="">
TWO-NOTE CALL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999106444444445" page_id="56264887"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
The distinctive two-note call of Bulwer's Pheasant Lophura bulweri is
being broadcast over the audio system at New York's Bronx Zoo Pheasant
Aviary as part of the effort to promote mating by the zoo's two males and
one female. Breeding success in captivity with this rare Bornean pheasant
has been universally poor so concerted efforts are being made to simulate
its natural habitat with a view to rectifying this situation.
The calls are broadcast at one-minute intervals from 6.30am - 7.30am
and again between 5.30pm - 6.30pm, because Bulwer's Pheasants tend to
be more active early and late in the day. The zoo also provides the pheasants
with daily rain showers (they breed during the rainy season in Borneo)
together with dust baths which is another important activity. According to
initial observations, both the males and female increase their activity when
the vocalisations are played.
The Bird Department's Assistant Curator, John Rowden has collected
information about the mating habits of this species through research at the
zoo and fieldwork in Borneo. It has been found that it uses a lek breeding
system, whereby the males gather in the same general area and set-up display
arenas while remaining visually isolated from each other.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998049" page_id="56264888"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
44
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9960695" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264888" page_num="44" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp;VIEWS
MOSQUITO-BORNE VIRUS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.933907347826087" page_id="56264888"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
The Wildlife Conservation Society Annual Report 2000 states that the
year was marked by the loss of birds to West Nile virus, and that a great deal
of time was spent dealing with the consequences of these losses and finding
solutions to the problems created by it. The latter included mosquito-proofing
facilities and removing standing water, in addition to which keepers worked
with WCS veterinarians in exploring further ways of protecting and treating
the Bronx Zoo bird collection should West Nile virus recur.
Despite the setback, birds bred during the year included Crested Wood
Partridge Rol lulus roulroul , White-naped Crane Grus vipio. Pink Pigeon
Columba mayeri , Marianas Fruit Dove Ptilinopus roseicapilla, Montezuma
Oropendola Psarocolius montezuma, Fairy Bluebird Irena puella and birds
of paradise Paradisaea spp. The bird department received the AZA Edward
H. Bean Award for long-term breeding of the Red and Lesser Bird of Paradise
P. rubra and P minor. Offspring of the Lesser were sent to Cologne Zoo in
Germany and of the Red to Chester Zoo in England.
The smallest evacuee from the WCS's St Catherines Island Wildlife
Survival Center during Hurricane Floyd, was a three-week old Palm
Cockatoo Probosciger aterrimus, which was being hand-reared and needed
to be fed every two hours. Floyd, as he was named, thrived along with his
sister, Irene; named after the eighth hurricane of 1999. Wattled and Northern
Helmeted Curassows Crax globulosa and C. pauxi were parent reared for
the first time at the center, and a Rhinoceros Hombill Buceros rhinoceros
chick was hatched.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.559011" page_id="56264888"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.902531" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264888" page_num="44" year="" vol="">
WALK OF LIFE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9963414" page_id="56264888"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
Lindy Rodwell and the Wattled Crane Bugeranus carunculatus captive
breeding programme on which she has been working for 10 years in South
Africa, where only about 250 remain in the wild, were the subjects of a two
page illustrated feature in the Telegraph Magazine.
Lindy and her team collect many of the abandoned second eggs, of the
two egg clutches, and hatch them and raise the young for reintroduction to
the wild. During the first weeks the chicks are kept in pens with a heat
lamp, and feather dusters or a stuffed bird for company. They also have
access to outside runs, and because in the wild they leave the nest within
hours of hatching and walk great distances with their parents, the chicks are
kept very active. At 10 weeks old they are moved to a big wetland pen and
two women dressed in crane costumes spend eight hours a day with them,
behaving like the chicks' parents would, walking them great distances
building up their stamina, teaching them how to feed and encouraging them
to fly.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.948271" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264889" page_num="45" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp;VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997428" page_id="56264889"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
45
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99245275" page_id="56264889"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
After much early experimentation and high mortality, released birds are
now integrating successfully with wild cranes and the programme has won
a Whitley Award and received a grant of #40,000 (approx. US$60,000),
which has given it a fantastic boost.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.715006" page_id="56264889"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.875839" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264889" page_num="45" year="" vol="">
ANOTHER FIRST FOR SAN DIEGO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.953698" page_id="56264889"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
Last year seven Long-toed Lapwings Vanellus crassirostris were bred at
San Diego Wild Animal Park. It was the first time this species has been
bred in the USA and it is hoped the birds will be successful again this year.
At present it is the only American collection which exhibits this African
lapwing, which in the wild is almost as adept as jaganas at walking on floating
vegetation as it searches for food. The zoo's pair of Harpy Eagles Harpia
harpyja hatched another chick in the Bird of Prey exhibit. This prolific pair
has produced one or two chicks almost every year for the past six years, two
of which have been released into the wild in Panama.
Sparkling Violet-eared Colibri coruscans and Oasis Hummingbirds
Rhodopis vesper are recent additions to the Hummingbird House at the zoo
and the Hidden Jungle Rainforest exhibit at the wild animal park. Other
additions to the Hidden Jungle exhibit are Northern Spotted Tangara
punctata , Western Bay-headed T. gyrola and Peruvian Blue-necked Tanagers
T. cyanicollis.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.89199" page_id="56264889"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.629931" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264889" page_num="45" year="" vol="">
NUMBERS TUMBLE DOWN UNDER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996237066666667" page_id="56264889"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
Further preliminary findings of the Birds Australia survey reveal that
the Emu Dromaius novaehollandiae population may have declined by more
than 50 percent. Those of the Wedge-tailed Eagle Aquila audax, Brolga
Grus rubicundus, lyrebirds Menura spp. and Scarlet Robin Petroica
multicolor may have declined by up to 40 percent. As the expansion of
urban areas is a major cause of habitat loss, efforts are being made to
determine ways to make gardens more attractive to native birds and encourage
them back into these areas.
A minor recovery is occurring in western New South Wales, following a
five year campaign to exterminate foxes and feral cats, which wreak havoc
among native wildlife. The control programme has resulted in numerous
reports of species not recorded there for more than 20 years, including the
Banded Lapwing Vanellus tricolor and Malleefowl Leipoa ocellata. More
than 160 Malleefowl bred at Western Plains Zoo at Dubbo, have been released
to help boost the population.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996713" page_id="56264890"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
46
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.781526" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264890" page_num="46" year="" vol="">
ROB HARVEY SPECIALIST FEEDS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.2363375" page_id="56264890"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
Everything From Hummingbird Nectar to Elephant food!
Supplying over so Zoological Parks
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.938593" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264890" page_num="46" year="" vol="">
MEALWORMS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99979275" page_id="56264890"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
We sell a complete range of
livefoods &amp; frozen foods.
If you use 51b of mealworms a time then
enquire about our unbeatable trade prices.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.979587" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264890" page_num="46" year="" vol="">
ARCADIA BIRD LAMPS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993764" page_id="56264890"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
Improves feeding and breeding behaviour.
Fits into standard fluorescent fittings or we
can supply fittings and reflectors. j
We can mail order to your door.
Visit our new updated &amp; friendly website www.robharvey.com
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9864125" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264890" page_num="46" year="" vol="">
OVER 1000 WORLD WIDE LINKS!
BREEDERS DIRECTORY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98551575" page_id="56264890"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
vc . . , Advertise your surplus
E-mail us if you want to be J ^
it j , , , i. . stock FREE
added to our breeders directory
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.945648666666667" page_id="56264890"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
WITTE MOLEN TUBS
Moist eggfood - #14.25 5kg
Hedgerow Eggfood - #15.50 5kg
Universal Food - #14.25 5kg
Low Iron for Touracos - #16.25 5kg
Eggfood Red- #15.50 5kg
DRIED FRUITS
Chilean jumbo golden raisins
Iranian whole pitted sair dates
Turkish sultanas &amp; Chilian Flame raisins
Sri Lankan raw thin chip coconut
Philippine whole honey dipped banana chips
Any combination - Delivery included
1kg #5.95 5kg #12.95 10 kg #19.95
WITTE MOLEN
</table>
<figure confidence="0.591546033333333" page_id="56264890"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
PARROT PREMIUM
5kg for #8.00
15kg for #19.75
30kg for only #35.00
AVI-PLUS
LORIKEET
SPECIAL
used by many zoos
#4.95 per kg
AVI-PLUS PARROT
HANDREARING FOOD
used to raise over 10,000 parrots
in South Africa last year alone -
#4.95 per kg
p&amp;p.
#3.95 up to 1kg
#4.95 up to 30kg
HEMP ROPE
As used in zoos and bird parks.
Enhance your bird's environment.
36mm #6.99 per metre or 10m for #55!
24mm #3.45 per metre or 10m for #27!
We also stock
carrying boxes and
stainless steel bowls.
Please ask for our
new price list
Mail order on all products.
-- For our price list or advice please contact
Rob Harvey (ex-owner &amp; curator of Birdworld for over 20 years)
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.924159333333333">
E-mail: admin@robharvey.com Tel: 01420 23986 Fax: 01420 23078
Rob Harvey, Kookaburra House, Gravel Hill Road, Holt Pound,
Famham, Surrey, GU10 4LG.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.996488" page_id="56264891"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
47
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.832215" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264891" page_num="47" year="" vol="">
RICHARD HUGHES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.876986166666667" page_id="56264891"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
Richard Hughes, who (with Andrew Owen) described Hand-rearing the
Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber (Avicultural Magazine , Vol.94, Nos.l &amp; 2,
pp.96-100 (1988)) and who wrote about Hand-rearing the Crimson-ramped
Toucanet Aulacorhynchus haematopygus at Padstow Bird Gardens, Cornwall
(Avicultural Magazine , Vol.94, No.4, pp. 183-189 (1988)), died February
17th, days after being struck by one of the elephants he was working with at
Chester Zoo. Richard was just 34.
His career began in 1984, when he went to work at Guilsborough Zoo.
Later he moved to Padstow Bird Gardens here in Cornwall, where he became
head keeper, and then joined the staff at Beale Park, near Reading, Berks.
Richard went onto complete an environmental degree at Keele University
and set-up a bird-rearing service, hand-rearing parrots. Knowing of this, I
asked him to review the video Hand Rearing Parrots with Rosemary Low
and Rob Harvey. Richard's review was published in the Avicultural
Magazine , Vol.103, No.2, p.92 (1997).
When Raymond Sawyer was looking for a keeper for the collection at
Cobham, I had no hesitation in recommending Richard, who was then
working at Chester Zoo. However, when I telephoned Richard to talk to
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999159" page_id="56264892"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
48
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99414025" page_id="56264892"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
him about working with the wonderful collection of birds at Cobham, he
was very excited about having recently transferred to the elephant section at
Chester, and very much wanted to continue working with the elephants and
living at home, so he could continue to look after his parrots he kept there.
The accident and his subsequent death came as a great shock. All those
I have spoken to have had nothing but praise for Richard, both as a keeper
and as a person. Dr Roger Wilkinson described him as 'a lovely person' and
Peg Brown at Padstow, said repeatedly, 'you couldn't meet a nicer person
than Richard.'
We offer out sincere condolences to his parents (his father Brian is
Administrator of the NCA (National Council for Aviculture)), brother and
sister, and girl friend, Julie.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.443625">
Malcolm Ellis
</subsectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.911447" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264892" page_num="48" year="" vol="">
COUNCIL MEETING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.988821115384615" page_id="56264892"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
A council meeting was held on Sunday, September 17th at Twycross
Zoo, Warwickshire.
The following members were present: K. Dolton, Prof. J. R. Hodges,
C.J.S. Marler, R.C.J. Sawyer (Vice Presidents), K. J. Lawrence (Chairman),
R.H. Grantham, N. Hewston, Mrs D. Holloway, R. E. Oxley, S. Pyper.
Minutes of the previous meeting were approved following the addition
of N. Hewston to the list of apologies for absence.
The Hon. Editor sent a written report. The council passed a vote of
thanks to him for maintaining the standard of the magazine and improving
the frequency with which issues are sent out. He was asked to explore ways
of increasing the number of Letters to the Editor suitable for publication in
the magazine.
There was no report from the Hon. Secretary/Treasurer, but members of
the council were of the opinion that the society remains in a financially
sound position.
The Hon. Editor reported that there has been a good response to the
society's website (www.avisoc.co.uk). He is to attempt to establish a bird
exchange list and investigate the possibility of selling advertising space on
the website.
Election of Officers: K. W. Dolton was re-elected a Vice President for a
further five year term. G. R. Greed was re-elected Hon. Secretary/Treasurer
for a further five year term, and R. E. Oxley was re-elected to the council for
a further five year term.
The society's Certificate of Merit was awarded to Birdworld for the first
breeding in Great Britain or Ireland of the Southern Helmeted Curassow Pauxi
unicornis unicornis (Avicultural Magazine, Vol.104, No.4, pp. 152-156).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.987701" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264893" page_num="" year="" vol="">
PIONUS RESEARCH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98833435" page_id="56264893"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
As so little is known about the diets, breeding habits and general
behaviour of the Pionus parrots in the wild, in 1999 a group of Pionus keepers
and others interested in these small Central and South American parrots
founded the Pionus Parrots Research Foundation. Its goals are to conduct,
support and fund amateur and professional research on the parrots of this
genus and share the information gathered with scientific and avicultural
communities and other interested parties.
It funded its first trip in the autumn of 1999. This was to Mindo in
Ecuador, to explore the possiblities of studying Pionus species in the wild.
Such was the success of this preliminary study that another visit to Mindo
recently took place. A group of 10 aviculturists, biologists and students
from the USA, Costa Rica and Ecuador planned to observe and record data
about populations, feeding behaviour, flock behaviour, and locate nest sites,
as part of the Bronze-winged Parrot Study. It also hoped to examine what
effect flocks of Bronzed-winged P. chalcopterus , Coral-billed P. sordidus
and White-headed P. seniloides Parrots have on local agricultural
communities. The Pionus Parrot Research Fund needs to raise over US$7,000
(approx. #5,000) and is seeking donations, which can be as little as US$5 -
US$20 (approx. #3.50-#14), to help fund its work. If you would like to
learn more or make a donation you can contact: - Russell W. Slade, Managing
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.735436666666667" page_id="56264893"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Director, Pionus Parrots Research Foundation, PO. Box 34, Danielsville,
PA 18038, USA. Tel: 610 767-8595 (evenings)/e-mail: rshade@fast.net/
website: www.fatparrots.org
* * *
NEW SUBSPECIES
The Red-billed Hombill Tockus erythrorhynchus , over most of its range,
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.994232428571428" page_id="56264893"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
has pale yellow or pink facial skin. However, in Senegal, The Gambia and
western Mali, where all Red-billed Hornbills are usually regarded as
belonging to the nominate subspecies, all adults have black facial bare skin
and brown eyes. Studies suggest that these black-faced/brown-eyed birds
from the western-most part of Africa belong to a yet undescribed subspecies.
It is proposed to name it T. e. kempi, in honour of Dr Alan Kemp, who was
first to call attention to the existence of these black-faced birds.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.62304" page_id="56264893"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.950001" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264893" page_num="" year="" vol="">
QUAIL NUMBERS DECLINE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9586312" page_id="56264893"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Some species of quail, including the Northern Bobwhite Colinus
virginianus in the east and the Scaled Quail Callipepla squamata in the
south-west USA, are suffering serious population declines according to Frank
Gill of the National Audubon Society, quoted in Birdscope, Winter 2001/
Vol.15, No.l, p.4.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.926543" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264894" page_num="" year="" vol="">
SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION LIBRARIES
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.96020736" page_id="56264894"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
3 9088 01769 6410
CONTENTS
Breeding the Blue-bellied Roller
by R. C. J. Sawyer.1
An examination of potential reasons for variation in egg-laying
cycles of Wattled Cranes
by Nicole R. Bohlman.4
Notes on behaviour and ecological requirements of the
Rothschild's Mynah Leucopsar rothschildi
by Walter A. Sontag Jr.10
Breeding the Grey-winged Trumpeter Psophia crepitans
by Rosemary Low.21
Breeding the Mali or Kulikoro Firefinch Lagonosticta virata
by Ian Hinze.27
The Spring Social Meeting
by Stewart Pyper.35
The President's Garden Party 2000
by Stewart Pyper.36
The Society's Autumn Social Meeting
by Stewart Pyper.38
Book Reviews
Threatened Birds Of The World.39
Wildlife Guide To Hawaii.41
News &amp; Views.42
Obituary - Richard Hughes
</table>
<page confidence="0.85378" page_id="56264894"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
47
</page>
<figure confidence="0.89743925" page_id="56264894"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Council Meeting
48
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</figure>
</algorithms>
