<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.6683125" page_id="56260817"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
X? /
VICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 111
No. 3
2005
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260818" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990424428571429" page_id="56260818"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2005 as for 2004: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.617273" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260818" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE..
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.968854318181818" page_id="56260818"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, ARCADIA, THE MOUNTS, TOTNES, DEVON TQ9 7QJ, UK.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TNI 3 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail: Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998476" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260818" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982477333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7334825" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260819" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<category confidence="0.370989">
VoL 111 - No. 3 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2005
</category>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.973324" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260819" page_num="" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE DESERT FINCH Rhodopechys obsoleta
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.945457620689655" page_id="56260819"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Jeffrey Trollope
This attractive Palearctic species was listed by Howard &amp; Moore (1980)
as Lichenstein's Desert Finch and is also known as the Black-billed Finch.
It measures 14cm- 16cm (5 3 /4in-6V4in) in length. The plumage is mainly
pale greyish-buff. The flight feathers are black with white edgings and
there is a vivid pink area on the coverts and base of the secondaries. The tail
feathers are black with white edges. The bill is black and the male has a
black line from the base of the bill to the eye. The female is paler with the
pink area on the coverts and base of the secondaries smaller and duller. She
lacks the black line from the base of the bill to the eye.
R. obsoleta is monotypic. Its range extends from the Middle East through
Afghanistan to central Mongolia. In the northern and eastern parts of its
range it migrates in the autumn. In the southern and western areas it
undertakes short distance dispersal movements away from its breeding areas.
The habitat of the Desert Finch varies from dry plains and semi-desert to
cultivated land such as orchards and vineyards. Clement et al. (1991) noted
that it avoids open sandy or stony deserts. In the Central Asian part of its
range it can be found in orchards and gardens in the middle of large cities.
Aviculture
The first breeding of the Desert Finch in the UK occurred in 1990 (Coles,
2001). Since then it has been listed as having been bred in six of the years
between 1990-2003 (The Foreign Bird Federation Register of Birds Bred in
the UK under Controlled Conditions). The highest number recorded was
12 in 2003 and the lowest was one in 1990 and 2002, respectively. I have
been told of two other breedings which apparently have not been included
in the Register. I am sure that every year there are many breedings across
the taxonomic spectrum which are not reported. (. Later in this magazine
two Desert Finches are reported as having been bred at Paignton Zoo
Environmental Park in 2004. -Ed.).
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999433" page_id="56260820"  page_num="98" year="" vol="">
98
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.733393" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260820" page_num="98" year="" vol="">
TROLLOPE - DESERT FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97717269047619" page_id="56260820"  page_num="98" year="" vol="">
Breeding
In May 1993 I purchased pair of Desert Finches (pair A) from a company
selling birds and all types of avicultural supplies. After three weeks in
isolation in a birdroom they were ringed (banded) with plastic I/D rings and
released into an aviary measuring approximately 3. lm x 1.2m x 2.4m high
(10ft x 4ft x 8ft high). This was one of a block of three aviaries. The roof,
back and sides of the block were covered in translucent plastic panels. The
front, including the doors, consisted of wire mesh panels. Each door had an
access hatch and a platform approximately 1.2m (4ft) above the ground for
food and water containers. A second hatch gave access at ground level.
With all newly acquired birds I offer a wide range of seeds, from
pannicum millet to small sunflower seed. An insectivorous softbill mixture,
egg food and greenfood are also always provided. In addition, mini
mealworms and waxworm larvae are available at all times. A banana-based
fruit fly culture is viable outside from the end of April-September. Seeding
grasses are collected during the season.
I have noticed that some of the Palearctic finches I have bred have been
reluctant to eat livefood, especially commercially bred livefood, such as
mealworms. This protein source can be replaced by a softfood mixture and
in other ways, if the birds will eat such foods.
Cut branches, mostly from conifers, were hung at the rear of the aviary.
Cup-shaped wire baskets and half-open wooden nest-boxes of various sizes
were hung up at different sites and heights around the aviary. These sites
were screened with small cuttings from conifers. Nesting material provided
included coconut fibres, grass stems, fine twigs, feathers and moss.
From June-July pair A was very active. The male sang and was frequently
observed courtship feeding the female. She began to build a nest in a cup-
shaped wire basket sited close to the roof of the aviary. The nest consisted
of coconut fibres along with fine grass stems and a few twigs. Often the
male would sit in the nest with the female.
By late June five eggs had been laid. The female was the tightest sitter
of any of the species I have bred. Owing to the height of the nest site (just
under 2.4m (8ft) above the ground) I had to use a pair of steps to reach the
nest. Even then, I had to use a finger to gently push her off the eggs so that
I could examine them. She had resumed sitting before I had time to climb
back down.
After some 16 days of possible incubation, she gave up sitting and the
eggs proved to be infertile. A the end of July both birds went into a heavy
moult. It was also noticeable that the female's bill had faded from black to
yellowish horn. At the end of October I removed both birds to a birdroom
for the winter.
Pair A was released into the same aviary in April 1994. The aviary block
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.649868" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260821" page_num="99" year="" vol="">
TROLLOPE - DESERT FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997896" page_id="56260821"  page_num="99" year="" vol="">
99
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997925833333333" page_id="56260821"  page_num="99" year="" vol="">
was later damaged by wind, so I gave the pair to a local bird keeper who had
space available. I purchased another pair (pair B) in April 2002. As there
was no aviary space available at that time I housed the pair in my birdroom.
On May 17th 2003 pair B was released into an aviary of the same
dimensions, structure and layout as that previously described for pair A.
The nest sites, receptacles, food and feeding were as close as possible to
those that had been provided for pair A. Within minutes of the release of
pair B into the aviary the male began to sing. Both birds gave a flight call
similar to the " tchirrip " of the House Martin Delichon urbica , and also a
purring "prrreee" contact call. The male sang constantly and was often
seen courtship feeding the female. Both birds began to take coconut fibres
and grass stems to a cup-shaped wire basket close to the roof of the 2.4m
(8ft) high aviary. The nest was completed in about three days.
Both birds would sit on the nest, for short periods with the male almost
sitting on top of the female. He would also sit on the rim of the nest basket.
Like the female of pair A she was also a close sitter. The male would feed
her whilst she was sitting. Whilst she was incubating, I saw her off the nest
only on two occasions, both times to feed herself.
Incubation appeared to commence on May 29th. Again I had to use
steps to inspect the nest and, as with the female of pair A, I had to gently
push her off the nest to do so. She sat on a nearby conifer twig whilst I
inspected her clutch of five eggs. These were pale blue marked, mostly at
the larger end, with black and purplish-black dots and fine lines.
The female was totally tolerant of my nest inspection and was covering
her eggs again by the time I had started to climb back down. Before I was
out of the aviary the male was sitting alongside her at the nest site.
On June 12th I found a piece of eggshell on the aviary floor. I had a
quick look in the nest and found that five chicks had hatched, which I judged
to be three or four days old. Their gapes were pale pinkish-red with the
gape flanges very pale yellow. Their skin was grey with greyish and light
pink down. I have found that the skin colour of some finches and related
forms changes during the nestling period.
The female brooded the chicks until they were about eight days old,
with the male tirelessly taking food to the nest. They fed the chicks on seed,
seeding grasses, softfood and eggfood. I never saw them take any livefood
to the nest or eat any themselves.
On June 13th the pair started taking material to a new nest site. This was
a half-open-fronted box that was fixed to the side of the aviary at a height of
1.2m (4ft). The nest was made of coconut fibres, grass stems, twigs and a
few feathers. The first egg of a five egg clutch was laid on June 14th. The
male continued to feed the chicks at the first nest site and they were also fed
occasionally by the female.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.956398" page_id="56260822"  page_num="100" year="" vol="">
100
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.817385" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260822" page_num="100" year="" vol="">
TROLLOPE - DESERT FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.975431806451613" page_id="56260822"  page_num="100" year="" vol="">
On June 25th I found two chicks from the first brood dead on the aviary
floor. A third chick was dead in the nest. The two surviving chicks were
perched on conifer twigs near the first nest site. They solicited food by
calling " whit-whit " with their wings flapping. Their bills were a light
yellowish horn and their upperparts were a light brownish colour, with the
belly and abdomen greyish shading to whitish grey. Their wings and tail
were not fully developed. The tail feathers, primaries and secondaries were
blackish with a narrow dull white edging. There is a faint pinkish wash on
the secondaries.
On June 30th the second clutch of five eggs hatched. The male began to
feed the chicks, he also continued feeding the two surviving chicks of the
first brood. On July 1 st one chick of the second brood died and a second
died on July 4th. On July 5th the two surviving chicks from the first brood
were feeding themselves and seemed fit, so I removed them to the birdroom.
From that date the remaining chicks from the second brood were fed by
both parents. The male was the most dedicated 'feeder', but inspite of his
efforts a third chick died on July 7th. The remaining two chicks thrived.
They left the nest on July 14th and were feeding themselves by July 21st.
They were removed to the birdroom on July 23rd. The parents (pair B)
were removed to the birdroom on October 15th for the winter.
On May 1st 2004 pair B was released into the same size and type of
aviary as that occupied in 2003. The male was singing and courtship feeding
the female until May 24th. On May 29th a nest had been completed in a
half-open box fixed to the side of the aviary at a height of just under 2.4m
(8ft). The nest consisted of coconut fibres, grass stems, a few twigs, feathers
and moss.
The first egg of a clutch of four eggs was laid on June 1 st. All four eggs
hatched on June 14th. As with the previous broods in 2003 no livefood was
fed to the chicks, although it was always available. The rearing of the chicks
was trouble-free. They left the nest on June 29th and were feeding themselves
on July 15th and were removed to the birdroom.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.960677">
Table 1. Pair B breeding results 2003-2004.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.997493730769231" page_id="56260822"  page_num="100" year="" vol="">
Year
Clutch
No.
No. of
eggs
Hatched
Chicks
fledged
Reared to
independence
2003
1
5
5
4
2
2
5
5
5
2
2004
1
4
4
4
</figure>
<page confidence="0.821937" page_id="56260822"  page_num="100" year="" vol="">
4
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.955423666666667" page_id="56260822"  page_num="100" year="" vol="">
The Desert Finch has many virtues for the aviculturist. It can be sexed
visually and once established thrives in an aviary environment. Here in the
UK it is desirable even for established birds to be kept in a birdroom between
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.64981" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260823" page_num="101" year="" vol="">
TROLLOPE - DESERT FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999305" page_id="56260823"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
101
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9992142" page_id="56260823"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
October-April/May, with heat available as required. The Desert Finch is a
willing breeder which is tolerant of nest inspection. Problems can arise if a
pair have two overlapping broods. This could be solved by hand-rearing, a
practise I personally do not favour unless it is to maintain stocks of
endangered species or for release programmes etc.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.927435" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56260823" page_num="101" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.723167714285714" page_id="56260823"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
Clement, R, Harris, A. and Davis, J. 1993. Finches and Sparrows. Christopher Helm/A &amp; C
Black, London.
Coles, D. 2001. Additions and Corrections to UK First Breeding Records. AviculturalMagazine
107,3:125-135.
Foreign Bird Federation. 1999-2003. Register of Birds Bred in the UK Under Controlled
Conditions.
Howard, R. and Moore, A. 1980. A Complete Checklist of the Birds of the World. Oxford
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.518887" page_id="56260823"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
University Press, Oxford, New York, Toronto, Melbourne.
Avicultural Society Council Member Jeffrey Trollope has achieved a
number of UK first breedings and is the author of Seed-eating Birds their
Care and Breeding. Blandford, London.
* * *
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.892766333333333" page_id="56260823"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
D. H. S. RISDON AWARD
The winner of the D. H. S. Risdon Award for 2004, was B. N. Lowde for
My Woodcock Study ( Avicultural Magazine Vol.110, No.2, pp. 82-90 &amp;
Vol.110, No.3, pp. 130-139, 2004), which at the recent Avicultural Society
Council Meeting, held at Paignton Zoo Environmental Park on Saturday,
September 24th, was considered to have been the best article published in
the magazine last year. After much discussion, when it came to the vote, it
was narrowly ahead of Luis J. Ortiz Merry's account of The Hand-rearing
of an Umbrellabird ( Avicultural Magazine Vol. 110, No.3, pp. 108-115,2004).
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.448373" page_id="56260823"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.715611" genericHeader="introduction" page_id="56260823" page_num="101" year="" vol="">
DULCIE COOKE AWARD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.87931325" page_id="56260823"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
The Dulcie Cooke Award for 2004, went to Luis J. Ortiz Merry for his
photos of the umbrellabird chick, used to illustrate his account of the hand-
rearing of an umbrellabird at Centro de Aclimitacion Zoologica, Santiago,
Chile.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999271" page_id="56260824"  page_num="102" year="" vol="">
102
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.874218666666667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260824" page_num="102" year="" vol="">
AFRICAN BIRD SAFARI -
LONDON ZOO'S NEW WALK-THROUGH AVIARY
by John Ellis
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995073828571429" page_id="56260824"  page_num="102" year="" vol="">
As a visitor to London Zoo one of the first exhibits you will see is the
Stork and Ostrich House. Built in 1896, the house has over the last 109
years been home to an amazing variety of species including cassowaries,
ostriches, cranes, Shoebill Stork Balaeniceps rex , kiwis and even Pygmy
Hippopotamus Hexaprotodon liberiensis. In the early 1990s the exterior
paddocks were re-fenced and landscaped and housed a number of other
species including the zoo's successful colonies of Abdim's Stork Ciconia
abdimii and Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber.
As the aviaries had become in need of extensive restoration, last year we
took the opportunity to update the area to allow maximum living space for
the birds and give our visitors the chance to get really close to the birds by
creating an inspiring walk-through experience.
Moving home
In October the aviaries' occupants were removed and housed in temporary
winter accommodation while the site was cleared. The blueprint showed an
ambitious new 10m (approx. 32ft) tall aviary covering the entire area in
front of the house. Extensive work was also undertaken to upgrade the
indoor areas so as to create a new environment for the storks. Constructing
the aviary during the winter months was timed so as to allow the birds to be
returned to the aviary, for new occupants to be added and for the birds to
acclimatise to the new set-up with visitors walking into the aviary, in time
for the 2005 summer season.
The new aviary
The new aviary is 51m long x 10m at its highest point (approx. 167ft
long x 32ft at its highest point) and offers a huge flying space for the birds
and thanks to new materials, the aviary is light and airy. For the most part it
is covered in an extremely strong nylon mesh, which not only allows
maximum visibility but also has some flexibility. The interior wood utilised
for the banking and entry/exit vestibules is recycled non-treated hardwood
Indian railway sleepers. A filtration system operates in the large pool and
'foggers' are strategically placed under the bridge to add both a visual element
for the visitors and to provide a humid atmosphere for the poolside plants.
Although there is still a great deal of growing needed, the planting already
looks green and vibrant and acts as the perfect backdrop for the birds,
providing shelter, nesting places and, for the waterfowl, food.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.701867" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260825" page_num="103" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - NEW WALK-THROUGH AVIARY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997347" page_id="56260825"  page_num="103" year="" vol="">
103
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.52845" page_id="56260825"  page_num="103" year="" vol="">
London Zoo's new walk-through aviary.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999671" page_id="56260826"  page_num="104" year="" vol="">
104
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.88662" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260826" page_num="104" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - NEW WALK-THROUGH AVIARY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.901134868421052" page_id="56260826"  page_num="104" year="" vol="">
The birds
Occupants of the new aviary include Hamerkop Scopus umbretta ,
Abdim's Stork, Scarlet Ibis, White-faced Whistling Duck Dendrocygna
viduata , Comb Duck Sarkidiornis melanotus, Madagascar Teal Anas bernieri ,
Lilac-breasted Roller Coracias caudata , Blue-bellied Roller C. cyanogaster,
Von der Decken's Hombill Tockus deckeni , Hartlaub's Turaco Tauraco
hartlaubi and Superb Starling Spreo superbus. For the sharp-eyed,
geographically aware, the flock of Scarlet Ibis may come as a shock because
they are definitely not African. They are merely short-term lodgers and we
are hoping to be able to house them in a new aviary very soon. In the
meantime, they have settled in extremely well and are proving to be one of
the most popular birds in the aviary.
Planning and management
When we were planning how to utilise and manage such a large space,
we identified that the keepers would need some way of being able to check
the birds at close quarters or get them into the indoor aviaries with the
minimum of fuss and stress. A training programme was implemented and
this was geared to accustoming the birds to go into the off-view indoor
areas when they heard a certain sound. In addition, the keepers working in
the aviary have trained the birds to come to them and feed close up, which
not only allows the keepers to check the birds are well without having to
catch them, but also gives visitors the opportunity to get to know some of
the birds such as the hombills and rollers.
Settling in
All new ventures need a period of bedding in and time will allow us to
observe how well the birds have settled into their new home. Already the
signs are positive - in the first six months the Abdim's Storks and Madagascar
Teal bred and the White-faced Whistling Ducks and Von der Decken's
Hombills attempted to breed but were unsuccessful. The Superb Starlings
were nest building within 48 hours of being released into the aviary.
African Bird Safari - London Zoo s New Walk-Through Aviary by John
Ellis, Curator of Birds, Zoological Society of London (e-mail: John, ellis
@zsl.org) is based closely on - Flight of Fantasy London Zoos African Bird
Safari is already proving to be a great success - which John wrote for
Lifewatch (Summer 2005, pp. 8-9), the magazine for members and supporters
of the Zoological Society of London. It is reproduced here with the approval
of Debbie Curtis, Aquarium and Internal Communications Manager, ZSL,
who also kindly supplied the photo of the aviary.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.983651" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260827" page_num="105" year="" vol="">
PAIGNTON ZOO ENVIRONMENTAL PARK
&amp; LIVING COASTS BREEDING REVIEW - 2004
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999107" page_id="56260827"  page_num="105" year="" vol="">
105
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.947077041666667" page_id="56260827"  page_num="105" year="" vol="">
by Colin Bath
Last year was an important year for the collection as it was the first full
breeding season for Living Coasts, our large marine/coastal exhibit on the
Torbay seafront. The most notable breeding there, the first breeding in the
UK of the Pigeon Guillemot Cepphus columba, was described in the previous
issue (Avicultural Magazine Vol. Ill, No.2, pp. 53-55 (2005)). Of special
note also were the park's repeated success with the Southern Cassowary
Casuarius casuarius , the breeding of the Socorro Dove Zenaida graysoni
which is extinct in the wild and the rearing of a large number of Azure-
winged Magpie Cyanopica cyana. The rearing of several smaller species
such as the Orange-headed Ground Thrush Zoothera citrina , Desert Finch
Rhodopechys obsoleta and Striated Mousebird Colius striatus, might be of
interest to private aviculturists, who perhaps cannot relate to keeping birds
such as penguins and cranes.
There were one or two disappointments, our breeding female Ural Owl
Strix uralensis died after many successful nests and in spite of hatching
several Hooded Pittas Pitta sordida , we had problems rearing them, though
we think we have now solved these particular problems.
Several species bred for the first time in the collection, with the breeding
of the Pigeon Guillemot also being the UK first breeding of this species (as
stated above), and the breeding of the Grey Gull Larus modestus (described
later in the magazine) and the Sulawesi White-eye Zosterops consobrinorum ,
probably also being UK first breedings.
Breeding results for 2004
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.827455928571429" page_id="56260827"  page_num="105" year="" vol="">
2 Southern Cassowary Casuarius casuarius
8 Jackass/African Penguin Spheniscus demersus (LC)
6 Little Egret Egretta garzetta
4 Common Shelduck Tadorna tadorna
7 Chestnut Teal Anas castanea
4 Meller's Duck Anas melleri
22 Laysan Teal Anas laysanensis
5 Chiloe Wigeon Anas sibilatrix
2 Ringed Teal Callonetta leucophrys
6 Rosy-billed Pochard Netta peposaca
23 Red-crested Pochard Netta rufina
21 Mandarin Duck A ix galericulata
17 Carolina/Wood Duck A ix sponsa
1 Bare-faced Curassow Crax fasciolata
</figure>
<address confidence="0.369574">
106 BATH - PAIGNTON ZOO BREEDING REVIEW
</address>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.904015" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260828" page_num="106" year="" vol="">
6 Speckled Pigeon Columba guinea
12 Red/Dwarf Turtle Dove Streptopelia tranquebarica
6 Turtle Dove Streptopelia turtur
</sectionHeader>
<footnote confidence="0.6526364">
1 Emerald Dove Chalcophaps indica
13 Socorro Dove Zenaida graysoni
5 Crested Quail Dove Geotrygon versicolor
3 Pied Imperial Pigeon Ducula bicolor
1 Palawan Peacock-Pheasant Polyplectron emphanum
2 Scaled Quail Callipepla squamata
1 Red-crowned Crane Grus japonensis
2 White-naped Crane Grus vipio
1 Grey-winged Trumpeter Psophia crepitans
1 Red-legged Seriema Cariama cristata
</footnote>
<figure confidence="0.945837407407407" page_id="56260828"  page_num="106" year="" vol="">
13 Redshank Tringa totanus (LC)
12 Pied Avocet Recurvirostra avosetta (LC)
2 Grey Gull Larus modestus
10 Inca Tern Larosterna inca (LC)
1 Pigeon Guillemot Cepphus columba (LC)
2 Princess of Wales Parakeet Polytelis alexandrae
2 Hooded Parakeet Psephotus dissimilis
5 Bourke's Parakeet Neophema bourkii
2 Yellow-shouldered Amazon Amazona barbadensis
2 Red-tailed Amazon Amazona brasiliensis
2 Green-crested Turaco Tauraco persa
2 Great Grey Owl Strix nebulosa
2 Ural Owl Strix uralensis
24 Speckled Mousebird Colius striatus
2 Blue-crowned Motmot Momotus momota
1 Red-vented Bulbul Pycnonotus cafer
5 Orange-headed Ground Thrush Zoothera citrina
1 Pekin Robin/Red-billed Leiothrix Leiothrix lutea
1 Sulawesi White-eye Zosterops consobrinorum
2 Desert Finch Rhodopechys obsoleta
8 Cut-throat Finch Amadina fasciata
4 Superb Starling Spreo superbus
6 Bali Starling Leucospar rothschildi
30 Azure-winged Magpie Cyanopica cyana
2 Red-billed Chough Pyrrhocoraxpyrrhocorax
(LC) denotes bred at Living Coasts, all other species were bred at Paignton
Zoo Environmental Park.
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.908153333333333">
Colin Bath is Curator of Birds &amp; Reptiles at Paignton Zoo Environmental
Park, Totnes Road, Paignton, Devon TQ4 7EU, UK. Website:
www. paigntonzoo. org. uk
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999342" page_id="56260829"  page_num="107" year="" vol="">
107
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.620824" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260829" page_num="107" year="" vol="">
THE GREY-WINGED TRUMPETER Psophia crepitans
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.981888205128205" page_id="56260829"  page_num="107" year="" vol="">
by Jo Gregson
The rarely bred Grey-winged Trumpeter (according to Dave Coles'
breeding records it was first bred in the UK by Will Harrison in 1986) was
once a common sight in zoos and private collections. Now, however, it is
seldom seen and is sought by many public and private collections/
aviculturists.
There are three species of trumpeter, the other two being the White-
winged P. leucoptera and Green-winged P. viridis, all of which are found
living deep in forest in South America. They are certainly not shy birds and
are often kept as pets by South Americans, who sometimes run them with
their chickens to act as watchbirds. Their calls warn their owners when a
snake or other predator is approaching. It is this call that has earned the
trumpeters their name; until quite recently it was thought that the sound was
made by wind passing through the cloaca, but this of course is not the case.
Trumpeters live in groups, each group having a large territory in which
the birds spend the day feeding on rotting fruits found scattered on the forest
floor and often rummaging below trees in which capuchin and spider
monkeys are feeding. The parties of monkeys lack table manners and many
of the fruits are carelessly dropped onto the forest floor below where the
trumpeters are eagerly waiting.
Polyandry, wherein a female mates with two or more males, is unusual
among birds, but this is the case with trumpeters, where within each group
there is only one dominant female and all dominant males mate with her.
Males of less importance may get the chance of a sneaky mating, while
unimportant males have no chance at all The latter will sometimes join
another group to improve their social standing. All the group will protect
and feed the dominant female while she is laying but once she begins
incubation only the most dominant male will feed her, although he will take
food from other group members to pass on to her.
In captivity trumpeters are usually kept in pairs, so are unable to carry
out their full breeding behaviours and this may be one of the reasons why
they rarely breed. Males often do not reach full breeding condition and fail
to fertilise the eggs. As with many males a little competition does wonders
for testosterone levels.
Here at Paignton Zoo Environmental Park we have bred the Grey-winged
Trumpeter for the past two years. During the summer months they are housed
in a large densely planted aviary, then each winter the birds are brought
inside and housed in a much smaller heated enclosure. Being such confiding
birds the move does not distress them and we have found that they reach
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999548" page_id="56260830"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
108
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.919518" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260830" page_num="108" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - GREY-WINGED TRUMPETER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9986426875" page_id="56260830"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
breeding condition early in the year, sporting their green legs by the end of
February. In previous years the birds had been kept in their summer quarters
all year round, and even though they had a heated shelter, the male did not
colour-up until May.
All eggs are removed and broody bantams are used to incubate them
until the first pip, when they are moved to a wet incubator for hatching. The
incubation period is 25 days. During the hatching it is vital to keep the
humidity high. Once they have hatched and are dry the chicks are moved
into a small rearing box, which has a substrate of wood bark and small logs.
Trumpeter chicks do not pick up food for several days and for this reason
we do not use bantams to rear them. Chicks are fed a mixed diet of young
mice, ox heart, fruit and boiled egg sprinkled with Nutrobal calcium/vitamin
powder. All food is offered by hand for at least the first week. As with all
long-legged young birds, exercise is extremely important and as soon as the
chicks are strong enough they are taken outside each day for a walk, being
quite happy to follow their keeper.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.618446555555556" page_id="56260830"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
Jo Gregson is Senior Head Keeper of Birds at Paignton Zoo
Environmental Park, Totnes Road, Paignton, Devon TQ4 7EU, UK.
Tel:01803 697500/Fax:01803 523457/Website:www.paigntonzoo.org.uk/
E-mail :jgregson@paigntonzoo. org. uk
In the Avicultural Magazine Vol.107, No.1, pp.21-26 (2001), Rosemary
Low described raising Grey-winged Trumpeters at Palmitos Park, Gran
Canaria, and included chick weights and colour photos of a newly hatched
chick, an eight day old chick and two aged about three weeks.
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.844" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56260830" page_num="108" year="" vol="">
SPECIFICALLY DISTINCT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99334" page_id="56260830"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
The Mali or Kulikoro Firefinch Lagonosticta virata has for a considerable
time now been regarded as specifically distinct. Bates, in 1932, described it
as a new subspecies of the African or Blue-billed Firefinch L. rubricata.
However, in Estrildid Finches of the World (British Museum (Natural
History), 1982) our member Derek Goodwin, based on its call and broad
outer primary, considered it a subspecies of Jameson's Firefinch L.
rhodopareia. Recent field observations and molecular analysis confirm it
is specifically distinct and that it is more closely related to the Rock Firefinch
L. sanguinodorsalis and Jameson's Firefinch than to the African or Blue-
billed species, according to Robert B. Payne writing about the Mali Firefinch
in the Bulletin of the African Bird Club Vol.12, No.2, pp. 168-169, August
2005.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999355" page_id="56260831"  page_num="109" year="" vol="">
109
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7659675" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260831" page_num="109" year="" vol="">
NOTES ON A SHORT VISIT TO PENINSULAR MALAYSIA
by Rosemary Low
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.966293133333333" page_id="56260831"  page_num="109" year="" vol="">
Peninsula Malaysia is the southern part of the Malay Peninsular between
southern Thailand to the north and Singapore to the south. I had been to
Singapore many times to visit the world-famous Jurong BirdPark and had
promised myself that one day I would go birdwatching on the peninsular.
Seeing large hombills on the wing must surely be one of the most impressive
sights in the avian kingdom.
Many years ago the peninsula was entirely covered by lush rainforest,
much of which was replaced with rubber and tea plantation by settlers and,
more recently, has been planted with monotonous groves of oil palms. Virgin
forest survives in national parks, the best known of which is Taman Negara
in the eastern-central part of the peninsula. At least 270 species of birds
occur there. It was declared a conservation area in 1938, and named then
the King George V National Park. Now the country's premier national park,
it covers 1,676sq miles (4,343sq km) - an area slightly larger than the county
of Kent, in south-east England.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.2696105">
Copyright Rosemary Low
Taman Negara National Park.
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98916075" page_id="56260831"  page_num="109" year="" vol="">
There is a very attractive resort there that can be reached by a 2V2-hour
boat trip from Kuala Tembeling. It is near the town of Jerantut, a 4-hour
drive from Kuala Lumpur. On the right side of the river the forests of the
national park stretch for many miles (km). The left bank is also forested,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996765" page_id="56260832"  page_num="110" year="" vol="">
110
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.650628" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260832" page_num="110" year="" vol="">
LOW - PENINSULAR MALAYSIA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998336642857143" page_id="56260832"  page_num="110" year="" vol="">
but has signs of human habitation. I was with a group of eight birdwatchers,
plus a very knowledgeable guide. On the river journey the sight of a
Rhinoceros Hombill Buceros rhinoceros flying above the canopy filled us
with excitement and anticipation. This is the largest and arguably the most
magnificent of the Malaysian species with its black and white plumage and
huge red and yellow bill and casque. During the following few days we had
more sightings of single birds and of pairs and learned to distinguish this
species' "kronk krank" duetting calls when in flight, the pitch of the call
being different in male and female.
After travelling 38 miles (60km) upriver, with occasional glimpses of
people of the Orang Asli tribe, we reached the park's headquarters and the
lodge at Kuala Tahan. Buildings located near the landing stage include a
spacious restaurant, reception area and a small shop. Attractive wooden
cabins are set around a clearing in the forest, one of which was to be my
home for the next four days. Not far away, hidden by trees, flows the busy
Sungai Tembeling (river), the main thoroughfare. Every now and then a
flash of blue indicated a White-throated Kingfisher Halcyon smyrnensis was
active.
The shrill whistling calls of Magpie Robins Copsychus saularis pierced
the dawn and scarcely ceased until sunset. These songsters occupy much
the same ecological niche as our own European Robin Erithacus rubecula,
being familiar garden birds, darting around on the lookout for insects, first
on the ground, then on a higher vantage point. The male is of course a
handsome black and white and the female is attired in sombre shades of
grey and white.
Not far from my cabin a Bauhinia tree was flowering, its gorgeous pink
blooms attracting nectar-feeding species such as the Little Spiderhunter
Arachnothera longirostra, which was making a "chip chip" call as it moved
within the tree. It was joined by a tiny (8cm (SVdn)) female flowerpecker,
its bright red rump identifying it as the Scarlet-backed Dicaeum cruentatum .
Alas, I did not see the male with its brilliant scarlet plumage from forehead
to rump. The large Grey-breasted Spiderhunter A qffinis was also seen.
The clearing around the lodge was a good place to watch for parrots.
The trisyllabic, sweet, almost melodious calls of the little Blue-ramped
Psittinus cyanurus heralded their presence, usually in a group of eight to 12
birds but sometimes just a lone pair. Their calls are unparrot-like, blending
in with those of songbirds, but unmistakeable once familiar. Their short-
tailed silhouette and fluttering flight are also distinctive - but the red under
wing-coverts of these high-fliers are seldom noticeable.
The parrots would appear from the forest a little more than one hour
before dusk, flying around and calling before settling down for the night,
usually in a high tree. Having observed where they were roosting one night,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.356778" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260833" page_num="111" year="" vol="">
LOW - PENINSULAR MALAYSIA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998978" page_id="56260833"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
111
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998713047619048" page_id="56260833"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
I was curious to know what time they would leave their roost next morning.
Arriving at the tree just before first light, I observed a woodpecker fly into a
dead stump behind the roost tree. It was a White-bellied Dryocopus javensis,
a large handsome woodpecker, black above, white below, with a prominent
red crest and bold white eyes. I was later informed that this species is much
sought by birders and its presence in Malaysia was not discovered until
about eight years ago. The woodpecker was an early riser, unlike the parrots
which did not leave their roosting site for another 20 minutes. The parrots
departed for the forest and put in a brief appearance overhead until about
9.00am when the sun's strength caused them to seek shade.
The Blue-rumped Parrot is only Tin (18cm) in length. It is sexually
dimorphic, the male's head being blue and the female's brown. It is the
only member of its genus and is fairly widely distributed, from Thailand
and Myanmar (Burma), through Malaysia to Borneo and Sumatra. On the
Malay Peninsular it is widespread but not particularly numerous, although
it does occur in oil palm plantations as well as in wooden habitats in the
lowlands, including forest edges and cultivated areas. Deforestation
throughout its range in Indonesia has been so extensive (and the situation is
little better in Malaysia), that the species is now classified as Near-threatened
(close to facing a high risk of extinction in the medium-term future). Its
ability to exist in second-growth forest might ensure its survival.
About an hour before dusk the parrots would reappear in rapid, direct
flight, flying to and fro before choosing their roosting site. One night I
witnessed a dramatic scene. Six or more parrots had just gone to roost near
the clearing, in a slender tree with sparse leaf cover, when the sky darkened
ominously. As I watched to see if they would stay there, a violent wind
arose. The tree swayed from side to side, reaching angles of 45-degrees.
The wind was picking up leaves with a rushing sound, until it seemed that it
was snowing leaves, then whirling them around and around. A loud and
prolonged cracking sound mingled with the thunder. It signalled the end of
a forest giant that had crashed earthwards, making space for another to take
its place. Before the violent wind subsided, the parrots realised they had
made a mistake and left the flimsy tree to seek refuge elsewhere. Then as
darkness fell the rain came - just a few spots at first. I ran for my cabin,
knowing a torrent would follow. The night was pleasantly cool and at
daybreak cloud hung low over the forest and the ground was still damp. By
9.00am the sun was strong. A pair of Stripe-throated Bulbuls Pycnonotus
finlaysoni, their yellow-streaked throats and bright yellow under tail-coverts
shining in the sun, searched a tree for insects. A pair of Little Spiderhunters
hovered in front of the Bauhinia blossoms. Overhead, two Black Magpies
Platysmurus leucopterus were flying high, their white wing flashes being
diagnostic. The presence of a pair of malkohas Phaenicophaeus sp. was
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998892" page_id="56260834"  page_num="112" year="" vol="">
112
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.649604" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260834" page_num="112" year="" vol="">
LOW - PENINSULAR MALAYSIA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999469452380952" page_id="56260834"  page_num="112" year="" vol="">
betrayed by their pale faces and long tails which were just visible through
the foliage of a tree. On bright rufous wings, a pair of Greater Coucals
Centropus sinensis swooped across the clearing, heading towards the river.
There they were sometimes seen foraging in the marshy vegetation at the
river's edge. These birds, described as "lumbering and archaeopteryx-like",
have character!
Species of bulbul, barbet and babbler are numerous in this part of the
world, but in Taman Negara they were seldom easy to see. My sighting of
a Black-capped Babbler Pellorneum capistratum was therefore memorable.
He perched a short distance away, singing his loud song. The monotonous
calls of barbets rung out from the treetops every day - but locating the birds
was a challenge. Barbets frequently have colourful head markings and in
the case of the Red-throated Megalaima mystacophanos, which was seen or
heard daily, a colourful red throat as well.
By 10.00am it was too hot to stay in the clearing. I went to the Tahan
hide, just three minutes away in the forest and reached by a boardwalk. It
was a different world there. The hide looks out onto a grassy space where a
family of wild pigs (with five tiny striped piglets) were snuffling and foraging,
before finally disappearing. Suddenly a gorgeous Black-and-Red Broadbill
Cymbirhynchus macrorhynchos landed on a vertical liana with a convenient
short horizontal perch at the bottom. It swung there for a minute, as surprised
by my presence as I had been by its unexpected appearance. My first sighting
of this beautiful broadbill is indelibly etched in my mind. Deep in the forest,
a pair was sitting side by side on a curved liana between two trees,
immediately overhead. The sun filtered through the canopy, glinting on
their almost iridescent blue upper mandibles. Black and red birds have
always held a great appeal to me. This one prefers forested areas near water.
The broadbills left a big impression on me. Those I saw are, with the
exception of the Dusky Corydon sumatranus, so colourful or striking. Of
the 14 species that exist, four are found in Africa and the rest all live in
south-east Asia, west of Wallace's Line. They usually perch high in the
forest, making them difficult to observe. They build hanging nests,
elaborately constructed from vegetation and suspended precariously by a
single thin strand of vine. On another day I saw the tiny Black-and-Yellow
Broadbill Eurylaimus ochromalus. With its gleaming black head encircled
by a white collar, black wings with streaks or patches of yellow, and bright
blue beak and yellow eyes, it hardly looks real. Its underparts are a delicate
pink, merging into yellow.
While in the hide, I suddenly heard loud calls. Looking towards the
forest I saw the movements of large black and white birds, partly hidden by
the foliage, and knew they must be Oriental Pied Hombills Anthracoceros
albirostris. There were four. They moved around for about 15 minutes,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.356699" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260835" page_num="113" year="" vol="">
LOW - PENINSULAR MALAYSIA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998651" page_id="56260835"  page_num="113" year="" vol="">
113
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.364207" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56260835" page_num="113" year="" vol="">
Copyright Rosemary Low
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9968805" page_id="56260835"  page_num="113" year="" vol="">
Black-and-Yellow Broadbill. The adult has a black head and breast band
(sometimes broken), a white collar and pinkish underparts merging into
yellow on the lower belly and under tail-coverts.
calling and probably feeding. Late in the afternoon I was sitting in the
clearing, waiting for the parrots to appear, when I got in conversation with a
young Indian man from London. With a whooshing sound hombills were
flying over the clearing and I jumped up excitedly. The four hombills landed
in a large tree at the forest's edge. The young man (who was on his
honeymoon) had just come from an island resort and when he saw the
hombills, he exclaimed "Oh, they are so tame on the island they fly down
and take food from the breakfast tables!" Illogically, this instantly devalued
my sighting of them.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999645" page_id="56260836"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
114
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.646222" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260836" page_num="114" year="" vol="">
LOW - PENINSULAR MALAYSIA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9984785" page_id="56260836"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
My rarest hornbill sighting was that of the extraordinary Helmeted
Hombill Rhinoplax vigil. Nowhere common, it is not an easy bird of which
to catch a glimpse. Arguably the most distinctive of all hombills, it is a
slender bird (not massive like the Rhinoceros Hombill) with an extremely
long tail, which is white with a black band near the tip. It was its tail that
betrayed its presence, high in a tree close to the river's edge. In actual fact
it has a normal length hombill tail with two enormously elongated central
feathers. It was indeed a thrilling moment to behold this bird.
Another memorable bird seen deep in the forest was the Orange-backed
Woodpecker Reinwardtipicus validus. It took me by surprise when I saw it.
With its golden-orange back and red underparts, it is a real beauty. The
male has a red crest, while the female's crest is brown and she has a white
line on the underparts. Except for inconspicuous barring on the primaries,
it has none of the barred or scalloped plumage one tends to associate with
woodpeckers.
Pheasants are very wary, often heard but seldom seen. On the forest
trials one can hear them, not far away, but they hurry into the undergrowth
when people approach. At Taman Negara there are three species. One of
these is the Malaysian Peacock-Pheasant Polyplectron malacense, a female
of which with several chicks was close to the path one day but soon
disappeared. This species' "kwok kwok" call was often heard. The plumage
of a displaying male, with the sun glinting on the green 'eyes', is a tmly
amazing sight, one of the countless remarkable products of thousands of
years of evolution. The forests in which it evolved are said to be 130 million
years old - the most ancient in the world - yet during the past few decades
they have been destroyed at a rate that will spell extinction for the Malaysian
Peacock Pheasant unless deforestation is halted.
This species has declined rapidly in recent years due to fragmentation
and erosion of its lowland forest habitat. It might already be extinct in
Thailand and may survive only in Peninsular Malaysia. In 1977 it was
found in only 54% of the localities in which it occurred before 1970. Taman
Negara is, of course, a protected area, thus the population there is important.
All of the species of peacock-pheasants are confined to this region and all
are in the threat category. That endemic to Borneo is the most endangered.
As dusk fell one evening, tipped off by an enthusiastic bird photographer,
I went quietly to the entrance of a forest trial in search of a special bird. He
roosted, I was told, not far from the forest edge. Sure enough, there he was,
a male Crested Fireback Lophura ignita, perched in a tree about 9ft (2.7m)
from the ground. The scientific name seems very appropriate as the male's
blazing orange rump feathers really do look as though they are about to
ignite! However, it was almost dark and his colours were difficult to
determine.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.356416" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260837" page_num="115" year="" vol="">
LOW - PENINSULAR MALAYSIA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997581" page_id="56260837"  page_num="115" year="" vol="">
115
</page>
<author confidence="0.364223">
Copyright Rosemary Low
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.282792">
Female Malay Peacock-Pheasant.
</affiliation>
<bodyText confidence="0.999598304347826" page_id="56260837"  page_num="115" year="" vol="">
The third species of pheasant found there, the Great Argus Argusianus
argus , has arguably the most intricate plumage of any bird in the world.
Unfortunately, it was neither seen nor heard. Apparently a male used to
display (to people!) close to the forest trial, but he had disappeared. The
display is extraordinary, as the male shows-off his lengthened wing-coverts
and long tail. Each feather is a masterpiece, with its central theme of eye
spots (ocelli), with two different patterns of smaller spots, one each side of
the shaft. Each large eye spot has a white line and subtle shading which
mimics a reflection. These feathers surely epitomise art in nature!
Just 62 miles (99km) north-east of Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia's capital, is
Fraser's Hill. One of three hill stations well-known to birdwatchers, it is a
small town 5,000 ft (1,520m) above sea level with a colonial atmosphere.
The forests in the area are home to a wide variety of small softbills, many of
which are familiar to aviculturists. It was interesting to see some of these in
the wild for the first time and observe others that were new to me.
In the grounds of the Shahzan Inn, where I stayed, the most conspicuous
species was the Long-tailed Sibia Heterophasia picaoides. These slender
birds moved around in small restless groups, making their "chip" contact
call, and searching the trees for small berries. They are not colourful, being
mainly grey, but they have character. This is said to be the easiest place to
observe this species. Nevertheless, a photo eluded me: they were so active.
Bamboo is a noticeable element of the montane forests around Fraser's
Hill and the famous birdwatching spot called The Gap. To reach it one
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999296" page_id="56260838"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
116
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.4779765" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260838" page_num="116" year="" vol="">
LOW - PENINSULAR MALAYSIA
Copyright Rosemary Low
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.96055432" page_id="56260838"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
Long-tailed Broadbill.
transverses a road so winding and narrow that only one-way traffic is allowed,
the direction alternating every hour. Ferns are everywhere - huge tree ferns,
their trunks almost hidden by climbing convolvulus, and roadside banks
15ft (4.5m) or more high entirely covered in ferns. The forest consists of
broad-leaved evergreen trees, pines and many kinds of introduced flora that
I suspect might be blamed on the British, who exerted such influence here a
century ago (Louis Fraser was a trader with interests in tin, opium and
gambling). It is built on seven hills and there are distant views of mountain
ranges. The Tudor-style houses are said to "evoke all the charm of the
English countryside." To me they looked out of place, as though one had
suddenly wandered into a smart part of Finchley, north London.
Birdwatching from the road was very successful as many species prefer
the edges of forest. One of the first I saw, the Grey-chinned Minivet
Pericrocotus Solaris , left an indelible impression on me. I was entranced by
its grace and colour. Five or so were flitting about and feeding in a tree with
large leaves and small orange-yellow fruits, lighting up the tree in their
contrasting shades of orange (the males) and bright yellow (the females).
One female was shivering her wings to be fed by the male. On another day
I saw a male Scarlet Minivet P. flammeus , with black head and wings, the
female yellow where the male is red. This bird is well named with flammeus
meaning flaming. These two species are extremely beautiful and among
the most colourful birds of the region.
I did not know of the existence of the Brown Barbet Calorhampus
fuliginosis until I saw it. Once located, these frugivores can be easier to
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.356082" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260839" page_num="117" year="" vol="">
LOW - PENINSULAR MALAYSIA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995804" page_id="56260839"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
117
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.355495" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56260839" page_num="117" year="" vol="">
Copyright Rosemary Low
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.979886" page_id="56260839"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
Fire-tufted Barbet.
observe than many forest birds as they sit motionless for some minutes -
motionless that is except for the movement of the throat as they utter their
monotonous calls. One of the first species I saw was the Fire-tufted
Psilopogon pyrolophus, a handsome bird with red forward-pointing bristles
over the beak. Most barbets have simple calls (duetting by the male and
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999046" page_id="56260840"  page_num="118" year="" vol="">
118
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.644271" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260840" page_num="118" year="" vol="">
LOW - PENINSULAR MALAYSIA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998985904761905" page_id="56260840"  page_num="118" year="" vol="">
female is common) but this one has a call that has been described as a cicada-
like buzz that rises in pitch. Lineated M. lineata , Gold-whiskered M.
chrysopogon and Black-browed Barbet M. oorti were also seen. Their calls
are an integral part of the forest symphony which was notable for the number
of fine songsters.
The babblers (Timaliidae) are a huge and diverse family that includes
such species as the laughingthrushes and the Silver-eared Mesia Leiothrix
argentauris. A memorable sighting was that of five mesias foraging in a
tree one morning. I was lucky to see them in good light when their colours
were positively glowing. For me though, the most active and charismatic
birds in the area were the Chestnut-capped Laughingthrushes Garrulax
mitratus. A small flock was foraging through the trees, forever on the move,
plucking a berry here, taking an insect there. About 9in (22cm) long, they
have an orange bill, legs and feet, a conspicuous white ring around the eyes,
white forehead and wing stripe and grey and olive body plumage. They
were fascinating birds to observe.
The same was true of a group of Mountain Fulvettas Alcippe
brunneicauda , a common yet inconspicuous species. I watched a small
group with young feeding at ground level and in some low shrubby
vegetation. These little babblers, mainly grey and brown, moved about with
their tails cocked at a jaunty angle. All these babblers were a joy to watch;
most other birds in the area were glimpsed for a second or two only as they
skulked high in the trees or in dense cover.
A species that is eagerly sought by keen birdwatchers is the Cutia Cutia
nepalensis , of which I was very lucky to see four or five very high in the
trees. Apparently the name Cutia is derived from the Nepalese name for the
species. A very unusual little short-tailed babbler, the sole member of its
genus, it has been described as being like a cross between a nuthatch and a
shrike-babbler. It creeps around trunks and branches just like a nuthatch.
(Sometimes I feel that if taxonomists could not decide in which family a
bird - like the strange Cutia - belonged, they threw it in with the babblers!).
A rare photo of the Cutia, taken at Fraser's Hill, can be seen on p.284 of A
Photographic Guide to the Birds of Southeast Asia by Morten Strange (Helm,
2002). The male has a slaty blue crown with a black band along the sides of
the head and rufous upperparts with slaty blue and black wings. The female
(the bird in the photo) is duller and has a black streaked, brownish back.
Both have white to pale buffy white underparts boldly barred with black on
the sides.
The male Fairy Bluebird Irena puella (moving on from the babblers),
must surely be a contender for the title of one of the most beautiful birds in
south-east Asia. It was very exciting to see this species in the wild, including
a distant male perched boldly at the top of a tree. Another blue species is the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.35681" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260841" page_num="119" year="" vol="">
LOW - PENINSULAR MALAYSIA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999321" page_id="56260841"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
119
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998016976744186" page_id="56260841"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
Verditer Flycatcher Muscicapa thalassina. The male a wonderful shade of
greenish blue. One brightened up an afternoon when few other colourful
birds were to be seen.
Trogons are among the larger and more easily-watched birds of the
tropics, often sitting motionless waiting for insects. One day I sat down on
a forest trial on the edge of a bank. There was no sound and nothing was
moving. Then I looked downwards, into the forest below, and there sitting
quite still was a female Red-headed Trogon Harpactes erythrocephalus. A
true bird of the forest, she is dark cinnamon brown, with a red abdomen and
under tail-coverts. The male is even more spectacular, with a crimson head,
nape and breast. Trogons move with speed and stealth when hunting - one
moment you see them and the next they are gone.
Another day I saw a flock of about 12 gorgeous Long-tailed Broadbills
Psarisomus dalhousiae moving through the treetops - an unforgettable sight.
Their plumage blends into the foliage, so they are not the easiest birds to see
as they forage for fruits and insects.
There are 39 species of bulbuls in Asia. A few have small crests, but the
Black-crested Pycnonotus melanicterus is exceptional on account of length
of its prominent crest. This species was common here and was seen at the
edge of the forest. Sometimes still known among bird keepers as fruitsuckers,
and cherished for their lovely colours, the leafbirds ( Chloropsis spp.) are
also wonderful songsters. I got brief glimpses of three species their green
plumage making them difficult to spot and almost impossible to photograph.
The Greater Racquet-tailed Drongo Dicrurus paradiseus was a fairly
conspicuous inhabitant of the same habitat. It was always pleasing to see
one in flight, catching insects in mid-air, with its tail held almost horizontally
and the two long tail wires and racquets streaming behind. The thin bare
shafts that support the racquets can be up to lOin (25cm) long. Very vocal,
it has a variety of whistles and screams and is also a talented mimic. The
Lesser Racquet-tailed Drongo D. remifer , which differs mainly in its smaller
body size, longer bare shafts and its straight-tipped not forked tail, can
sometimes be found in the same area. They are just two of several species
of these glossy black birds in Malaysia.
As a contrast to observing forest birds, we visited Kuala Selangor Nature
Park, 75km (46 miles) from Kuala Lumpur, on the west coast. The area was
once dominated by mangroves and the rare Milky Stork Mycteria cinerea
was formerly abundant. Now only a strip of remnant mangrove forest
remains and the storks have gone. Behind the mangroves is an area of
brackish lakes and ponds and secondary forest. The most conspicuous birds
were egrets, herons and Brahminy Kites Haliastur indus. White-throated
Kingfisher and the Collared species H. chloris made brief appearances,
darting along the water's edge. The Common Myna Acridotheres tristis
and Javan Myna A. javanicus were also seen.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.901877" page_id="56260842"  page_num="120" year="" vol="">
120
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.5103475" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260842" page_num="120" year="" vol="">
LOW - PENINSULAR MALAYSIA
Copyright Rosemary Low
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98189695" page_id="56260842"  page_num="120" year="" vol="">
Black-crested Bulbul.
It was here that I had my first sight of tailorbirds, with their jauntily-
cocked tails. I had often read about how these little brownish birds 'stitch'
together one or two large leaves with spiders' web and plant fibre, forming
a pouch in which they build their nest. This seems to me to be one of the
most remarkable accomplishments among nest-building birds. I saw a pair
of Ashy Tailorbirds Orthotomus ruficeps, the male with a rufous head. Active,
vivacious and endearing, they also produced some wonderful liquid notes.
They moved so fast, side to side along the perch, that they reminded me of
the manakins of South America, that whiz around like mechanical toys.
There are some beautiful woodpeckers in Malaysia, few more striking
than the Common Flameback or Goldenback Dinopium javanense. This
handsome bird made a big impression on me.
Most if not all members will be aware that the Red Junglefowl Gallus
gallus is the ancestor of the domestic chicken. I was surprised to have the
good luck to see one of these shy birds for a fleeting second or two. It
reinforced the impression of the wonderful variety of birdlife to be seen in
Malaysia which was disappointing only for its scarcity of parrots.
Rosemary recently returned to the Canary Islands to take up a position
with the Loro Parque Fundacidn.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996005" page_id="56260843"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
121
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.4795805" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260843" page_num="121" year="" vol="">
THE CUCKOO-ROLLER Leptosomus discolor
by Dieter Rinke
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.914965333333333" page_id="56260843"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
This enigmatic bird, endemic to Madagascar and the Comoro Islands,
represents a monotypic family, whose true relationship to other families is
not yet resolved. Generally accepted as being a member of the highly diverse
Coraciiformes, there are indications that the Cuckoo-Roller may be a sister
species to the frogmouths. Having seen the 'long-haired' nestlings, one
may be willing to accept this hypothesis, which has yet to be proved.
Copyright Christopher Brack
Cuckoo-Roller Leptosomus discolor photographed at VogelPark Walsrode
in 2004, when all six were in juvenile female-like plumage.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997736" page_id="56260844"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
122
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.97345" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260844" page_num="122" year="" vol="">
RINKE - CUCKOO-ROLLER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9966275" page_id="56260844"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
The Cuckoo-Roller is widespread in Madagascar, where it favours dry
forests and savannah-like habitats. It is not found in deep rainforest. Its
loud call and elegant flight displays make it one of the most spectacular
birds of Madagascar. It feeds on large insects, reptiles and various kinds of
invertebrates, eating even the furriest caterpillars. Pairs are territorial and
nest in tree holes, in which the female lays up to five eggs. Nothing is
known about the incubation and nestling periods, although from our
experience of rearing young birds from the wild, it seems that the young
fledge at the age of approximately four weeks.
VogelPark Walsrode, Germany, received three pairs of Cuckoo-Rollers
in early 2004. All were in juvenile female-like plumage. The males acquire
their full colour after one year. The birds readily accepted a mixed diet of
baby mict^ one day old chicks (cut into pieces) and insects which was a
result of them having been hand-reared on such a diet in Madagascar. Now,
at the age of one year, the birds are housed in pairs in large aviaries, but to
date have not yet made any attempt to breed.
The Cuckoo-Roller is one of a number of species from Madagascar which
can be seen at VogelPark Walsrode, others not to be missed include the
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.986108111111111" page_id="56260844"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
Blue-headed or Pitta-like Ground-Roller Atelornis pittoides , Madagascar
Blue Pigeon Alectroenas madagascariensis , Madagascar Crested Ibis
Lophotibis cristata , Madagascar Sacred Ibis Threskiornis aethiopicus
bernieri , Madagascar Pond Heron Ardeola idae, Sickle-billed Vanga Fulculea
palliata , Blue Coua Coua caerulea and Crested Coua C. cristata.
Dr Dieter Rinke is Zoological Director, VogelPark Walsrode, Am
Reiselbach, D-29664 Walsrode, Germany. Tel:+49-5161-604 410/Fax:+49-
5161-604 440/E-mail:dieter rinke@vogelpark-walsrode.de
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.963574" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56260844" page_num="122" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.919793375" page_id="56260844"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
The society has a large stock of back issues mostly from 1935 onwards
but there are also some earlier issues still available. They are priced #3.00
each (including p&amp;p). Please check availability before placing an order.
Overseas members may be able to pay by credit card through a Paypal
invoice, but this service is not available in all countries. All enquiries should
be addressed to: P. Boulden, Hon. Secretary/Treasurer, Avicultural Society,
Arcadia, The Mounts, East Allington, Totnes, Devon TQ9 7JQ, UK or
E-mail :admin@avisoc. co.uk
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998933" page_id="56260845"  page_num="123" year="" vol="">
123
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.983049" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260845" page_num="123" year="" vol="">
COULD THIS HAVE BEEN ANOTHER GRAY'S LORY?
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.89908075" page_id="56260845"  page_num="123" year="" vol="">
by Herbert Schifter
In Vienna Zoo (Austria), better known as Tiergarten Schonbrann, a lory
was received on April 18th 1944 which looked quite similar to the bird
named Trichoglossus coccineifrons by G. R. Gray in the Proceedings of the
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.664289">
Zoological Society of London in 1858. The specimen had been collected in
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998841147058824" page_id="56260845"  page_num="123" year="" vol="">
the Am Islands by Alfred Russel Wallace during his stay there from J an u ary
March 1857. It was figured in Mivart's A Monograph of the Lories, or
Brush-TonguedParrots published in 1896 where the name Gray&amp;apos;s Lory was
given to the bird. Subsequently it has been considered to have been a hybrid,
possibly between T. haematodus nigrogularis (the resident subspecies of T,
haematodus on the Am Islands) and Chalcopsitta sintilata , the Ye I low -
streaked Lory.
In his account of his journey to the Am Islands Wallace (1857) did not
mention how and where he got the specimen of I coccineifrons he only
said that "a most beautiful brush-tongued parrot, closely allied to I
cyanogrammus (the former name of the subspecies of the Rainbow Lory or
Lorikeet occurring on the Am Islands) had been very common in Dobo" (a
small island near the west coast of Kepulauan Am). In the Am Islands in
1857 Wallace had also collected the type specimens of Chalcopsitta
rubrifrons (now C. sintillata rubrifrons) and T. nigrogularis (now T.
haematodus nigrogularis) both of which were named by G. R. Gray in 1858
in the same paper as T coccineifrons.
Unfortunately nothing is known about the probable hybrid origin of the
specimen received by Vienna Zoo in 1944. It came from Edgar Glas, at that
time a well known parrot breeder and dealer in exotic birds in Austria. It
was probably Prof Dr Otto Antonius, Director of the zoo at that time, who
considered it to be very similar to the lory named Trichoglossus coccineifrons
by Gray and therefore in the translation of the Latin name the Vienna bird
was given the German name Rotstirnlori (Red-fronted Lorikeet). The bird
lived in the zoo until its death on October 30th 1962. It was not given to the
museum as had been usual in the past probably due to some cases of 'Parrot
disease' at that time. Fortunately I had taken some transparencies of it earlier
that year one of which was reproduced recently in Papageien 2/2005, p/59,
two other pictures of it are reproduced here. The bird was very well known
to me during the many years that I was a regular visitor to the zoo and
remained in good condition until its death, though it had not been very agile
during the last year and was very often sitting on the floor of the aviary.
Certainly one of its parents had been a subspecies of T haematodus , but
the Yellow-streaked Lory was practically unknown in continental aviculture
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998785" page_id="56260846"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
124
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.531859" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260846" page_num="124" year="" vol="">
SCHIFTER - GRAY'S LORY?
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9277605" page_id="56260846"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
in the 1940s. However, the Violet-necked Lory Eos squamata ( ricinata )
was kept in Austria at that time and may have been the other parent.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.6563735" page_id="56260846"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
Herbert Schifter
This bird known as the Rotstirnlori lived in Vienna Zoo from 1944-1962.
Herbert Schifter
Another view of the same bird.
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.226999" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260847" page_num="125" year="" vol="">
SCHIFTER - GRAY'S LORY?
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996147" page_id="56260847"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
125
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.97526" genericHeader="references" page_id="56260847" page_num="125" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.971557380952381" page_id="56260847"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
Gray, G.R. 1858. A List of the Birds, with Descriptions of New Species obtained by Mr. Alfred
R. Wallace in the Aru and Ke Islands. (Aves PI. CXXXII-CXXXVII), Proceedings of the
Zoological Society of London, Part XXVI: 169-198.
Mivart, St. G. 1896. A Monograph of the Lories, or Brush-Tongued Parrots, comprising the
family Loriidae.
Wallace, A.R. 1857. On the Natural History of the Aru Islands. The Annals and Magazine of
Natural History, Supplement to Vol.XX. December 1857 {Ann. &amp; Mag. N. Hist. Ser.2.
Vol.XX.Suppl.):473-485.
Wallace s bird is in The Natural History Museum collection at Tring.
Robert Prys-Jones, Head of the Bird Group there was extremely helpful and
wrote to say: "Although still in Wallace's personal collection at the time of
its description, it was passed to the BMNH in 1873 along with many other
Wallace specimens. '' It still bears an original Wallace label. Dr Prys-
Jones provided copies of the appropriate pages (pp.169 &amp; 183) in the
Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London (1858), along with copies
of the appropriate pages relating to T. coccineifrons in the Catalogue of the
Psittaci, or Parrots, in the Collection of the British Museum by T. Salvadori
(1891) and Type-Specimens of Birds in the British Museum (Natural History),
Void Non-Passerines by Rachel L. M. Warren (1966). The latter (p. 66)
states that the bird was an adult male and was collected by Wallace in the
Aru Islands, January 11th - March 12th 1857. It has the Registration
No. 1873.5.12.1504.
In the Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London (p. 183), Gray
described it as: Green; front and spots on the head carmine; head and chin
whitish blue; nape and upper part of the abdomen scarlet; the two latter
margined with blue; some of the lesser wing-coverts marked with yellow
and scarlet; under wing-coverts and inner margins of tail-feathers scarlet;
base of quills beneath yellow tinged with scarlet, quills above green marked
in some places with yellow; abdomen varied with blue, green, scarlet and
yellow; under tail-coverts varied with yellow, green and pale scarlet. "
In the Catalogue of the Psittaci, or Parrots, in the Collection of the British
Museum (p.56), Salvadori described it as: "Green; head purple; forehead
and some scattered feathers on the pileum red; a red collar around hind
neck; breast red, with purple cross bands; abdomen blue; flanks green and
yellow; thighs green; under tail-coverts orange, green in the middle; smaller
upper wing-coverts with orange-red irregular spots and edges; under wing-
coverts red; inner webs of the quills towards the base orange-red; tail-
feathers green, the lateral ones with the inner webs golden red towards the
bases; bill orange; feet plumbeous. Total length about 11 inches, wing 6,
tail 4.3, bill 0.85, tarsus 0.6. ''
I am also grateful for the assistance I received from Marie Hitchcock,
Assistant Librarian, The Library, Zoological Society of London. - Ed.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999044" page_id="56260848"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
126
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993992" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260848" page_num="126" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE GREY GULL Lams modestus
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.979063974358974" page_id="56260848"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
by Jo Gregson
The Grey Gull Larus modestus is a medium-sized gull (length 18in
(46cm)) approximately the same size as the Common Gull L. canus and the
Ring-billed Gull L. delawarensis. Its range extends along the west coast of
South America from Colombia to Chile (maximum range during winter
dispersal). It breeds in colonies on the inland deserts of northern Chile and
Peru.
It is best described as being of typical gull proportions with the adult
having mainly grey plumage with a striking white head (which becomes
brownish when the bird is in non-breeding plumage) and the primaries and
secondaries being dark, almost black, with the wings having a white trailing
edge which remains visible when the wings are closed. Adult plumage is
acquired in the third winter. Young birds have overall brownish-grey plumage
which, with each moult, becomes greyer on the body and the wings, and the
head becomes progressively paler.
A pair of Grey Gulls arrived at Paignton Zoo Environmental Park on
March 6th 2001. The pair came from Heidelberg Zoo, Germany, where the
male was hatched in 1998 and the female in 1996. Ever since their arrival
here they have been housed in the Cottage Aviary, a large planted aviary
with a pond and shelter. The aviary measures approximately 12m x 15m x
3m high (roughly 40ft x 50ft x 10ft high) and has a substrate of gravel areas
and grass areas as well as a shallow concrete pond. The pair has bred
consistently for the past four years and the gulls are being kept as a growing
colony.
Other current occupants of the aviary include: Red-billed Chough
Pyrrhocorax pyrrhocorax , Northern Lapwing Vanellus vanellus, Black-
necked Stilt Himantopus mexicanus, Madagascar Teal Anas bernieri,
Chestnut Teal A. castanea , White-faced Whistling Duck Dendrocygna
viduata , Mandarin Duck Aix galericulata and Palawan Peacock-Pheasant
Polyplectron emphanum. The gulls have not interacted badly with any other
species and are more likely to be chased off by other birds than to assert
themselves. This quiet, almost docile, behavour is hardly what is expected
from a gull but their repeated breeding has demonstrated that they are healthy
and contented. The breeding results from 2002-2005 have resulted in one
chick being reared in June 2002, two in June 2003, two in June 2004 and
one in July 2005.
The nest is a simple scrape in the gravel in which a clutch of two eggs is
laid. The nest has always been in roughly the same spot, an open area at the
back of the aviary. Unfortunately the site is at the bottom of a small slope
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.882723" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260849" page_num="127" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - GREY GULL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998218" page_id="56260849"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
127
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.920726583333333" page_id="56260849"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
and therefore liable to flooding and it is thought that this may have caused
the loss of one of the eggs earlier this year.
In the wild the Grey Gull nests in large colonies up to 100km (approx.
60 miles) inland. There they lay one to three eggs, the lowest average clutch
size of any gull. The nest is attended by one of the pair at a time whilst the
other flies off to feed. Due to the considerable distances between the feeding
areas and the nests the chicks are fed only once a day (mainly on fish). This
may contribute to the slow growth rate of the young (the slowest rate of any
gull) which do not move to the coast until they are at least 40 days old when
they join the adults, feeding mainly on Mole Crabs Eremita analoga but
Paul Boulden
Juvenile Grey Gull hatched earlier this year.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998116" page_id="56260850"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
128
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.972312" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260850" page_num="128" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - GREY GULL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.984152" page_id="56260850"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
also finding food along the strandline and scavenging behind fishing boats.
The global population numbers about 100,000 pairs and they are not
considered threatened although large scale egg collecting may be a problem.
They are also vulnerable to the effects of El Nino and do not breed in years
when the conditions are too severe.
At the zoo their main diet consists of Sprats Clupea sprattus but they
also have access to a variety of other foods provided for the other species
sharing the aviary. During the breeding season mealworms are also provided
for some of the other aviary occupants.
As far as I am aware the Grey Gull has not previously been bred in
captivity in the UK.
Bibliography
del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A., Sagatal, J. (eds.) 1996. Handbook of the Birds of the World, Vol. 3
Hoatzin to Auks. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona, Spain.
As described above, the Grey Gull Larus modestus, has been bred at
Paignton Zoo Environmental Park. This is thought to be the first breeding
of this species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who knows of a previous
breeding is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.856209" page_id="56260850"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.507601" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56260850" page_num="128" year="" vol="">
WEST AFRICAN VULTURE CRISIS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997994375" page_id="56260850"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
A study warns that vulture populations in West Africa have plummeted
in rural areas, on a scale comparable to the dramatic decline in south Asia.
The numbers of vultures counted in Mali, Burkina Faso and Niger during
2003-2004 were compared with data from 1969-1970 and showed an
alarming decline. Apart from small numbers in protected areas, the White-
headed Vulture Trigonoceps occipitalis and Lappet-faced Torgos tracheliotus
have almost completely disappeared. The African White-backed Vulture
Gyps africanus has declined by 97% and Riippelfs Griffon Vulture G.
rueppellii by 96%. The Hooded Vulture Necrosyrtes monachus has declined
by 45%.
The authors of the study, Jean-Marc Thiollay and Guy Rondeau, have
only been able to speculate as to the causes of such massive declines. These
may include habitat loss and overhunting having led to a lack of animal
carcasses on which to feed, domestic stock receiving improved veterinary
care, hunting for use in traditional ceremonies, in medicine and for food,
and perhaps the widespread use of pesticides.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996424" page_id="56260851"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
129
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.544812" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260851" page_num="129" year="" vol="">
BIRD NEWS FROM CHESTER ZOO - 2004
by Roger Wilkinson
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.737306" page_id="56260851"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
At Chester Zoo 2004 was a very good year for waterfowl Two dozen
(24) Black-billed Whistling Ducks Dendrocygna arborea were bred. This
improved fecundity probably resulted in part from the direct import by
Chester Zoo of new blood lines from Rotterdam Zoo. Eleven Hooded
Merganser Mergus cucullatus and eight Common Eider Somateria
mollissima were also bred and other ducks successfully reared included
White-headed Duck Oxyura leucocephalus , Red-crested Pochard Netta
rufina, Baer's Pochard Aythya baeri , Ferruginous Duck A. nyroca , Marbled
Teal Marmaronetta angustirostris and Falcated Teal Anas falcata. Three
Lesser White-fronted Geese Anser erythropus and two Ross's Snow Geese
A. rossi were also bred.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.882582">
Roger Wilkinson
Humboldt's Penguins at Chester Zoo.
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.867125375" page_id="56260851"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
Our Humboldt's Penguins Spheniscus humboldti hatched 12 chicks in
2004, all of which were parent-reared and of which only two failed to reach
the 30-day mark customarily used as the indicator of infant survival by most
zoos. This contrasts with the situation of some 20 years ago when in many
collections very few penguin chicks were reared by their parents and efforts
were concentrated on developing successful hand-rearing protocols (Williams
&amp; Golding, 1987). These authors reported that at the Cotswold Wildlife
Park, Oxon., UK prior to mid-1980, from only one of approximately 40
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994649" page_id="56260852"  page_num="130" year="" vol="">
130
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.835758" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260852" page_num="130" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - CHESTER ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995688095238095" page_id="56260852"  page_num="130" year="" vol="">
eggs hatched under the parents was the chick reared successfully in contrast
to 26 of 32 hand-reared successfully in the period from 1983, when a hand-
rearing programme was introduced. There was a similar situation then at
Chester Zoo with only one chick being parent-reared in 1985 as compared
to 16 out of 17 being hand-reared in 1986 (Wilkinson, 1987). The
improvements in parent-rearing represent important advances in penguin
husbandry and management that have included greater attention to the design
of more hygienic nesting areas and perhaps also the development of better
parenting behaviour by individual birds.
Seven Chilean Flamingos Phoenicopterus chilensis were reared in 2004
but disappointingly only one Caribbean Flamingo P. ruber ruber. (Things
are looking better this year with to date (mid-September 2005) some seven
Caribbean Flamingo chicks currently being reared and eight Chilean
Flamingo chicks already hatched.) Three West African Black Crowned
Cranes Balearica pavonina pavonina were hatched of which one was reared
to maturity. Eurasian Spoonbill Platalea leucorodia and Waldrapp Ibis
Geronticus eremita reared chicks in the Eurasian aviary Europe on the Edge.
Close by outside this aviary a pair of Little Egrets Egretta garzetta nested
hidden high in a willow tree in the zoo grounds. The female of the pair
escaped from the zoo in April 1998 following an unseasonal heavy snowstorm
that damaged the nylon net roof of the aviary. This bird has been at liberty
since then but had returned to the zoo each spring to greet her former aviary
companions from a vantage point on the roof of the Europe on the Edge
aviary. In April 2000 she was twice seen in the zoo together with an un-
rung wild bird. She returned alone in 2002 and again in 2003 but in 2004
again came back with an un-rung egret that proved to be her mate.
Disappointingly this pair of egrets was unsuccessful in its breeding attempt
(and neither bird returned to the zoo in 2005).
Another highlight of 2004 was the first breeding in the UK of the Red-
billed Curassow Crax blumenbachii. Lady Amherst's Pheasant Chrysolophus
amherstiae and Blue Peafowl Pavo cristatus also bred. It was also a good
year for owls with the breeding of four Great Grey Owls Strix nebulosa,
two Spectacled Owls Pulsatrix perspicillata and two White-faced Scops
Owls Otus leucotis. A Tawny Frogrnouth Podargus strigoides was also
bred. A Blue-eyed Cockatoo Cacatua ophthalmica, two Stella's Lorikeets
Charmosynapapou, two Greater Vasa Parrots Coracopsis vasa, four Princess
Parakeets Polytelis alexandrae and two Derbyan Parakeets Psittacula
derbiana were bred on the Parrot Section. A new purpose built off-show
parrot breeding facility now rehouses many of the more threatened parrot
species that were until this spring held in the much smaller aviaries of the
recently demolished old Parrot blouse. Stock now housed in these specialist
breeding aviaries includes nine Philippine Red-vented Cockatoos C.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.558765" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260853" page_num="131" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - CHESTER ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998538" page_id="56260853"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
131
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.994706" page_id="56260853"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
haematuropygitt and two pairs of Blue-throated Macaws Ara glaucogularis.
In equally spacious planted aviar ies, another pair of Blue-throated Macaws
remain on public display as do many other spectacular parrots including
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.838592285714286" page_id="56260853"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
Hyacinth Macaws Anodorhynchus hyacinthinus, Red-tailed Amazons
Amazona brasiliensis , Golden Conures Aratinga guarouba and Keas Nestor
notabilis .
Seven Speckled Pigeons Columba guinea and three Crested Bronzewing
Pigeons Ocyphaps lophotes were bred in the free flight Tropical Realm,
The Victoria Crowned Pigeons Goura victoria , Green* napcd Pheasant
Pigeons Otidiphaps nobilis, White naped Pheasant Pigeons Cl n. aruensis
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.966232363636363" page_id="56260853"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
and Mindanao Bleeding Hearts Gallicolumba criniger each hatched a chick
but disappointingly none of these were reared.
The White-collared Kingfishers Halcyon chloris were especially
productive with 14 chicks hatched of which nine were reared. Two Blue-
winged Kookaburra Dacelo leachii and six Lilac-breasted Rollers Coracias
caudata were also reared. Other softbills bred included the Azure-winged
Magpie Cyanopica cyana and White-ramped Shama Copsychus malabarica.
Two Red Birds of Paradise Paradisaea rubra were hatched in an incubator
but sadly neither was reared.
A spectacular 51 Java Sparrows Padda oryzivora, 13 Pekin Robins
Leiothrix lutea, seven Emerald Starlings Larnproiornis iris, two Golden-
breasted or Royal Starlings L. regius , two Asian Glossy Starlings Aplonis
panayensis and a Pope Cardinal Paroaria dominicana were reared in the
free flight area of Tropical Realm.
The Curator and several of the bird keeping staff were involved in
conservation work. One of our bird keepers assisted with Echo Parakeet P.
echo field conservation on Mauritius. Two others helped with intensive
captive management of the Mauritius Fody Fodia rubra at the Black River
Aviaries, where their zoo-acquired incubation and hand-rearing skills and
experience contributed significantly to this project's success. Chester Zoo's
out-of-country and field conservation programmes and project support will
be the subject of future reports in the Avicultural Magazine.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.944198" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56260853" page_num="131" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9926855" page_id="56260853"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
Thanks are due to Curator of Higher Vertebrates Mike Jordan and Team
Leaders Wayne McLeod and Andrew Woolham along with the bird team at
Chester Zoo for providing information on recent happenings in the bird
collection.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.989547" genericHeader="references" page_id="56260853" page_num="131" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.989852">
Williams, M.P. and Golding, R. 1987. Breeding and rearing the Humboldt Penguin at Cotswold
Wildlife Park. Avicultural Magazine 93,2:61-72.
Wilkinson, R. 1987. Chester Zoo - 1986. Avicultural Magazine 93, 2:90-97.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998537" page_id="56260854"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
132
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.974846" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260854" page_num="132" year="" vol="">
BIRD KEEPING IN THE TROPICS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987755384615384" page_id="56260854"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
by Robin Restall
When I lived in England, I, like so many aviculturists, often had wistful
thoughts about the avicultural joys of living in a tropical land in which the
sun shone 12 hours a day, where there were never any problems acclimatizing
birds and there were bound to be endless supplies of insects. Well, I have
been living here in Venezuela for 11 years now, ever since my retirement
from business, and for those who believe the grass is greener on the other
side of the fence, there follows an account of a weekend in the life of a bird
keeper in Venezuela.
On a Saturday afternoon recently I was sitting quietly reading the
newspaper when it occurred to me that I really should go to the birdroom to
check everything was in order. My birdroom is attached to the house, but it
is open to the elements, with half of the roof covered by metal mesh. There
is a metal mesh door into the garden, which is kept locked, and another into
the aviary, which is also attached to the house. Right now, I am working on
a project to breed the Slate-coloured Seedeater Sporophila schistacea and
have recently succeeded in breeding the Sooty Grassquit Tiaris fuliginosa
(see Avicultural Magazine Vol.lll, No.2, pp.64-74 (2005)). The latter
included a photo (p.68) showing some of the 12 breeding cages in my
birdroom, each of which houses a pair of these species.
I trotted downstairs and into the birdroom and was at once attracted by a
rapid flapping sound coming from one of the upper cages. Only one bird,
the male, was perched, and I thought the poor female had in some way
become trapped by something on the floor of the cage and was flapping
frantically to free herself. I stood on tiptoes so I could see what was happening
on the floor of the cage and was confronted by a snake, which opened its
mouth wide and threatened me, while at the same time vibrating the tip of
its tail like a rattle. The female finch was nowhere to be seen.
I stepped back to collect my senses and decided that a couple of nets
might come in useful. I also brought the birdroom chair to stand on and
opened the door on the left side of the front of the cage and managed to get
the small net inside. The snake was very agitated and after attempting to
strike at me dived towards the front of the cage and succeeded in squeezing
its head and half of its body between the bars. However, having swallowed
the missing bird, it had a bulge in the middle which caused it to become
stuck and unable to escape. To cut a long story short, it eventually managed
to make a rapid retreat and I took out a feeding pot and fixed the feeder flap
open, through which the snake emerged and was caught by me in the big
net. I attempted to kill it by applying pressure to the nape, as I wanted it to
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.617612" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260855" page_num="133" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - BIRD KEEPING IN THE TROPICS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999398" page_id="56260855"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
133
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998915833333333" page_id="56260855"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
remain undamaged in order to take to the museum. However, the snake was
very angry and escaped from the net and charged towards me. I managed to
kill it by stepping on its head. Later identified as a Brown-lined Snake
Mastigodryas hoddaerti, it measured over lm (3ft Sin) in length, but was
only as thick as my thumb - except that was for the bulge in the middle!
It was our third snake. The first was caught by our cat, a magnificent
achievement, as the cat is both old and small. The next was killed by the
gardener. Long, slender, beautiful creatures with bright golden yellow eyes,
they were a type of tree boa. Of coarse I checked all the cages and looked
around the aviary and wondered if there was anything I could do to prevent
a recurrence. We had been having a great deal of rain, and as we live on the
top of a hill it seems likely that the snakes had travelled uphill to escape the
flooding below. As I walked out of the birdroom I glanced into a large jug
I had put aside. It was half full of rainwater, floating on top of which was a
dead spider. Including its legs, it measured almost 20cm (8in) across and
had a horrid face and large jaws. It was the first of its kind I had seen but
unfortunately was not sufficiently intact for me to take it to the museum for
identification.
On the Sunday afternoon, I decided to take a nap in the bedroom and
switched on the air-conditioner. I went to the open window to close it and
there, in the well between the outer louvred window and the sliding inner
window, was another snake. It was the fourth snake in a month. It made me
jump so much, that I nearly hit the ceiling. It rattled its tail fiercely and with
a lunging open mouth threatened me. This time I eased the window open a
fraction and spayed some powerful insecticide into the space between the
two windows. It took about 15 minutes to do the trick, during which time
the snake demonstrated its amazing skill at climbing up the sides of the
apparently smooth window frame. This snake was about the same length as
the one in the birdroom, but was slimmer and had a smaller head. The
gardener said it was a Macagua , a very poisonous species, but to me it
looked like another tree boa. It had reached the window via the fronds of a
palm tree that is growing in front of the house, the fronds of which touch the
bars covering the window.
Over the past three years, I have lost some birds in the aviary - they have
simply disappeared. Three others in the cages were found dead on the nest,
when sitting on eggs. In each case part of the head and both eyes had been
eaten away and the corpses were riddled with ants. I had never figured how
the birds disappeared from the aviary and thought the cage deaths were the
result of egg-binding followed by an instant ant attack. Now I have two
possible villians, snakes and spiders.
On the Sunday night we had a ferocious storm of the kind that leaves
branches of trees on the ground and forces rain under roof tiles that have
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.9996" page_id="56260856"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
134
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.735713" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260856" page_num="134" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - BIRD KEEPING IN THE TROPICS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9977606" page_id="56260856"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
never leaked before. For some reason, the birds in the aviary always build
their nests in the bushes in the front half of the aviary, which is open to the
rain, even though the rear half that joins onto my studio, has plate glass over
the metal mesh. These storms regularly destroy their nests. My hard-working
male Blue-black Grassquit Volatinia jacarina has had four nests wrecked in
as many months. One had eggs in it and another containing a chick.
I have bought a small industrial freezer just to keep my tubs of seed in.
We have a moth here that lays its eggs in the seed pots. The tiny larvae eat
the seed and weave cocoons which have seed mixed in with them, so that
what might look like a full pot of seed, may in fact be only a thin layer of
seed, beneath which the rest of the pot is filled with moth cocoons. Therefore
the seed pots need to be emptied more often - usually onto the bird table
where the local Ruddy Ground Doves Columbina talpacoti stuff themselves
silly. Keeping the seed in the freezer helps prevent the moths' eggs from
hatching. There is no such thing here as super-cleaned seed.
This is not meant as a litany of woe, but as I do occasionally get letters
from envious correspondents who think I live in a bird keeper's paradise
(which in so many ways I do), following the snake and spider incidents, I
thought the above account might be of passing interest to members who
ocassionally look over the fence at the grass on the other side.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.4696854" page_id="56260856"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
Robin Restall is a Research Associate at the Phelps Ornithological
Collection in Caracas, Venezuela. E-mail:Restall@cantv.net
* * *
PROBABLE FIRST UK BREEDING
Cage &amp; Aviary Birds , July 28th 2005, p.3, reported that Andy Younger,
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.994781769230769" page_id="56260856"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
a falconer living in Scotland, had achieved what is thought to be the first
successful UK breeding of the South American Black-chested Buzzard-
Eagle Geranoaetus melanoleucus. An egg was laid on March 15th, but was
broken the next day. A further three eggs were laid and were incubated for
25 days, before they were mysteriously broken and thrown out of the nest.
There followed a further clutch of three eggs, two of which were removed
after 14 days and placed in an incubator. The first hatched on June 11th and
the second on June 14th. The third egg, which was left with the parents
(along with two large duck eggs filled with plaster), started to hatch but
there were difficulties, so it was removed to an incubator, where with
increased humidity the chick eventually managed to free itself. A photo
showed all three chicks being reared by the female, the male having been
removed when the female became aggressive towards him.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998888" page_id="56260857"  page_num="135" year="" vol="">
135
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.994558" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260857" page_num="135" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
AMAZON PARROTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.980684157894737" page_id="56260857"  page_num="135" year="" vol="">
Amazon Parrots: Aviculture, Trade and Conservation by Rosemary Low
is a useful and attractive book which is divided into two more or less equal
parts. The first part is a general account divided into 11 chapters dealing
with Amazon parrots in aviculture, as companion birds and in the wild. The
second part focuses on the individual species accounts.
An introductory chapter precedes chapters on housing, diet, captive
breeding, Amazon parrots as companion birds and health care. The author's
lifetime of experience working with these birds ensures that good advice is
given on all these subjects. She favours natural varied diets and her
preference is for outdoor aviaries rather than suspended indoor flight cages.
Rosemary also indicates which species are most suitable as companion birds
and for novice Amazon breeders.
Following this section are chapters on introduced populations, life in the
wild, conservation, extinct Amazon parrots and trade. Amazon parrots that
have escaped or been released from captivity have become established in
the southern states of the USA and can be seen flying free in Barcelona and
some of the other major cities in Spain. Even in their native countries Amazon
parrots may now be found living in cities. On a recent visit to Mexico,
whilst staying in urban areas of Mexico City, I regularly observed small
flocks of several Amazona spp. - all far from their natural forest habitats.
The popularity of Amazons as pets both in their native countries and
abroad has had serious consequences for the conservation of many species.
The IUCN Red List for 2004 lists 16 species as threatened of which seven
rank as Endangered or Critically Endangered. A further two species are
Near Threatened and many distinctive subspecies are at risk. The preference
for captive bred birds both as companion birds and good avicultural subjects
relates not only to ethical considerations over sustainable trade but also to
the fact that these birds are so much more suitable and better adapted to
captive life.
Currently 27-31 species of Amazon are recognised, the most recent of
which KawalTs Amazon Amazona kawalli was proposed in 1989. Parrot
taxonomy is unstable and the definition of species subject to debate. All
currently recognised species and subspecies are dealt with in this book
although perhaps not surprisingly there are occasional inconsistencies within
the text as to the number of species recognised. Rosemary notes 28 species
in the introduction but delivers accounts of 29 - the additional species perhaps
being KawalTs Amazon.
The species accounts are each subdivided into sections entitled:
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999397" page_id="56260858"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
136
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.967113" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260858" page_num="136" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.93957836" page_id="56260858"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
Distinguishing Features, Immature Birds, Subspecies, Aviculture, Country
of Origin, Habitat, Habits and Status and Threats. A map indicating the
range of the species is included and numerous colour photos illustrate not
only the species but most importantly the various subspecies. At Chester
Zoo we have had the privilege to work with many of these birds and I must
thank Rosemary for mentioning our breeding successes with the Red-tailed
Amazon A brasiliensis and Ecuador (Lilacine) A autumnalis lilacina. Less
well known may be the history of the zoo's previous successes with the
Yellow-billed Amazon A. collaria and Green-cheeked Amazon A.
viridigenalis. Much original information comes from the author's own
experience gained whilst working with the excellent parrot collections at
Palmitos Park and Loro Parque on the Canary Islands. She also includes
accounts of captive breedings from a diversity of other sources including
those of many successful private breeders.
I happily recommend this book to all who are interested in keeping and
breeding Amazon parrots. As is always the case with Rosemary's books
this is well written, beautifully illustrated, a joy to read and a mine of
authorative information.
Amazon Parrots: Aviculture, Trade and Conservation (ISBN 0-9531337-
4-5) by Rosemary Low, 324 page hardback, numerous colour photographs,
published 2005 by Dona Publishing/Insignis Publications. Available in the
UK from Hampshire Breeders and Books (Tel: 01730 301340) and Natural
History Book Services (Tel:01803 865913). It is currently being offered by
Hampshire Breeders and Books, price #24.95 including p&amp;p, for Europe
add 10%, for the rest of the world add 20%.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.748925">
Roger Wilkinson
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987080428571429" page_id="56260858"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
A MULTICOLOURED FINCH OF UNRIVALLED BEAUTY
Several years ago, during a birding trip to Australia, my travelling
companion and I stopped at a water hole. We were hoping to photograph
cockatoos as they came to drink, but instead a more imposing gem appeared
- a multicoloured finch whose beauty is unrivalled. That finch is the subject
of A Guide to...Gouldian Finches and their Mutations, a completely revised
edition of the original Guide to Gouldian Finches which was published in
1991. In this new revised edition, Dr Rob Marshall, one of the original
contributors, is joined by Dr Milton Lewis, Dr Terry Martin and Ron Tristram
as co-authors. All are Australian and possess an intimate knowledge of this
finch.
A Guide to...Gouldian Finches and their Mutations covers every
imaginable aspect of the Gouldian Finch Erythrura gouldiae in the field
and aviary. The table of contents includes:
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909713" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260859" page_num="137" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998814" page_id="56260859"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
137
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9907745" page_id="56260859"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
The Gouldian Finch in the Wild
The Gouldian Finch in Captivity
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.888292">
Mutations and Colour Breeding
Health and Disease
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.981125487179487" page_id="56260859"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
In each of these important sections the authors share their knowledge of
this species with the reader.
The Gouldian Finch used to be placed with the giassfinches in the genus
Poephila, but this taxonomic decision was not to everyone's liking. Some,
for example, regarded it as being closer to the Asian mannikins. Nowadays
taxonomists lean towards treating it as a parrot finch of the genus Erythrura ,
as do the authors of this guide, who explain why in their view this current
treatment is justified.
In its native Australia its range has contracted and there has been a decline
in its numbers. Part of the problem has been caused by habitat modification;
in Australia many plants have evolved with a fire regime, which spurs new
growth and even profuse seeding, but introduced hoofstock, rabbits and even
birds and controlled burning have affected the natural cycle. The Gouldian
prefers savannah woodland with a grassy understory and permanent water.
It has often been suggested that it is insectivorous, but it feeds almost solely
on seeds, which require the aforementioned fire regime.
The Gouldian Finch has evolved to live in a hot, dry climate. This
explains why many pairs prove poor sitters. This is not due to poor breeding
or genetic deterioration but is normal behaviour: in the wild the heat of the
day insures that the eggs do not cool down if they are not being continuously
incubated. This same habit is seen in other birds that share a similar
environment (e.g. the Golden-shouldered Parrot Psephotus chrysopterygius).
Learning about the habits of the Gouldian in the wild is important if a
breeder is to maximize breeding results in captivity. This book covers this
aspect amply. It is one of most valuable features of the book. For the
breeder of mutations, it offers the most recently available information on
genetics. It is richly illustrated and virtually all mutations are represented.
Husbandry is also well covered. The contentious issue of fostering Gouldian
Finches under Bengalese is addressed, with the arguments both for and
against it.
ABK Publications has in recent years produced some superb books. They
are concise, informative and richly illustrated. These traits are evident in
this title, which is highly recommended to those interested in breeding the
spectacular Gouldian Finch.
A Guide to...Gouldian Finches and their Mutations, 160 pages, extensive
photographic collection, is published by ABK Publications, PO Box 6288,
Tweed Heads South, NSW 2486, Australia. Tel: 07 5590 7777/Fax:07 5590
7130/E-mail:birdkeeper@birdkeeper.com.au/Website: www.birdkeeper.
com.au In the UK it is available from Hampshire Breeders and Books, 12
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998827" page_id="56260860"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
138
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.966768" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260860" page_num="138" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.96739275" page_id="56260860"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
Inwood Road, Liss, Hampshire GU33 7LZ (e-mail; pollywood@
supemet.com).Price #24.95 including p&amp;p, for Europe add 10%, for the
rest of the world add 20%.
Derian A. Silva Moraton
A GUIDE TO...BLACK COCKATOOS
A Guide to...Black Cockatoos by Neville and Enid Connors is a book on
aviculture based on years of practical experience and sound common sense
which is uncommon (unfortunately). When it is also written by
acknowledged experts in their field, it becomes a rare gem, worth its weight
in gold. This is how I would describe the book under review. It is an
impressive example of a husband and wife team who tmly know what they
are writing about, passing on their expertise, for this and future generations
of breeders.
It follows ABK's usual formula of discussing all avicultural aspects,
such as housing, feeding, breeding and hand-rearing, then covers each species
in depth, in the wild and in captivity, under a series of useful headings that
are consistent for each species. This makes it easy to find information on
specific topics.
Neville and Noddy (as she is known) have been breeding black cockatoos
Calyptorhynchus spp. for more than 20 years. By the mid-1980s they had
bred and hand-reared all members of the genus. They are known especially
for their successes with the delightful Glossy Cockatoo and they not only
achieved an Australian first breeding with it but have also reared young
consistently ever since.
I love their common sense observations, such as those on the subject of
commercial bird diets (pellets, etc.). Noting that black cockatoos in the
wild either move from one food source to another or use one source that
changes seasonally in nutritional value, they write: "...there have been few
comprehensive studies carried out in the wild on the species featured here
and nothing of note with captive species. Manufacturers' claims that they
have formulated the ultimate diet must be viewed with suspicion if not
contempt unless there is 'proof' that research has been undertaken."
On the subject of aggressive male cockatoos, they offer an alternative to
clipping the feathers of one wing and suggest that at the commencement of
aggressive behaviour black electrical tape is wrapped around four or five of
the primaries. This can be removed when desired. They make the very
pertinent observation that: "...aggressive behaviour is not as sudden as usually
described. There are always subtle telltale signs of disharmony between the
pair. It is when these signs go unnoticed by the aviculturist that more serious
and determined aggression is seen."
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909704" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260861" page_num="139" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999087" page_id="56260861"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
139
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.967145125" page_id="56260861"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
On the subject of hand-rearing they comment that it is inconceivable to
use a commercial mix that has, as its major components, grain types that are
seldom taken by the adult birds and that does not contain a greenfood - a
chlorophyll component. "The result is droppings that resemble a sick child's,
rather than a bird's droppings with the clearly defined faeces and urates."
Information on the various species covers pp.69-147. In addition to the
Calyptorhynchus spp., it includes the Gang Gang Cockatoo and the Palm
Cockatoo. There are countless interesting photos, such as that by Peter
Odekerken of a wild Yellow-tailed Black Cockatoo devouring a grub that it
has just extracted from a tree trunk. The photographs are also invaluable in
the often difficult task of identifying different subspecies of Calyptorhynchus.
Readers should realise that comments such as those about Gang Gang
and Yellow-tailed Black Cockatoos making excellent pets are not relevant
outside Australia, where so few exist and their high price would deter pet
owners.
In Australia the Palm Cockatoo is almost non-existent in aviculture. The
chapter on this species and most of the photos are the work of William
Horsfield of South Africa, one of the world's most experienced breeders of
this species. This is an extremely detailed and useful chapter. He shows an
interesting sequence of five photos of a Palm Cockatoo from pipping to
hatching. The book concludes with a useful section on diseases by avian
vet Bob Doneley.
ABK's A Guide to... series, now boasting more than 20 titles, are
user-friendly books, printed on glossy paper and loaded with colour photos,
one or more to a page. The name is synonymous with quality and this latest
title is one of the best.
A Guide to...Black Cockatoos as Pet and Aviary Birds by Neville and
Enid Connors, 160 pages, 300 colour photographs, is published by ABK
Publications. In the UK it is available from Hampshire Breeders and Books,
12 Inwood Road, Liss, Hampshire GU33 7LZ (e-mail: pollywood
@supemet.com). Hard cover price #27.95 including p&amp;p, for Europe add
10%, for the rest of the world add 20%.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.32942025" page_id="56260861"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
Rosemary Low
* * *
US BANK ACCOUNT
Those who would prefer to make payments in US dollars are reminded
</table>
<reference confidence="0.7333536">
that the society now has a US bank account. Overseas membership for
2006 will remain at US$38 for receiving the magazines by regular mail or
US$50 for air mail. Checks and money orders should be made payable The
Avicultural Society and sent to: The Avicultural Society, c/o Jane Cooper,
12650 Hearst Road, Willits, California 95490-9231, USA.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.995214" page_id="56260862"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
140
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9792865" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260862" page_num="140" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
POSH PIGEONS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.992754333333333" page_id="56260862"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
According to the latest scientific survey, quoted in The Times , September
10th 2005, p.33, the UK population of the Ring-necked Parakeet Psittacula
krameri is increasing by 30% a year and is likely to reach 100,000 by the
end of the decade. The colony that roosts at the rugby ground at Esher in
Surrey, just to the south-west of London, is the largest in the country and is
estimated to number 7,000 birds. In parts of London the parakeets are said
to be referred to as "posh pigeons". They compete for nesting holes with
native species such as the Tawny Owl Strix aluco and Jackdaw Corvus
monedula and perhaps the Green Picus viridis and Great Spotted Woodpecker
Dendrocopos major. A vineyard had its expected 3,000 bottles of wine
reduced to 500, after parakeets descended on it and devoured most of the
season's grape crop.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.689454" page_id="56260862"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.738474" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260862" page_num="140" year="" vol="">
LONG-LIVED GLOSSY STARLINGS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98850685" page_id="56260862"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
In Gefiederte Welt 128:101 (2004) Dr Heinz-Sigurd Raethel provided a
potted history of an extremely long-lived Purple Glossy Starling
Lamprotornis purpureus. It arrived at Berlin Zoo in 1909 from the former
German colony of the Cameroons, West Africa. In 1928 it became blind in
one eye and during 1930 became totally blind. Its keeper Paul Dahne noted
in Gefiederte Welt 66:385-387 (1937), that despite being blind the bird never
missed its daily bath and was a magnificent specimen. Sadly, it was killed
during the bombing of Berlin in 1943, which destroyed the large bird house.
It had lived in the zoo for 34 years, which must surely be a longevity record.
Dr Herbert Schifter, who has a special interest in the longevity of birds,
was kind enough to send a copy of Dr Raethel's letter in Gefiederte Welt
and Christopher Brack kindly translated it from German to English. Dr
Schifter knew of the Berlin bird and at his suggestion Dr Raethel researched
its history and published his findings. Details of Dr Raethel's research were
not available in time for inclusion in Dr Schifter's compilation of longevity
records of starlings published in Gefiederte Welt 127:201 (2003). At that
time the longest-lived starling for which details were available to Dr Schifter
were of a Long-tailed Glossy Starling L. caudatus that had lived in Basle
Zoo, Switzerland, from 1948-1977. It lived there for 28 years, three months
and 18 days.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.679039" page_id="56260862"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700168" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260863" page_num="141" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995866" page_id="56260863"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
141
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995651" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260863" page_num="141" year="" vol="">
SUPPORT FOR CONSERVATION PROJECTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986184666666667" page_id="56260863"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
Chester Zoo supports a number of conservation projects around the world,
one of which, the work with hombills in the Philippines, where earlier this
year on the island of Panay the Critically Endangered Visayan Wrinkled
Hornbill Aceros waldeni was bred for the first time in captivity, was
mentioned in the previous issue (see News &amp; Views Vol, 111, No.2, p.92
(2005)). It also continues to sponsor Great Buceros bicornis and Rhinoceros
Hombill B. rhinoceros nests in Thailand (as does the Avicultural Society).
The zoo also gives major financial support to the Philippine Cockatoo
Conservation Programme on Palawan Island and supports the Greater
Adjutant Stork Leptoptilos dubius rescue and rehabilitation project in Assam,
India. Funding is also provided for the Birecik Northern Bald Ibis Project
in Turkey. The Critically Endangered Northern Bald Ibis Geronticus eremita
breeds only at a few sites, one of which is in Turkey. The project manages
and protects this important breeding population and helps increase local
conservation awareness through a visitor centre.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.678614" page_id="56260863"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.775164" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260863" page_num="141" year="" vol="">
PROBABLY FIRST RECORDED BREEDING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.950316625" page_id="56260863"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
On the subject of the Guira Cuckoo Guira guira (see News &amp; Views
Vol. 111, No.2. p.96 (2005)), Christopher Brack has written from Germany
to say that in 1987, Berlin Zoo imported a small group of these cuckoos
from Uruguay. They bred rapidly and during 1987-1988, from 11 clutches
of eggs, 42 young were hatched of which 28 were reared. This was probably
the first recorded breeding of the Guira Cuckoo in a German zoo. Many of
those bred at Berlin Zoo were acquired by other zoos and bird gardens in
Germany.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.4444295" page_id="56260863"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
* * *
PARROT JUNGLE SETTLES INTO NEW HOME
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.964508" page_id="56260863"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
Parrot Jungle, Miami, Florida, USA, moved to a new home in 2003. It
moved to a custom-built site on Watson Island, a man-made island which
helps connect downtown Miami with Miami Beach. The new park was
designed with the aim of recreating the best attractions of the old park and
enhancing some of the most popular activities. The shows performed at the
old Parrot Jungle always topped the list of attractions visitors enjoyed most,
therefore when the new park was being designed, great effort was put into
designing three larger and distinctive show theatres.
The largest of these, the Parrot Bowl, is capable of seating over 1,200
visitors and is the venue for the park's new bird show - Winged Wonders. A
greater emphasis is now placed on displaying the birds flying, rather than
just performing tricks. The new show also features a greater variety of
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998669" page_id="56260864"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
142
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.927045" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260864" page_num="142" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.928453714285714" page_id="56260864"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
species, which in addition to the familiar performing parrots, includes a
King Vulture Sarcoramphuspapa , Andean Condor Vultur gryphus, Marabou
Stork Leptoptilos crumeniferus, Sarus Crane Grus antigone and even a
Southern Cassowary Casuarius casuarius.
The Serpentarium has a show presentation - Reptile Giants - with
performances throughout the day, which feature a variety of reptiles including
alligators, crocodiles, snapping turtles, monitors, iguanas, tegus, pythons,
boas and venomous snakes. The exhibit area features a variety of reptiles
including two crocodilians of note: an adult albino American Alligator
Alligator mississippiensis and an adult Saltwater Crocodile Crocodylus
porosus which measures 20ft (approx. 6m) in length and weighs l,8001bs
(just over 800kg). The Jungle Theatre features a variety of small to medium-
sized mammals, that include primates and carnivores.
Perhaps the most striking exhibit is a walk-through aviary, which has a
waterfall and a stream and along one entire side, an artificial cliff wall,
which is modelled after the famous claylick cliffs in the Manu National
Park, Pern. More than 60 macaws of five species - the Blue and Gold Ara
ararauna. Green-winged A. chloroptera. Scarlet A. macao, Severe or
Chestnut-fronted A. severa and Red-bellied Orthopsittaca manilata -
currently live in this exhibit. Living along with them are smaller groups of
Mealy Amazons Amazona farinosa, Orange-winged Amazons A amazonica ,
Yellow-crowned Amazons A. ochrocephala and Blue-headed Pionus Pionus
menstruus.
Alongside many of the pathways through the park are exhibits featuring
a good variety of other parrot species. These include the St Vincent Parrot
A. guildingii , Red-vented Cockatoo Cacatua haematuropygia, Red-tailed
Black Cockatoo Calyptorhynchus banksii, Palm Cockatoo Probosciger
aterrimus, Blue-throated Macaw A. glaucogularis , Thick-billed Parrot
Rhynchopsitta pachyrhyncha, Cape Parrot Poicephalus robustus , Illiger's
or Blue-winged Macaw Propyrrhura maracana and Blue-naped Parrot
Tanygnathus lucionensis.
Two walk-through aviaries in which visitors will be able to feed the
birds, the first which will house lorikeets and the second which will house
Australian parakeets, are being completed. Non-parrot species on display
include kookaburras, crowned pigeons, fruit pigeons and turacos. Other
softbills will be added to the collection in the coming months.
Miami sits close to the edge of the Everglades National Park, and the
Everglades exhibit, with replica habitat, various waterbirds, alligators, turtles,
fish and a host of plant species, is a popular attraction and serves as an
outdoor classroom for over 100,000 school children each year.
Flamingo Lake was a central feature of the old Parrot Jungle and has
been included in the new park. Although best known for its bird collection.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700177" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260865" page_num="143" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999409" page_id="56260865"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
143
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9894674" page_id="56260865"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
the park also features a number of mammal species particularly primates.
The lush tropical landscaping and horticultural collection have in a short
time surpassed those of the old park and provide a perfect backdrop for the
park's existing exhibits, and will provide a wonderful backdrop for those
which will be added in the coming years.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.5343175" page_id="56260865"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
* * *
MONITORING FLAMINGOS* HEALTH
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.975634764705882" page_id="56260865"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
Richard Kock, Zoological Society of London Wildlife Epidemiologist,
has for the past 10 years been studying populations of Lesser Flamingo
Phoeniconaias minor on Rift Valley lakes in East Africa. One of the most
widespread and abundant African birds, it is vulnerable because it has so
few suitable breeding sites.
The large number of deaths at some lakes, for example at Lake Nakura
and Lake Bogoria in Kenya, have been associated with droughts and sudden
changes to the lakes' algal flora. Subsequent research has identified bacterial
disease as a significant component of ill health. Tuberculosis, avian cholera
and other infections have been diagnosed as the cause of death of many of
the birds, but what is more important to understand are the possible
contributory factors relating to a breakdown in the immunity of these birds.
These may include nutrition, algal toxins, disturbance and other
environmental stressors.
Richard and other workers have found that monitoring flamingos' health
can act as an indicator as to the overall health of the ecosystem, and have
used data to create baselines to assist with ecosystem assessment techniques.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.754447" page_id="56260865"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.590623" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260865" page_num="143" year="" vol="">
PAINTINGS TO BE CATALOGUED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9964285" page_id="56260865"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
With a #30,000 (approx. US$50,000) donation from The Michael Marks
Charitable Trust, the Zoological Society of London is to embark on a
programme of cataloguing the estimated 6,000 paintings in the ZSL Library,
which include works by such renowned artists as Joseph Wolf and Edward
Lear. It is part of a wider scheme which will also include the cataloguing of
the books and the zoo archives.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.626998" page_id="56260865"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.988183" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260865" page_num="143" year="" vol="">
BRED FOR THE FIRST TIME
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9611716" page_id="56260865"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
In an e-mail sent in mid-October, John Ellis, Curator of Birds at the
Zoological Society of London, mentioned that the Toco Toucans Ramphastos
toco had bred again and had hatched three chicks and the Red-billed Toucan
R. tucanus had bred for the first time at the zoo. One chick had already
fledged and another was still in the nest-box.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999597" page_id="56260866"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
144
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.98178" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260866" page_num="144" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
BRED AT HAREWOOD IN 1985
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996618388888889" page_id="56260866"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
Dr Herbert Schifter was asked recently if he could provide information
on the breeding of the Black-naped Oriole Oriolus chinensis in captivity?
The International Zoo Yearbook Vol.27, p.395, listed two has having been
bred at Harewood Bird Garden, near Leeds, in 1985. He had also found a
reference to this species having been bred at Chester Zoo in 1996. However,
neither breeding was included in Dave Coles' UK Breeding Records and in
his Chester Zoo Bird Review 1996 (. Avicultural Magazine Vol.102, No.4,
pp. 174-179 (1996)) Roger Wilkinson did not mention this species having
been bred there. Could I, Dr Schifter asked, possibly find out about these
breedings?
David Haines, a friend and former colleague from our days working
together in the Bird House at London Zoo, who later worked at Harewood
with Peter Brown, visited the bird garden and asked Peter Stubbs, who has
worked there for over 30 years, about the breeding. He confirmed that two
were bred there in 1985 when Bill Timmis was in charge. Roger Wilkinson
said the reference to this species having bred at Chester Zoo in 1996 was
obviously an error as at that time the Black-naped Oriole was not represented
in the collection at Chester Zoo.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.778377857142857" page_id="56260866"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
I also referred Dr Schifter to the breeding of a Crimson-breasted Oriole
Oriolus cruentus in 2000, listed in The Foreign Bird Federation Register of
Birds Bred in the UK under Controlled Conditions for the Years 1999-2002.
* * *
PUBLISHING PHENOMENON SPANNING 65 YEARS
Neville Brickell wrote recently from South Africa with the news that the
new Roberts Birds of Southern Africa has just become available there. Austin
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.973787571428572" page_id="56260866"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
Roberts' The Birds of South Africa was first published in 1940 and has been
in print ever since. In all, well over 300,000 copies have been sold. This
latest edition, the seventh, runs to 1,296 pages and has completely new text
and new specially commissioned artwork, though in a fitting touch of
nostalgia, Norman Lighton's original frontispiece, depicting a bushveld scene
with ostriches, a ground hombill and Bateleur Eagles soaring majestically
overhead, has been retained.
In the same letter, Neville mentioned that the Javan Munia Lonchura
leucogastroides, whose numbers in South Africa had declined to no more
than 10 birds, has now increased to about 80 individuals. This follows the
purchase by the Indigenous Bird Breeders' Research Group of all the odd
birds and the setting-up of a breeding colony. Neville said that unfortunately
the Green Avadavat Amandava formosa is no longer available in South Africa,
so we must be thankful for the present breeding programme in Australia.
</bodyText>
<bodyText confidence="0.936547125" page_id="56260867"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
In A Photographic Guide to the Birds of Indonesia by Morten Strange,
p.348 (Helm, 2002), the Javan Munia is described as being a widespread
and common resident on Java, Bali and Lombok, which has expanded its
range into southern Sumatra where it possibly has been introduced. In the
AviculturalMagazine Yol.93, No.3, pp. 130-135 (1987), Robin Restall wrote
about the Javan Munia and described watching this species feeding on the
balcony of his first floor hotel room in Singapore. This munia was, Robin
wrote, introduced to Singapore from Indonesia in the 1920s.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.5193134" page_id="56260867"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
* * *
Paignton Zoo Environmental Park
requires
EXPERIENCED AVICULTURISTS
Paignton Zoo Environmental Park is seeking
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.8962232" page_id="56260867"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
two experienced aviculturists to assist a joint
project with the RSPB and English Nature
rearing Cirl Buntings for releases in South West England.
The positions are required to cover 4-6 months starting
Spring 2006 with the possibility of recurring work at a
similar time in 2007/8. Applicants will have experience of
hand-rearing birds, particularly passerines.
Accommodation at the release site will be provided.
Please apply in writing to Colin Bath,
Curator of Birds, Paignton Zoo Environmental Park,
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.6315642">
Totnes Road, Paignton TQ4 7EU.
Closing date: 1st January 2006
Paignton Zoo Environmental Park, Living Coasts and the Whitley
Wildlife Conservation Trust are education and conservation charities
dedicated to protecting our global wildlife heritage.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.780938" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260868" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.96023275862069" page_id="56260868"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
3 9088 01173 8432
Breeding the Desert Finch Rhodopechys obsoleta
by Jeffrey Trollope.97
African Bird Safari - London Zoo's new walk-through aviary
by John Ellis. 102
Paignton Zoo Environmental Park &amp; Living Coasts
Breeding Review - 2004
by Colin Bath. 105
The Grey-winged Trumpeter Psophia crepitans
byJoGregson. 107
Notes on a short visit to Peninsular Malaysia
by Rosemary Low. 109
* The Cuckoo-Roller Leptosomus discolor
by Dieter Rinke. 121
Could this have been another Gray's Lory?
by Herbert Schifter. 123
Breeding the Grey Gull Larus modestus
byJoGregson. 126
Bird News from Chester Zoo - 2004
by Roger Wilkinson. 129
Bird keeping in the tropics
by Robin Restall. 132
Book Reviews
Amazon Parrots ... 135
A Multicoloured Finch of Unrivalled Beauty. 136
A Guide To...Black Cockatoos. 138
News &amp; Views.. 140
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</table>
</algorithms>
