<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.978874166666667" page_id="56264895"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
QLj
Savicultural
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 106
No. 4
2000
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990772" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264896" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991526142857143" page_id="56264896"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in freedom and captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2000 as for 1999: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.551217" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264896" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.72716" page_id="56264896"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Subscription, changes of address, orders for back numbers etc. should be
sent to:
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, c /o BRISTOL ZOOLOGICAL GARDENS, CLIFTON,
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.900506333333333" page_id="56264896"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
BRISTOL BS8 3HA, ENGLAND.
Enquiries regarding membership should be sent to:
THE MEMBERSHIP SECRETARY, Stewart Pyper, 21, Primrose Hill,
Nunney, Frome, Somerset BA11 4NP.
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.996264666666667" page_id="56264896"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998437" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264896" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.9972025">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.820994" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264897" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.398732" page_id="56264897"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 106 - No. 4 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2000
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.986988" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264897" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE POTENTIAL CONTRIBUTION OF AVICULTURE TO
CONSERVATION BREEDING OF ESTRILDID FINCHES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9897313" page_id="56264897"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Andy C. Birchenough and Stewart M. Evans
Introduction
Captive breeding may be the last resort for many species which are on
the brink of extinction and whose natural habitat is no longer able to sustain
them. It has been used successfully to maintain populations of several
species, including the Bali Starling or Rothchild's Myna Leucopsar
rothschildi (Taynton &amp; Jeggo, 1988), Hawaiian Goose Branta sandvicensis
(Black et al. 1991; Black, 1995), Californian Condor Gymnogyps
californianus (Toone &amp; Risser, 1988) and Mauritius Kestrel Falcopunctatus
(Jones et al. 1995). So far, the prime responsibility for maintaining breeding
programmes has fallen on zoological gardens and/or specialist organisations,
such as the Wildfowl and Wetlands Trust and the International Crane
Foundation (Stewart, 1989). However, zoos and wildlife parks have
insufficient staff, space and financial resources to cope with the huge range
and number of species that are currently endangered, and which could benefit
from captive breeding. Even with the enlightened approach to conservation
that is now prevalent, the scope for captive breeding is limited. Tudge (1991)
estimated that, if all of the world's zoos collaborated together, it should be
possible to establish captive breeding programmes for no more than the 800
species of mammals that will require help in the next 200 years (see also
Magin et al. 1994). This would be a commendable achievement, but it is
put in perspective by the plight of just one other class of vertebrates, the
birds. According to Collar et al. (1994), 1,029 of the 9,000 or so species of
land birds are currently at risk, and a further 637 are near-threatened.
However, members of many amateur organisations also keep and breed
animals in captivity, and several of them cater for species which are not
normally given high priority in zoos. The UK-based Australian Finch Society
(AFS) is one such organisation. It was founded in 1971 to cater for hobbyists
who are interested in keeping and breeding Australian grassfinches, belonging
to the family Estrildidae. There are 19 species (Immelmann, 1965) but, one
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99918" page_id="56264898"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
146
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.411893" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264898" page_num="146" year="" vol="">
BIRCHENOUGH &amp; EVANS - ESTRILDID FINCHES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995989097560975" page_id="56264898"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
of them, the Zebra Finch Taeniopygia guttata, was excluded from the AFS
remit from the outset because its interests were catered for by the Zebra
Finch Society. However, the AFS subsequently decided to embrace the 11
species of Indo-Pacific and Pacific parrot finches Erythrura spp., which are
also members of the Estrildidae (Ziswiler et al. 1972; Evans &amp; Fidler, 1990).
Their inclusion was justified because the range of one species, the Blue-
faced Parrot Finch Erythrura trichroa, includes Cape York, on the north-
east tip of Australia. There was an international trade in wild-trapped
Australian grassfinches prior to the Australian Government's ban on the
export of its native flora and fauna in 1960. Wild-caught birds have not
been available since then. Some of the parrot finches are still trapped in the
wild in Indonesia and the Philippines and available to aviculturists from
these sources.
The AFS has some 500-600 members, most of whom are based in the
UK. The AFS became interested in establishing conservation breeding
programmes for species which are threatened in the wild and those which
are endangered in captivity. It set-up the Rare and Difficult Species (RADS)
scheme in 1995. Initially, four species were selected for inclusion in the
scheme: the Gouldian Finch E. gouldiae, Bamboo Parrot Finch E. hyperythra,
Pin-tailed Parrot Finch E. prasina and the Tri-colour Parrot Finch E. tricolor.
It was expected to increase this number as the scheme progressed. A specialist
group of eight to ten experienced breeders, with one of them acting as Group
Manager, was formed for each of the selected species. The objective in
each case was to set-up a viable breeding programme for the species and to
develop and record husbandry techniques. Special attention was given to
the use of studbooks (Olney, 1990). Each bird in the scheme was identified
by a special RADS ring, provided by the AFS, and breeding records were
collated centrally. They were kept on the Single Population Analysis and
Records Keeping System (SPARKS), which has been adopted widely by
zoos and wildlife parks. It enables the ancestry of individual birds to be
traced, and inbreeding coefficients between potential mates calculated so
that pairings between closely-related individuals can be avoided. Group
managers were expected to direct exchanges of birds between breeders, in
much the same way as happens in programmes operated by zoos. The AFS
also recognised the importance of field work, although this was unlikely to
be undertaken by many of its members. Nevertheless, it could be encouraged
by, for example, support for scientific research to: (i) gain information about
food, breeding and habitat requirements of wild birds in order to develop
improved husbandry techniques for captive ones; and (ii) provide information
on the general ecology of the species in order to assess their conservation
status and develop plans for the management of wild populations.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.474331" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264899" page_num="147" year="" vol="">
BIRCHENOUGH &amp; EVANS - ESTRILDID FINCHES 147
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99210403125" page_id="56264899"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
It soon became clear that the original formula for RADS was too
prescriptive. The procedure of record keeping, in particular, was unrealistic
and too demanding for amateur aviculturists, whose main motive in joining
the hobby was often in the pleasure derived from keeping captive birds.
Another problem was that members of RADS groups were reluctant to
exchange birds simply on the instructions of the Group Manager.
Furthermore, a relatively small proportion of the AFS was involved in the
scheme and it was seen by many members as being elitist.
The scheme was therefore revised in 1997 so that all members of the
AFS could be involved. It was decided that all species within the AFS remit
should be included in the new project, RADS PLUS, so that any member
keeping them could be involved. Informal groups dedicated to particular
species would be formed but centralised studbooks would not be kept.
However, although the more flexible arrangement was expected to bring
advantages, there were also disadvantages. For example, the lack of control
of stock makes it more difficult to avoid inbreeding. It was argued that the
way forward was to educate AFS members, and raise their awareness of bad
avicultural practices, so that the AFS as a whole contributed to the
conservation effort on a voluntary basis.
The object of the present paper is to assess the potential contribution
that the AFS can make to the long-term conservation of estrildid finches
within RADS PLUS and the changes in husbandry techniques that will be
needed if its potential is to be achieved. It is based primarily on a
questionnaire, which was sent to all members of the AFS as part of the
RADS PLUS initiative, in order to census birds kept and bred by them in
1997 and 1998. This was needed to assess the status of species in captivity,
and identify those species which are in need of conservation action either
because of their status in captivity or in the wild. The census was also
designed to identify some of the husbandry techniques, such as selecting for
certain traits, and using Bengalese Finches Lonchura striata dom. as foster
parents to rear young, which might be considered to be bad practice as far as
conservation breeding is concerned.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.647977">
Methods
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9653215" page_id="56264899"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
Questionnaires were sent out to all members of the AFS in March 1998
and February 1999. Each was sent with a stamped addressed envelope for
reply as means of encouraging a good response.
Members were asked to provide the following information:
1. The numbers of finches kept at the end of the previous year (December
31st), listing separately adult males, adult females and juveniles in two
categories: (i) normals (i.e. the species as it normally occurs in the wild);
and (ii) colour varieties that have arisen in captivity.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99887" page_id="56264900"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
148
</page>
<note confidence="0.323218">
BIRCHENOUGH &amp; EVANS - ESTRILDID FINCHES
</note>
<listItem confidence="0.869327625" page_id="56264900"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
2. Details of the colour varieties kept (i.e. white-breasted Gouldian Finch,
yellow Star Finch Neochmia ruficauda ).
3. The numbers of finches bred (i.e. surviving until fledging) during the
previous year.
4. The numbers of Bengalese Finches kept, and the numbers of Australian
and parrot finches which were parent-reared or foster-reared by Bengalese
Finches.
5. In the case of Gouldian Finches only, the numbers of normals and colour
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.926874" page_id="56264900"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
varieties which were parent-reared or foster-reared by Bengalese Finches.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.923466">
Results
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99582940625" page_id="56264900"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
291 questionnaires were completed and returned for 1997 and 190 for
1998, representing 50.2% and 32.8% of the AFS membership respectively.
Fourteen of the 19 Australian grassfinches listed by Immelmann (1965)
and eight out of the 11 parrot finches (Ziswiler et al. 1972) were kept by at
least some members of the AFS in both 1997 and 1998. The Gouldian
Finch was easily the most commonly kept species. It was included in more
than 70% of the returns in both years (Table 1). There were more than 3,500
Gouldians in 1997 and 1998, averaging more than 20 of these finches per
breeder. Large numbers of them were also bred in both years of the census.
The Longtail Finch Poephila acuticauda , Star Finch N. ruficauda,
Bicheno Taeniopygia bichenovii, Diamond Firetail Stagonopleura guttata.
Cherry Finch N. modesta. Chestnut-breasted Mannikin Lonchura
castaneothorax, Parson's Finch P. cincta and Masked Finch P. personata of
the Australian grassfinches, and the Red-headed Parrot Finch E. psittacea.
Blue-faced Parrot Finch and Tri-coloured Parrot Finch, are also well-
established in captivity. In each case, more than 10 breeders kept the species,
more than 100 individuals of that species were owned by them and more
than 50 birds were bred per year.
The status of other species in captivity is probably less secure. This
applied to five Australian finches, the Crimson Finch N. phaeton, Painted
Finch Emblema picta. Red-browed Finch N. temporalis, Yellow-rumped
Mannikin L. flavipryma and Pictorella Mannikin Heteromunia pectoralis,
and five parrot finches, the Pin-tailed, Bamboo, Peale's E. pealii, Katanglad
E. coloria and Papuan E. papuana. They were kept by more than 10 breeders,
who between them owned over 100 birds, and over 25 young were bred per
year.
Each of the three naturally-occurring head colour morphs of the Gouldian
Finch is kept in captivity, although the relative proportions in which they
are kept by AFS members is different from those in which they occur in the
wild. About 75% of individuals in the wild are black-headed, and 25% are
red-headed; the yellow-headed morph is unusual (Evans et al. 1985, Evans
&amp; Fidler, 1986). Roughly one third of the captive population was red-headed
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.258048" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
BIRCHENOUGH &amp; EVANS - ESTRILDID FINCHES
</equation>
<page confidence="0.998753" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
149
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.9627105">
Table 1. The numbers of AFS members keeping finches, numbers kept by
them and numbers bred in 1997 and 1998.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.990855181818182" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
Numbers of
breeders
1997 1998
Numbers of
finches kept
1997 1998
Numbers of
finches bred
1997 1998
Australian Grassfinches
Gouldian Finch
</figure>
<page confidence="0.927888" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
206
142
</page>
<figure confidence="0.2150356" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
4868
3581
3432
2744
Longtail Finch
</figure>
<page confidence="0.948472" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
83
63
870
628
769
362
</page>
<author confidence="0.286424">
Star Finch
</author>
<page confidence="0.984729666666667" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
73
51
615
326
388
174
</page>
<figure confidence="0.293422" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
Bicheno
</figure>
<page confidence="0.968511666666667" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
69
47
626
266
426
169
</page>
<figure confidence="0.4348825" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
Diamond Firetail
55
</figure>
<page confidence="0.868554" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
36
335
235
211
</page>
<figure confidence="0.685288666666667" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
130
Cherry Finch
54
</figure>
<page confidence="0.8700355" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
32
414
190
403
</page>
<figure confidence="0.7456665" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
96
Chestnut-breasted Mannikin
36
30
</figure>
<page confidence="0.93691575" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
225
216
141
126
</page>
<table confidence="0.236349" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
Parson's Finch
</table>
<page confidence="0.884231333333333" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
36
22
189
105
166
108
</page>
<figure confidence="0.918480577777778" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
Masked Finch
25
13
193
110
139
58
Crimson Finch
8
8
33
27
6
4
! Painted Finch
7
7
36
44
15
0
Red-browed Finch
10
4
37
27
10
9 i
Yellow-ramped Mannikin
7
4
20
13
5
0
Pictorella Mannikin
4
3
24
17
6
1
Parrot Finches
Red-headed Parrot Finch
59
</figure>
<page confidence="0.9531374" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
43
461
330
323
123
</page>
<table confidence="0.31765" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
Blue-faced Parrot Finch
</table>
<page confidence="0.9478872" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
47
37
322
186
153
</page>
<figure confidence="0.82983775" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
100
Tri-coloured Parrot Finch
44
25
</figure>
<page confidence="0.852321333333333" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
354
205
11
</page>
<figure confidence="0.942282685714286" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
96
Pin-tailed Parrot Finch
26
15
151
56
39
13
Bamboo Parrot Finch
18
11
88
65
20
23
i Peale's Parrot Finch
8
5
66
49
11
19
Katanglad Parrot Finch
2
3
10
32
0
0
Papuan Parrot Finch
1
2
37
11
16
</figure>
<page confidence="0.795103" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
2
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9971554" page_id="56264901"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
and more than 15% was yellow-headed (Table 2). The differences in wild
and captive populations were significant in both 1997 and 1998 (PcO.OOl in
both cases; Chi-square Test). Several colour varieties have arisen in captivity.
They have been grouped together in Table 2 because there is inconsistency
in the descriptive names given to them by breeders. It is clear, nevertheless,
that a range of colour morphs have been established in the Gouldian Finch.
The white-breasted form is commonly kept but a number of other morphs,
affecting breast, wing and general body colouration, are now available.
Roughly one third of Gouldian Finches in captivity in 1997 and 1998
expressed at least one of these colour mutations. There are also colour
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.985839" page_id="56264902"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
150
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.310987" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264902" page_num="150" year="" vol="">
BIRCHENOUGH &amp; EVANS - ESTRILDID FINCHES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.374727" page_id="56264902"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
varieties of other species. Some of them, especially those of the Long-tail
Finch, Star Finch, Diamond Firetail, Parson's Finch and Red-headed Parrot
Finch, are well-established in captivity.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.856409">
Table 2. The occurrence of naturally-occurring colour morphs and colour
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.472705" page_id="56264902"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
varieties which have been established in captivity in stock kept by
members of AFS.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.962373833333333" page_id="56264902"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
Colour variety
Numbers
kept
1997 1998
Percent kept
of total birds
1997 1998
Naturally-occurring morphs
Australian Grassfinches
Gouldian Finch
Black-headed
1111
</figure>
<page confidence="0.873597666666667" page_id="56264902"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
734
47.7
48.3
</page>
<figure confidence="0.565221" page_id="56264902"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
Red-headed
</figure>
<page confidence="0.82609175" page_id="56264902"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
845
517
36.3
34.1
</page>
<figure confidence="0.559467" page_id="56264902"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
Yellow-headed
</figure>
<page confidence="0.856321" page_id="56264902"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
375
269
</page>
<figure confidence="0.931696083333333" page_id="56264902"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
16.1
17.6
Domestically established varieties
Australian Grassfinches
Gouldian Finch
Body colour
1318
1338
27.1
37.4
Long-tail Finch
Body colour
</figure>
<page confidence="0.890861" page_id="56264902"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
98
101
</page>
<figure confidence="0.8934115" page_id="56264902"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
11.3
16.1
Star Finch
Body coloured/pied
148
121
24.1
37.1
Diamond Firetail
Body colour
69
69
4.9
10.6
Chestnut-breasted Mannikin
Body colour
11
23
10.6
13.3
Parson's Finch
Body colour
20
14
</figure>
<page confidence="0.8185415" page_id="56264902"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
166
108
</page>
<figure confidence="0.9475405" page_id="56264902"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
Crimson Finch
Body colour
2
2
6.1
7.4
Parrot Finches
Red-headed Parrot Finch
Body colour/pied
58
93
12.6
28.2
Blue-faced Parrot Finch
Body colour
20
3
6.2
</figure>
<page confidence="0.891669" page_id="56264902"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
1.6
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.964206">
Table 3. The use of Bengalese finches as foster parents.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.931671961538461" page_id="56264902"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
1997
1998
Numbers of breeders keeping Bengalese Finches
137
102
Percent breeders keeping Bengalese Finches as a percent of
total breeders
47.1
53.7
Mean number of Bengalese Finches kept per breeder
26.2
22.3
Number of breeders using Bengalese Finches as foster parents
124
82
Numbers of breeders using Bengalese Finches as foster parents
as percent of those keeping them
90.5
80.4
Percent of wild-type (normal) Gouldian Finches foster-reared
by Bengalese Finches
33.9
26.6
Percent of domestically-established colour varieties of the
Gouldian Finch foster-reared by Bengalese Finches
54.5
</figure>
<page confidence="0.746907" page_id="56264902"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
53.9
</page>
<equation confidence="0.258725" page_id="56264903"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
BIRCHENOUGH &amp; EVANS - ESTRILDID FINCHES
</equation>
<page confidence="0.998422" page_id="56264903"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
151
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999060375" page_id="56264903"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
Approximately half the AFS members kept Bengalese Finches, and most
of them used these finches as foster parents for rearing Australian finches or
parrot finches; more than 40% of the finches bred in 1997 and 1998 were
reared by them (Table 3). At least in the case of the Gouldian Finch, there
was the tendency for the more valuable (domestically-arising) colour varieties
to be foster-reared than wild type (normal) birds; more than 50% of the
Gouldian Finches of the various colour varieties were reared by Bengalese
Finches, compared with less than 40% of wild-type birds.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.749736">
Discussion
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99450234375" page_id="56264903"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
Amateur aviculture has the potential to make an enormous contribution
to conservation breeding of birds, and therefore to the maintenance of bird
biodiversity. Members of the AFS constitute a specialist, and numerically
small section of the avicultural hobby, and yet they have the skills and
commitment to maintain the large majority of Australian grassfinches in
captivity. These species have been established without any recourse to wild-
caught birds for more than 40 years, that is, since the Australian Government's
1960 ban on the export of indigenous flora and fauna. AFS members have
been almost as successful with parrot finches, although several species are
not yet fully established in captivity. Although the AFS restricts itself to
two groups only of the Estrildidae, there is little doubt that, given the same
commitment and a larger membership, it could establish possibly all of the
120 or so species in the family (Goodwin, 1982) in captivity. Interestingly,
Australian aviculturists have been as successful as their European
counterparts in breeding estrildids. They have established several of the
Asian and African species, which were imported into their country before
1960, but became unavailable as wild-caught birds after that date (Evans &amp;
Fidler, 1990). It should be noted that estrildids are not normally kept in
significant numbers in zoos, or even specialist bird gardens, so the
contribution is in addition to existing conservation efforts. Furthermore,
since the costs are borne by the hobby, they compare highly favourably with
the huge costs of many professional conservation programmes (eg. Kleimann
etal. 1991).
However, amateur aviculture is currently unfocused, as far as
conservation breeding is concerned. Aviculturists keep and breed whichever
species appeal to them. The information provided in the census presents an
opportunity for them to decide to concentrate on species which are in need
of attention because they are threatened in captivity and/or in the wild. Three
of the species currently kept by AFS members are globally threatened:
Gouldian Finch, Star Finch and Katanglad Parrot Finch (Collar et al. 1994).
In addition, two species are near-threatened: the Pictorella Mannikin and
Yellow-ramped Mannikin. The Gouldian Finch and Star Finch are both
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998659" page_id="56264904"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
152
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.412081" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264904" page_num="152" year="" vol="">
BIRCHENOUGH &amp; EVANS - ESTRILDID FINCHES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998605642857143" page_id="56264904"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
secure in captivity, although captive populations of both of them have been
'corrupted' by colour mutants (see below). Conversely, there are few
members of the AFS who keep the three remaining species, the Katanglad
Parrot Finch, Pictorella Mannikin and Yellow-rumped Mannikin. Each of
them was included in small numbers only in the census returns, and were
bred infrequently. In fact, there were no breeding records at all of Katanglad
Parrot Finches in either 1997 or 1998. There is a clear need to concentrate
on these species, and groups are being established within the RADS PLUS
to cater for them. A specialist group is also being formed to breed strains of
wild-type Gouldian Finches, in which the various colour mutants will be
selected out (P. Holland pers. comm.).
There are, nevertheless, three important respects in which the husbandry
practices in the AFS differ from those practised in the conservation breeding
programmes that are operated by zoos and wildlife gardens. Each of them
need to be addressed if aviculture is to realise its potential in captive breeding.
The first concern is that most of the major zoo conservation breeding
programmes depend heavily on detailed record keeping based on studbooks,
computer analysis of kinship and mechanisms for identifying and exchanging
unrelated birds, in order to avoid inbreeding and retain genetic diversity in
the stock (Ballou &amp; Lacy, 1995). Experiences in the AFS RADS Scheme
suggest that this level of record-keeping is not feasible in an amateur hobby.
However, the huge commitment of human resources in the professional
programmes must also be a concern for them. In fact, less demanding, low
intensity management techniques have been developed for species that are
maintained in social groups or colonies and for which detailed pedigree
data cannot therefore be collected (Burlingham-Johnson et al. 1994; Princee,
1995). These techniques are probably more appropriate for aviculture (and,
due to lack of resources, possibly some zoos as well). They ensure that at
least some attention is given to procedures which promote the maintenance
of genetic diversity, such as outbreeding stock and ensuring that as many
individuals as possible have the opportunity to reproduce.
The second concern is that aviculturists are artificially selecting for
particular traits in their stock and this will eventually lead to the
morphological, behavioural or physiological changes that have occurred in
other domestic animals (Hafez, 1969). The result is that, like the domestic
fowl and the canary, they come to bear little resemblance to their wild
counterparts. The domestication process is still in its infancy in captive
estrildids but is, nevertheless, occurring. The clearest example of artificial
selection relates to the selective breeding for particular head colour morphs
in the Gouldian Finch. Yellow-headed morphs are rare in the wild but have
increased significantly in captivity, representing almost 20% of the Gouldian
Finches included in the censuses for 1997 and 1998. There is also selection
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.258263" page_id="56264905"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
BIRCHENOUGH &amp; EVANS - ESTRILDID FINCHES
</equation>
<page confidence="0.999409" page_id="56264905"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
153
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999212380952381" page_id="56264905"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
for colour morphs which have arisen in captivity. Only one colour morph
of the Gouldian Finch, the white-breasted form, had been established in
captivity in the mid-1980s (Evans &amp; Fidler, 1986) but several different colour
varieties are now available. There are also morphs of the most of the
Australian grassfinches and parrot finches that are well-established in
captivity. Selective pressure for them is evidently high because the
percentage numbers of colour morphs in the census returns for 1998 were
higher than those for 1997 in eight of the nine species in which they were
reported. There is some hybridisation between species. Immelmann (1965)
lists many of those that have occurred between species of Australian
grassfinches. They occur most frequently between closely-related species,
and he cites a successful mating between the Gouldian Finch and the Blue-
faced Parrot Finch as evidence that they are close relatives. Unfortunately,
many of these hybrids are fertile and they can blur species distinctions if
they are allowed to interbreed with the 'true' species. It is reported that this
has happened in Australia where aviculturists have, since the 1960 import
ban, maintained the three African cordon bleus : the Red-cheeked Cordon
Bleu Uraeginthus bengalus, Blue-capped Cordon Bleu U. cyanocephalus
and Blue-breasted Cordon Bleu U. angolensis. They have been interbred
and it is said that almost all birds now have characteristics of at least two of
the species.
The third concern relates to the widespread use of Bengalese Finches as
foster parents. It is generally recognised that these foster parents have been
invaluable in establishing estrildid species in captivity (M.E. Fidler pers.
comm.). However, they are still used extensively and, as the census has
shown in the case of the Gouldian Finch, they are used to increase production
from valued birds. This is bad avicultural practice because it reduces the
numbers of birds that are reproducing and contributing to the gene pool, and
therefore the genetic diversity of the captive population. It also encourages
the rate at which mutant genes can spread through the population. The
white-breasted colour variety was introduced into the UK from South Africa
in 1969 and 1970. The introduced birds were valuable and were interbred
with wild-type birds. Numbers of offspring were increased by fostering
clutches of eggs under Bengalese Finches and, a decade later, almost 20%
of the Gouldian Finches kept by leading breeders were white-breasted (Evans
&amp; Fidler, 1986).
Avicultural bodies must also look to collaborate closely with scientists
and organisations which specialise in captive breeding. Mallinson (1991)
has argued strongly for increased partnership between zoos, local
governments and non-governmental organisations, and strong links would
be equally beneficial for aviculture. Similar collaboration has occurred
between professional and amateur ornithologists, often with spectacular
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999534" page_id="56264906"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
154
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.412192" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264906" page_num="154" year="" vol="">
BIRCHENOUGH &amp; EVANS - ESTRILDID FINCHES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994511066666667" page_id="56264906"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
results in projects, such as those involved in the Birds of Estuaries Enquiry
(Prater, 1981) and in producing the Atlas of Australian Birds (Blakers et al.
1986) . However, collaboration with avicultural organisations has
undoubtedly been inhibited in the past by the poor profile generated by their
supposed dependence on the pet trade to obtain birds. Unsavoury aspects of
the international trade in wild-caught birds (Carter &amp; Curry, 1987; Beissinger
et al. 1991) and the damage caused by bird-trapping to wild populations,
especially of parrots (Collar &amp; Juniper, 1991), are unacceptable to most,
perhaps all, scientists. Wisely, therefore, the AFS has disassociated itself
from the bird trade and has publicly spoken out against it. Since doing so, it
has strengthened its links with the scientific community. For instance, the
RADS Scheme, and the census reported here which is part of RADS PLUS,
is due in large part to collaboration with Newcastle University scientists.
The AFS has also supported their field studies of estrildid finches in the
Kimberley region of northern Australia (Evans et al. 1985; Evans &amp; Bougher,
1987) , and these have subsequently formed the basis of a monitoring
programme of Gouldian Finch abundance undertaken by the Northern
Territory Conservation Commission. The AFS and Newcastle University
are still involved and the most recent (1999) Kimberley finch counts involved
a group of AFS members. Additional scientific work has been sponsored
on the Samoan subspecies of the Royal Parrot Finch E. cyaneovirens in
Western Samoa in 1993 (Evans et al. 1994), on the Tri-colour Parrot Finch
E. tricolor in Timor (Indonesia) in 1996 (Madden et al. 1997), on the
Vanuatuan subspecies of the Royal Parrot Finch E. cyaneovirens in Vanuatu
in 1998 (Birchenough &amp; Evans in preparation) and on the Pink-billed Parrot
Finch E. kleinschmidti in Fiji in 2000. Harewood Bird Gardens is also
involved in the research in the South Pacific. The AFS is now contributing
to the work of the UK Zoo Federation's Passerine Taxon Advisory Group.
An Estrildid Working Group, on which the AFS is represented, has been
formed, and has held two meetings, in 1999 and 2000.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.869295" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56264906" page_num="154" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995719666666667" page_id="56264906"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
We would like to thank innumerable members of the Australian Finch
Society for their support. Percy Holland and Mike Fidler, in particular,
have always provided stimulating discussion and encouragement. Percy is
leading RADS PLUS and deserves every success. We would also like to
thank Simon Tonge for his constructive criticism of an earlier version of
this article.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.942428" genericHeader="references" page_id="56264906" page_num="154" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.892672666666667" page_id="56264906"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
Ballou, J.D. and Lacy, R.C. 1995. Identifying genetically important individuals for management
of genetic variation in pedigreed populations. In: Population Management for Survival and
Recovery , pp. 76-111. Eds. Ballou, J.D., Gilpin, M. and Foose, T.J. Columbia University
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.258093" page_id="56264907"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
BIRCHENOUGH &amp; EVANS - ESTRILDID FINCHES
</equation>
<page confidence="0.998869" page_id="56264907"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
155
</page>
<reference confidence="0.915427809523809">
Press, New York.
Beissinger, S.R., Snyder, N.F.R., Derrickson, S.R., James, F.C. and Lanyon, S.M. 1991. The
conservation crisis. International trade in live birds creates a vast movement that must be halted.
Auk 108: 982-994.
Black, S.M. 1995. The Nene Branta sandvicensis. Recovery initiative: research against
extinction. Ibis 137: S153-S160.
Black, S.M., Duvall, F., Hoshide, H., Madeiros, J., Hodges, C.N., Santos, N. and Telfer, T.
1991. The current status of the Hawaiian goose Branta sandvicensis and its recovery programme.
Wildfowl 42: 149-154.
B lakers, M., Davies, S.J.J.F. and Reilly, P.N. 1984. The Atlas of Australian Birds. Melbourne
University Press, Melbourne.
Burlingham-Johnson, A., Clarke, D. and Pearce-Kelly, P. 1994. CERCI: a computer system
for demographic and genetic analysis of captive invertebrates, fish and other populations of
colony animals. International Zoo Yearbook 33: 278-283.
Carter, N. and Curry, D. 1987. The Trade in Wildlife. Mortality and Transport Conditions.
Environmental Investigation Agency, Calvert Press.
Collar, N.J. and Juniper, A.T. 1991. Dimensions and causes of the parrot crisis. In: New World
Parrots in Crisis: Solutions from Conservation Biology. Eds. Beissinger, S.R. and Snyder,
N.F.R. Smithsonian International Press, Washington. D.C.
Collar, N.J., Crosby, M.J. and Stattersfield, A.J. 1994. Birds to Watch 2. The World List of
Threatened Birds. BirdLife International, Cambridge.
</reference>
<figureCaption confidence="0.711188833333333">
Evans, S.M. &amp; Bougher, A.J. 1987. The abundance of estrildid finches at waterholes in the
Kimberley (W.A.). Emu 87: 101-104.
Evans, S.M. and Fidler, M.E. 1986. The Gouldian Finch. Blandford Press, Poole, New York,
Sydney.
Evans, S.M. and Fidler, M.E. 1990. Parrot Finches. The Aviculturist's Guide. Blandford, London.
Evans, S.M., Collins, J.A., Evans, R. and Miller, S. 1985. Patterns of drinking behaviour in
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.729395923076923" page_id="56264907"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
some Australian estrildine finches. Ibis 127: 348-354.
Evans, S.M., Fletcher, F.J.C., Loader, P.J. and Rooksby, F.G. 1992. Habitat exploitation by
landbirds in the changing Western Samoan environment. Bird Conservation International 2:
123-129.
Goodwin, D. 1982. Estrildid Finches of the World. British Museum (Natural History), Oxford
University Press, Oxford.
Hafez, E.S.E. 1969. The Behaviour of Domestic Animals. Bailliere, Tindall and Cassell, London.
Immelmann, K. 1965. Australian Finches in Bush and Aviary. Angus and Robertson, Sydney
and London.
Jones, C.G., Heck, W., Lewis, R.E., Mungovo, Y., Slade, G. and Cade, T. 1995. The restoration
of the Mauritius Kestrel Falco punctatus population. Ibis 137: S173-S180.
Kleiman, D.G., Beck, B.B., Dietz, J.D. and Dietz, L.A. 1991. Costs of reintroduction and
criteria for success: accounting and accountability in the golden lion tamarin conservation
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.977107545454546">
programme. In: Beyond Captive Breeding: Reintroducing Endangered Species to the Wild, pp.
125-142. Ed. Gipps, J.H.W. Oxford University Press, Oxford.
Madden, J., Bird, C., Williams, S. and Retraubun, A. 1997. Threats to estrildid finches of West
Timor. Grassfinch 21: 95-98.
Magin, C.D., Johnsong, T.H., Groombridge, B., Jenkins, M. and Smith, H. 1994. Species
extinctions, endangerment and captive breeding. In: Creative Conservation: Interactive
Management of Wild and Captive Animals, pp. 3-31. Eds. Olney, P.J.S., Mace, G.M. andFeistner,
A.T.C. Chapman and Hall, London.
Olney, P.J.S. 1990. Studbooks, their history, organisation and uses. In: Pheasants in Asia 1989.
Eds. Hill, D.A., Garson, P.J. and Jenkins, D. World Pheasant Association, Reading.
Prater, A.J. 1981. Estuary Birds of Britain and Ireland. T. &amp; A.D. Poyser, Calton.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999361" page_id="56264908"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
156
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.400846" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264908" page_num="156" year="" vol="">
BIRCHENOUGH &amp; EVANS - ESTRILDID FINCHES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9312078" page_id="56264908"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
Princee, F.P.G. 1995. Overcoming the constraints of social structure and incomplete pedigree
data through low-intensity genetic management. In: Population Management for Survival and
Recovery, pp. 124-154. Eds. Ballou, J.D., Gilpin, M. and Foose, T.J. Columbia University
Press, New York.
Stewart, J.M. 1989. The 'lily of birds': the success story of the Siberian white crane. Oryx 21:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.574673" page_id="56264908"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
6 - 10 .
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.3735225" page_id="56264908"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
Taynton, K. and Jeggo, D. 1988. Factors affecting breeding success of Rothschild's Mynah
Leucospar rothschildi at the Jersey Wildlife Preservation Trust. Dodo Journal of the Jersey
Wildlife Preservation Trust 25: 66-76.
Toone, W.D. and Risser, A.C. 1988. Captive management of the California Condor Gymnogyps
californianus. International Zoo Yearbook 27: 50-57.
Tudge, C. 1991. Last Animals at the Zoo. Hutchinson Radius. London, Sydney, Auckland,
Johannesburg.
Ziswiler, V., Guttinger, H.R. and Bregulla, H. 1972. Monographic der gattung Erythrura
Swainson 1873 (Aves, Passeres, Estrildidae). Bonner Zoologische Monographien No. 2.
Dr Stewart Evans is a Senior Lecturer at Newcastle University,
Department of Marine Sciences and Coastal Management, Dove Marine
Laboratory, Cullercoats, North Shields, Tyne and Wear NE30 4PZ, England.
He is also President of the Australian Finch Society. With Anthony J.
Bougher, he wrote Field and aviary notes on the behaviour of the Crimson
Finch Neochima phaeton in the Avicultural Magazine 92,3:143-147. Andy
Birchenough is a postgraduate research student reading for a PhD.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.982933" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264909" page_num="157" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE WHITE-BREASTED AMAZILIA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.341752" page_id="56264909"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
Amazilia amazilia leucophoea
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998217" page_id="56264909"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
157
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.985480815789474" page_id="56264909"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
by Ivor Grogan
In spring 1990, the female White-breasted Amazilia was living in a flight
in a lean-to conservatory aviary designed and built five years earlier for the
keeping of nectar-feeding birds. The aviary itself is 12ft long x 3ft wide x 7ft
6in high (approx. 3.6m long x 1m wide x 2.2m high). The bottom 2ft (61cm)
is walled-up and has a Sin (12.5cm) layer of pea shingle, on top of which is an
18in (46cm) layer of soil and compost, retained within a pond liner which has
a hole in it beneath which is a drain. Ficus, dracena, jasmine and bellbine are
planted in the aviary. It is wired on one side only as it is connected to the
kitchen window, the idea being that the birds can be seen without the view
being obstructed by wire. The glass-covered side backs onto not only the
office but the access to the garden and the bird sheds, while on the other side
there is an outside toilet and another shed. The planting of the aviary has been
done in such a way that the birds cannot gather enough speed to fly in a
straight line and strike the glass. Within the first year some of the plants
growing by the glass had to be replaced by artificial plants because the sun
burnt them and they died. The inside of the aviary is sprayed most days and a
large flower pot saucer, on an up-turned log, acts as a bath.
As there is a considerable number of visitors, new arrivals are not put
into aviaries here until they have become accustomed to humans being near
them when they are feeding, etc., but are tended to and left in peace until
they settle down. They are caged separately and placed in the office where
the temperature can be more accurately controlled, and the cages are cleaned
out only when it is really necessary. The female White-breasted Amazilia
was brought back from the continent along with some other hummingbirds
and sunbirds, plus some finches, three years ago. She was so young that she
still had gape marks on the sides of the bill. Although I stated earlier that
birds are on arriving caged separately, some species can be mixed, but in
my experience often for no longer than a maximum of two to three days.
Initially the female was caged with two others that needed watching, and
they were checked every few hours of the day and night, and for the first 24
hours were fed by hand with a quite strong nectar mixture.
When the birds were being sorted out for that year's National Exhibition
of Cage and Aviary Birds, the decision was taken that she and three others
were too young to travel again or be passed on to other bird keepers, so they
were left behind. After the National Exhibition things become quiet here
for about two months and there was time to reflect and plan what to do next,
now that my hobby was turning into a business.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999106" page_id="56264910"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
158
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.857158" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264910" page_num="158" year="" vol="">
GROGAN - WHITE-BREASTED AMAZILIA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999604511627907" page_id="56264910"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
In the next few months, as their condition improved, the three birds took
on characters of their own. However, we made sure they did not become
too inactive, as hummingbirds can if caged. To help guard against this we
pushed grapes between the cage wires and sprayed the birds daily.
The policy here is that birds have to adapt to living together in as near
harmony as possible. As hummingbirds and sunbirds are so territorial, in
the aviary in question nine nectar tubes were placed at various heights, with
some hidden behind plants. The female White-breasted Amazilia was for
sale but no one was interested, probably because of her small size and dull
coloration, so in December 1998 she was placed in the aviary along with
two Violet-eared Colibri thalassinus, a Ruby-Topaz Chrysolampis mosquitus,
a Blue-throated Sapphire Chlorostilbon notatus, another Amazilia Amazilia
spp., plus a Burnished Buff Tanager Tangara cay ana, a pair of Splendid
Sunbirds Nectarinia coccinigastra, a pair of Scarlet-chested Sunbirds N.
senegalensis and a Ruby-cheeked Sunbird Anthreptes singalensis. All were
placed in the aviary at the same time in the hope that this would minimise
territorial disputes. The tanager though decided it was going to build a nest
in the middle of the aviary and had to be removed, as all hell broke loose
whenever any other bird went near where it was building.
In March 1999 the female White-bellied Amazilia started to build a nest
in the most exposed part of the aviary, in a canary coconut nest-pan intended
for the sunbirds. It was attached to a cut wigela branch suspended from a
post on the wired side of the aviary. As the branch dried out it twisted
around so that the nest-pan was almost.on its side. It bothered me that no
fresh cobwebs were available, leaving me to provide old ones, along with
dog hair, cotton wool, horse hair and kapok from the lining of a coat. The
female used the cotton wool to make a cup-shaped nest which was only
about Vun (6mm) high when the first egg was laid. A bit more building
work took place before the second egg appeared. Despite not having a
male, I checked the eggs just in case she may have mated with one of the
other male hummingbirds in the aviary.
I rang everyone I could think of in the UK who might be able to help me
obtain a male, but without success. So I then switched my search to Belgium.
Three weeks later I found someone in the UK with a male. However, he
wanted it for showing and was not willing to sell it. He did though loan it to
me and though it was in show condition, appeared not to be in breeding
condition and was returned a month later. Much to the amusement of bird
keepers who visited here, the female continued her nesting behaviour until
midsummer and laid two single eggs which showed signs of being fertile,
but failed to hatch.
In late October I received a phone call to say that a consignment of
hummingbirds from Peru were due to arrive in Belgium. Three weeks
later I received a call to say that the birds had left Peru and two days later
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.520801" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264911" page_num="159" year="" vol="">
GROGAN - WHITE-BREASTED AMAZILIA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999411" page_id="56264911"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
159
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999260714285714" page_id="56264911"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
learnt that they had arrived in Belgium. Twelve hours later I was standing
in the dealer's premises in Belgium and was surprised to see these amazing
little birds in such numbers - 30 of one species, 10 of another, and so on. I
selected three males as possible mates for my female. One was very young,
one was about two years old and the third was a brilliantly coloured older
bird.
I returned home to England hoping that the birds would come through
their quarantine in Belgium without any problems. As always things did
not go according to plan, a week later I received a phone call with the bad
news that the second of my males had died. I turned down the chance of a
replacement, deciding instead to stick with the two males I had already paid
for, although I realised this might create a problem.
As soon as they had completed their quarantine, I gathered together the
paperwork and made arrangements to travel to Belgium to collect them,
praying that the French would not blockade the port of Calais when we
were travelling home, as they had done on previous trips. We had no desire
to get stuck abroad, with delicate hummingbirds that required nectar about
every twenty minutes and heated accommodation. Also, I had been stopped
no less than eight times before when leaving France, once even being escorted
to the Customs because of confusion over the identity of one of the species
I was bringing back to England, a misunderstanding which had taken six
hours to resolve. This time thankfully there were no such difficulties and
we soon reached Dover where we were held up at Customs for just 10
minutes, before driving home at great speed and arriving back some five
hours after leaving Belgium.
The week before Christmas the birds had already been taken out of the
aviary ready for the National Exhibitions in England, Scotland and Wales,
leaving the female White-bellied Amazilia with the flight all to herself. The
birds did amazingly well on the show bench and the first to be returned to
the aviary was the female Scarlet-chested Sunbird. She had been back in
the aviary for all of five minutes when she had to be removed again because
although the sunbird was at least twice as big as the hummingbird, she was
being attacked by it. It was decided to leave the hummingbird in the aviary
on her own. Then in early January one of the males was introduced into the
aviary. I wondered how long it was likely to be before I would have to get
into the aviary to separate them, which would not be easy as it was designed
without a door, and has to be entered by climbing in through a window!
I stood back and waited to see what would happen but much to my
surprise, the female sat at one end of the aviary and the male sat at the other.
This went on for two days, before I removed the male and and replaced him
with the oldest of the original three. In the meantime the female had started
nest building in earnest.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99454" page_id="56264912"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
160
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.839572" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264912" page_num="160" year="" vol="">
GROGAN - WHITE-BREASTED AMAZILIA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999139930232558" page_id="56264912"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
I shall never forget the pair trying to display is such a small area. After
an hour or so though they ended up on the floor of the aviary, spinning
around in circles like two fighting cocks. This lasted about two minutes and
stopped just as the decision was being taken to intervene and separate them.
After this I thought it was the end of trying to get her to live with the male,
but how wrong could I be! I have never seen them fight again. Further
flying displays were seen and on the third day I witnessed them mating.
Following the mating I thought it best to remove the male, but he failed to
settle down back in a cage and two days later was returned to the aviary.
Within seconds of being returned to the aviary the male showed renewed
interest in the female, but she saw him off. There was no fighting though
and after five minutes they stopped chasing each other and started to display.
After doing this periodically for 20 minutes, the female alighted on a branch,
having first taken a sip of nectar from one of the tubes, while the male
perched at the other end of the aviary. The female started to bow and as if
by invitation the male perched beside her and then mating took place. This
behaviour always followed the same pattern. She would mount him and
then fly a short distance (about 2in (5cm)) and then allow him to copulate
with her. This happened speedily after which they would part and then keep
their distance from each other. After about an hour the male was removed
for a while. On the fourth day the female laid her first egg followed two
days later by another on January 15th. Neither hatched.
Following this the plants in the flight were rearranged, some being pruned
and others moved. Because of concern that the female would lay another
clutch without having mated, the nest was destroyed. February 1st the male
was reintroduced in an all-wire finch cage and was released from this. The
female was still exploring the rearranged aviary but as soon as the male was
reintroduced the birds started to display again. The male mated with the
female and was removed after two hours. Next day he was reintroduced
and because the female was nest building quickly, was not taken out until
two days later.
During the visit of a friend who doubted my claim that I was attempting
to breed hummingbirds, I reintroduced the male into the brightly lit aviary
and the friend was able to witness the birds displaying and mating three
times within 20 minutes, by which time it was 6.00pm and dark outside.
The male was removed at 8.00pm and returned again the next day because
the female was building the nest very quickly. He was removed again about
3.00pm. The female's flight changed slowly during the next few days and
by Sunday was more butterfly-like and graceful and elegant, and, as she
twisted and turned it was possible to see all the glittering feathers as never
before. The male has a helmeted crest seen only when he is displaying.
When changing the bird's bath water that Sunday I stood on something
to take a sneak look into the nest and to my great delight there was a
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.520768" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264913" page_num="161" year="" vol="">
GROGAN - WHITE-BREASTED AMAZILIA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998543" page_id="56264913"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
161
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999615880952381" page_id="56264913"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
translucent pink egg in the saucer-shaded nest of white dog hair and cotton
wool. When I checked the nest on Tuesday there were two eggs, the first of
which had started to turn white. The following day the female was sitting
high in the flight with her plumage fluffed- up. I did not panic as if you do
you often make mistakes, instead I watched her carefully during the morning
to make sure she was feeding, and when I was satisifed about this, left her in
peace. That afternoon I was visited by a lady from MAFF (Ministry of
Agriculture, Fish &amp; Food), who came to stamp my licences. She took an
interest in the birds, having previously only seen hummingbirds on TV, and
felt I should not be surprised by the female&apos;s 'rough 5 appearance and
suggested that a small bird laying two such large eggs must be equivalent to
a woman giving birth to a 501b (22kg) baby!
The next morning, to my utmost delight, I found that the female was
sitting on the eggs in the nest. She was sitting in earnest and came off about
once an hour for seven minutes, with this lengthening over the next few
days. She bathed in the evening. As incubation progressed, she spent longer
periods off the nest. It was decided to cover the aviary windows with dark
cloth in case she was frightened by anything. The kitchen window and the
wired side of the aviary were left uncovered though, as she was used to the
three dogs in the yard at night next to her flight.
The temperature of the flight had risen to 78*F (25.6*C) since January
and I sprayed the aviary to increase the humidity. During the following
days when the sun came out though, the temperature at the nest site got up
to 84*F (28.9*C) and at night fell as low as 66*F (18.9*C) - and the fan
heater blew-up due to the condensation.
The weather was quite warm on February 10th and the female was staying
off the nest for approximately half an hour at a time, so in the afternoon
when she was feeding, 13 days after incubation commenced, I checked the
eggs. It was the first time she had been vocal throughout the incubation.
Neither egg had hatched, though one looked as so it might be on the point of
pipping. The next day curiosity again got the better of me and I got a severe
vocal reprimand from the female when I went into the aviary again. In the
nest was a chick with an orange yellow face and feet and a slate grey back.
Hatching had taken 15 days from when the female began sitting in earnest,
and 19 days from when the first egg was laid.
I added a quantity of a probiotic and SMA gold milk powder to the
nectar mixture. Two days later I checked the nest again and there was a
second chick about half the size of its older sibling. After about a week the
two chicks were nearly the same size. The temperature settled down to an
average 78*F (25.6*C). The humidity continued to be kept high to encourage
the fruit flies to breed. Up to U /2 in (4.5cm) high the nest was a work of art
woven from cotton wool and dog hair and it was amazing how as the female
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998492" page_id="56264914"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
162
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.856259" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264914" page_num="162" year="" vol="">
GROGAN - WHITE-BREASTED AMAZILIA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997951047619048" page_id="56264914"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
sat on the nest, she pulled nest material towards her as so she was tucking
the chicks in. As the chicks grew larger, the female caught increasing numbers
of fruit flies, feeding twice an hour and catching nearly 50 at a time which
she regurgitated an fed to the chicks. The lights were left on throughout the
night, and on at least one occasion the female was continuing to catch fruit
flies at 1.00am. The female tolerated me, visitors, the dogs, and even a
Blackbird Turdus merula banging about on the plastic roof of the aviary.
March 3rd the female stopped brooding the chicks and took up a position
above the nest. The next day the bath water was replaced by a small dish of
water on the window sill. March 6th the first chick's eyes opened and both
chicks started to take on a hedgehog-like look as their pin-feathers started to
emerge. The colour of their faces was changing from bright orange to pink
and their beaks had turned light pink with a black tip, the inside of their
beaks though remained brilliant orange. Their feet had changed from orange
to light pinkish white. Their backs were grey in places while the wings
were light grey with white tips. March 9th the first chick exercised its wings
after being fed. It hung one wing over the side of the nest and propelled it
amazingly fast, then did the same with the other wing. March 10th the
female was seen with her eyes closed for the first time and the chicks, which
were now larger than her, were beginning to get longer more typical
hummingbird-like beaks.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.505021" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264915" page_num="163" year="" vol="">
GROGAN - WHITE-BREASTED AMAZILIA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.964791" page_id="56264915"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
163
</page>
<figure confidence="0.93125175" page_id="56264915"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
Ivor Grogan
One chick sitting on top of nest, other in nest
Ivor Grogan
Similar view at a later stage
</figure>
<page confidence="0.999513" page_id="56264916"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
164
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.848188" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264916" page_num="164" year="" vol="">
GROGAN - WHITE-BREASTED AMAZILIA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998077555555556" page_id="56264916"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
March 14th the eldest chick left the nest. The second chick was not yet
ready to leave and the female was feeding it three times as often as she was
feeding the eldest chick. She spent a lot of time encouraging the chicks to
leave the nest and called loudly if she thought there was a threat to them.
Although the female had been in captivity for three years, she obviously
retained many of her wild traits.
Although large quantities of fruit-flies were taken when the chicks were
being reared, they were not taken to the extent that had been envisaged.
March 20th the eldest chick was seen feeding on its own while perched.
The second chick was not developing as quickly as its older sibling and was
hand fed for two days while remaining perched in the aviary. Subsequently
sexed and found to be a female, it soon gained confidence and began to feed
from a perch as its older sibling, found to be a male, was already doing.
March 29th the breeding male was returned to the aviary, as the female
was rebuilding at the same site, and was left there for 24 hours before he
had to be removed because of his amorous advances towards the female
chick. I hope to eventually breed from the chicks and with this in mind
acquired a year old female at a show recently.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.962578142857143" page_id="56264916"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
Diary of events
January 15th
January 18th
Jan. 20th - Feb. 5th
February 6th
February 8th
February 10th
February 24th
February 26th
March 3rd
March 4th
March 6th
March 10th
March 11th
March 14th
March 20th
March 21st
March 23rd
March 29th
March 31st
April 1st
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.99058524" page_id="56264916"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
Male introduced to the female.
Male removed as he appears to be losing too much weight.
Male put in with female for two hours every day.
First egg laid.
Second egg laid.
Female commences incubation, but continues building the nest
for the next four days.
First chick hatches.
Second chick hatches at 10.00am. This chick was fed before it
had fully emerged from the egg. The female consumes nectar,
then 30-50 fruit-flies and then nectar again, before feeding the
chicks. The temperature at the nest-site is 78*F (27*C).
The female stopped brooding the chicks.
Bath removed in case of accident.
Chicks' eyes open.
Oldest chick exercises its wings.
Flight feathers emerge from sheaths.
Oldest chick leaves nest.
Oldest chick feeds from perch. Youngest chick leaves nest.
Both chicks test their wings.
First chick feeds on the wing.
Youngest chick flying but is not as strong as its sibling.
Youngest chick feeds on the wing.
As both chicks are feeding on their own they are removed from
the aviary.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998909" page_id="56264917"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
165
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7117945" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264917" page_num="165" year="" vol="">
NOTES ON KEEPING AND BREEDING
THE ELEGANT PITTA Pitta elegans
by Theo Pagel
Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970336612903226" page_id="56264917"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
At the beginning of April Cologne Zoo opened its new tropical house
called The Rainforest. It is a complex of about 2,000 sq m. (approx. 21,500
sq ft) in which we give visitors an impression of the flora and fauna of an
Asian rainforest. In it we keep insects, fishes, amphibians, reptiles, birds
and mammals. It is a combination of a walk-through aviary and separate
enclosures. We have already been quite lucky with the successes we have
achieved in this new house. We have bred fishes, reptiles and birds. In this
article I provide details about keeping and breeding the Elegant Pitta Pitta
elegans.
Systematics
Pittas belong to the family Pittidae of the Order Passeriformes.
Depending upon which classification you follow there are one to six genera
and about 30 species with several subspecies. The Elegant Pitta has the
following subspecies: P. e. elegans, P. e. virginalis, P. e. vigorsii, P e. hutzi,
P e. concinna and P e. maria. They differ from each other in distribution,
size and coloration (for details see Erritzoe and Boullet-Erritzoe, 1998).
Description
Adult: length 155mm-190mm (just over 6in-7V2in) depending on the
subspecies; wing 108mm-119mm; bill 28mm-39mm; tarsus 35mm-37.5mm;
weight 48-63g (Lambert and Woodcock, 1996). Both sexes have a black
cap, with a beige coloured stripe above the eyes, shading to bluish-white
behind the eyes, in the case of P. e. concinna; the sides of the head, neck and
throat are black. The back and wings are green, with azure-blue lesser wing-
coverts (like many other pittas); the short tail is dark green. The breast and
flanks are warm cinnamon; the belly and under tail-coverts are red. The bill
is black, the eyes brown, and the legs beige.
Nestling: (previously undescribed) blackish with dark legs and bill (see
photo p.166).
Juvenile (fledgling): a little smaller than adult, bill dark beige with some
red; lighter ring around eyes; otherwise, all in all, not that light and with the
back more or less blackish (see photo p.167).
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.988605142857143" page_id="56264918"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
PAGEL - ELEGANT PITTA
Theo Pagel
Nest of Elegant Pitta
Theo Pagel
Egg of Elegant Pitta
Theo Pagel
Nestling at about 10 days old
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.386275" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264919" page_num="167" year="" vol="">
PAGEL - ELEGANT PITTA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.988703" page_id="56264919"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
167
</page>
<table confidence="0.609773375" page_id="56264919"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
Theo Pagel
The first fledged Elegant Pitta at Cologne Zoo
Distribution
The Elegant Pitta is an Indonesian endemic, occurring on the Moluccas,
Sulawesi, Lesser Sunda Islands and Penida (for the distribution of the races
see Erritzoe and Boullet-Erritzoe, 1998).
Status
Most accounts suggest that the Elegant Pitta is a widespread and relatively
</table>
<listItem confidence="0.249397" page_id="56264919"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
common species. On Sumba in the mid-1990s it was estimated that there
was a population of about 11,000 birds. Only in some parts of its distribution
is it uncommon or rare, as for example on Flores.
</listItem>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.518397">
Habitat
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.956002" page_id="56264919"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
The Elegant Pitta can be found in different forested habitats, from dry
monsoon woodlands to the wetter rainforests of the South Moluccas. Even
in small patches of trees along watercourses, often close to villages, you can
observe this beautiful bird. It can occur from sea level up to 1,500m (approx.
5,000ft) on Burn.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998567" page_id="56264920"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
168
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.730661" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264920" page_num="168" year="" vol="">
PAGEL - ELEGANT PITTA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.979415690476191" page_id="56264920"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
Living in the wild
So far as we know, P. e. elegans and P. e. vigorsii, make migratory
movements, but we have few details about those movements. Lambert and
Woodcock (1996) do not say anything about the food but in Erritzoe and
Boullet-Erritzoe (1998) we learn, that in the stomach of one bird collected
on Timor there were small beetles and in another's stomach there were snail
remains. From time to time it seems as so they accompany Emerald or
Green-winged Doves Chalcophaps indica searching for food.
Their breeding season is also poorly documented. Eggs of P e. concinna
were found in April in the Lesser Sundas. If one combines all available data
it is possible to say that the breeding season of all subspecies spans the
middle part of the year. They build a typical closed nest, using leaves and
branches, with the entrance at the side. The interior of the nest is lined with
fine rootlets or fungal hyphae. The eggs are white, covered all over with
rufous-brown and purplish-grey patches. Eggs of P. e. concinna have
measured 26.9mm x 21.1mm, 27.3mm x 21.9mm and 28.1mm x 21.9mm.
Keeping and breeding
As most of the pittas have seldom been kept, very little information has
been published about keeping and breeding them. I have been unable to
find any about keeping and breeding Elegant Pittas and if any member knows
of any, I will be pleased to learn in which publication or publications it has
appeared.
Pittas should be kept only in larger planted aviaries or even better in
tropical houses. Keeping them in smaller enclosures makes little sense as
they are unlikely to breed in these. Pittas can be very aggressive between
each other so they need plenty of room and places to hide from each other.
Our adult pair came from a dealer in the Netherlands. Both are wild
caught and we do not know how old they are. They belong to the subspecies
P. e. concinna which occurs on the northern Lesser Sunda Islands, namely
Lombok, Sumbawa, Flores, Adonara, Lomblen, Alor and some other small
islands.
We got them at the end of 1999. After a quarantine period (when we
kept them together in a cage measuring lm x lm x 2.5m (approx. 3ft 3in x 3ft
3in x 8ft 2in) we put them in our walk-through aviary in the new tropical
house called The Rainforest. The free-flying part is about 1,250sq m (approx.
13,500sq ft) and is up to 17m (approx. 56ft) high. The temperature varies
from 20*C-35*C (68*F-95*F) and the humidity from 65%-99%. The
enclosure is planted with different south-east Asian plants and trees up to
7.5m (approx. 25ft) high. The vegetation and birds get daylight through the
transparent roof. We offer the birds a low-iron, softbill food and a lot of
different livefood (flies, crickets, mealworms, etc.) several times a day.
Since the beginning of March the two adult birds have lived in the tropical
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.389828" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264921" page_num="169" year="" vol="">
PAGEL - ELEGANT PITTA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99913" page_id="56264921"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
169
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999434333333333" page_id="56264921"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
house, in which the hill in the middle of the house is their preferred territory.
They have shown no aggression towards other birds such as the Silver-eared
Leiothrix Leiothrix argentauris and Vietnamese Pheasant Lophura
hathinensis. Together with the birds living in the same enclosure are live
fish, amphibians, reptiles and fruit bats.
On May 3rd this year we observed the pittas carrying nest material, and
in three days they had built a nest which measured 40cm (approx. 16in) in
diameter and 35cm (approx. 14in) high. It was built using only dry materials
such as leaves and branches, and had the entrance at the front (see photo p.
166). The nest was on an artificial rock at a height of 125cm (5in) directly
by the wall. On May 10th we found three eggs in the nest and on May 28th
saw two youngsters in the nest. On June 7th we found a dead youngster and
an infertile egg in the nest. One bird was missing. The egg was white with
brownish spots and measured 27.0mm x 21.0mm (see photo p. 166). The
pair immediately began to build a new nest again by the wall and 5m
(approx. 16ft) from the first nest. It was a little larger than the first nest and
again built on an artificial rock, this time at an height of 140cm (5V2in). The
pair again took about three days to complete the nest. After consulting
colleagues at the zoos at Arnhem and Frankfurt about their experiences with
pittas, we decided not to examine the nest anymore. On July 12th we saw
two young Elegant Pittas hopping on the ground. One of them was larger
than the other, and it seemed as if one was from the first clutch and the other
from the second. We observed the adults bringing up to six mealworms to
the youngsters. When they realised that we were observing them they would
not feed the young and would not even get close to them. After a short
alarm call the youngsters hid themselves and waited until we had gone.
Both adults fed the youngsters but we do not know for sure if the birds
brooded both of them.
Both young pittas are independent now and the pair has built a new nest,
and we hope that further youngsters will follow.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.869299" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56264921" page_num="169" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999183" page_id="56264921"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
I would like to thank my colleagues at Arnhem and Frankfurt for their
advice, also our horticulturist and the keepers for their work and passion
without which this success would not have been possible.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.987294" genericHeader="references" page_id="56264921" page_num="169" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.998064833333333">
Erritzoe, J. and Boullet-Erritzoe, H. 1998. Pittas of the World. The Lutterworth Press,
Cambridge, England.
Lambert, F. and Woodcock, M. 1996. Pittas, Bwadbills and Asities. Pica Press, Nr.
Robertsbridge, East Sussex, England.
Theo Pagel, Zoologischer Garten Koln, Riehlerstr. 173, 50735 Koln,
Germany. Tel: 0221-7785-108/E-mail:tpagel@zoo-koeln.de
</reference>
<page confidence="0.995089" page_id="56264922"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
170
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99162" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264922" page_num="170" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE PURPLE-BELLIED PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970808923076923" page_id="56264922"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
Triclaria malachitacea
by Bob Grantham
The Purple-bellied Parrot is endemic to the forested areas of south-east
Brazil (see Low, 1997). Both sexes have dark green plumage tinged with
blue on the underside of the wings and tail. The male is distinguished by the
purple patch on his abdomen. The iris is brown, the beak hom-coloured and
the feet grey in both sexes. The male of my pair has a vivid orange outer
ring in the iris.
Having had the privilege of owning a pair of Purple-bellied Parrots 25
years ago (Low, 1976), I have had a lasting fascination with this species.
No chicks were reared by that pair. I always hoped that one day I would be
able to obtain another pair of Purple-bellied Parrots. In January 1997 my
dream came true when a pair arrived from Loro Parque. However, on arrival
the female lacked a tail. During the past three years no sign of tail growth
has occurred.
After the normal quarantine period of 35 days the pair was placed in an
aviary measuring 9ft x 6ft x 3ft (2.7m x 1.8m x 91cm). The shelter of this
aviary adjoins a large kitchen window so I was able to observe them closely.
They were provided with a nest-box measuring 24in x 8in x 8in (60cm x
20cm x 20cm). In January and February 1998 the male was seen to feed the
female and to mate with her. This behaviour was observed on many
occasions. Four eggs were laid at the beginning of March. These proved to
be infertile and were removed. The pair did not nest again that year. The
same behaviour was observed in January and February 1999. Eggs were
laid at the beginning of March. Again they were infertile.
In January 2000 the male was observed feeding and mating with the
female on several occasions. Four eggs were laid in March. These proved
to be infertile and were removed approximately two and a half weeks after
they were laid. To my surprise the female laid a second clutch of five eggs
at the end of April. On May 25th a chick was heard. The feeding of soft
food was immediately increased to twice daily at 8.30am and 5.30pm.
Inspection of the nest was left until June 4th when two chicks were observed.
From then on the chicks were inspected twice daily. If they had not been
fed well they would have been removed for hand-rearing. The three
remaining eggs were removed. One contained a chick which was dead in
shell and the other two were infertile.
By the 40th day the first chick was fully feathered. There was a large
discrepancy in size and age between the two chicks and, at that time, the
plumage of the second was only just starting to appear.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.396297" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264923" page_num="171" year="" vol="">
GRANTHAM - PURPLE-BELLIED PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.843827" page_id="56264923"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
171
</page>
<figure confidence="0.651419" page_id="56264923"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
Male Purple-bellied Parrot
Bob Grantham
</figure>
<page confidence="0.998636" page_id="56264924"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
172
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.84034" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264924" page_num="172" year="" vol="">
GRANTHAM - PURPLE-BELLIED PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998359111111111" page_id="56264924"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
During the first four weeks the female remained in the nest-box. During
the fifth week she came out, returning only to feed the chicks. Occasionally
the male was seen to enter the box. On July 11th the first chick was observed
at the nest hole. It came out permanently on July 14th. The second chick
left the nest on July 20th, although it was not completely feathered on the
back and wings. The immature plumage is similar to that of the female.
Both young ones were then fed by her alone. The first one was seen to feed
itself on the sixth day out and the second one on the seventh day.
The young were extremely steady. On the day it left the nest, the second
youngster flew on to the shoulder of the lady who feeds the birds. Ten days
later it still allowed her to stroke its head. The whole family are very placid.
Three neighbours' cats are in the habit of sitting on the roof of the aviary.
The parrots try to nibble the cats' feet!
The diet of the Purple-bellied Parrots consisted of sweetcom, apple,
carrot, celery, pear and EMP rearing food. Powdered cuttlefish bone was
sprinkled over the food. The seed consisted of sunflower, canary, millet,
buckwheat, safflower and hemp. Greenfood such as lettuce, cabbage and
watercress was also given. Fresh water was available at all times.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.802511" genericHeader="references" page_id="56264924" page_num="172" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991703777777778" page_id="56264924"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
Low, R. 1976. The 1975 breeding season. Avicultural Magazine 82: 11-20.
Low, R. 1997. The Purple-bellied Parrot Triclaria malachitacea: its natural history and
aviculture. Avicultural Magazine 103: 149-158.
As described above, the Purple-bellied Parrot Triclaria malachitacea ,
has been bred by Bob Grantham. This is probably the first successful
breeding of this species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who knows of
a previous breeding is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
Bob Grantham, who for several years has served as a Council Member,
joined the Avicultural Society in 1953.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995698666666667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264925" page_num="173" year="" vol="">
BREEDING AND GROUP DYNAMICS IN MAGPIE
SHRIKES Corvinella melanoleuca
AT DISNEY'S ANIMAL KINGDOM
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998704" page_id="56264925"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
173
</page>
<author confidence="0.210866">
by Paul Schutz
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.1254">
Magpie Shrikes Corvinella melanoleuca , also called Long-tailed Shrikes
</affiliation>
<bodyText confidence="0.992862971428571" page_id="56264925"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
because of the length of their tails, are conspicuous inhabitants of the acacia
bush and open savanna in eastern and southern Africa. Two subspecies
have been described: C. m. melanoleuca found in southern Africa south of
the Zambezi River; and C. m. aequatorialis found in eastern Africa,
specifically south-western Kenya and Tanzania.
Magpie Shrikes are gregarious and usually found in groups of six or so
birds, consisting probably of a breeding pair and previous offspring. During
the breeding season, the non-breeding shrikes act as 'helpers' that assist in
the care of others' chicks. In species in which cooperative breeding has
been observed, the 'helpers' are usually offspring of the breeding pair which
as yet have been unable to acquire breeding territories of their own. However,
the author has worked with a group of four unrelated, wild-caught Magpie
Shrikes which split into a breeding pair and two 'helpers' which assisted in
the care of the chicks at Houston Zoological Gardens, Texas, USA. In
captivity perhaps, the absence of a real family group leads Magpie Shrikes
to 'adopt' long-term cage-mates as relatives, which become 'helpers' at the
nest. The chicks, when fledged, also joined in the care of subsequent clutches
of chicks. On one occasion, a total of seven birds were seen at the nest
awaiting their turn to feed the chicks.
Disney's Animal Kingdom acquired a group of five Magpie Shrikes,
which includes the two 'helpers' from Houston Zoo, for its new African
aviary, located along its Pan gam Forest Exploration Trail attraction. The
aviary measures 162ft long x 62ft wide x 45ft high (approx. 50m long x
20m wide x 14m high). The thickly planted habitat has a plateau about 20ft
(6m) high running along the western third of its length. From the northern
edge of the plateau, two waterfalls cascade into a large pool, which is the
main source of drinking water for the aviary's inhabitants. The aviary
contains more than 20 species, including Hadada Ibis Hagedashia hagedash ,
Hammerkop Scopus umbretta , Ross's Touraco Musophaga rossae , African
Grey Parrot Psittacus erithacus, Carmine Bee-eater Merops nubicus , Superb
Starling Spree superbus , Racquet-tailed Roller Coracias spatulata , African
Pygmy Goose Nettapus amitus and Brimstone Canary Serinus sulphuratus.
A total of eleven feeding stations are scattered throughout the aviary, plus
one at the pool's edge specifically intended for the exhibit's waterfowl. The
basic diet consists of chopped mixed fruits, chopped greens, soaked Mazuri
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999538" page_id="56264926"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
174
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.777886" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264926" page_num="174" year="" vol="">
SCHUTZ - MAGPIE SHRIKE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9991485" page_id="56264926"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
brand parrot breeder and carnivore diet. The carnivore diet is mixed with
the soaked parrot breeder to encourage mostly carnivorous birds, such as
the shrikes, to ingest the more nutritionally complete pellets. These diets
are supplemented with livefood, such as mealworms, waxworms and crickets.
Throughout the quarantine period the five shrikes were kept within visual
contact but in two separate groups: the 'helper' pair from Houston Zoo
(hereafter referred to as pair A, or male A and female A) and a male and two
females (hereafter referred to as group B, or male B, female B1 and female
B2) which were acquired from a private aviculturist. Despite them being
unrelated, the Houston experience led us to the expectation that these five
birds would form a cohesive social group. On February 16th 1998 the two
groups were moved into two acclimation pens inside the aviary. Two days
later, all five were released into the aviary. Pair A exhibited breeding
behaviour almost immediately, and by March 1st had begun constructing a
nest high in a ficus tree.
By April 4th one egg was present in the nest constructed by pair A. At
this point, it became obvious that the five birds had begun to revert to their
earlier groupings. The three individuals of group B spent much of their
time at the opposite end of the aviary, away from the nest that pair A had
constructed, vocalizing and doing their wing-flashing display which entails
raising their wings above their heads to reveal their white wing patches.
Pair A began to defend the nesting territory, actively chasing other species
from the area. Aggression was also observed between female A and male B.
On one occasion the two locked feet and fell together from a tree before
separating. Interestingly, just four days later, male A and female B2 were
observed jointly displacing a Racquet-tailed Roller. Three eggs were present
by April 7th and the hypothesis was made based on the Houston experience
that once chicks hatched, even non-breeding birds would assist in caring for
them. Unfortunately, all three eggs were missing on April 24th and pair A
began nest building again.
While the two groups seemed to stay separate most of the time, they
were occasionally seen perched together, although not much interaction was
noted between them. This would change within a few months. By mid-
May, 1998, pair A had five eggs and were again defending their territory.
An interesting interaction occurred on May 16th, when one of the Hadada
Ibis perched in the tree that contained the nest. Soon all five shrikes
repeatedly scolded and mobbed the ibis in an obviously coordinated effort
until it left the area. Just two weeks later, all the eggs were missing again
and keepers removed the nest. It measured 672 in (16.5cm) in diameter and
5in (12.7cm) deep, with the cup constructed mostly of Spanish moss, pliable
small twigs (about 5in (12.7cm) long and less than Vioin (2mm) in diameter)
and larger twigs (about 6in-10in (15.3cm-25.4cm) long and Vidn-Vsin (2mm-
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.442604" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264927" page_num="175" year="" vol="">
SCHUTZ - MAGPIE SHRIKE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996325" page_id="56264927"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
175
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.27896" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264927" page_num="175" year="" vol="">
Natalie Mashburn-Lindholm
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994918625" page_id="56264927"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
Adult pair of Magpie Shrikes. The female (right) has white on the flanks.
3mm) in diameter). The lining of the nest consisted of moss, pine needles,
and pliable small twigs. Nest construction began again just two days later.
On June 10th, pair A were observed displacing female Bl. This event
seemed to signal the beginning of a period of more active interaction between
the two groups. Now, when the two groups came together, there were
vocalizations, and wing-flashing was observed among them. These wing-
flashing ceremonies were probably territorial displays, but might also be
interpreted as greetings among members of a group (Lefranc, 1997). Three
eggs were discovered in the nest on June 12th, but by July 1st 1998, they
were missing and this time, the nest appeared to have been partly destroyed.
When nest construction began again, female Bl was observed on at least
one occasion carrying nesting material to the site. The new site they had
chosen was apparently not suitable and pair A eventually constructed a nest
in the ficus tree where they had built originally with, apparently, no help
from group B.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999354" page_id="56264928"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
176
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.765969" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264928" page_num="176" year="" vol="">
SCHUTZ - MAGPIE SHRIKE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998671452380953" page_id="56264928"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
Increased insect consumption led keepers to check pair A's nest on
October 30th. Two chicks were present which appeared to be a few days
old. All five adults vigorously defended the area around the nest from other
birds, especially the White-collared Kingfisher Halcyon chloris, with which
they seemed to be particularly fixated. However, only the parents were
observed attending to and feeding the chicks. Crickets, waxworms and
mealworms made up the majority of the food taken to the nest during the
first two weeks. The parents were observed removing a faecal sac from the
nest and dropping it elsewhere in the aviary. By November 8th, both chicks
were observed exercising their wings, and appeared close to fledging, and
one chick fledged on the 13th. However, by the 15th there was no sign of
either chick. An extensive search of the aviary turned up the body of one of
the chicks which had been dragged into a hollow beneath a tree stump.
Apparently unphased by the setback, pair A had by the first week in
December laid four more eggs and were incubating them. During the
incubation period the breeding male as usual displaced other birds from the
area of the nest. On December 13th 1998, pair A were observed carrying
waxworms and mealworms up to the nest. A check of the nest on December
21st revealed no eggs but a single, large, healthy looking chick. January 4th
1999, the chick left the nest. Shortly thereafter, it was attacked by birds of
group B. The attack, while not well observed, was vigorous enough to
cause serious damage to a toenail of the fledgling's right hallux, resulting in
the removal of the nail. The chick was removed to the nursery where its
rearing was completed by keepers.
Undaunted, pair A returned to nesting, and by January 25th, had four
more eggs. Despite group B's aggressive behaviour towards the fledgling,
the three continued to join the breeding pair mobbing and displacing larger
birds which approached the nest. A nest check on February 15th revealed a
single chick. The chick was seen exercising its wings on a branch close to
the nest on February 28th. On March 6th, the chick left the nest and was
attacked by group B.
The three flew at the young bird, grabbing its wings and feet. The parents
sat nearby, vocalizing and puffing out their feathers, but did not intervene or
actively defend the chick. The attacks continued and the decision was taken
to intervene. Keepers caught the fledgling and placed it in a small holding
cage. The decision was made to try to lure one or both of the parents into a
holding cage so that they could finish rearing the chick. Shortly before the
fledging of this second chick, the juvenile that had been removed to the
nursery for hand rearing was returned to the holding cage in the aviary where
it was in visual contact with the five adults.
The adults treated the first juvenile like an intruder, displaying and uttering
their threat vocalizations while perched around the holding cage. Oddly, all
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.443252" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264929" page_num="177" year="" vol="">
SCHUTZ - MAGPIE SHRIKE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998953" page_id="56264929"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
177
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999710409090909" page_id="56264929"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
five adult shrikes showed the same reaction to the fledgling in the cage.
They perched in close proximity to the chick and vocalized, but would not
approach or feed it, despite the presence of food and the constant begging
and distress vocalizations of the fledgling. It quickly became apparent that
this chick too would have to be hand reared.
Three days after the fledging of their most recent chick, pair A began
nesting again. The decision was made to prevent any further nesting attempts
until group B could be removed from the aviary. To this end female BI was
caught and placed in a holding cage with the two juveniles to await shipment
to another institution. Pair A continued to build nests and lay eggs, but each
time keepers dismantled the nest and discarded the eggs. On June 7th, keepers
observed that the breeding female had an injured right leg. Over the next
two weeks the injury appeared to worsen but she foiled numerous capture
attempts and on June 22nd was discovered dead in the aviary.
The death of the breeding female left two males and a single female in
the aviary, and breeding behaviour began again shortly afterwards. Both
males were observed courtship feeding the female. At the time of writing
the original breeding male, male A, and the remaining female are building a
nest and it is planned to let them breed. It is our hope that male B will
recognise the female as a member of his group and will not interfere. It will
be interesting to see if he assists the parents in rearing any chicks, thus re-
forming a cohesive group. Only time will tell if this scenario is played out.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.868735" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56264929" page_num="177" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgments
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.854557444444444" page_id="56264929"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
Most importantly, I would like to thank the staff of the aviary department
at Disney's Animal Kingdom, including Curator Grenville Roles, zoological
managers Chelle Plasse and Scott Barton, and keepers James Grant, Susan
Congdon, Greg Bockheim and Shannon Mezzell. Without their
encouragement, assistance and observations, this paper would not have been
possible. I would also like to thank the bird department at Houston Zoological
Gardens, especially Curator Lee Schoen, senior keeper Trey Todd and keeper
Ric IJrbant all of whom were particularly supportive and helpful. Finally,
thanks to Natalie Mashbum-Lindholm for providing the photo.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.35704">
Reference and bibliography
</subsectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.975821375">
Harris, T. and Amott, G. 1988. Shrikes of Southern Africa. Struik, Winchester.
LeFranc, N. 1997. Shrikes: A Guide to the Shrikes of the World. Yale University Press, New
Haven, USA.
Skutch, A. 1999. Helpers at Birds' Nests: A Worldwide Survey of cooperative Breeding and
Related Behavior. University of Iowa Press, USA.
Paul Schutz is with the Conservation Station Administration at Disney's
Animal Kingdom, PO. Box 10,000, Lako Buena Vista, Florida, USA 32830-
1000 .
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998846" page_id="56264930"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
178
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7680734" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264930" page_num="178" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE LEMON-BREASTED CANARY Serinus
citrinipectus AND NOTES ON SOME OTHER Serinus
SPECIES
by Tony Jolliffe
General notes
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98396365" page_id="56264930"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
The pair of Lemon-breasted Canaries were bought in 1998 in Belgium
on impulse because I thought them beautiful. I also purchased enough of
the food they were eating to last a month. I knew nothing more about them
at that stage.
Nesting occurred and eggs were produced late in 1998. However, the
shells were very thin and porous and all proved to be infertile. Because the
female was showing signs of stress the pair was separated and reintroduced
early in 1999. The first nest produced similar results to those in 1998 but
the second nest produced three young. All were reared and proved to be
three females. The same pair has hatched and reared two young in 2000.
Housing and food
The pair are housed in a standard canary double-breeder which measures
120cm x 30cm x 45cm (approx. 39V2in x 12in x WUm). The standard diet
was mixed small millets with wild food when available. This has since
been replaced with a good British bird mix which seems to have advantages.
Food taken during rearing includes the standard seed mix both dry and soaked
for 24 hours, chickweed Stellaria spp., seeding grasses (Cock's Foot Dactylis
glomerata. Rye-grass Loliumperenne. Annual and Rough-stalked Meadow-
grasses Poa annua and P. trivialis). Redshank Polygonum persicaria , Pale
Persicaria P lapathifolium, Groundsel Senecio vularis, Rat's-tail Plantain
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.542548">
and Mouse-ear Plantain Plantago spp.
Nesting
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999603222222222" page_id="56264930"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
The pair nested in an all-wire basket with a felt lining. The eggs were
pure white. Incubation is thought to have taken 13-14 days. Upon hatching
the chicks had blackish brown skin and copious white down. The gape was
brilliant red. During the first few days the male seemed to feed the female
which then fed the chicks. Feeding was shared after about three days.
Development of the chicks was roughly five to seven days more advanced
at each stage compared to that of the domestic canary. The adults were
particularly devoted and protective parents. The female would attack the
hand rather than leave the nest.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.466018" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264931" page_num="179" year="" vol="">
JOLLIFFE - SERINUS SPECIES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999134" page_id="56264931"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
179
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999001452380953" page_id="56264931"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
General information and observations
The birds are very territorial, and the male will sing at the slightest sound.
Opening the door of the birdroom or dropping something will start him
singing. Oddly enough although his singing continued throughout incubation
it stopped the day the chicks hatched and did not start again until the chicks
fledged. Another interesting observation is that on several occasions just
after the chicks fledged, both parents were seen driving them down, and on
two occasions grabbed them and threw them down when they were fluttering
against the wire. Although it worried the hell out of me, no damage was
done to the recently fledged young in what appeared to be an instinctive
process aimed at getting them to safety.
Once, just as the young were starting to feed, one begged for food but
got no response from the male. The young bird immediately adopted a
'head down shoulders up' aggression posture and was then fed.
Because the colour of the chick's gape, the skin and the eggs differed
from those observed in southern Africa where the gape was recorded as
being bright yellow, the skin pale pinkish with sparse whitish down and the
eggs white, lightly streaked with brown (Brickell, 1997; The Avicultural
Research Unit, 1997), I have been reluctant to introduce new birds until this
matter is resolved. Instead, I decided to try to mate the male with several
females as one can with domestic canaries. I put the male in with the female
which had started nesting as I have done hundreds of times with domestic
canaries and have never seen such panic in a bird. I had to remove the male
before the female injured herself.
Later I put a male Tibetan Siskin S. thibetanus in with the same female
to see if the result would be the same and there was no problem at all. Because
the female Tibetan Siskin had died and I was short of space I left him there.
They have now gone to nest and it is fascinating to watch the male, which is
more fastidious than the female, cleaning out the nest whenever she leaves
it.
I later managed to obtain another pair of Lemon-breasted Canaries in
Belgium which at the time of writing (August 8th), are hatching out their
third nest. The first was lost, along with other newly hatched young, as a
result of an infestation of mite the likes of which I have never experienced
before in all my 50 odd years of bird keeping. It has taken until now and
just about every chemical known to get rid of them and get the birds back
into a decent condition. I hope it is a case of third time lucky, as this pair is
supposed to have come from northern Mozambique, as opposed to my
original pair which is believed to have come from southern Mozambique. I
am very keen to study them.
I bred the White-bellied Canary S. dorsostriatus last year but I imagine
that this species has been bred often enough for you not to require details.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.992411" page_id="56264932"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
180
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.660939" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264932" page_num="180" year="" vol="">
JOLLIFFE - SERINUS SPECIES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985868238095238" page_id="56264932"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
I have bred domestic canaries most of my life starting from when I was
10 years old and even as a child their range of shapes and sizes fascinated
me. As I grew older I began to wonder more about how they evolved and
question the accepted belief as to their origin. A series of articles written by
a Dutchman who has translated most of the seventeenth and eighteenth
century canary books encouraged me in my view that not all type canaries
evolved from S. canaria - the wild Canary.
My attention first turned to the Red-fronted Siskin S . pusillus. Later I
turned my attention to the Cape Canary S. canicollis on account of its size,
posture and origin. In the seventeenth century the port of Gent was Dutch
and the trade between there and southern Africa was already well developed
making it likely this species would have been available to canary breeders
of Gent at that time.
About three years ago I went with one of the buying trips to Belgium
where I found two Cape Canaries - both immature and very plucked. I
brought them back with me and as I have learned more about the Cape or
Yellow-crowned Canary and its subspecies, I have realised that it is a very
complicated subject and also I have not enjoyed myself so much for years.
What started off as a study of the origins of the varieties of domestic canary
has become a study of the Cape or Yellow-crowned Canary.
They are by and large, quiet, confiding little birds the beauty of which is
too easily missed when they are packed together in dealers' cages. Often
immature and dirty, they appear drab and uninteresting but these same birds
when clean and fit, and in full adult plumage have an amazing range of
colours. I am finding sorting out the differences between the subspecies
extremely difficult and suspect one reason for so few captive breeding
successes may be because pairs are often made up of males and females of
different subspecies.
At the moment I think I have specimens of S. c. canicollis, S. c.
grisetergum, S. c. flavivertex and S. c. sasii, but only two true pairs. I am far
from sure though. Although most do well on my canary regime there are
problems with S. c. sasii, which shed feathers and become bald very quickly.
I feel sure this is a dietary problem and am looking closely at this. I have
increased their vitamin and protein intake which looks as if it is helping to
improve the situation. They appear to be far more gregarious than the others
and I am wondering if the stress of being isolated is also a factor. S. c.
flavivertex too might have specific requirements. Unfortunately, I have
recently lost my male. I had a male for two years and although it was always
fit it never really came into breeding condition, lacking perhaps the
stimulation of a female.
It is a highland bird, occurring for example on Mt Elgon, Mt Kenya and
Mt Kilimanjaro, leading me to also question whether I have got the conditions
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.465979" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264933" page_num="181" year="" vol="">
JOLLIFFE - SERINUS SPECIES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998478" page_id="56264933"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
181
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997858090909091" page_id="56264933"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
quite right for it here in Kent.
Recognition of the problems of obtaining true pairs, especially of species
such as the Cape or Yellow-fronted Canary, with a diversity of subspecies,
led to the idea of undertaking an African Serins Survey. The aim of this is to
discover which species and subspecies are being kept, not just in the UK but
worldwide, and through this establishing contacts with other keepers with a
view to exchanging information and birds in order to make-up true pairs
and establish captive populations while these birds remain relatively freely
available.
If you keep African Serinus species and wish to participate in the survey,
would you write to:- Bryan Reed and Tony Jolliffe, African Serins Survey,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7167255" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264933" page_num="181" year="" vol="">
62 Northwood Drive, Sittingboume, Kent ME 10 4QS, England.
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996913555555556" page_id="56264933"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
Brickell, N. 1997. Further Notes on the Lemon-breasted Canary Serinus citrinipectus.Avicultural
Magazine 103, 1:4-5.
The Avicultural Research Unit. 1997. African Birds in Field &amp; Aviary: A guide to a mixed
collection. Compact Edition. African Bird Book Publishing, Westville, KwaZulu-Natal, South
Africa.
As described above, the Lemon-breasted Canary Serinus citrinipectus,
has been bred by Tony Jolliffe. This is probably the first successful breeding
of this species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who knows of a previous
breeding is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996723" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264933" page_num="181" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.943989333333333" page_id="56264933"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
A large stock is available including some early issues. Sales are by post
only! Further details are available from:- Hon. Secretary, Avicultural Society,
c/o Bristol Zoological Gardens, Clifton, Bristol BS8 3HA, England.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998396" page_id="56264934"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
182
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7797" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264934" page_num="182" year="" vol="">
THE PROBABLE FIRST UK BREEDING OF THE
MARABOU
by Malcolm Mycock
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999113081081081" page_id="56264934"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
The Marabou Leptoptilos crumeniferus, a species very common in the
wild throughout much of tropical Africa and renowned for its ugly appearance
and rather unattractive feeding habits, has proven among the most difficult
birds to breed.
Marabous have been exhibited at Blackbrook Zoological Park for
approximately nine years, and although they are not the most attractive of
birds, visitors find them fascinating. After numerous setbacks and a lot of
hard work we hatched and reared Marabous here last year (1999). It was,
we believe, the first breeding of this species, in the UK and one of only a
handful of successes worldwide. Although Marabous have been kept in
captivity for a great many years and egg laying is not uncommon, fertile
eggs are rare.
We had a partial success with our Marabous three years ago, when they
hatched but failed to rear a chick, which was seen and heard but went missing
at only three days old having, we presumed, been eaten by one or both of its
parents. Last year seven eggs were laid and as we did not want to risk
losing them, it was decided to take them from the parents and attempt to
hatch and rear the chicks ourselves. The first four eggs were placed under
broody hens but this, unfortunately proved unsuccessful. One of the four
eggs was fertile but failed to hatch, due it seemed to too much humidity. So,
somewhat nervously, we decided to attempt to incubate the other eggs in an
incubator set at 37*C (98.6*F) with a relative humidity of 35%-40%.
One morning during my inspection of the eggs in the incubator room,
sounds were heard coming from two Marabou eggs. Luckily it was very
early in the morning and no one else was present to hear my shouts of
excitement and see me jumping around like a lunatic in the hatchery. Both
eggs hatched after incubation periods of 32 days and the long and worrying
task of rearing the chicks began.
They were fed on a diet of spratts and boned and skinned day-old chicks
that were very finely chopped, and with the addition of zoovite vitamin
supplement and warm water, offered to the birds in the form of a thick soup
in a shallow dish. Neither were fed for the first 24 hours, after which both
fed themselves from the start. The amount of food given to each chick per
feed was no more than 10% of its body weight. After the second day of
feeding themselves, mice pinkies were added to the diet along with a calcium
supplement. Both chicks were fed six times a day, the first feed being given
at 6.00am and the last at midnight. The diet remained the same as the chicks
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.423892" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264935" page_num="183" year="" vol="">
MYCOCK - MARABOU
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.896089" page_id="56264935"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
183
</page>
<figure confidence="0.847898" page_id="56264935"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
J. Roger son
Adult Marabous
Aged four days
J. Rogerson
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.758564333333333" page_id="56264935"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
grew older, except that larger pieces of food were provided, in warm water
still. Also, as the chicks grew older and bigger the number of feeds per day
was decreased.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999333" page_id="56264936"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
184
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.708125" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264936" page_num="184" year="" vol="">
MYCOCK - MARABOU
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.908333" page_id="56264936"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
J. Rogerson
Three months old
I am pleased to report that both chicks were reared to independence.
Unfortunately, however, Ml, the older of the two by 24 hours, ruptured a
tendon in one of its legs. The leg was operated upon and the tendon repaired
successfully, but a number of weeks standing on the injured leg proved too
much for the bird and eventually it was put to sleep.
The second young Marabou, M2, developed normally without any
problems and is the same size as her parents now and is on show at
Blackbrook Zoological Park.
An egg laid this year proved to be infertile.
As described above the Marabou Leptoptilos crumeniferus, has been
bred at Blackbrook Zoological Park. This is probably the first successful
breeding of this species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who knows of
a previous breeding is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
Malcolm Mycock is Manager of Blackbrook Zoological Park, Winkhill,
Nr. Leek, Staffordshire ST 13 7QR, England. The zoo which occupies a 70
acre (28.3 hectares) site was founded in 1991 by its owner Diana Holloway,
an Avicultural Society Council Member.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998815" page_id="56264937"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
185
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.980286" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264937" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
FIRST BREEDING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9949775" page_id="56264937"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
Neville Brickell, co-author with Trevor Konigkramer of Further Notes
on the Drakensberg Siskin Serinus totta symonsi (.Avicultural Magazine
106,3:118-121), has written to say that Trevor has finally succeeded in
breeding this species. One youngster left the nest after 19 days. It is the
first breeding in captivity of the Drakensberg Siskin and in recognition of
this, Trevor, a member of the Natal Bird Breeder&apos;s Society, has been awarded
that society's diploma. At the time of writing (October 10th), the female
was sitting again, this time on three eggs.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.983276545454546" page_id="56264937"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
* * *
NEW DIRECTOR
Simon Tonge, formerly Senior Curator at London Zoo, is the now Director
of Paignton Zoo, Devon, replacing Peter Stevens who has retired. Simon
Tonge joined London Zoo from Jersey Zoo in 1993, and for a time served as
an Avicultural Society Council Member. Curatorial responsibility for both
the London Zoo and Whipsnade collections is now in the hands of Nick
Lindsay, who wrote recently about The New Penguin Development at
Whipsnade (Avicultural Magazine , Vol. 106, No.2, pp.85-86) and earlier about
Flamingos at Whipsnade (Avicultural Magazine, Vol.104, No.3, pp.100-101).
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.71429" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264937" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
HEALTH MATTERS FOR LOVED ONES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.85762" page_id="56264937"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
By visiting the website - avianconsult.com - it is possible now to get
avian veterinary advice from certified avian veterinary specialists. You can
e-mail:info@avian consult.com to obtain a brochure. Payment is by credit
card.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.60162" page_id="56264937"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.894391" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264937" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
BIRDING CONFERENCE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9399405" page_id="56264937"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
The second World Birding Conference - website:www.wbc2.corn is to
be held March 30th - April 1st 2001, at The Hayes Conference Centre,
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.7888078">
Swanwick, Derbyshire, England. Further details are available from:- Sue
Starling, World Bird Conference, c/o BTO, The Nunnery, Thetford, Norfolk
IP24 2PU, England. Tel:01842 750050/Fax:01842 750030/E-mail:
sue. starling @ bto. org.
* * *
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999309" page_id="56264938"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
186
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.967799" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264938" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
EXOTICS QUEST 2000
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.972037826086957" page_id="56264938"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
Organised by Adrian Fowler of the University of Bristol School of
Veterinary Science at Langford, Exotics Quest 2000 was a great success.
Almost 200 fourth and fifth year students, a high percentage of them female,
attended on what was a cold day in late spring. The society had a stand
there and in the information pack given to each student and stand holder
was a copy of the Avicultural Magazine and a membership form.
Avicultural Society Council Member Laura Gardner was one of the
speakers and brought with her a pair of Bali Starlings Leucopsar rothschildi.
The Tropical Bird Gardens, at Rode, provided a selection of birds including a
Triangular Spotted Pigeon Columba guinea , Grey Hombill Tockus nasutus
and a Green-crested Touraco Tauraco persa. Shirley Lawton, a member from
Northamptonshire, showed a selection of parrots she was rearing including
Triton Cacatua galerita triton and Goffin's Cockatoos C. goffini, Blue &amp; Gold
Macaws Ara ararauna , African Greys Psittacus erithacus and Black-headed
Caiques Pionites melanoleuca. There was a display by the Rhea and Emu
Association and a Toco Toucan Ramphastos toco in wonderful condition
belonging to Adrian Fowler. Also present was Mike Downman, formerly a
keeper at Rode, who is now working with primates at Howletts Zoo.
The day concluded with an excellent film show and talk by Mike
Salisbury of the BBC Natural History Unit based in Bristol. Mike was the
producer of Sir David Attenborough&apos;s Life of Birds TV series.
Hopefully, it was a good PR exercise for the Society and some of the
students may eventually become members.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.793281" page_id="56264938"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
* \0x2756 *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.671721" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264938" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
UNUSUAL HAPPENINGS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989745133333333" page_id="56264938"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
The Violet-backed Starling Cinnyricinclus leucogaster is a surprise
inclusion in The European Bird Report (a '...continent-wide report on
population trends and significant, nationally accepted records of rarities')
in British Birds 93,9:428-433 (September 2000). It is on account of the first
record of this species in Israel, at Eilat from July 5th - August 14th, back in
1983. The same report includes the first and second breeding records of the
(Indian) House Crow Corvus splendens in the Netherlands in 1997 and 1998.
The section on non-native birds breeding in the UK in 1998, includes two
pairs of Alexandrine Parrakeets Psittacula eupatria which nested at Fazackerly,
Merseyside, and raised broods of five and three young. All 12 were seen
together later, but sometime afterwards several were shot by youths with
airguns. At least one pair though are known to have survived through the
following winter. Malcolm Ogilvie and the Rare Breeding Birds Panel noted:
'While we must condemn the vandalism, we also do not wish another member
of the parrot family to become established as a breeding species in Britain.'
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998655" page_id="56264939"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
187
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.987288" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264939" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
OBITUARY
KENNETH JAMES LAWRENCE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997799333333333" page_id="56264939"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
The sudden death of the Society's Chairman Ken Lawrence came as a
great shock. He died on November 1st, when travelling home from the office
of the weekly magazine Cage &amp; Aviary Birds, where he had been busy
working on the arrangements for the National Exhibition of Cage &amp; Aviary
Birds.
When Ken and his wife Jean married in 1953, he began keeping foreign
birds and had continued to do so ever since. In those early days he kept a
fine array of lories, lorikeets and small seedeaters. Many rare birds came
into his possession, among them South African and South American species
he acquired from sailors when their ships docked at Harwich. These included
an Orange Cock of the Rock, a Naked-throated Bellbird, Orange-breasted
Sun birds, Dufresne's Waxbills and various hummingbirds. Later Ken
specialised in starlings - he was particularly fond of Spreos - and bred a
number of different species. He also kept a small stud of Zebra Finches.
As well as keeping, breeding, exhibiting and judging foreign birds, Ken
was a tireless worker and administrator. &apos;He joined the Avicultural Society
in 1955. He was elected a Council Member in 1970 and on the retirement
of Prof. Hodges was elected Chairman. Ken also arranged the social events;
and if the collection we were to visit lacked suitable catering facilities, often
would visit the nearest town or village in advance and find a nice pub in
which we could hold our Council Meeting and in which members and their
guests invariably enjoyed a splendid lunch at a reasonable price, before setting
off to view the birds.
Ken also joined the Foreign Bird League in the early 1950s and was
elected onto its Council some 10 years later. He became its first Chairman
in 1968, a post he retired from 20 years later, upon which he was made an
Honorary Life Member. In 1980 Ken was a joint winner of the League's
Herbert Wragg Memorial Shield, an annual award for meritorious breedings.
A number of prominent foreign bird enthusiasts in the London area
became acquainted with Ken following the formation of the Southern Foreign
Bird Club in 1961. Two years later he was elected Chairman, a position he
held for the next 25 years. Ken also served on the committee of the National
Council for Aviculture (NCA), and served as Chairman of that organisation
too.
Our sincere condolences are extended to his wife Jean, his daughters
Jane and Nicola, and his three grand-daughters.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997915" page_id="56264940"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
188
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.917412" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264940" page_num="188" year="" vol="">
CONTRIBUTORS TO VOLUME 106 - 2000
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.881558333333333" page_id="56264940"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
BIRCHENOUGH, Andy C. &amp; EVANS, Stewart M.
The potential contribution of aviculture to conservation
breeding of estrildid finches.............145
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.875285653846154" page_id="56264940"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
BLACK, Kara
How I came to keep mousebirds...104
BOCKHEIM, Greg
The unique fishing techniques and nest building behaviour of
captive Hammerkops Scopus umbretta ..56
BRICKELL, Neville &amp; KONIGKRAMER, Trevor
Further notes on the Drakensberg Siskin Serinus totta symonsi ... 118
BURDEN, P.
Breeding the White-collared Yuhina.97
CALLAGHAN, Eric
The San Bias Jay, a cooperative breeder.......Ill
COLLEN, Rose, HOLLAND, Glen, TWENTYMAN, Caroline,
PAULI, Jerry &amp; WATTS, Betty
Stitchbirds - an avicultural challenge...... 22
CONGDON, Susan &amp; ZIMA, Bill
Breeding the African Jagana Actophilornis africanus at
Disney's Animal Kingdom.62
CORNEJO, Juan
Hand-rearing an Asian Green Starling Aplonis panayensis ....122
GRANTHAM, Bob
Breeding the Purple-bellied Parrot Triclaria malachitacea ..170
GREENEY, Harold F., GORDON, Caleb E.,
KAPLAN, Matthew E &amp; CHIMERA, Charles G.
The high occurrence of brood patches in mist-netted birds
in a lowland Ecuadorian rainforest.......10
GROGAN, Ivor
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.522529">
Breeding the White-breasted Amazilia Amazilia a. leucophoea... 157
HILL, Ryan L. and GREENEY, Harold F.
Ecuadorian birds: nesting records and egg descriptions
from a lowland rainforest..........49
HINZE, Ian
Waxbills and their allies: the Lavender Waxbill ... 80
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998034" page_id="56264941"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
189
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8184105" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264941" page_num="189" year="" vol="">
CONTRIBUTORS TO VOLUME 106 - 2000 (Cont'd)
JOLIFFE, Tony
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.7735625" page_id="56264941"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
Breeding the Lemon-breasted Canary Serinus citrinipectus and
notes on some other Serinus species ..178
LINDSAY, Nick
The new penguin development at Whipsnade....85
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.97270616" page_id="56264941"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
MYCOCK, Malcolm
The probable first UK breeding of the Marabou ..182
PAGEL, Theo
Notes on keeping and breeding the Elegant Pitta Pitta elegans ... 165
PYPER, Stewart
The Society's visit to Wem ......... 87
ROMER, Charlie
Three months - three continents....... 99
RUBERY, Mark
Breeding the Lesser Flamingo Phoeniconaias minor .. 126
SCHOFIELD, Philip
Breeding the Madagascar Turtle Dove Streptopelia picturata ..... 107
Thirty years with pheasants.....1
SCHULTZ, Paul
Breeding and group dynamics in Magpie Shrikes Corvinella
melanoleuca at Disney's Animal Kingdom ..... 173
SMITH, Chris
Notes and observations on hand-rearing African Pygmy Falcons
Polihierax semitorquatus .....12
WILKINSON, Roger
Chester Zoo bird review 1999 .....74
WILLIAMS, Trace
Watching Bali Starlings at Jersey Zoo ..54
WOOLHAM, Frank
The Rufous-capped and other babblers.....34
</figure>
<page confidence="0.996351" page_id="56264942"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
190
</page>
<table confidence="0.9358662" page_id="56264942"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
INDEX TO VOLUME 106 - 2000
Actophilornis africanus, breeding........ 62
Amazilia amazilia leucophoea, breeding.157
Amazilia, White-breasted, breeding.157
Aplonis panayensis, the hand-rearing of.....122
Babblers, Rufous-capped and others...34
Book Reviews
African Parrots.134
Australian White Cockatoos.......43
Handbook of the Birds of the World.41
Management of Laughing Thrushes in Captivity...129
Parrot Action Plan ......... 130
The Loving Care of Pet Parrots.......133
Brood patches, high occurrence in mist-netted birds ..10
Canary, Lemon-breasted, breeding and notes on some others.178
Chester zoo, bird review 1999.74
Cissilopha sanblasiana, a cooperative breeder........Ill
Colius striatus, experiences keeping.104
Conservation, potential contribution of aviculture...145
Cooperative breeder, the San Bias Jay.Ill
Corvinella melanoleuca, brooding and group dynamics... 173
Council Meetings.....40 &amp; 88
Dove, Madagascar Turtle, breeding...... 107
Ecuadorian birds, brood patches in.....10
Ecuadorian birds, nesting records and egg descriptions....49
</table>
<reference confidence="0.808588625">
Estrilda caerulescens, notes on. 80
Falcon, African Pygmy, notes and observations on hand-rearing ..12
Finches, Australian, captive breeding as a potential
contribution to conservation.....145
Finches, Parrot, captive breeding as a potential contribution
to conservation .. 145
Flamingo, Lesser, breeding .. .....126
Hammerkop, fishing techniques and nest building behaviour.56
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998621" page_id="56264943"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
191
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.682977" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264943" page_num="191" year="" vol="">
INDEX TO VOLUME 106 - 2000 (Cont'd)
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.604302416666667" page_id="56264943"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
Jacana, African, breeding ..................................................................... 62
Jay, San Bias, a cooperative breeder .................................................. Ill
Leptoptilos crumeniferus, probable first UK breeding ....................... 182
Letters ....................................................................................... 36, 37, 38
Leucospar rothschildi , watching at Jersey Zoo .................................... 54
Marabou, probable first UK breeding ................................................ 182
Mousebird, Striated, experiences keeping.......................................... 104
Notiomystis cincta, an avicultural challenge ........................................ 22
Obituaries ...... 141,142,143,187
Parrot, Purple-bellied, breeding.......................................................... 170
Parrots, see three months - three continents ......................................... 99
Penguins, new development at Whipsnade .......................................... 85
Pheasants, thirty years with .................................................................... 1
Phoeniconaias minor , breeding .......................................................... 126
Pitta elegans, keeping and breeding................................................... 165
Pitta, Elegant, keeping and breeding .................................................. 165
Polihierax semitorquatus, notes and observations on hand-rearing ..... 12
Serinus citrinipectus , breeding and notes on some others.................. 178
Shrike, Magpie (or Long-tailed), breeding and group dynamics ....... 173
Siskin, Drakensberg, further notes on ................................................ 118
Stachyris ruficeps , and other babblers.................................................. 34
Starling, Asian Green, the hand-rearing of......................................... 122
Starling, Bali, watching at Jersey Zoo.................................................. 54
Stitchbird, an avicultural challenge ...................................................... 22
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.930655333333333">
Streptopeliapicturata , breeding ......................................................... 107
Triclaria malachitacea , breeding ....................................................... 170
Waxbill, Lavender, notes on ................................................................. 80
Wem, the Society's visit to ................................................................... 87
Yuhina diademata, breeding ................................................................. 97
Yuhina, White-collared, breeding......................................................... 97
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.625617" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264944" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ROB HARVEY SPECIALIST FEEDS
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.7846035" page_id="56264944"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Everything From Hummingbird Nectar to Elephant food !
Supplying over 50 Zoological Parks
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.935421" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264944" page_num="" year="" vol="">
MEALWORMS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999743" page_id="56264944"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
We sell a complete range of
livefoods &amp; frozen foods.
If you use 51b of mealworms a time then
enquire about our unbeatable trade prices.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.983644" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264944" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ARCADIA BIRD LAMPS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993784" page_id="56264944"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Improves feeding and breeding behaviour.
Fits into standard fluorescent fittings or we
can supply fittings and reflectors.
We can mail order to your door.
Visit our new updated &amp; friendly website www.robharvey.com
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9873555" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264944" page_num="" year="" vol="">
OVER 1000 WORLD WIDE LINKS
BREEDERS DIRECTORY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990676" page_id="56264944"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
E-mail us if you want to be Advertise your surplus
,, , u a a- e stock FREE
added to our breeders directory
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.950250866666667" page_id="56264944"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
WITTE MOLEN TUBS
Moist eggfood - #14.25 5kg
Hedgerow Eggfood - #15.50 5kg
Universal Food - #14.25 5kg
Low Iron for Touracos - #16.25 5kg
Eggfood Red - #15.50 5kg
DRIED FRUITS
Chilean jumbo golden raisins
Iranian whole pitted sair dates
Turkish sultanas &amp; Chilian Flame raisins
Sri Lankan raw thin chip coconut
Philippine whole honey dipped banana chips
Any combination - Delivery included
1kg #5.95 5kg #12.95 10 kg #19.95
WITTE MOLEN
</table>
<figure confidence="0.840840263157895" page_id="56264944"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
PARROT PREMIUM
5kg for #8.00
15kg for #19.75
30kg for only #35.00
AVI-PLUS
LORIKEET
SPECIAL
used by many zoos
#5.95 per kg
AVI-PLUS PARROT
HANDREARING FOOD
used to raise over 10,000 parrots
in South Africa last year alone -
#6.95 per kg
Buy 2 &amp; get one FREE!
p&amp;p.
#3.95 up to 1kg
#3.95 up to 30kg
HEMPROPE
</figure>
<table confidence="0.619581333333333" page_id="56264944"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
As used in zoos and bird parks.
Enhance your parrot's environment.
36mm #6.99 per metre or 10m for #55!
24mm #3.45 per metre or 10m for #27!
We also stock j
carrying boxes and
</table>
<reference confidence="0.711953111111111">
stainless steel bowls.
Please ask for our
new price list
Mail order on all products.
-- &amp;quot;&apos;1- For our price list or advice please contact
Rob Harvey (ex-owner &amp; curator of Birdworld for over 20 years)
E-mail: admin@robharvey.com Tel: 01420 23986 Fax: 01420 23078
Rob Harvey, Kookaburra House, Gravel Hill Road, Holt Pound,
Famham, Surrey, GU10 4LG.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999276" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264945" page_num="" year="" vol="">
IN THE PINK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986275" page_id="56264945"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
In 1997, the Wildlife Conservation Society (WCS), of New York,
spearheaded the first comprehensive censuses of Andean and James'
Flamingos Phoenicoparrus andinus and P. jamesi. Two censuses in the
summers of 1997 and 1998, and three in the winters of 1997, 1998 and
2000, simultaneously in Argentina, Bolivia, Chile and Peru, recorded at least
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.83547875" page_id="56264945"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
34,000 Andean and 64,000 James'. Other census results, reported in Wildlife
Conservation , Vol.103, No.6, November-December 2000, put the total
population of Caribbean Flamingos Phoenicopterus ruber ruber at just over
270,000,40,000 in the Bahamas, 17,000 in Venezuela, 180,000 in Cuba and
34,000 on Mexico's Yucatan Peninsula.
* * *
NEW DIRECTOR
American, James (Jamie) D. Gilardi PhD, one of the four editors and an
author of the Parrot Action Plan reviewed recently in the Avicultural
Magazine (Vol.106, No.3, pp. 130-133), is the new Director of the World
Parrot Trust. Mike Reynolds has taken on the role of Chairman.
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.6232" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264945" page_num="" year="" vol="">
SENTENCE REDUCED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.845453090909091" page_id="56264945"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Harry Sissen had his appeal against his conviction for illegally importing
into the UK three Lear's Macaws Anodorhynchus leari and six Blue-headed
Macaws Ara couloni (see News &amp; Views, Vol.106, No.2, p.90 &amp; Vol.106,
No.3, p.136) dismissed at the Court of Appeal in London, but his sentence
was reduced from two and a half years to one and a half years and he became
eligible for parole at Christmas.
It has been reported that a further 13 of the seized birds have died. They
are: two Red-vented Cockatoos Cacatua haematuropygia , a Thick-billed
Parrot Rhynchopsittapachyrhyncha, four Hyacinth Macaws A. hyacinthinus,
two Red-fronted Macaws A rubrogenys , two Buffon's Macaws A ambigua,
a Blue-throated Macaw A. glaucogularis and a Scarlet Macaw A. macao.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993394" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264946" page_num="" year="" vol="">
SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION LIBRARIES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996732" page_id="56264946"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
111
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8429095" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56264946" page_num="" year="" vol="">
3 9(
CONTENTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.787176" page_id="56264946"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The potential contribution of aviculture to conservation
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.916709125" page_id="56264946"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
breeding of estrildid finches
by Andy C. Birchenough and Stewart M. Evans.145
Breeding the White-breasted Amazilia Amazilia amazilia
leucophoea
by Ivor Grogan.157
Notes on keeping and breeding the Elegant Pitta Pitta elegans
by Theo Pagel.165
Breeding the Purple-bellied Parrot Triclaria malachitacea
by Bob Grantham.170
Breeding and group dynamics in Magpie Shrikes Corvinella
melanoleuca at Disney's Animal Kingdom
by Paul Schutz....173
Breeding the Lemon-breasted Canary Serinus citrinipectus and
notes on some other Serinus species
by Tony Jolliffe....178
The probable first UK breeding of the Marabou
by Malcolm Mycock.182
News &amp; Views.185
Obituary
Kenneth James Lawrence.187
Contributors to Volume 106 - 2000 ... 188
Index to Volume 106 - 2000.190
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</table>
</algorithms>
