<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.77611425" page_id="56269405"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
&amp;lt;&amp;&amp;lt;-
671
{\ c \ c 57
AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 108
No. 4
2002
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="method" page_id="56269406" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991782428571429" page_id="56269406"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2002 as for 2001: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.614423" genericHeader="method" page_id="56269406" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.915113888888889" page_id="56269406"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, P.O. BOX 47, EDENBRIDGE, KENT TN8 7WP, ENGLAND.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TN13 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail:lee.palm@virgin.net
Enquiries regarding membership should be sent to:
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.79275925" page_id="56269406"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE MEMBERSHIP SECRETARY, Stewart Pyper, 21, Primrose Hill,
Nunney, Frome, Somerset BA11 4NP.
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.9966775" page_id="56269406"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998476" genericHeader="method" page_id="56269406" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982477333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<figure confidence="0.189991666666667" page_id="56269407"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
Vol. 108 - No. 4 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2002
THE BLACK-RUMPED WAXBILL Estrilda troglodytes
by Ian Hinze
Description
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.997603357142857" page_id="56269407"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Length 9.5cm (3 3 /4in). The sexes are alike. The upperparts are light
brownish grey with delicate vermiculations on all feathers apart from those
of the forehead and wing quills. A bright red or crimson eye-stripe runs
from the base of the bill and passes above and below the eye and across the
top of the ear-coverts before tapering to a point. The cheeks and lower ear-
coverts are whitish or pale buff, which extends to the chin and throat before
becoming pinkish buff on the lower breast, flanks and upper belly. The
lower belly and a patch in front of the vent are reddish pink, the coloration
sometimes spreading up over the median parts of the lower breast and, less
frequently, reaching the upper breast, sides of the breast and flanks. The
under tail-coverts are pinkish white. The under wing-coverts are pale huffish.
The rump, upper tail-coverts and tail are black. The outermost pair of tail
feathers have white to the outer webs, with the next pair sometimes possessing
a small amount of white at the tips of the outer webs. The tail is wedge-
shaped when spread. The bill is bright waxy red to crimson. The irides are
reddish brown. The legs and feet are dark brown or sometimes brown with
a purplish hue.
The juvenile is light drab brown above and pale huffish brown below,
with no cross-barring on the feathers. The diagnostic white outer tail feathers
are clearly visible. It lacks the red eye-stripe but may possess a slightly
darkish area with reddish traces where the stripe later appears. Even at
fledgling age and while still possessing conspicuous bluish white gape
tubercles the red traces are sometimes clearly evident. The bill is black.
Goodwin (1982) reported the nestling as at first having yellowish skin
and pale bluish down, but those I examined were flesh coloured and
completely naked. There is a semi-circular gape mark either side of the
upper mandible and two bluish white globules, one on the 'join' and the
other immediately in front of it on the lower mandible.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99909" page_id="56269408"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
146
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.552773" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269408" page_num="146" year="" vol="">
HINZE - BLACK-RUMPED WAXBILL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.920702789473684" page_id="56269408"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
Field guide
A tiny brownish grey bird with a red bill and red eye-stripe and a black,
white-edged tail that is frequently jerked from side to side. It can be
distinguished from the Common Waxbill E. astrild and the Rosy-rumped
Waxbill E. rhodopyga by its black rump and tail and from the Arabian Waxbill
E. rufibarba by its red belly patch, pink tinged body plumage and its entirely
red bill.
Voice
Its calls are rather loud and harsh for a bird so small, with "cheu-cheu "
or " chit-chit " being the locomotion-intention and/or short distance contact
calls. There is a louder, upwardly inflected " cheeer" or " chee-ey ", which
is uttered in alarm and possibly some other states of excitement. One of my
own birds uttered "Chexv-tchu-tchu" and "Chet-ow-uh-eee Chet-ow-uh-eee"
with a hard "Chi". Defensive or aggressive threats give rise to a harsher
but less loud and more buzzing "cheer" or "cheea " (Goodwin, 1982). Flocks
in flight emit "tiup-tiup-tiup" calls (Bannerman, in Goodwin, 1982) and a
characteristic drawn-out "tsooeet" is frequently uttered (Serle et ah, 1977;
and pers. obs.). Goodwin (1982) found the nest call used, and occasionally
when changing over at the nest during incubation, was a soft murmering
twitter, "tswee-tswee-tswee ". The song of the male is a loud, explosive and
rising (on second note) "tche-tcheeer\, chee-eeerC, or "t'chu-weee", but
with the second note descending. The song of the female is "pwich ! cheee "
with the second note inflected, or the first explosive note repeated, i.e.
" pwichl pwichl " I have heard very young begging nestlings emit "pet-uh-
pet-uh-pet-uh-pet-uh-pet-uh", with older nestlings emitting "tch-chew-tch-
chew-tch-chew" and still older ones "tch-zrr-tch-zrr-tch-tch-tch-zrr-tch-zrr".
Distribution
Senegal (where it is widely but patchily distributed in the north and south),
The Gambia and Guinea east to southern Mali, Burkina Faso, Ghana, southern
Niger, northern Nigeria, northern Cameroon, southern Chad, the Central
African Republic, extreme northern Congo and north-east Democratic
Republic of Congo, northern Uganda from West Nile, Wadelai and Kidepo
Valley National Park south to Kabalega Falls National Park and Kumi, Sudan
north to Darfur and Sennar, Eritrea and north-western Ethiopia, and western
Kenya (Siaya and Kisumu east to Ahero and north to Ukwala).
Status
Widespread, often a resident but absent from some of its breeding places
in the dry season.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.304454" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269409" page_num="147" year="" vol="">
HINZE - BLACK-RUMPED WAXBILL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997577" page_id="56269409"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
147
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.987333487804878" page_id="56269409"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
Introduced distribution
It was introduced onto Puerto Rico in the mid-1960s and onto Guadeloupe
later that same decade. It was also introduced successfully onto the Hawaiian
Islands (Hawaii and Oahu) (Lever, 1987), but unsuccessfully onto Tahiti
(Long, 1981).
It has been established on Basse-Terre, Guadaloupe, since at least the
late 1960s and also occurs on Grande-Terre, but in smaller numbers. On
Guadaloupe the bird feeds largely on the seeds of Panicum maximum , which
was introduced long ago from Africa and can be found along roadside verges
and abandoned cane fields. Both H.A. Raffaele and the American
Ornithologists' Union (in Lever, 1987) confirmed it is established on Puerto
Rico.
Birds on the Hawaiian Islands appear to be established in the Kapiolani
Park-Diamond Head area where they were observed every year from 1966-
1976 and were slowly increasing (Hawaiian Audubon Society and Pyle in
Long, 1981). They are likely the progeny of released or escaped birds, in
1965, on the island of Oahu (Berger in Long, 1981). C.F. Zeillemaker and
J.M. Scott recorded the species as local and uncommon in dry lowland
residential and community parklands on Oahu (in Lever, 1987) and, in 1983,
the American Ornithologists' Union reported that it occurs in small numbers
on Oahu and Hawaii.
Eastham Guild released birds on Tahiti in 1938 and they were reported
by him to have nested and reared young there. Two years later he reported
that they were still established, but later records point to the introduction as
having been unsuccessful (Long, 1981).
This species has also been recorded almost annually since 1975 on the
Rock of Gibraltar and it was thought possible it and other waxbills, derived
from released or escaped cage birds, were consolidating their presence in
Iberia (J. E. Cortes et al. in Lever, 1987).
Writing more recently, about exotic birds in Portugal, Costa et al. (1997)
noted it has been recorded at several places in the Algarve, listed it as probably
breeding in Portugal and also mentioned that it has been recorded at several
places in Galicia, north-west Spain, close to Portugal's northern border. Snow
and Perrins (1998) state it and the Crimson-rumped Waxbill have recently
been reported breeding in the Algarve and hybrids also occur.
Habitat, general behaviour and feeding
It is found at 750m-1,500m (approx.2,450ft-4,950ft) (van Perlo, 1995)
inhabiting grassy savannahs, scrub and grassy areas near water, open country
with thorn scrub, marshes and is occasionally spotted on the edge of
cultivation, but it is not generally found in the close vicinity of human
habitations. Usually it is recorded in pairs, small groups or may occasionally
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998746" page_id="56269410"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
148
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.716682" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269410" page_num="148" year="" vol="">
HINZE - BLACK-RUMPED WAXBILL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.980811926829268" page_id="56269410"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
be spotted in large flocks, often with other waxbills. Gore (1990) reported
up to 50 birds were observed gathering at laterite pools, between August-
November, at Bansang, Gambia. However, between August-October in the
Banjul area, parties of up to only 10 birds were recorded, indicating some
dispersal in the non-breeding season. Its tail is often flicked from side to
side when excited or alarmed. It feeds principally on grass seeds, both on
the ground and from growing vegetation, and the growing tips of young
grass. It is very agile among vegetation and, when feeding from grass
panicles, may hold them underfoot. Small insects, such as midges, are also
taken.
Courtship display
The male picks up a piece of nesting material (usually a long grass stem)
by one end in his bill, flies up to a branch and lifts his head upwards to an
angle of 60*-70*. The plumage on the belly is slightly fluffed out but
otherwise the feathers look slick. If the female is alongside the male he will
angle his tail towards her, but if she is immediately in front, the tail is held
straight. The male then proceeds to bob stiffly up and down by bending and
straightening his legs but does not let go of the branch with his feet as he
does so. During this display the male repeats his song and glances in the
direction of the female. Kunkel (in Goodwin, 1982) mentioned that the
female may sometimes display but that this is usually done without singing.
The display does not immediately lead to copulation, this takes place in the
nest.
Nesting
The ball to pear-shaped nest is usually built on the ground, at the base of
a clump of long grass or a small bush and made of dry grass heads (Shuel in
Goodwin, 1982) and, based on my captive studies, likely dry grass stems
and grass leaves, even fresh ones if they have been found broken or uprooted.
There is often a cock-nest built on top and the entrance to the real nest is
usually by way of an entrance tube. The nest is often lined with soft plant
material and/or a few feathers and so, too, is the cock-nest. Both the outside
of the real nest and the outside and inside of the cock-nest may be decorated
with bits of dried earth, excreta, pieces of eggshell, dead beetles and even
the corpse of a nestling.
The eggs usually number four to five. Both sexes take turns to incubate
them for about 11 days and both brood the young, which are fed primarily
on tender grass seeds and small insects. Fledging occurs at 17-20 days but
the young are led back to the nest to roost and for protection for a few days
afterwards. Both parents feed the young until they are independent. It is
believed the species is a breeding host of the parasitic Pin-tailed Whydah
Vidua macroura.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.30454" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269411" page_num="149" year="" vol="">
HINZE - BLACK-RUMPED WAXBILL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998274" page_id="56269411"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
149
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.990298418604652" page_id="56269411"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
Captive observations
It is a frequently imported species but has an extremely poor breeding
record, in spite of having been bred first in the UK as long ago as 1903, by
Lady Dunleath (Coles, 1986). It is a very timid, gregarious species that is a
delight to possess. It is attractively coloured without being overly gaudy,
peaceful and vivacious. An obvious drawback is acquiring a true pair, though
the main reason for it not being domesticated is due to the lack of interest in
its propagation because of its common availability, cheapness to buy and
the desire of many aviculturists to possess less frequently available and/or
more colourful species. Insufficient livefood of the correct type and quantity
is also blamed for breeding failures, but this species can be reared on the
milky green seeds of some indigenous plants and grasses, as well as eggfood,
once it has become accustomed to it.
Nests containing eggs and/or young are frequently lost due to interference
from other species (though I have witnessed a particularly determined male
chase off a rather too inquisitive male Blue-headed Cordon-bleu Uraeginthus
cyanocephalus ), nest inspection by the owner or by being washed out in a
storm if nesting in an outside aviary. Nests (complete with cock-nest) are
frequently built on the ground out of dried and fresh grasses and coconut
fibres. If dried grass is placed in the corner of a birdroom the nest starts off
as a depression caused by the male pressing his body downwards, with both
sexes then constructing the sides and roof. Dried grass is collected and bent
in semi-circular fashion, by the bird pushing up with its bill and the crown
of its head, until eventually the front (or side) opening gradually becomes
smaller and smaller in a concentric circle-like manner.
Nests may be decorated on the outside with charcoal, dried earth, dried
excreta, small pieces of gravel, the corpse of a nestling, tiny white shells,
bits of tissue paper - in fact, anything the birds take a fancy to. A male in my
collection showed particular excitement, fanning and twitching his tail from
side to side, on finding the tail feather of a Goldfinch Carduelis carduelis
and, holding it by the quill, succeeded in pushing it into the fibres of the
nest. This 'excitement' behaviour was taken to its highest extent when the
corpse of a Gold-breast Amandava subflava nestling was discovered on the
floor. The male which found it was about to clasp it in his bill when he was
suddenly joined by two other male Black-rumped Waxbills. Immediately a
tug of war ensued, until one of birds emerged victorious - for a moment!
On flying off to his nest he was pursued by the other two birds and no
sooner had he placed the corpse onto the wall of his nest when it was stolen
by one of the pursuers. The corpse was carried first this way and then the
other as each bird took it in turns to quickly snatch it away at the first
opportunity. Eventually calm resumed and the battered corpse was wiped
all over one nest, right up to the cock-nest, before finally being embedded in
the outer wall.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99101" page_id="56269412"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
150
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.703415" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269412" page_num="150" year="" vol="">
HINZE - BLACK-RUMPED WAXBILL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99875419047619" page_id="56269412"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
On some occasions a 4in-5in (approx. 10cm-12.5cm) diameter 'territorial'
semi-circle was made around each nest and this contained pieces of compost
or charcoal. When I opened up an old nest for examination I found it had
been lined with feathers and pieces of charcoal and/or compost. On another
occasion I observed a male using saliva and other mouth contents, such as
eggfood, as well as fresh faeces, to wipe into the outer layer of its nest. On
examining the nest after the young had fledged I was struck by how heavier
than normal it seemed. I had great difficulty in breaking the nest open as the
coconut fibres used in its construction had been cemented together. To date,
this is the only time I have seen such a nest.
The instinctive drive to decorate the nest is a strong one and birds that
instead of building their own nest utilise a wicker basket, often spend
considerable time and energy trying to place various items on the outside.
These invariably fall off because of the shape of the nest and the fact that
wicker material is too hard to allow such items to be impregnated into it.
Dry fine grass is especially good for lining the insides of wicker baskets. A
wicker basket in close proximity to one being nested in may be used as a
substitute cock-nest, with the male bird lining it and even sitting in it while
his mate sits in the real nest.
When they first emerge from the nest fledglings may be clumsy fliers
and hardly get airborne. Often they crash-land on the floor and are quickly
joined by their concerned parents, and conspecifics if they are housed
together, which offer protection and encouragement. Within a day, however,
they are usually competent enough to fly to a perch. They are also reasonably
steady and it is only after a few days of liberty from the nest that they take
on the flightiness of their parents. The parents entice them back into the
nest for the first few days after fledging or sometimes for only the first day.
Birds may sleep all in a line on a perch during the day, but only in their pairs
or small groups of about four individuals during the night. A juvenile male
in my collection was observed singing and performing the courtship display,
and I have also witnessed a juvenile standing its ground and then bettering
an adult at the food dish.
This is potentially a really good beginner's bird. Providing keepers give
it the attention it deserves I see no reason why it cannot be bred in cages.
The minimum birdroom temperature in which it should be kept is 15*C
(60*F). The staple seed mixture for my birds consists of a Foreign Finch
mix and a British Finch mix blended together. Prior to and then throughout
the breeding season very small livefood, such as fruit-fly larvae and soft,
white-skinned mini-mealworms, should be provided fresh at least twice a
day, as well as daily amounts of fresh eggfood and seeding grasses. Over
the following weeks the livefood should be very gradually withdrawn until
the birds have only the staple seeds, seeding grasses and eggfood to consume.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.304711" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269413" page_num="151" year="" vol="">
HINZE - BLACK-RUMPED WAXBILL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998879" page_id="56269413"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
151
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.842967" page_id="56269413"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
Eventually it should be possible to breed one&amp;apos;s birds without any livefood at
all
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.479743" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56269413" page_num="151" year="" vol="">
References and bibliography
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.895955807692308" page_id="56269413"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
Britton, P. L. (ed.) 1980. Birds of East Africa. E.A.N.H.S., Nairobi.
Clement, R, Harris, A. &amp; Davis, J. 1993. Finches and Sparrows. Christopher Helm/A &amp; C
Black, London.
Coles, D. 1987. First Records for Birds Reared to Independence under Controlled Conditions
in the U.K. Coles, Berks.
Costa, H,. Elias, G. L. &amp; Farinha, J. C. 1997. Exotic birds in Portugal. British Birds 90,12:562-
568.
Goodwin, D. 1982. Estrildid finches of the world. British Museum (Natural History), London.
Gore, M. E. J. 1990. Birds of The Gambia , Second Revised Edition, B.O.U., Oxford.
Hinze, I. 1993. Common red-ears heading for rarity status. A. F. A. Watchbird. Vol.XX, No.3,
pp.34-37. American Federation of Aviculture.
Hinze, I. 1995. The Black-ramped Waxbill. The Estrildian 3,2:16-25. Estrildid Forum.
Hinze, I. 1995. Success with black-ramped and rosy-ramped waxbills. The NFSS Bulletin
11,5:47-49. USA.
Lever, C. 1987. Naturalised Birds of the World. Longman Scientific and Technical, Harlow,
Essex.
Long, J.L. 1981. Introduced birds of the world. Agr. Pro. Board of Western Australia.
Snow, D. W. &amp; Perrins, C. M. (eds.) 1998. The Birds of the Western Palearctic, Concise Edition,
Vol.2. Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York.
van Perlo, B. 1995. Collins Illustrated Checklist, Birds of Eastern Africa. HarperCollins,
London.
Ian Hinze specialises in the study of waxbills and their allies and writes
extensively about these birds . He was awarded the society&amp;apos;s medal for the
UK first breeding of the Mali or Kulikoro Firefinch Lagonsticta virata.
He lives in Manchester, England, and can be contacted by e-mail:
i. hinze @ ntlworld. com
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999175" page_id="56269414"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
152
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.791687333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56269414" page_num="152" year="" vol="">
PARENT REARED AFRICAN JACANAS Actophilornis
africana AT DISNEY'S ANIMAL KINGDOM
by Susan Congdon
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997334378378378" page_id="56269414"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
Relatively easy to house given the right habitat, the challenge with
keeping African Jaganas has been successfully breeding and rearing them.
Disney's Animal Kingdom (DAK), Florida, USA, is one of the few
institutions to have had success hand-rearing jagana chicks, and is now one
of even fewer to have had them successfully parent reared.
During our first breeding season, their eggs disappeared from the large
free-flight mixed species aviary in which thejaganas are housed, and a time
lapse camera revealed that these eggs had been destroyed by rodents and a
breeding pair of Black Crakes Limnocoraxflavirostra. As no US institutions
were at that time successfully breeding African Jaganas, we made the decision
to remove all eggs and hand-rear the chicks. However, by late 2000 we
noted that the numerous jaganas that we had raised by hand were showing
signs of imprinting, likely due to the high level of interaction just after
hatching, when attempting to get the chicks to eat (see Congdon and Zima,
2000). As a result, we were determined to allow the parents to rear their
own chicks during the next breeding season. As we had produced 13 chicks
from the only wild-caught pair that was breeding in the USA, we decided to
take the risk and leave the eggs with the parents. We made one other
management change for that breeding season, we removed the breeding
pair of Black Crakes from the aviary and instead housed an all-female group.
The first clutch that was left for the male to incubate was laid in January
2001. The male sat much tighter than he had in the past and was much more
defensive of the nest site. The first egg hatched under the male on January
27th. The chick hatched a full day before the next two; however, the male
appeared more interested in the unhatched egg than in the chicks. Due to
his lack of attention, the chicks were removed for the night and taken to the
nursery where they were given subcutaneous and oral fluids and pipercillian.
The next morning the chicks were placed back on the nest and the remaining
egg was removed. Later that day, the male was observed carrying the chicks
under his wings and flew to the female when she called, apparently dropping
the chicks as he did so, which fell into the pond below containing a species
of large tilapia (fish). The chicks were not seen again.
It was not long before the male was incubating another clutch. On March
4th the first chick hatched, again a full day before the remaining chicks
hatched. Like before, the male attempted to fly with the chicks tucked under
his wings and they dropped into the pond. On this occasion, a large tilapia
was observed to swallow one of the chicks but then spat it back out. This
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.821301" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269415" page_num="153" year="" vol="">
CONGDON - AFRICAN JA#ANAS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999549" page_id="56269415"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
153
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998988413793103" page_id="56269415"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
time, three of the four chicks were recovered and both the male and the
chicks were moved to our off-exhibit Avian Research Center (ARC), where
the parent-rearing process continued. Here the chicks initially failed to gain
weight and were rotated through the nursery for supplemental feeding, but
with one or more of the chicks always being left with the adult. We came to
the conclusion that the earlier chick mortality was due to the chicks getting
a little chilled, as despite the room being heated, it has a concrete floor.
Subsequently, a heater was placed on the floor to warm that part of the
room. By day six the male again had all three chicks and was successfully
caring for them.
When the chicks were about 60 days old and eating on their own, the
male was released back into the aviary. Within a few days he was again
sitting on eggs, but unfortunately this third clutch disappeared shortly after
the fourth egg was laid. On June 28th a fourth clutch of eggs hatched in the
aviary. Due to construction work, the male and chicks were immediately
moved to the ARC. This time the chicks gained weight and did not require
supplementary feeding. This was most likely due to the combination of
warmer daytime temperatures and the heating unit on the floor.
Around day 70 the male was again returned to the aviary while the chicks
remained in the ARC. At that point the decision was taken to remove all
further eggs due to possible over-representation of this male and female's
offspring in US institutions.
Copenhagen Zoo, Denmark, succeeded in producing parent reared chicks
at the same time and we exchanged birds so as to be able to introduce fresh
genes into the US population. The two males that we have taken great pains
to acquire from Copenhagen will be paired with females that are unrelated
to our breeding pair, to ensure genetic diversity. Our breeding female has
since died and the former breeding male, because he is related to most of the
females in the USA, will in future be used only as an exhibit bird.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.865404" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56269415" page_num="153" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.949116" page_id="56269415"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
This paper was made possible due to the detailed observations made by
the aviary team at DAK. The DAK bird department management team of
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.74446775">
Grenville Roles, Chelle Plasse, Paul Schutz and Scott Barton also provided
valuable feedback.
Reference
Congdon, S. and Zima, W. 2000. Breeding the African Jacana Actophilomis africana at Disney's
Animal Kingdon. Avicultural Magazine 106, 2:62-73.
Susan Congdon is an aviary keeper at Disney's Animal Kingdom, PO.
Box 10,000, Lake Buena Vista, Florida 32830-1000, USA. Tel:407-938-
6383/Fax:502-333-3966.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.99861" page_id="56269416"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
154
</page>
<figure confidence="0.751725333333333" page_id="56269416"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
HOW DO TWO STURNIDS, Leucopsar rothschildi AND
Gracupica nigricollis , GET ALONG TOGETHER IN
LIMITED SPACE?
by Walter A Sontag, Jr,
Introduction
In my study of habitat use by Leucopsar , Bali Starlings Leucopsar
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.9817854375" page_id="56269416"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
rothschildi were kept together in an aviary with another (though non-
sympatric) south Asian stumid, the closely related Black-collared Starling
Gracupica nigricollis (Sontag, 2001b). The former are known to be highly
aggressive towards conspecifics (e.g. Sieber, 1978; Sontag, 2001b). In order
to avoid or reduce intra- and potential interspecific aggression the aviary
was spacious and highly structured. Moreover, the number of inhabitants
never exceeded six individuals. No severe aggression was observed between
the two species.
The Black-collared Starlings generally spent more time on the ground
layer than L. rothschildi, but the frequency of individual ground visits was
distinctly higher in the latter (cf. Sontag, 2001b). This study addressed the
question if and what type of correlation may exist between these two stumids
when sharing the same aviary? Theoretically, Bali Starlings might use the
ground space more when Black-collared Starlings spend more time on the
ground, or the opposite may be the case. Note also that in the wild mixed
aggregations of starling species have often been described. For instance,
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.5941965">
Brahminy Starlings Sturnus pagodarum associate freely with Grey-headed
Starlings S. malabaricus when feeding on flowering and fruiting trees and
with Asian Pied Starlings S. contra, Common Acridotheres tristis and Jungle
Mynahs A. fuscus when hunting grasshoppers etc. on the ground layer (Ali
&amp; Ripley, 1972: 161); A pagodarum also roost communally with Rosy
Pastors S. rose us and Common Mynahs (Ali &amp; Ripley, 1972). In Thailand
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.991404833333334" page_id="56269416"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
I have seen mixed starling associations such as tristis/javanicus (frequently),
tristis./javanicusl&amp;apos;nigricollis (regularly in wet cultivated areas also intensely
used by contra , Bang Pra area, s. e. Thailand) and tristis!javanicusl contra
(regularly, Chiang Mai district) (Sontag, 1997). Bali Starlings were recorded
using the same roost sites as Asian Pied Starlings and Black-winged Starlings
A. melanopterus (Ash, 1984). On the other hand, Sieber (1978) stated that
the latter was a food competitor of Leucopsar in the Bali Barat Nature
Reserve.
As the Bali Starling and Black-collared Starling are close relatives, I
first discuss phylogenetic aspects. I will present information from the
literature and my own observations. This may help to better understand (a)
some similarities and discrepancies between the two species, including
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.325361" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269417" page_num="155" year="" vol="">
SONTAG - TWO STURNIDS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999272" page_id="56269417"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
155
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997457024390244" page_id="56269417"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
habitat use and (b) corresponding properties that are potentially relevant to
interspecific behaviour. Secondly, I will report on the interspecific impact
in the study aviary, i.e. in the particular environmental (= experimental)
design to which the mixed species groups were exposed. Such knowledge
is useful for the aviculturist when maintaining mixed species groups.
The relationship of both species
Both belong to a complex of ca. 25 sturnids grouped around the genera
Sturnus and Acridotheres. The members of this group typically occur in
open habitats, move largely on the ground or exploit this part of the
environment, have a tendency for 'prying' (i.e. 'open-bill probing', due to
anatomical adaptations to the jaw muscles and skull), and form flocks
(Beecher, 1978; Sontag, 1992; Wickler, 1961; and others). Harrison (1963)
described characteristic behaviour patterns and compared them
interspecifically in order to propose a reliable scheme of the relationships
within the group. In a parasitological investigation apparently overlooked
by Feare &amp; Craig (1998), unknown Ischnocera have recently been described
from four closely related sturnids including the Bali Starling and the Black-
collared Starling (Mey, 1989). Mey arranged these mallophags according
to their morphologicial characters: with respect to the male genitalia (a key
mallophagan identification feature) the feather louse discovered on the Black-
collared Starling deviated strikingly from the mallophaga found on the other
three sturnid species, all of which are attributed to the genus Leucopsar in
Wolters' (1975-1982) checklist. Within this sub-set, the Ischnocera collected
from the Bali Starling clearly differed from the mallophaga settling on the
Black-winged Starling and the Vinous-breasted Starling A. burmannicus.
However, Sturnidoecus stresemanni, the Bali Starling feather louse, differed
completely from the other mallophaga in having a reduced subgenital plate
and in its overall colour (almost perfectly white) (Mey, 1989). This fits in
with the set of particularities found in L. rothschildi , i.e. its appearance,
peculiar bobbing style (Harrison, 1963; see below), shyness in the wild
(different from Black-winged Starling, Sieber, 1978), and its probable
adaptation to living in open forest (Sontag, 2001b).
My own observations made in the aviary and in the field (Nepal, Thailand)
support and even extend Harrison's contribution concerning the nodding
display. I saw the up-down movements of the head and bill along the
underparts in the Common Mynah and Jungle Mynah in Nepal and in the
Common and White-vented Mynah A. javanicus in Thailand (taxonomy
according to Ali &amp; Ripley, 1972 and Lekagul &amp; Round, 1991). Moreover,
in 1988 I observed a single Vinous-breasted Starling kept in a cage move its
head in a similar manner (see photo p.163). During later fieldwork in
Thailand I confirmed this type of nodding display in that species (which, as
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999537" page_id="56269418"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
156
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.706353" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269418" page_num="156" year="" vol="">
SONTAG - TWO STURNIDS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99863443902439" page_id="56269418"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
mentioned above, Wolters (1975-1982) had placed in the genus Leucopsar
as he had the Black-winged Starling). Harrison (1963), however, had already
reported the same nodding behaviour by the latter. Thus, the Bali Starling is
the only known member of the Sturnus-Acridotheres complex sensu Sontag
(1992) whose bobbing style involves the characteristic 'head back movement'
and 'body up thrusts'.
Specific behaviours of the Black-collared Starling
I studied Black-collared Starlings (four individuals + one juvenile from
a 'natural brood' that died before fledging) from 1985-1988 at the Institute
for Comparative Ethology of the Austrian Academy of Sciences in Vienna.
Thereafter, I observed this species under natural conditions in the wild in
Thailand.
To the best of my knowledge, the 'bobbing' display of the Black-collared
Starling is completely different from the displays of all the other sturnids of
the aforementioned group. This species raises the head feathers, bristling
the black feathers on the back of the neck, lowers the body, swells out the
plumage of the underparts, thrusts the bill 'cautiously' and repeatedly down
towards the substrate, and coos 'hoarsely' and in a low tone (see photo p. 163).
This behaviour is presented close to the companion. However, no copulation
has been observed at this time. The slow motion of the 'bowing movement
sequence', the type of 'cooing' and the momentary maintenance of the
bowed position clearly differentiate the display from the nodding modes
mentioned earlier.
In another characteristic display Black-collared Starlings behave in a
conspicuous manner based on visual and acoustic elements. An individual
screams harshly and very loudly, opening the bill widely and directing it
forward, i.e. +/- parallel to the ground. The white feathers on top of the head
and the black plumage at the back of the neck are ruffled, and the plumage
of the head and underparts is raised. Simultaneously, a short wing quiver-
beat was often observed. Generally speaking, wing-flicking and sideward
tail-flicking were frequently observed under captive conditions. Such
behaviour rapidly modifies the presentation of the complex blackish-greyish-
black-white wing pattern, the blackish rectrices with the white tail-tip and
the white rump-marking might suddenly become visible.
A striking feature of the Black-collared Starling is its voice. While the
above mentioned, strange nasal sounds - uttered in the bowing display - are
soft, three categories of high intensity vocalizations may roughly be
distinguished mainly by ear: (a) loud 'pure-tone' fluting, (b) vigorous harsh
'noisy' screaming (cf. above), and (c) harsh high-amplitude screaming (very
loud) when individuals join, rejoin or settle at a site (however, this behavioural
complex remains unclear). More detailed research may lead to an increased
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.325408" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269419" page_num="157" year="" vol="">
SONTAG - TWO STURNIDS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999303" page_id="56269419"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
157
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.995967902439024" page_id="56269419"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
number of distinguishable high-intensity vocalisation classes and find
connections between (b) and (c).
Apart from potential differences between captive and free-living
individuals, both the bowing display and the acoustic behaviours mentioned
may possibly occur in different contexts and accordingly may vary in their
particular expressions.
On one occasion I noticed a Black-collared Starling perform an anting
movement in the aviary. Such behaviour was observed in a group of three
(one adult, two young) wild and four released captive-bred Bali Starlings,
which were 5m-6m (approx. 16ft-19ft) above the ground in a Pilang tree Acacia
leucophloea (van Balen, 1996).
Rationale of the experimental design, aviary, subjects and groups,
statistical analyses
Based on the assumption of constant aviary and keeping conditions, a
clear positive correlation in using the same 'enclosure segments' by both
species would be interpreted as interspecific attraction; on the other hand, a
clear negative interspecific relation in habitat use would indicate that at
least one species avoids the other or both do. A third possiblity was that
there would be no clear trend, which would be equally intriguing. In this
case an interspecific connection would be largely lacking, especially when
overt conflicts (aggression, flight, etc.) were rare. Floor use appeared to be
a good measure for testing this issue. Stays on the floor vs. the other parts
of the aviary were recorded for both species.
The starlings studied were housed in a partly roofed, spacious, richly
structured aviary subdivided into two sections at the Institute for Comparative
Ethology of the Austrian Academy of Sciences in Vienna (for details see
Sontag, 2001b). Food was offered on the floor and on a board at an upper
level. The structural variety provided an abundance of environmental
conditions in the aviary which were intended to reduce aggression.
Subjects (six individuals), group compositions, study periods and
chronological order were the same as reported by Sontag (2001b). Three
mixed species groups were studied: Group 1 consisted of an adult pair of
Bali Starlings and an adult pair of Black-collared Starlings (the Bali Starling
nestlings were disregarded); Group 2 consisted of the same individuals plus
the two recently fledged offspring of the Bali Starlings; Group 3 consisted
of the aforementioned pair of Black-collared Starlings and the two by then
young (subadult) Bali Starlings.
The cumulative time spent on the ground per observation session was
determined for each sub-group (i.e. adult Black-collared Starlings; adult
Bali Starlings; young Bali Starlings). The result from the summation of the
individual ground stay durations of the sub-group, independent of whether
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999104" page_id="56269420"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
158
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.706845" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269420" page_num="158" year="" vol="">
SONTAG - TWO STURNIDS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997510875" page_id="56269420"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
one or both members of the sub-group were on the ground (i.e. if both
individuals were simultaneously on the ground, this period was taken into
account only once). This calculation was possible because all sub-groups
consisted of the same number of individuals (two). Correspondingly, one
ground visit was defined as the continuous presence of a sub-group on the
ground (again independent of whether one or both members of the sub-
group visited the ground). The respective number of observation sessions
is given in the tables and the text. The potential within-group-relations
between the ground stay values of both species were tested using Spearman's
coefficients of rank correlation. For all statistical analyses SPSS was used.
Total-time budgets of ground visits
As pointed out earlier (cf. Sontag, 2001a), in total. Black-collared
Starlings spent more time on the ground than Bali Starlings. However, this
difference was statistically significant only in half of the interspecific
comparisons. This may have been due partly to the difficult observation
conditions: free-running dogs were often present and disturbed observation
sessions had to be terminated and excluded from further investigation,
reducing the data set. This handicap becomes evident when reconsidering
the data of Groups 1 and 2. When both study groups are analyzed separately,
no statisical difference is detectable between the Black-collared Starlings
and the adult Bali Starlings in either group: the significance level is missed
by far in Group 1 (p = 0.245, Ni = N 2 = 20 sessions; U test, two-tailed),
whereas in Group 2 the difference is marginally short of being significant (p
= 0.065, Ni = N 2 = 12 sessions; U test, two-tailed). Pooling the data of both
groups, however, yields a statistically substantiated distinction between the
same individuals based on the same test algorithm (p = 0.034, Ni = N 2 = 32
sessions).
In order to roughly assess the potential importance of the ground section
in aviary use, the arithmetic means of the time spent on the ground (in percent
of the observation time) are given. The range was between 15.9% and 22.6%
in the Bali Starlings (adults: 19.6 +/-13.9 SD, 15.9 +/-10.0 SD; juveniles: 22.6
+/-16.9 SD, 19.0 +/-14.0 SD), and between 28.6% and 34.1% in the Black-
collared Starlings (28.6 +/-23.3 SD, 28.6 +/-18.4 SD, 34.1 +/-20.5 SD).
Correlations of cumulative ground stay time: yes or no? (Table 1)
Surprisingly, no negative correlation coefficient was ever calculated for
the cumulative ground stay times of the compared birds (including the pooled
data of different groups). Rather, only definite positive correlation
coefficients (r s = 0.150 to 0.608) occurred. Thus, apart from the respective
absolute total-time sums, this expresses the following tendency: the more
time the Black-collared Starlings spent on the ground, the more so did both
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.325395" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269421" page_num="159" year="" vol="">
SONTAG - TWO STURNIDS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999484" page_id="56269421"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
159
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.987238153846154" page_id="56269421"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
the adult and juvenile Bali Starlings (and vice versa ) in all comparisons.
Nonetheless, for most comparisons no significant correlation could be
confirmed (including the comparison between the adult and juvenile Bali
Starlings). A positive correlation coefficient for the time-sums was
statistically relevant only between the Black-collared Starlings and the
juvenile Bali Starlings, rather weakly in Group 3 (p &amp;lt; 0.05), and very strongly
in the lumped Groups 2 + 3 (p = 0.005), although the coefficient itself
remained rather low (r s = 0.557; theoretically 1 would be the highest possible
value) (Table 1). Why did a relationship exist just between the young Bali
Starlings and the members of the other species? Perhaps young birds are
perse more 'curious' than older individuals and their exploratory behaviour
was facilitated or even partially elicited by the - generally speaking - non-
hostile, different looking Black-collared Starlings.
Correlations of ground visit frequencies: yes or no? (Table 2)
Not a single case showed evidence of a significant rank correlation
between the ground visit frequencies of the compared group members,
including the combined data of different groups. Moreover, with one
exception, the correlation coefficients were very low (i.e. r s = &amp;lt; 0.16), and
in one case even marginally negative. The only comparison which may
suggest a (positive) trend was that of the Black-collared Starlings and adult
Bali Starlings in Group 2 (r s = 0.495, p = 0.102).
These results fit in with the fact that the individual ground visits of
the Black-collared Starlings were highly variable in duration, while those
of Leucopsar were short and rather constant (Sontag, 1992, 2001b).
Overt interspecific effects
Both sturnids were observed on the ground at the same time. Some
incidents suggest that one species occasionally caused the other to take flight
from the floor of the aviary. In one case, for example, a Bali Starling flew
up and called harshly; immediately, a Black-collared Starling that was also
on the aviary floor was seen flying off (Group 2). Shortly after the hatching
of the Bali Starlings, interspecific antagonistic interactions frequently took
place between the adult birds, and the Black-collared Starlings often withdrew
when confronted by their smaller sized counterparts. Unfortunately, I did
not make a separate note of which individuals were involved in these
interactions.
General discussion and conclusion
On one hand, starlings (Stumidae) represent a very social group of birds
that often form interspecific aggregations (cf. Feare &amp; Craig, 1998; also see
Introduction); on the other hand, severe intraspecific aggression has been
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994534" page_id="56269422"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
160
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.704464" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269422" page_num="160" year="" vol="">
SONTAG - TWO STURNIDS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993741926829269" page_id="56269422"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
reported in the Bali Starling (e.g, Hughes &amp; Turner, 1975: 116; Sieber, 1983;
Sontag, 2001b). An example of fatal aggression can be added from my own
experience with groups of another stumid, the Brahminy Starling. The birds
were kept in spacious indoor-outdoor aviaries measuring ca. 4.5m x 3m x
2m (approx. 14ft 6in x 9ft 9in x 6ft 6in) at the University of Mainz and in a
much larger enclosure (the inside of which was hexagonal and the outside
pentagonal with dense vegetation) at Mainz Municipal Park, Germany. At
least four of the deceased, crested, at least nearly adult individuals, died as
the result of intraspecific fighting. Attacks were initiated by short singing,
which was followed by a physical assault. An attacking individual selectively
pecked at the head of the conspecific. In at least one case, attacks continued
on the corpse. The case of S. pagodarum, which also belongs to the Sturnus-
Acridotheres complex, stresses the importance of comparative studies in
systematics and phylogeny among that group.
Based on the general behaviour patterns, the mixed species study groups
appeared to coexist without problems. These semi-qualitative observations
require a quantitative method to verify the general impression. Due to
methodological restrictions, only a few measures could be selected. Both
the cumulative ground use periods and ground visit frequencies seemed
appropriate for examining the potential connection between the behaviour
of the sub-groups. First, the cumulative and frequency measures never
provided the slightest evidence of any true trend in a sub-group to avoid
visiting and using the aviary floor when the coexisting sub-group(s) spent
more time at floor level (or went there more often; note the relations of the
individual ground visit durations to the total times on the ground, Sontag,
2001b). Second (and surprisingly), most comparisons also yielded no positive
connection between the sub-groups. Furthermore, the absence of detectable
behavioural relations was more prominent in the case of ground visit
frequencies. For this parameter, no statistically significant value occurred
at all; its correlation coefficients were much lower in almost all sub-group
comparisons than those of the cumulative ground stay times (see Tables 1 &amp;
2). In summary, the results support the idea that the sub-groups representing
different species obeyed their own activity patterns rather than the impact
of the other group members. Accordingly, the fact that both species are
closely related biased the interaction between these sturnids only minimally
if at all. This finding is important in the light of the strong intraspecific
aggression that often has been described in L. rothschildi (see above). The
results are also in accordance with literature reports that coexistence between
different sturnids is a widespread phenomenon (see above). This may be
due partly to similarities in the flocking tendency within this family and
similar roosting requirements and feeding niches (see Feare &amp; Craig, 1998).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.325403" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269423" page_num="161" year="" vol="">
SONTAG - TWO STURNIDS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998705" page_id="56269423"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
161
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.985626885714286" page_id="56269423"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
Based on the presented data, other interpretations cannot be excluded
per se. However, there is not sufficient evidence for an antithetic conclusion.
The exception was the juvenile Bali Starlings that tended to spend more
time on the ground, the more the Black-collared Starlings used that part of
the aviary, which remains to be explained. The juvenile birds might have
been attracted to inspect the ground segment of their enclosure by the
presence there of the similar-sized Black-collared Starlings. This potential
attraction may be related to the fact that the latter species is less conspicuous
on the ground than the Bali Starling.
Summary
Sturnids of the Sturnus-Acridotheres complex sensu lato (= S.-A.
complex) are social birds and often form mixed associations with members
of the same species complex under natural conditions. The Bali Starling,
however, is known for its severe intraspecific aggression. Examples of fatal
intraspecific aggression under aviary conditions have been reported, the
species involved being the Brahminy Starling, also a member of the S.-A.
complex.
Three groups of Bali Starlings and Black-collared Starlings, two
species which belong to the S.-A. complex, were kept together in a spacious,
richly structured aviary and coexisted without any major problems. Here,
cumulative ground stay time and the ground visit frequency were the
parameters selected to quantify habitat use, specifically whether the activity
of one species was influenced by the other. With two exceptions no
behavioural connections were evident between the compared group members
(not even between the adult and juvenile Bali Starlings). The two significant,
positive cases (Spearman's coefficients of rank correlation) were for the
cumulative ground stay times of the Black-collared Starlings and juvenile
Bali Starlings in Group 3 and Groups 2+3 (combined). Thus, both sturnids
generally tended to follow their own activity pattern.
In addition, the phylogenetic relations of both species and closely related
allies within the S.-A. complex are discussed including parasitological
findings from the literature. Different bobbing and nodding displays occur
in the group; the A. burmannicus, G . nigricollis and L. rothschildi patterns
are characterised. Specific behaviours of the Black-collared Starling are
presented, based partly on studies in the field.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.962744" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56269423" page_num="161" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9527995" page_id="56269423"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
I am grateful to Dr H. Hoi (Konrad Lorenz Institute for Comparative
Ethology, Vienna) for providing valuable comments on the manuscript. My
thanks also go to Dr M. Stachowitsch (Institute of Ecology and Conservation
Biology, University of Vienna) for substantially improving its English. I
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99853" page_id="56269424"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
162
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.6259255">
SONTAG - TWO STURNIDS
Table 1. Spearman's coefficients of rank correlation r s for total time spent
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.865229" page_id="56269424"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
on the ground per observation session by Black-collared Starlings and Bali
Starlings in different groups (including data combined groups). See methods.
N number of sessions, p probability of error. Significant probabilities in
bold type.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.930302642857143" page_id="56269424"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
Group 1
Black-collared vs ad. Bali
N=20
r s =0.150
p-0.527
Group 2
Black-collared vs ad. Bali
N=12
r s =0.455
p=0.138
Black-collared vs juv. Bali
N=12
r s =0.462
p=0.131
ad. Bali vs juv. Bali
N=12
r s =0.448
p=0.145
Groups 1+2
Black-collared vs ad. Bali
M=32
r s =0.263
p=0.146
Group 3
Black-collared vs juv. Bali
N=12
r s =0.608
p=0*036
Groups 2 +3
Black-collared vs juv. Bali
N=24
r s =0.557
p=0.005
Table 2. Spearman's coefficients of rank correlation r s for ground visit
frequencies of Black-collared Starlings and Bali Starlings in different groups
(including data combined groups). See methods. N number of sessions, p
probability of error.
Group 1
Black-collared vs ad. Bali
M=20
0,063
p-0.792
Group 2
Black-collared vs ad. Bali
N=12
r s =0.495
p=0.102
Black-collared vs juv. Bali
N-12
r s =0.011
p=0.974
ad. Bali vs juv. Bali
N=12
r s =0.039
p=0.905
Groups 1+2
Black-collared vs ad. Bali
N=32
r s =0.154
p=0.400
Group 3
Black-collared vs juv. Bali
N=12
r s =0.127
p=0.694
Groups 2 +3
Black-collared vs juv. Bali
N=24
r s =0.101
p=0.639
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.322151" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269425" page_num="163" year="" vol="">
SONTAG - TWO STURNIDS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.989347" page_id="56269425"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
163
</page>
<table confidence="0.9610605" page_id="56269425"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
Walter A Sontag , Jr.
Probably the first photo of a Vinous-breasted Starling 'nodding'. It was housed with
Black-collared Starlings in an aviary in Thailand
Walter A Sontag, Jr.
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.94664875" page_id="56269425"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
A Black-collared Starling in its 'bowing' position while its companion stands besides it.
am deeply indebted to A. Seidel for help with statistical and software matters.
Finally, I would like to express my gratitude to the Hon. Editor for his
constructive advice on the manuscript.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999542" page_id="56269426"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
164
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.889314" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269426" page_num="164" year="" vol="">
SONTAG - TWO STURNIDS
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.3923416">
All, S. &amp; Ripley, S. D. 1972. Handbook of the birds of India and Pakistan together with those
of Nepal, Sikkim, Bhutan and Ceylon. Vol. 5. Oxford University Press, Bombay, London &amp;
New York.
Ash, J. S. 1984. Bird observations on Bali. Bull Br. Orn. Club 104: 24-35.
Beecher, W. J. 1978. Feeding adaptations and evolution in the starlings. Bull Chicago Acad.
</reference>
<construct confidence="0.726506625" page_id="56269426"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
Scl 11: 269-298.
Feare, C. &amp; Craig, A. 1998. Starlings and mynas. Christopher/A &amp; C Black Ltd,London.
Harrison, C. J. O. 1963. The displays of some starlings (Sturnidae), and their taxonomic value.
Ardea 51: 44-52.
Hughes, A. &amp; Turner, C. G. 1975. Breeding and behaviour of Rothschild's Mynah Leucopsar
rothschildi at the National Zoological Park, Washington. Int. Zoo Yearb. 15: 116-120.
Lekagul, B. &amp; Round, P. D. 1991. A guide to the birds of Thailand. Saha Kam Bhaet Co. Ltd,
Bangkok.
</construct>
<bodyText confidence="0.9634084" page_id="56269426"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
Mey, E. 1989. Die auf Leucopsar und Gracupica (Sturnidae) parasitierenden Sturnidoecus-
Arten (Phthiraptera, Ischnocera). Mitt. Zool. Mus. Bed. 65 Suppl: Ann. Orn. 13: 153-165.
Sieber, J. 1978. Freilandbeobachtungen und Versuch einer Bestandsaufnahme des Bali-Stars
Leucopsar rothschildi. Journal fiir Ornithologie 119:102-106.
Sieber, J. 1978. Nestbau, Brut und Jungenaufzucht beim Balistar ( Leucopsar rothschildi). Zool.
Garten N.F. 53:281-289.
Sontag jr., W. A. 1992. On habitat utilization in various South Asian starlings (Sturnidae). Mitt.
Zool. Mus. Berk 68 Suppl: Ann. Orn. 16: 115-123.
Sontag jr., W. A. 1997. Attribution of various stumids (Sturnidae, Aves) to different habitats in
Thailand. Verhandlungen der Deutschen Zoologischen Gesellschaft 90.1: 390. Gustav Fischer,
Stuttgart, Jena, Liibeck &amp; Ulm.
Sontag jr., W. A. 2001a. Cues for specific ethological adaptations of the Rothschild's Mynah
( Leucopsar rothschildi ) to the natural environment. UFZ-Bericht 2/2001 ( Naturschutz und
Verhalten ): 39-44. Umweltforschungszentrum Leipzig-Halle, Leipzig.
Sontag jr., W. A. 2001b. Notes on behaviour and ecological requirements of Rothschild's Mynahs
Leucopsar rothschildi. Avicultural Magazine 107, 1:10-20.
van Balen, S. 1996. Anting behaviour in Bali Starlings. Kukila 8:146-147.
Wickler, W. 1961. Uber die Stammesgeschichte und den taxonomischen Wert einiger
Verhaltensweisen der Vogel. Z. Tierpsychol. 18: 320-342.
Wolters, H. E. 1975-1982. Die Vogelarten der Erde. Paul Parey, Hamburg &amp; Berlin.
Dr Walter A. Sontag , Jr. is a zoologist living in Vienna, Austria. He has
been working on sturnid biology for more than 25 years, often in cooperation
with the Konrad Lorenz Institute for Comparative Ethology in Vienna. He
can be contacted at Trubelgasse 19/24, AH030 Vienna , Austria or by e-
mail: seidel @ pflaphy.pph. univie.ac.at
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998923" page_id="56269427"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
165
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.963699" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269427" page_num="165" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE SCARLET IBIS Eudocimus ruber
AT BELO HORIZONTE ZOO, MINAS GERAIS, BRAZIL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.93369372972973" page_id="56269427"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
by Cristiaeo Schetini de Azevedo, Angela Bemadete Faggioli
and Joao Bosco Ferraz
Introduction
The red or reddish plumage of the Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber always
arouses interest. Owing to its scarcity in bird collections here though, it is
not well known (Antas, 1979). A bird characteristic of mangroves, it was
found along the Brazilian coast, from Santa Catarina in the south, to Amapa
in the north (Teixeira &amp; Best, 1981). However, despite suitable ecosystem
stretching along almost the entire Brazilian coast, there are no records of
Scarlet Ibis in the States of Espirito Santo and Rio Grande do Norte
(Marcondes- Machado &amp; Filho, 1989). In the past, this species nested in
Guanabara Bay, Rio de Janeiro, but due to hunting and habitat loss, the Ibis
were forced to occupy only the northern part of their original distribution.
Nowadays, the Scarlet Ibis is a threatened species in Brazil (IB AM A, 2002).
Reproduction is a rare event in captivity in Brazil. According to records
in the birds census, only Sao Paulo Zoo (SP Zoo) 1981, Porto Alegre Zoo
(RS Zoo) 1983 and Emilio Goeldi Museum (EGM) 1999 have achieved
reproduction in recent years, with one chick being reared in each institution.
Earlier, Rio de Janeiro Zoo (RJ Zoo) in the 1970s, obtained a good rate of
reproduction, with 15 chicks reared (Antas, 1979). The Scarlet Ibis is a
species that nests colonially, but is extremely territorial, defending its nest
from conspecifics. At the above institutions, the number of individuals kept
was not high, but sufficient (eight SP Zoo, 10 RS Zoo, 17 EGM and 30 RJ
Zoo) to trigger successful reproductive behaviour. Belo Horizonte Zoo (BH
Zoo) has three Scarlet Ibis, a male which has been here since 1985, and a
pair which arrived in 2000.
The first breeding of E, ruber at Belo Horizonte Zoo
The enclosure
The Scarlet Ibis are kept in a large, outdoor enclosure 590 sq m (approx.
6,350sq ft). It has a freshwater lake 113sq m x 20cm deep (approx. l,215sq
ft x Bin deep), one clay island 7sq m (approx.75sq ft) and a grassed area 470
sq m (approxl 5,000sq ft), planted with ornamental shrubs and trees, such as
Ficus sp. (Moraceae), Oreodoxo oleracea (Palmae), Sanchesia nobilis
(Acanthaceae), Eugenia sprengelii (Myrtaceae), Impatiens walleriana
(Balsaminaceae), Zantedeschia aethiopica (Araceae) and Cuphea gracilis
(Lyrthaceae). The enclosure is surrounded by a 1.4m (approx. 4ft 9in) high
fence.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999174" page_id="56269428"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
166
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.379135" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269428" page_num="166" year="" vol="">
DE AZEYEDO, FAGGIOLI &amp; JO AO - SCARLET IBIS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.971852" page_id="56269428"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
The enclosure contains three Scarlet Ibis, 10 Chilean Flamingos
Phoenicopterus chilensis, one Cayenne Ibis Mesembrinibis cayennensis and
a few White-faced Whistling Ducks Dendrocygna viduata and Fulvous
Whistling Ducks D. bicolor.
Diet
At Bela Horizonte Zoo the Scarlet Ibis are given minced (ground) meat,
minced fish and dog ration. They are fed 300g (lOOg per bird), once a day
at 14.00hrs (2.00pm).
The red colour of the Scarlet Ibis' plumage is an important factor in
inducing reproduction (Sick, 1997). The pigment cantaxanthin (carotenoid)
must be added to their diet to prevent the gradual loss of this colour, but
when this pigment is stored in large quantities in the liver, it can be very
harmful to the liver (Saad pers. comm.). At this zoo the ibises are given lOg
per day of a natural red pigment extracted from the urucum plant Bixa
orellana (Bixacea). This plant provides carotenoid pigments less harmful
than cantaxanthin.
The nest
As the enclosure is open at the top, the ibis are pinioned and therefore
nest on or near the ground, whereas in the wild, nests are built in treetops.
The nests are twig platforms (Sick, 1997), with dried and fresh leaves also
being used in their construction (Antas, 1979). The nests are, in general,
45cm (approx. 18in) in diameter (Olmos &amp; Silva, 2001).
At Bela Horizonte Zoo both the male and female participated in nest
construction (two nests in total) (see photos p.167). Generally, the male
carried twigs to the female, which effectively built the nest, though eventually,
he too was seen carrying twigs.
One of the nests was built 10cm (approx. 4in) above the ground and was
30cm wide x 16cm high (1ft wide x 6V4n high). The other nest was built
directly on the ground and was 29cm wide x 27cm high (approx. llVzin
wide x 10 ! /2in high). Both were built beneath a Sanchesia nobilis
(Acanthaceae) shrub. The nests were difficult to observe, being visible only
from a short distance. They were built 1.5m (almost 5ft) from each other.
The first nest was built in October 2001, and three eggs were laid in
November. The second nest was built in January 2002 and, again, three
eggs were laid. These disappeared from the nest in February, after which
two more eggs were laid that month. Following the disappearance of the
earlier eggs, a trap was set in the enclosure in the hope of capturing the cats,
opossums (Didelphidae) or lizards Tupinambis sp., which may have taken
the eggs.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.903562428571429" page_id="56269429"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
ff
DEAZEVEDO, FAGGIOLI &amp; JOAO - SCARLET IBIS 167
Cynthia Cipreste
The nest was a platform of twigs and dry leaves
Cynthia Cipreste
The chick was covered with black down, had a short, straight bill and its eyes had not
yet opened
</figure>
<page confidence="0.998421" page_id="56269430"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
168
</page>
<address confidence="0.230045">
DE AZEVEDO, FAGGIOLI &amp; JO AO - SCARLET IBIS
</address>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.455225">
Eggs
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999015228571429" page_id="56269430"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
The eggs are greenish with dark brown markings, the shade of green and
the distribution of the markings varying. The eggs are oval in shape, with
one end slightly narrower (see photos p.167). Clutch size varied from two
to three eggs, with three being more common. The eggs were laid usually at
two day intervals. To avoid the danger of desertion only one egg was
measured; it was 53mm x 34mm,
The young and parental behaviour
The incubation period varied from 24-25 days, as cited by Antas (1979)
and Sick (1997). It was not possible to determine the intervals between
hatches because only one egg hatched in each clutch, producing two nestlings.
These had black down, straight short bills, black at the tip and base, with a
median white-reddish stripe and bluish edges and the eyes were closed,
characteristic of altricial birds (Pough et al. 1993) (see photo p. 16&amp;apos;/),
Outside the breeding period, the Scarlet Ibis is a shy bird. Flight is the
main defence. There is a pecking order within the colony. During the
breeding season, the behaviour changes and nests are defended against other
ibis and anyone who disturbs the nest site. The bill is effectively used in a
pincer movement and the nest is abandoned only as the last resort, the bird
remaining nearby and returning as soon as possible. After the chicks have
hatched, the protective instinct becomes even stronger and some birds will
attempt to remain on the nest even when handled (Antas, 1979). .
At BH Zoo, nest protection was undertaken mainly by the female. Antas
(1979) described this behaviour as having been undertaken by the male,
which when the female "squeaked", immediately returned and defended the
chick. The opposite behaviour was observed here. When the female began
to "squeak", the male ran away from the nest site, leaving the chick and
female alone. The female abandoned the nest only when touched by a keeper.
By two weeks old, the young had already moved off the nest and were
hiding among the vegetation, where they remained immobile. The young -
were fed by regurgitation and parental care continued for 40 days in the
case of the first chick and for 44 days in the case of the second, after which
the young began to feed alone and to explore the enclosure.
The immature ibis (at one month old) is blackish, except for the underparts
and rump which are white. The bill is now long and curved, just like that of
the adult.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.742475">
Discussion
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.96275" page_id="56269430"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
At BH Zoo the reproductive period extended from October Fehru.ary
and not April-July as described by del Hoyo et al (1991). Although Scarlet
Ibis breed in large colonies, the number of individuals does not seem to be a
</bodyText>
<address confidence="0.313544">
DE AZEVEDO, FAGGIOLI &amp; JO AO - SCARLET IBIS
</address>
<page confidence="0.999379" page_id="56269431"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
169
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998202529411765" page_id="56269431"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
limiting factor, as here at Belo Horizonte we had only two males and one
female. Neither did the plumage colour seem to be a limiting factor to
reproduction, as the Belo Horizonte birds lack bright red plumage and instead
are a faded pinkish colour.
According to del Hoyo et al. (1991), in the tropics the main factor that
induces nesting is not well understood, but it is usually related to hydrological
patterns (availability of food for the development of the chicks) and varies
between the different species. At BH Zoo, reproduction occurred in the
rainy season (September-May), which concurs with del Hoyo et al. (1991).
The zoo's breeding pair laid three clutches during the one reproductive
period. This number of clutches was also cited by Antas (1979) for captive
birds, and by Olmos &amp; Silva (2001) for wild birds.
It is hoped that, in spite of the initial failures, breeding in captivity can
play an important role in the recovery of this species (del Hoyo et al. 1991).
The reproduction in captivity of threatened species can provide an efficient
tool for conservation projects, for educational programmes and for collecting
biological data.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.949315" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269431" page_num="169" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.969355952380952">
Antas, R T. Z. 1979. Breeding the Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber at the Rio de Janeiro Zoo.
International Zoo Yearbook 19:135-139.
del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A. &amp; Sargatal, J. A. (eds.) 1991. Handbook of the Birds of the World Vol.l
(pp.472-491). Lynx Edicions, Barcelona, Spain.
IBAMA. 2002. Lista oficial de fauna ameagada de extingdo. Online at:http://www.ibama.gov.br
(accessed 12.07.02).
Marcondes-Machado, L. 0. &amp; Filho, E. L. A. 1989. Nota sobre a presenca dos guaras, Eudocimus
ruber (Linne, 1758) (Threskiomithidae, Aves), no litoral de Sao Paulo: alerta para a sua protegao.
Ciencia e Cultura 41,2:1213-1214.
Olmos, F. &amp; Silva, R. S. E. 2001. Breeding biology and nest site characteristics of the Scarlet
Ibis in southeastern Brazil. Waterbirds 24,1:58-67.
Pough, F. H., Heiser, J. B. &amp; McFarland, W. N. 1993. A vida dos vertebrados (p.839). Atheneu,
Sao Paulo.
Sick, H. 1997. Ornitologia Brasileira (p.912). Nova Fronteira, Rio de Janeiro.
Teixeira, D. M. &amp; Best, R. C. 1981. Adendas a ornitologia do Territorio Federal do Amapa.
Boletim do Museu Paraense Emilio Goeldi. Zoologia 104:1-25.
Cristiano Schetini de Azevedo, Angela Bernadete Faggioli and Joao
Bosco Ferraz, Bird Department, Fundaqdo Zoo-Botanica de Belo
Horizonte, Av. Otacilio Negrdo de Lima, 8000 Pampulha, CEP 31365-
450, Belo Horizonte, Brazil. Tel:(55) 3F277-7979/Fax: (55)31-277-7974/
E-mail: fzbzoo @pbh. gov. br and cristianoroxette @yahoo, com
</reference>
<page confidence="0.995782" page_id="56269432"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
170
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9973165" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269432" page_num="170" year="" vol="">
FOURTEENTH HARPY EAGLE CHICK
AT NUREMBERG ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989497833333333" page_id="56269432"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
At Nuremberg Zoo, Germany, the fourteenth Harpy Eagle Harpia harpyja
has been hatched, 10 (8.2) of which have been reared to independence.
Back in 1980, Nuremberg Zoo received a pair of Harpy Eagles from a
private falconry collection. The first chick hatched in 1984, but died shortly
afterwards. The male chick hatched in July 1986 was the first to be
successfully reared by its parents and the following year went to Antwerp
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.621132">
Copyright Chris Brack
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97472375" page_id="56269432"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
The photo above, taken August 8th 2002, shows the female Harpy Eagle hatched at
Nuremberg Zoo in July 1992 and hand-reared there, acting as foster-mother to the
chick hatched earlier in 2002
Zoo, Belgium. The parents reared their young only in the years 1986-1987;
other chicks have been hand-reared. Birds reared at Nuremberg Zoo have
also gone to Wuppertal, Dortmund, Mallorca (the former breeding station
belonging to Vogelpark Walsrode), Prague,&amp;apos;Tierpark Berlin and Sao Paulo
Zoo.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.944026" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269433" page_num="171" year="" vol="">
HARPY EAGLE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998566" page_id="56269433"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
171
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9984726" page_id="56269433"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
It was at Tier park Berlin that the first captive breeding occurred in 1981,
altogether four young were reared up until 1986, after which further breeding
attempts were unsuccessful In 1997, following an exchange of partners
between two pairs in the collection, the original breeding male was killed
by the female.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.493663">
Copyright Chris Brack
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.908942769230769" page_id="56269433"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
Keeper Martin Gelseedorfer feeding the chick while its foster-mother looks on. The
chick received two feeds a day, one given by Martin in the morning, who in the
afternoon fed the female, which then passed the food to the chick
As well as at Tierpark Berlin and Nuremberg, the Harpy Eagle has been
bred at Los Angeles, San Diego, the Peregrine Fund's World Center for
Birds of Prey (Boise, Idaho, USA) and in Panama at the Neotropical Raptor
Center.
At San Diego Zoo, at least one egg has been laid every year for the past
eight years, and two of the birds reared there have been released back into
the wild. At Boise, two females laid seven eggs, six of which were fertile
and three of which hatched, from which two young survived in 2001. Roberto
Ascerado, Belo Horizonte, Brazil, is also said to be breeding Harpy Eagles,
but no details are available.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997563" page_id="56269434"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
172
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9355" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269434" page_num="172" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE YELLOW-BREASTED MAGPIE
</sectionHeader>
<figure confidence="0.291955666666667" page_id="56269434"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
Cissa hypoleuca
by Neil Owen
Introduction
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.980603545454546" page_id="56269434"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
The genus Cissa can be somewhat confusing, as various authorities have
over the years recognised from two (King, Dickinson &amp; Woodcock, 1975)
to six species (Delacour, 1929). More recent works (Goodwin, 1986 and
Madge &amp; Bum, 1999) consider that three is the most likely number.
Description
The Yellow-breasted or Eastern Green Magpie is a stocky bird measuring
approximately 35cm (14in) long including the tail. Much of the plumage is
green, including the tail, which has the outer feathers edged with black and
white. The bill and legs are bright coral red, the toes are pink and the eyes
are dark brown, surrounded by a narrow red orbital ring. There is a black
mask from the base of the bill passing above and below the eyes to the nape.
The crown and nape are green and these feathers are rather long and can be
raised to form a crest when the bird is excited. The wing feathers are rich
chestnut-brown with the secondary feathers tipped with pale green.
As with the other green magpies Cissa spp., the plumage can fade from
a vivid pea green to a paler green, turquoise or even a very pale blue. The
reasons for this are not totally clear, although it seems likely that the plumage
fades because the birds are kept in bright sunlight for long periods and are
unable to hide in thick undergrowth. It may also be related to their diet. In
the wild green magpies have been seen feeding on bright green mantids,
crickets and stick insects (A. Owen pers. obs.).
Distribution
The Yellow breasted Magpie is found in tropical and subtropical
evergreen hill and lowland forest, and at lower elevations its range often
meets that of C. chinensis . The Yellow-breasted species is found in southern
China and is widespread through Vietnam from south Tonkin to Cochinchina
and west into parts of Laos and south-east Thailand, There are also isolated
populations on Hainan Island and the Yao Shan Hills of Guangxi in China.
Five subspecies are recognised (Madge &amp; Bum, 1999).
Voice
This species has a wide range of calls, some typically harsh and scolding
alarm calls similar to those of the European Magpie Pica pica , as well as
others which are quite musical and unusual. Both sexes whistle quite loudly,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.49185" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269435" page_num="173" year="" vol="">
OWEN - YELLOW-BREASTED MAGPIE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999433" page_id="56269435"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
173
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9736839" page_id="56269435"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
particularly in the morning and also make a strange sound which is very
similar to the "meeow" sound made by a cat. This sound is usually made by
two birds calling together. They sing out in the open and when hidden in
deep cover.
Accommodation
My birds are housed in an aviary measuring approximately 6m long x
2.5m wide x 2m high (20ft long x 8ft wide x 6ft 6in high). This has a
wooden shelter attached in which the birds are fed and in which they can be
shut in if the weather in the winter is severe. The back and part of the sides
of the aviary have wooden lapped fence panels attached to provide privacy
and some protection from strong winds. The roof is covered with corrugated
Perspex (Plexiglas) to give protection from the elements and to prevent
possible contamination from wild birds. Part of the roof is painted green
and a section is covered with dark coloured garden mesh in an attempt to
shield the birds from direct sunlight, which could affect the colour of their
plumage. The aviary is planted with various shrubs such as laurels, clematis,
ivy and a small conifer. There are several rotten logs on the aviary floor,
where the birds spend a lot of time. The earth floor is covered with a thick
layer of leaf litter, which is replenished regularly. A small concrete pond is
used by the birds for bathing.
Diet
The basic diet consists of a universal mixture to which is added soaked
mynah pellets, mashed hard-boiled egg, minced (ground) lean beef and
various chopped fruits, although the latter are not very popular. A day-old
chick, with the yolk sac removed, is given most days and occasionally a
small mouse. A few mealworms or crickets are scattered around the aviary
once a day. There is little doubt that the birds are mainly carnivorous, as the
meat and chicks are always favourite items. Various insects and earthworms
are found in the aviary and the birds become very excited if a small snail is
caught.
Behaviour
Although there are times when they hide in the undergrowth, the birds
are active a lot of the day and can often be seen sifting through the leaf litter,
bathing or flying back and forth the length of the aviary. They are very
inquisitive and usually come to investigate anything new, such as a new
perch or a rotten log that I have turned over. Various objects such as stones
are carried about and are often found in the food pots. One hot day I tipped
a jar of ants and their eggs into the aviary and both birds came down to
investigate, eating some of the eggs, but also spreading some through their
plumage in typical Jay-like anting behaviour.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99748" page_id="56269436"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
174
</page>
<figure confidence="0.7529052" page_id="56269436"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
OWEN - YELLOW-BREASTED MAGPIE
Andrew Owen
Adult Yellow-breasted Magpie Cissa hypoleuca
(see footnote p.177)
Breeding
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.9990259" page_id="56269436"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
In the summer of 2000 I bought from a private aviculturist what I hoped
was a pair of these birds. One was slightly larger and generally bolder than
the other, this I took to be the male. After coming through a heavy moult in
October the birds were in immaculate condition, although the smaller one
was not such a vibrant green as its mate. They preferred to roost outside,
but on very cold nights I shut them inside the shelter. In late January 2001
we had a few days which although cold were very bright and sunny and the
male was seen offering mealworms to the female. She did not appear
interested and as the male then began chasing her around the aviary while
whistling loudly, I decided to move him to another aviary for a while. As
soon as they were parted both birds began calling to each other but I decided
to keep the male separate for a week, in the hope that he might calm down.
When the pair was reunited the male was less boisterous and the pair seemed
more compatible.
In early March I provided several potential nest sites, including a wooden
platform high up in the aviary and hidden by conifer branches, a wire basket
fixed in a laurel bush and a 30cm (lOin) wicker basket placed low down in
a small conifer tree. As the weather warmed up both birds became more
vocal; in fact the singing was so loud and so similar that I thought I might
have two males. However, the larger bird once again offered mealworms to
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.423346" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269437" page_num="175" year="" vol="">
OWEN - YELLOW-BREASTED MAGPIE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.850577" page_id="56269437"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
175
</page>
<figure confidence="0.9759735" page_id="56269437"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
Andrew Owen
Aged 18 days
Andrew Owen
Aged one month
</figure>
<page confidence="0.999338" page_id="56269438"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
176
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.858659" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269438" page_num="176" year="" vol="">
OWEN - YELLOW-BREASTED MAGPIE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999201880952381" page_id="56269438"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
the smaller bird and this time they were accepted.
I began offering more varied livefood including not only mealworms
but crickets, waxmoth larvae, locusts, and occasionally a 'fuzzy' mouse (a
young mouse with soft velvety fur). I also scattered around the aviary floor
twigs of various sizes and some coconut fibre. The female was later seen
carrying coconut fibre but both birds were getting more secretive and
observing them was not easy.
One morning when I was cleaning the pond, I had a look in the conifer
where the birds were spending a lot of time, and was delighted to see a
completed nest in the wicker basket. It seemed to be made mostly from
coconut fibres with a few dried leaves woven into it. On May 10th I went in
to feed the birds and as both were in the shelter, I was able to look in the nest
which now contained two eggs, these were very pale blue with brown
speckles at the thick end.
The male was spending a lot of time in the shelter and I assumed and
hoped that the female was sitting, but observations were difficult as there
was more vegetation at this time of the year. On May 28th both birds were
away from the nest calling in alarm. I checked the nest and was relieved to
see that it now contained four eggs. The female went back as soon as I left
the aviary. At the morning feeding time on June 3rd both birds were again
briefly shut inside the shelter. I checked the nest and was delighted to see a
newly hatched chick. I swiftly left and returned with a handful of newly
sloughed mealworms, small waxmoth larvae and small crickets, these having
been lightly dusted with a 'stress' vitamin and mineral supplement.
Two days later a second chick hatched. I watched the female fly down
to bathe and the male go straight to the nest. Due to the thick vegetation it
was difficult to see if he was feeding the chicks or brooding them, but he
seemed to stay for a long time. As some corvids are known to eat their
young, I was concerned. However, I thought it best to keep disturbance
down to a minimum.
On June 9th I found an egg on the floor of the shelter (presumably
removed from the nest by one of the birds). This was found to be infertile.
It measured 31.6mm x 22.9mm. The adults were taking mainly waxmoth
larvae and 'fuzzy' mice but not in the huge amounts I had anticipated, in
fact there was often livefood from the previous day left in the pots. While
the adults were away feeding on June 12th, the nest was checked and still
contained two chicks which by then were covered in pin feathers. The fourth
egg had disappeared. I was by then giving six 'fuzzy' mice, one chopped
day-old chick and a few waxmoth larvae, hardly anything else was being
eaten. I was unable to check the nest for the next week as both adults had
become aggressive and attacked me whenever I entered the aviary.
On June 22nd the adults seemed quieter and I was able to approach
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.491868" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269439" page_num="177" year="" vol="">
OWEN - YELLOW-BREASTED MAGPIE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998914" page_id="56269439"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
177
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999115" page_id="56269439"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
close enough to see the chicks, which by then almost filled the nest. Both
were fully feathered. They were blue with dark brown wings and had the
distinctive black eye stripe. The preferred food remained 'fuzzy 5 mice (10
a day) and waxmoth larvae. Locusts and crickets were ignored but small
pieces of day-old chick were taken to the nest.
Both chicks left the nest on June 28th and were well cared for by their
parents and were first seen feeding themselves four weeks after leaving the
nest. Two months later they were removed to their own aviary. The adults
did not attempt to re-nest and soon afterwards went into a moult.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.950014" genericHeader="references" page_id="56269439" page_num="177" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.815425333333333">
Delacour, J. 1929. Revision du Genre Cissa. L'Oiseau 10:1-12 (cited in Madge and Bum,
1999).
King, B. K, Dickinson, E. C. and Woodcock, M. W. 1975. A Field Guide to the Birds of South-
East Asia. Collins, London.
Goodwin, D. 1986. Crows of the World. British Museum (Natural History), London.
Madge, S. and Bum, H. 1999. Crows and Jays. Christopher Helm/A &amp; C Black, London.
</reference>
<bodyText confidence="0.962429956521739" page_id="56269439"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
Neil Owen, who lives in Carmarthenshire, Wales, is interested to hear
from anyone in the UK who keeps the Yellow-breasted Magpie. His telephone
number is: 01558 668336.
As described above, the Yellow-breasted Magpie Cissa hypoleuca , has
been bred by Neil Owen. This is probably the first successful breeding of
this species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who knows of a previous
breeding is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
Footnote
Surprised that the bird in the photo has a green rather than a yellowish breast, I consulted
Crows &amp; Jays by Madge and Burn (Christopher Helm/A &amp; C Black, 1999) and decided that it
must belong to one of the two isolated Chinese subspecies, probably C. h. jini, described as:
"relatively longer-tailed and greener below than other races. " Though 1 must say that the
example depicted on Plate I6(4b) has a paler green breast than the bird in the photo.
Later, when doubts were expressed over the identity of the bird in the photo and Roland
Cristo was quoted as having said, it is "definitely chinensis " (the Green Magpie or Hunting
Cissa), I contacted Neil Owen and asked if he had any photos in which the tertiais (inner
secondaries) can clearly be seen?
He has provided me with photos which show that the tertiais are broadly tipped light green
(without any black or white markings) a diagnostic feature which distinguishes C. hypoleuca
from C. chinensis. The two-colour pattern on the tertiais and the length of the tail of the bird
in the photo also seem to rule out C. thalassina (the Short-tailed Magpie), sometimes considered
conspecific with the Yellow-breasted, which Madge and Burn treat as a separate species, on
account of the latter&amp;apos;s "striking vocal differences" - Ed.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998872" page_id="56269440"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
178
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995714" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269440" page_num="178" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL SOCIETY TO HELP FUND FURTHER
RESEARCH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996889" page_id="56269440"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
Having recently adopted a pair of Bushy-crested Hornbills Anorrhinus
galeritus living in the wild in Thailand (see Avicultural Magazine 108,2:89
(2002)) as part of its policy of becoming more actively involved in
conservation and research, the Avicultural Society has now taken the decision
to help fund a research project on the Yellow-throated Laughingthrush
Garrulax galbanus in China. It is a project that is already well established
and has the full support of the Chinese Government, local forestry authorities
and the local community.
In European collections since the late 1980s there have been several
apparently self-sustaining populations of the Yellow-throated Laughing-
thrush. It is far from clear, however, how these birds were imported and
from where. An exhaustive search of customs documents relating to birds
exported from China failed to find any records of this species.
In the early 1990s, when concern grew as to the status of the two
subspecies which occur on mainland China - G. g. courtoisi and G. g.
simaoensis - the Munich-based German conservation organisation ZGAP,
provided grants to Chinese colleagues to investigate the status of the wild
populations of these two Chinese forms. It required successive field surveys
over a seven year period though before, in the 2000 breeding season, G. g.
courtoisi was finally rediscovered in the wild in Wuyuan; G. g. simaoensis
has yet to be rediscovered.
During field observations in 2000, a total of 80-90 birds were counted,
in two breeding flocks approximately 40km (about 25 miles) apart. Although
researchers obtained a rudimentary understanding of the breeding biology
and habitat selection of the birds, all that could be said about their status
was that they appeared to be extremely rare. However, following field work
in 2001, when two more breeding sites were found, a more integrated picture
emerged, making it possible to outline the breeding range and status of G. g.
courtoisi in Wuyuan.
They breed in flocks, close to rivers. All four breeding flocks found so
far have been around villages, very close to villagers' houses, and the 20 or
more nests found have all been in the canopy of mature trees. The cinnamon
trees are traditionally protected by the villagers at these sites and with their
cooperation, the local forest office has declared the breeding sites mini-
protected areas.
From the limited data available at present, it is known there are 150-160
G. g. courtoisi living in one small area. In accordance with the latest IUCN
Red List Criteria 2000, on this evidence this subspecies qualifies as
Endangered or quite possibly even Critically Endangered, taking account of
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.987647" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269441" page_num="179" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL SOCIETY RESEARCH FUNDING
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99908" page_id="56269441"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
179
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997123153846154" page_id="56269441"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
its presumed population size and range. Of the four breeding sites found,
none is larger than 10 hectares (approx. 25 acres), which means that a very
small area is supporting this breeding population.
Much remains to be learnt about G. g. courtoisi, for example, we know
nothing about where the birds go and what they do during the non-breeding
season. Shortly after the young are able to fly, all the birds both young and
adult, disappear into the hills.
Finding the wintering place/places of G. g. courtoisi is an important
unresolved mystery. The quickest way to achieve this may be to fit some of
the birds with tiny radio transmitters, and this could be one of the things for
which the funding is used.
Prof. He Fen-qi, Academia Sinica, Beijing, is happy for the society to
publish in the magazine material and photographs from the project.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.816439" page_id="56269441"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.770528" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56269441" page_num="179" year="" vol="">
SUCCESSFUL SCANDINAVIAN SYMPOSIUM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.992663083333334" page_id="56269441"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
A symposium on the Omei Shan Liocichla Liocichla omeiensis, attended
by keepers from Denmark and Sweden, was held August 3rd 2002, at
Copenhagen ZoO, Denmark, reports John Sidor.
As a European Studbook has recently been established for this species,
it was felt there was the need to attempt to find answers to a number of
questions. How will it work? How can private keepers participate? Howto
adapt to the ways of management of non-commercial zoos? And many
other questions.
Flemming Nielsen of Copenhagen Zoo, gave a very interesting talk about
studbook keeping and related issues, and there were constructive discussions,
which produced helpful suggestions and initiatives.
The main outcome was:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.453073" page_id="56269441"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
1. All keepers agreed to follow the recommendations of the Studbook
</listItem>
<reference confidence="0.8361925">
Keeper (Nigel Hewston, UK (e-mail:nigelhewston@supanet.com)).
2. Work towards obtaining official import/export permits from/to
Sweden and the UK.
3. Set-up a website for the exchange of information.
4. Plan an international meeting in 2003, to which German and British
ESB (European Studbook) members should also be invited.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.995561" page_id="56269442"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
180
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99837" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269442" page_num="180" year="" vol="">
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996461153846154" page_id="56269442"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
Derek Goodwin writes: I read with great pleasure Philip Schofield's
interesting and informative article on the Mandarin Duck Aix galericulata
(Vol.108, No.2, pp.52-58 (2002)) and fully agree with what I infer are his
implied criticisms of the present laws (here in the UK), especially as they
affect introduced species and aviculture.
I should like to comment further on some of the subjects in his article.
Introduced species
The attitude that is now considered officially correct and endorsed by
the law is that these should be considered unwanted "aliens" (note the
pejorative word "alien"). It is now illegal to liberate any more, unless that
is they are of use for blood sports.
Thus any augmentation of our tiny populations of the Golden and Amherst
Pheasants Chrysolophus pictus and C. amherstiae is a criminal offence. Both
are uniquely beautiful, with limited world ranges, in which both would seem
doubtfully secure and which (Lever, 1987) appear not to have been
successfully naturalised anywhere else in the world except in Britain, in
spite of many attempts to do so. Yet the Common Pheasant Phasianus
colchicus which has an enormous natural range and has been successfully
introduced into the USA, New Zealand, Hawaii and much of Europe, may
be (and is) yearly liberated in thousands here in Britain, even in places still
inhabited by the decreasing Black Grouse Tetrao tetrix with which it may
compete (Lever, 1977 &amp; 1987; pers. obs.).
Obviously the pleasure of those who enjoy shooting beautiful birds for
sport carries more weight with those in authority than does that of those
who enjoy watching living birds. Ornithological writers and presenters of
TV programmes on birds in recent decades seem to have been mostly in
favour of the shooting of gamebirds and waterfowl for sport, though fiercely
condemming poor people in other countries who kill songbirds for food or
kill birds of prey that take their chickens. Though I and others recently had
a delightful surprise when, on TV, Bill Oddie couragerously stated his
disagreement with the Ruddy Duck Oxyura jamaicensis massacre now (I
write in July 2002) in progress here in the UK.
Usually, any concern for the status of introduced species is at least
implicitly condemmed and their destruction heartily approved. See, for
example, the comments on the Ruddy Duck and the Golden and Amherst
Pheasants in The State of the Nation's Birds (Mead, 2000). A book well
worth reading even if (or perhaps especially if?) one finds, as I did, that one
strongly opposes some of the author's opinions.
Yet, although the introduction of any species, however beautiful,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.994932" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269443" page_num="181" year="" vol="">
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998449" page_id="56269443"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
181
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997906904761905" page_id="56269443"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
interesting, and in need of 'a second home' it may be for conservation reasons,
is forbidden in case it might do harm, the reintroduction of the White-tailed
Sea Eagle Haliaeetus albicilla, Red Kite Milvus rnilvus and Goshawk
Accipiter gentilis has been officially brought about - in the case of the first
two and apparently with official connivance in the case of the third species
- despite the fact that when and where they were abundant they were usually
considered harmful.
It seems at least probable that the absence or almost complete absence
of the Goshawk in Britain for the past 150 years or more was what enabled
the Mandarin Duck and the Golden and Amherst Pheasants to become
established (the pheasants only in small numbers in a very few places) in
Britain and its presence part or whole of the reason for the failure of attempts
to establish them elsewhere in Europe.
Ironically it appears (Shurtleff and Savage, 1996) that the only country
other than England, in which the Mandarin Duck has been successfully
naturalised is the USA. The one country where there would seem to have
been justifiable objections to its being released for fear that it might compete
with the Wood or Carolina Duck A. sponsa, its only close relative and one
with similar habitat requirements. Fortunately it does not, so far, seem to
have had any adverse effects on the Wood Duck.
Aviculturists should, I believe do all they can to maintain viable captive
stocks of these three species. Despite official hostility now, things might
well improve. I know that many people are very much against the present
attempt to exterminate the Ruddy Duck in Britain, for example. They would,
I think, be even more appalled if, as I fear is likely to happen, the appetite
for killing beautiful living birds grows once the Ruddy Ducks have all been
killed, and those involved should decide that the Mandarin Duck must go
too.
However, things may change in the future and if aviculturists have
managed to preserve viable stocks of Golden and Amherst Pheasants which
have not been bred, deliberately or through default, for larger size or physical
deformities, at some future date they might be able to supply birds to augment
any dwindling stocks of already naturalised birds and/or start new
populations.
Opponents of aviculture often state that only wild-caught birds (or other
animals) can successfully establish themselves in a feral state. This is not
true. Admittedly the many modern grossly deformed show specimens of
many breeds of pigeons, canaries, chickens, ducks (of both Mallard Anas
platyrhynchos and Muscovy Cairina moschata origin) cannot long survive
in a truly feral state and the same is true of domestic mammals. We know,
however, that in many parts of the world species that have been domesticated
for hundreds or even thousands of years - dogs, horses, camels, goats,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998646" page_id="56269444"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
182
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998913" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269444" page_num="182" year="" vol="">
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986272414634147" page_id="56269444"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
donkeys, water buffaloes, chickens, pigeons Columba livia - have, when
given the chance, successfully become naturalised, often in spite of man's
heavy predation of them.
As I have pointed out in several letters and articles sent to official and
semi-official organisations, it is not true that all introduced life forms have
proved harmful to native bird species, many introduced plants and trees
have provided new supplies of food for many native species. Also that self-
introduced 'new' species, usually welcomed with protective legislation, are
more likely to pose a threat to native birds than non-predating exotic species.
I have also protested against the, now well underway, official plans to
either exterminate Britain's Ruddy Ducks or to reduce them to a pitiable
constantly persecuted remnant within the next 10 years. Not surprisingly
only two of these communications have been published, both in British Birds ,
one (Goodwin, 1992) was reduced by about 80% but the other (Goodwin,
2000) which was in reponse to a very anti-aliens article (Bibby, 2000) with
only about 10% of the orginal deleted. The same issue of British Birds
which contained my letter on the subject contained another shorter but very
readable and witty letter of protest (Lawson, 2000). It also contained a
letter from the RSPB's Director of Conservation (Avery, 2000) in which it
was suggested that legislation should be passed so that the costs of
exterminating alien species should be borne by those who released or lost
them.
It would, I suggest, be more justifiable if those responsible for
reintroducing the Goshawk, White-tailed Sea Eagle, even perhaps the Red
Kite, should have to pay for all the free range poultry and pigeons killed,
and other damage done by these birds. What about payments to the
descendants of those who enriched our lives by successfully introducing the
Mandarin Duck and, if modern DNA and other magical-seeming scientific
studies could identify them, the descendants of those who first brought the
domesticated Red Junglefowl Gallus gallus (the chicken) to Britain and
those who first introduced here and elsewhere that glorious bird the Blue or
Indian Peafowl Pavo cristatusl
I recall that a line in one of Frank Finn's verses, published long ago in
the Avicultural Magazine , ended:
"But I the Peacock lord it yet
Lest Man God's glory shall forget!"
Even those like myself, who do not believe in the existence of a single,
all-powerful God as described by the main monotheistic religions, cannot
and I think should not, look at the "Peacock in his pride" without a feeling
of awe, delight and gratitude to those who disseminated this bird so widely
throughout the world, albeit in a semi-domesticated state.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99493" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269445" page_num="183" year="" vol="">
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999129" page_id="56269445"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
183
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.995194976190476" page_id="56269445"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
Law and aviculture
There can be no doubt that the law in Britain (and also in many other
countries, especially Australia and the USA), has been in the main hostile to
those aviculturists who are ordinary in the sense of not being government
officials or very rich and very influential. In the past, as now, legitimate
sport (shooting gamebirds and waterfowl primarily for pleasure) and those
forms of bird-keeping primarily indulged in by the rich and powerful (though
not always only by them), such as the keeping of waterfowl collections and
falconry, were looked upon very much more favourably by the law than the
keeping of other birds by those wishing to study them or keep them as pets.
Peter Scott's (1936 &amp; 1939) early and still very evocative books made it
clear that the capture of wild geese to keep them alive was as legal as the
shooting of them.
I do not know what precisely is the law regarding birds of prey but
certainly whereas the aviculturist whether for pleasure or study (or both
combined) may not release any exotic species, not even the provenly
harmless, beautiful and long-established Mandarin Duck, both commercial
organisations that show free-flying birds of prey, both British and exotic, to
paying visitors and individual falconers, often with such exotics as the Harris
Hawk Parabuteo unicinctus on fist, are permitted to allow their birds to fly
free.
Admittedly, though not always realised by admiring members of the
general public, the raptors are not in either case set at liberty unless they are
thought (not always correctly) to be in such a state of hunger that they will
return to the lure when their owners wish them to. However they are not
always hungry enough. I have seen an obviously gone wild Lanner Falcon
Falco biarmicus near Chichester, a neighbour of mine once saw a Harris
Hawk in his garden, and Newton's 1986 monograph on the Sparrowhawk
Accipiter nisus has a photo of an escaped Goshawk, still with the remains of
the jesses on her legs successfully breeding in the wild.
Those interested in bird behaviour will know the enormous amount of
scientific information that has been amassed when and where it was legal
for private individuals to keep exotic (and native) species free-flying. Such
famous names as Delacour, Finn, Heinroth, Lorenz and Nicolai come
immediately to mind, but regular readers of the Avicultural Magazine ,
especially those who have (like me) been lucky enough to have had access
to pre-1940 and pre-1914 issues, will know that many less well known
aviculturists also contributed much to our knowledge of bird behaviour. It
has always seemed to me both unfair and not in the best interests of acquiring
knowledge of bird behaviour or physiology when the birds are not under
stress, that even, or perhaps especially, those countries with the most
restrictive anti-avicultural laws for the ordinary person behave very
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999555" page_id="56269446"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
184
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998896" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269446" page_num="184" year="" vol="">
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.992958414634146" page_id="56269446"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
differently towards those in high positions in official or quasi-official
organisations - conservational (sic), scholastic, medicinal, or in some cases
merely commercial.
Such people, often with little real interest in, and certainly no compassion
for or sympathy with birds are given carte hlache to capture, experiment
with or kill virtually unlimited numbers, even of rare or localised species.
Sometimes, when people with real knowledge of birds have been
involved, for example Oscar Heinroth, Jurgen Nicolai and the late and much
missed Luis Baptiste, a great deal of information has resulted. In some
other instances, however, little or nothing of any real use or interest has
resulted from great numbers of birds having been cruelly treated or killed.
I will not give examples for fear of upsetting sensitive readers. Suffice
to say that I have seen some grotty bird dealers' establishments both abroad
and in England but I have never seen birds, other than domestic poultry,
kept in worse conditions than I have seen in some official and prestigious
organisations in Britain, the USA and Australia. In these cases poverty
could not be pleaded as an excuse as it might be in the East End of London,
Egypt or the Middle East.
Pinioning of waterfowl
This is a certain means of preventing a bird from ever flying and is
commonly practised on captive waterfowl. It is said to have the advantage
that the birds so treated can then be allowed their liberty on ponds, lakes,
etc. and so lead a much more natural life than if they were confined in an
aviary.
As Philip Schofield said, if pinioned birds are put on unfenced waters
something will eat them or they will stray and come to a bad end. I recall
that Frank Finn in one of his books, but I cannot find which at the moment,
condemned pinioning and said owners who need to have their birds flightless
should clip their wings. He more briefly condemned it in his book Familiar
London Birds (p.129).
I agree. In either case the flightless bird is at a disadvantage when, as
too often in public parks and waterfowl collections, it has to compete with,
fight with or escape from other birds that are full-winged. But the pinioned
bird is worse off even in such situations as it is unbalanced. It cannot 'fly'
underwater, as many ducks do to escape attacks by birds of prey or aggressive
fellow captives. Also, when suddenly frightened or if impelled by the urge
to migrate or to accompany a full-winged companion, pinioned waterfowl
will often leap into the air, only to lose balance, spin round and fall with a
splash if on water but often heavy enough to injure the stump of the mutilated
wing if they do it often on hard ground.
Aesthetically, in my opinion, pinioning greatly detracts from the beauty
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.994931" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269447" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998902" page_id="56269447"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
185
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997088526315789" page_id="56269447"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
of any bird that has been so treated. Even more so, at least when the bird is
very close to one, than do the coloured leg rings (now known to affect the
bird's sexual attractiveness in at least one species, the Zebra Finch
Taeniopygia guttata&amp;apos;) and which both aviculturists (myself included, in the
past) and scientists widely use and the very unsightly wing tabs and back
tabs used by scientists studying raptors and gamebirds.
It is claimed that these and the various modern gadgets such as radio
transmitters on Black Grouse, bulky collars for the same purpose on Snow
Leopards IJncia uncia, etc., used by those studying these creatures, do not
incommode them in any way. This I rather doubt.
In conclusion
I think that aviculturists, who are in the position to do so, ought to try to
maintain stocks of beautiful and relatively easily kept and bred species and
encourage others to do so. And to try to ensure that breeding for show does
not, as it has with the Budgerigar and many breeds of Canaries and domestic
pigeons, result in the production of malformed, physically handicapped and
often downright ugly creatures and in normal sized and shaped examples of
their species becoming worthless and despised by those supposed to be
experts, and therefore no longer bred.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.819819" genericHeader="references" page_id="56269447" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.786572142857143" page_id="56269447"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
Avery, M. 2000. Ruddy Ducks and other aliens. British Birds 93:500.
Bibby, C. J. 2000. More than enough exotics? British Birds 93:2-3.
Finn, F. (No date given, probably early 1920s) Familiar London Birds. Hutchinson &amp; Co.,
London.
Goodwin, D. 1992. Should exotics be condemned or cherished? British Birds 85:334-335.
Goodwin, D. 2000. Introduced Birds. British Birds 93:500-504.
Lawson, T. 2000. Ducking the real issue. British Birds 93:504.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.936631555555556">
Lever, C. 1977. The Naturalised Animals of the British Isles , Hutchinson, London.
Lever, C. 1987. Naturalised Birds of the World. Longman Scientific and Technical, Harlow,
Essex.
Mead, C. 2000. The State of the Nation's Birds. Whittet Books Limited, Stowmarket, Suffolk.
Newton, I. 1986. The Sparrowhawk. T and AD Poyser, Staffordshire, England.
Scott, P. 1936. Morning Flight. Country Life Limited, London.
Scott, P. 1939. Wild Chorus. Country Life Limited, London.
Shurtleff, L. L. and Savage, C. 1996. The Wood Duck and the Mandarin. University of California
Press, USA.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999352" page_id="56269448"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
186
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.967131" genericHeader="method" page_id="56269448" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
NEW BREEDING PAIRS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9596694" page_id="56269448"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
The St Vincent Parrot Conservation Consortium (SVPCC) is
spearheading a new strategy regarding the captive population of the St
Vincent Parrot Amazona guildingii. The aim is to form several new pairs
from among those birds living in overseas collections. To this end, the Loro
Parque Fundacion, Tenerife, has received a female from Houston Zoo, Texas,
to pair with its lone male. Vogelpark Walsrode, Germany, has transferred
two males to Peter Hammond in the UK, to allow his male to choose a
partner and Toronto Zoo, Canada, is sending its single female to Avicultural
Society Vice President Dr Henri Quinque, who has three males and a female
in his private collection in France.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.773962" page_id="56269448"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.855246" genericHeader="method" page_id="56269448" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
THREE POSSIBLE WORLD FIRSTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.977563222222222" page_id="56269448"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
Having in 1995 become the first collection to breed the White-tailed
Trogon Trogon viridis, Vogelpark Walsrode/ Germany has now succeeded
in breeding three more species of trogon, the Javan Apalharpactes
reinwardtii. Red-headed Harpactes erythroeephala and Diard&amp;apos;s H. diardii.
Because trogons have weak feet and would probably have difficulty getting
out of deep nest-boxes, the boxes must not be very deep and are filled to the
top with wood shavings, which the birds remove until a slight depression is
formed just below the entrance hole, for they seem to like to be able to look
out of the hole while sitting.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.466479" page_id="56269448"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.576731" genericHeader="method" page_id="56269448" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
FOR THE FIRST TIME
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.960456833333333" page_id="56269448"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
Loro Parque, Tenerife, which on December 17th celebrated the 30th
anniversary of its opening in 1972, earlier in the year for the first time in its
history bred the Plum-faced Lorikeet Oreopsittacus arfaki major (a
subspecies of the Whiskered Lorikeet), at first listed as the Plum-faced
Lorikeet and now as the Greater Alpine Lorikeet. Also for the first time, it
bred the Swift Parrot or Parrakeet Lathamus discolor and, it believes for the
first time in any collection, Brotogeris chrysopterus tuipara, a subspecies
of the Golden-winged Parrakeet, as well as the Morotai subspecies of the
Chattering Lory Lorius garrulus morotanius. In the case of the latter, the
two chicks from the first clutch were hand-reared and the two from the
second clutch were reared by the parents.
New additions to the collection include the Aru Islands subspecies of
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.658986" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269449" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.93584" page_id="56269449"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
187
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.723510666666667" page_id="56269449"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
the Red-sided Eclectus Eclectus roratus aruensis and the Maroon-faced
Parrakeet Pyrrhura leucotis griseipectus (a subspecies of the White-eared
Conure). Other recent additions include two pairs of Josephine's Lorikeets
Charmosyna josefince from a German breeder, two female Bolborhynchus
aurifrons robertsi from a Swiss breeder and a pair of Triton Cockatoos
Cacatua galerita triton.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.559889" page_id="56269449"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.610014" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56269449" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
BOB GRANTHAM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998290814814815" page_id="56269449"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
It is with deep regret that I report the death on December 2nd, of a dear
friend, Bob Grantham, the well known parrot breeder. Bob, who had been
ill for some time, bore his illness with dignity until the very end.
I first met Bob over 40 years ago at another birdkeeper's home in
Hertfordshire, and we soon became good friends. Bob was a second-
generation birdkeeper, his father having kept birds before him. Bob started
breeding birds in 1926 at the age of 10 when his father built him an aviary
for some canaries in the garden of the family home in New Barnet, Herts.,
the home in which he lived until his death.
Until the 1960s, Bob exhibited a variety of species of foreign birds, two
of which, a Tacazze Sunbird and a Turquoise-naped Chlorophonia took
leading awards at the Foreign Bird League club show in the early 1960s.
Parrots were however, Bob's first love, and he kept and successfully bred
numerous species ranging in size from Australian grass parrakeets to lories
and lorikeets, cockatoos and Amazons. Bob, and his second wife, Rosemary
Low, were credited with breeding for the first time in the UK, the Bronze-
winged Pionus, Cape Parrot, Yellow-shouldered Amazon, Duyvenbode's
Lory and Meyer's Lorikeet, and more recently Bob succeeded in breeding
the Purple-bellied Parrot. The Avicultural Society medal was awarded for
each of these UK first breedings.
Bob had been an Avicultural Society Council Member for several years
and had recently been re-elected for a further five year term. At the time of
his death Bob was also the Southern Foreign Bird Club's Treasurer, a position
that he had held for 35 years.
I for one will miss Bob's likeable and cheerful personality and extend
sincere condolences to his two daugthers, Anita and Lynne and their families,
and his carer Julie, who cared for him so well in his last years.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.539908">
Ron Oxley
</subsectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99875" page_id="56269450"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
188
</page>
<table confidence="0.542940857142857" page_id="56269450"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
CONTRIBUTORS TO VOLUME 108 - 2002
AZEVEDO, Cristiano Schetini, FAGGIOLI, Angela Bernadete
and FERRAZ, Joao Bosco
Breeding the Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber at Belo Horizonte Zoo,
Minas Gerais, Brazil ............ 165
BANNOR, Brett K.
Scarlet Ibis incubate Sacred Ibis eggs and partly rear a Sacred Ibis
</table>
<figure confidence="0.957594304347826" page_id="56269450"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
chick............ 59
BOCKHEIM, Greg
Raising ostrich chicks at Potawatomi Zoo... 127
BRICKELL, Neville
Notes on the feeding and nesting of Olive Pigeons...63
CONGDON, Susan
Parent reared African Jananas at Disney&amp;apos;s Animal Kingdom.. 152
ELLIS, John A.
London Zoo Review 2001 .. 32
ELLIS, Malcolm
A summary of pittas in European zoological collections...75
GRAHAM, Jamie
Hand-rearing the Black-faced Ibis at the Cotswold Wildlife
Park..... 110
HINZE, lan
The Black-rumped Waxbill Estrilda troglodytes ..... 145
KEHL, Nicole and ROSS, Megan R.
The breeding behaviour of a pair of Cinereous Vultures at Lincoln
Zoo Park............. 3
LOW, Rosemary
Threats to parrots in aviculture ....... 49
OWEN, Neil
Breeding the Yellow-breasted Magpie Cissa hypoleuca .... 172
</figure>
<page confidence="0.998963" page_id="56269451"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
189
</page>
<table confidence="0.858379448275862" page_id="56269451"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
CONTRIBUTORS TO VOLUME 108 - 2002 (Cont'd)
PEAT. Louise
The Great Blue and other turacos. 123
PYPER, Stewart
The President&amp;apos;s Garden Party 2001 .... 80
The Society&amp;apos;s second visit to the Natural History Museum.83
The Society&amp;apos;s visit to Chester Zoo.82
RINKE, Dieter and MARCORDES, Bernd
Breeding the Blue-tailed or Banded Pitta Pitta guajana
at Vogelpark Walsrode. 113
SAWYER, R. C. J.
Some famous aviculturists I have known. 100
SCHOFIELD, Philip
The Mandarin Duck.52
SILVA MORATON, Derian A. L.
The Grey Parrot in aviculture.8
SMITH, Chris
Von der Decken&amp;apos;s Hornbill Tockus deckeni at the Oklahoma City
Zoological Park. 69
SONTAG, Jr., Walter A,
How do two sturnids, Leucopsar rothschildi and
Gracupica nigricollis, get along together in limited space?. 154
WENTZEL, Isabel
World of Birds Review 2001/2002.97
WILKINSON, Roger
Birdwatching in Papua New Guinea and New Britain. 17
Bird Notes from Chester Zoo, 2001.24
WISEMAN, Rosemary
My experiences breeding the Victoria Crowned Pigeon. 1
</table>
<page confidence="0.99592" page_id="56269452"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
190
</page>
<table confidence="0.893857076923077" page_id="56269452"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
INDEX TO VOLUME 108 - 2002
Actophilornis africanus, parent reared at DAK............................... 152
Aegypius monachus , breeding behaviour at Lincoln Zoo Park ................. 3
Aix galericulata. The Mandarin Duck..................................................... 57
Anorrhinus galeritus, The society adopts a pair....89
Aviculturists; Some famous, I have known ........................................... 100
Birdwatching in Papua New Guinea and New Britain ............................ 17
Book Reviews
Chatter of Choughs.... 40
Ducks, Geese and Turkeys ..... 138
Encyclopedia of Estrildid Finches ................................................... 137
Handbook of the Birds of the World (Vol.6)...................................... 41
Handbook of the Birds of the World (Vol.7).... 136
Hope is a thing with feathers ... 39
Pheasants, Partridges &amp; Grouse ... 88
Pionus Parrots ..... 87
Cissa hypoleuca , breeding...... 172
Columha arquatrix, pollenii, sjostedti, thomensis .... 63
Corythaeola cristata, The Great Blue Turaco and others...................... 123
Duck, The Mandarin................................................................................ 52
Eagle, Harpy, fourteenth chick ..... 170
Estrilda troglodytes , The Black-rumped Waxbill.................................. 145
Eudocimus ruber , breeding at Belo Horizonte Zoo............................... 165
Eudocimus ruber , nests parasitized by Sacred Ibis .. 59
Garrulax galbanus, Society funds research ... 178
Goura victoria, experiences breeding ....................................................... 1
</table>
<reference confidence="0.964815142857143">
Gracupica nigricollis, kept with Leucopsar rothschildi ....................... 154
Hornbill, Bushy-crested, The society adopts a pair................................. 89
Hombill, Von der Decken's, at Oklahoma City Zoo ............................... 69
Ibis, Black-faced, the hand-rearing of....... 110
Ibis, Sacred, parasitizing nests of Scarlet Ibis .. 59
Ibis, Scarlet, breeding at Belo Horizonte Zoo .. .165
Ibis, Scarlet, nests parasitized by Sacred Ibis.. 59
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998701" page_id="56269453"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
191
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.746105" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269453" page_num="191" year="" vol="">
INDEX TO VOLUME 108 - 2002 (Cont'd)
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.421379107142857">
Ja#ana, African, parents rear young at DAK. 152
Laughingthrush, Yellow-throated, Society funds research. 178
Leucospar rothschildi, kept with Gracupica nigricollis . 154
Letters to the Editor. 35,85,180
Magpie, Yellow-breasted, breeding. 172
Museum, Natural History, The Society's second visit.83
News &amp; Views .. 43,90,139,186
Ostrich, chicks raised at Potawatomi Zoo.127
Parrot, The Grey, in aviculture.8
Parrots, Threats to, in aviculture.49
Pigeon, Olive spp., feeding and nesting.63
Pigeon, Victoria Crowned, experiences breeding. 1
Pitta, Blue-tailed or Banded, breeding at Walsrode. 113
Pitta guajana, breeding at Walsrode .... 113
Pittas, Summary of species in European collections.75
President's Garden Party 2001 . 80
Psittacus erithacus, in aviculture.8
Starling, Bali, kept with Black-collared Starling. 154
Starling, Black-collared, kept with Bali Starling. 154
Struthio spp., raising chicks at Potawatomi Zoo. 127
Theristicus melanopsis, hand-reared. 110
Threskiornis aethiopicus, parasitizing nests of Scarlet Ibis .. 59
Turaco, Great Blue and other turacos. 123
Vulture, Cinereous, breeding behaviour at Lincoln Zoo Park.3
World of Birds, Review 2001/2002.97
Zoo, Chester, Bird Notes, 2001 . 32
Zoo, Chester, The Society's visit...83
Zoo, London, Review 2001 ... 32
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998763" page_id="56269454"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
192
</page>
<table confidence="0.984209533333333" page_id="56269454"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
Straights
Aniseed #5.50 kg
Brown Perilla #2.50 kg #11.50 5kg
Black Lettuce #5.50 kg #12.00 2.5kg
Blue Maw #2.50 kg #11.50 5kg
Buckwheat #1.50 kg #4.95 5kg
Chicory Seed #3.50 kg #15.00 5kg
Chillies #2.50 500g
Evening Primrose #5.50 kg
Fonio Paddy #6.95 500g #13.00 kg
Fresh Water Shrimps #5.00 500g #9.50 kg
German Thistle #4.50 kg #8.50 2.5kg
Groats #1.50 kg #5.00 5kg
Juniper Berries #4.00 500g#15 2.5kg
M. Sprays Chinese #3 kg #14.00 5kg
M. Sprays French #3.50 kg #16.00 5kg
Mountain Ash #3.25 500g #12.50 2.5kg
Mung Beans #2.00 kg #8.00 5kg
Niger Seed #2.50 kg #9.50 5kg
Paddy Rice #1.50 kg #4.95 5kg
Pine Seed Medium #3.50 500g
Plantain #4.00 500g #8.00 kg
Safflower #1.50 kg #4.95 5kg
Seasame Seed #2.50 kg #10.00 5kg
Sunflower Striped #1.95 kg #6.00 5kg
Sunflower Kemals #2.95 kg #10.00 5kg
Teasel Seed #4.50 500g #9.00 kg
White Lettuce Seed #6.95 kg
White Perilla Seed #3.00 kg #13.50 5kg
Whole Rosehips #2.50 500g #5.00 kg
</table>
<figure confidence="0.926453428571429" page_id="56269454"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
Vitamins &amp; Minerals
Sunbird Nectars
Livefoods
Soak Mixes
Nuts
Eggfoods
Softbill Diets
Straights
Seed Mixtures
mi
Parrot Mixes
Frozen Foods
Lorikeet Nectars
Supplements
Handrearing
Formulas
Mynah Pellets
Dried Fruits
Berries
Moist Eggfood
WITTE MOLEN Eggfood is a
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.6424315">
complimentary food enjoyed by all seed-
eating birds. This food contains the
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.888018333333333" page_id="56269454"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
correct amount of vitamins, minerals and
the essential amino and fatty acids to keep
your birds in good health.
Witte Molen Eggfood is composed of
light digestable egg products, bakery
products and various seeds. This food is
made from the highest quality products to
ensure your birds are maintained at their
optimal standard.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.4743025" page_id="56269454"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
5kg Tub #16.95 2 Tubs 10kg #28.50
25kg Sack #39.95 Prices include Delivery
Softfood With Fruit
WITTE MOLEN Softfood with fruit is a
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.982602083333333" page_id="56269454"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
complete food for insectivorous and fruit
eating birds such as thrushes, blackbirds,
starlings, turacos, toucans, green magpies,
birds of paradise and jays. This ideal,
balanced diet has a uniquely low iron
content of less than 70ppm. It contains
the right proportion of proteins, vitamins,
minerals and all the essential amino acids
and fatty acids. This food is enriched
with berries and pieces of papaya,
pineapple, figs and apricots. It also
contains honey, brewers yeast and vitamin C.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.431490142857143" page_id="56269454"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
5kg Tub # 19.95 2 Tubs 10 kg #34.95
25kg Sack #53.95 Prices include Delivery
P&amp;P only #4.95 up to 45kg unless included in price (for most postcodes). Rob Harvey Specialist
Feeds, Kookaburra House, Gravel Hill Road, Holt Pound, Famham, Surrey, GU10 4LG.
Tel: 01420 23986 Fax: 01420 23078 E-mail: rob@robharvey.com
Website: www:robharvey.com
Sole UK agent for Witte Molen &amp; Avi-Plus All major CC taken
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998632" genericHeader="method" page_id="56269455" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ON THE RIGHT TRACK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997475809523809" page_id="56269455"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
In Birds of the World (Austin &amp; Singer, 1961), mention was made of
the flock of Caribbean Flamingos Phoenicopterus ruber ruber living on the
racecourse at Hialeah, Florida, USA. In the IPC part-work of the same
name (Part 7, Vol.l, pp. 173-174 (1969)), mention was also made of the
famous flamingos: ".at Hialeah, near Miami, where a hundred strong,
wing-clipped flock lives and breeds on an artificial lake constructed in the
centre of a racecourse. This colony is a draw for many tourists, for whom
an added attraction is the annual 'flamingo derby', when the entire flock is
shepherded on to the racecourse and raced en masse around it."
Well, it seems that the race track finally closed in 2001, but the colony
of flamingos continues to thrive and now numbers more than 300 birds.
Ron Magill reports (Conservation Hotline, Wildlife Conservation , Vol.105,
No.6, November/December 2002) that Miami Metrozoo, working with the
American Zoo and Aquarium Association and US Fish and Wildlife Service,
was recently allowed to collect 60 eggs from the colony. Metrozoo retained
some and distributed the others to Birmingham Zoo, Alabama, Fort Worth
Zoo, Texas and Flamingo Gardens, Florida. The chicks hatched from these
eggs will help rejuvenate their flocks, which have been experiencing low
reproduction due to ageing birds and mortality.
When an egg is removed, the female flamingo will usually lay another,
and within two weeks, most of the Hialeah birds had already laid again.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8945585" genericHeader="method" page_id="56269455" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Ackroyd's Australian Avitours
RAY ACKROYD'S AUSTRALIAN BIRDWATCHING AND NATURAL HISTORY TOURS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.979069166666667" page_id="56269455"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
We offer adventure tours of the highest standard led by Ray Ackroyd a
knowledgeable and enthusiastic bush guide with 50 years outback
experience.
Our tours are well priced and we travel with small groups for that exclusive
personalised service that is so hard to find in today's tourist industry.
Everybody has a window seat and our accommodation is modern and
spacious.
So come down and discover Australia's unique fauna and flora, the tour of a life
time: Cockatoos, Parrots, Reptiles, Waterfowl, Kangaroos, Koalas, Wildflowers,
Landscapes.
Many overseas aviculturists have travelled with us to date, all
completely satisfied. So please join Ray and our Hostess Beryl on the Australian
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.19395375" page_id="56269455"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Outback Tour of a Lifetime.
Enquiries for itineraries:
Ray Ackroyd's Australian Avitours, PO Box 44, Bringelly N.S.W., Australia.
Tel: 0247 748471 Email: cockatoosgalore@hotmail.com Fax: 029 8261639
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.780096" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56269456" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.964050458333333" page_id="56269456"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
3 9088 01769 6485
The Black-rumped Waxbill Estrilda troglodytes
by Ian Hinze...145
Parent Reared African Jacanas Actophilornis africana
at Disney's Animal Kingdom
by Susan Congdon.152
How do two Stumids, Leucopsar rothschildi and Gracupica
nigricollis , get along together in limited space?
by Walter A Sontag, Jr.154
Breeding the Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber
at Belo Horizonte Zoo, Minas Gerais, Brazil
by Cristiano Schetini de Azevedo, Angela Bemadete
Faggioli and Joao Bosco Ferraz.165
Fourteenth Harpy Eagle chick at Nuremberg Zoo.170
Breeding the Yellow-breasted Magpie Cissa hypoleuca
by Neil Owen.172
Avicultural Society to Help Fund Further Research.....178
Successful Scandinavian Symposium.179
Letters to the Editor.180
News &amp; Views.186
Contributors to Volume 108 - 2002.188
Index to Volume 108 - 2002.190
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</table>
</algorithms>
