<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.74865175" page_id="56500657"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
tofAVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 109
No. 2
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500656" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991836571428571" page_id="56500656"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2003 as for 2002: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.581649" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500656" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE..
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.955137909090909" page_id="56500656"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Enquiries regarding membership should be sent to:
THE MEMBERSHIP SECRETARY, Stewart Pyper, 21, Primrose Hill,
Nunney, Frome, Somerset BA11 4NP. Tel: 01373 836293
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TN13 1LG,UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments.
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and.the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998476" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500656" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982477333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.738773" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500655" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.334502" page_id="56500655"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 109 - No. 2 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2003
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.75219" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500655" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE TRI-COLOURED MUNIA Lonchura malacca IN
VENEZUELA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.982882166666667" page_id="56500655"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Robin Restall
The Tri-coloured Munia's black head and belly, pure white breast and
flanks contrast dramatically with the rich rufous back, wings and tail. As
one drives along a country road, a flock of these birds whirring in slight
undulations alongside the vehicle, just above the endless run of tall Panicum
maximum or across an expanse of emerald green rice, is unmistakable. And
unforgettable. I have seen these birds in southern India and studied them in
Sri Lanka. In addition I have kept them in most of the countries in which I
have lived. In fact they were the first birds I ever kept as a schoolboy in
London, back in 1947. They have remained a favourite ever since. However
these notes are dedicated to this species in Venezuela where it is well
established in the wild and regularly appears as a locally-caught bird in pet
shops.
In Venezuela, while it is not illegal to keep native birds, it is illegal to
offer them for sale. This of course does not stop anybody from trapping
birds and offering them (and other creatures) for sale at the roadsides at
every opportunity, though in the case of the Tri-coloured Munia it is classified
as an exotic, feral species, and as such is not protected by the law. Thus it is
one of the few wild-caught birds that appears in pet shops here. In Venezuela,
the local name is Monjita, or little monk, referring to its black hood or cowl.
They sell for the equivalent of about #4 (US$6.50) each. When I had a
flock in my garden aviary here they were the birds everybody remarked on
and admired. That is their commercial secret, for they have no song to talk
of. The aficionados of singing finches look at them and think they are related
to the Oryzohorus seed-finches. Because of their lovely songs these are
prized as cage birds all over South America, and people buy the munias
thinking they are getting a songbird cheap. A tame, adult male seed-finch in
song can fetch as much as the equivalent of #100 (approx.US$160) - a
whopping price in a country in which half of the population live on #1
(approx.US$1.60) or less a day. The seed-finches have massive white bills
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.986097" page_id="56500654"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
50
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.871144" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500654" page_num="50" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - TRI-COLOURED MUNIA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994708380952381" page_id="56500654"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
and are not dissimilar to munias. One species has a rufous belly and when
I first netted one here I really thought I had caught a munia until I handled it
and saw it properly.
Tri-coloured Munias were being imported into Venezuela in the 1940s
and a letter about them written by Dr Fernandez, head of the Veterinary
Faculty at Maracay University, appeared in a newspaper. In his letter, he
claimed that if the Monjitas continued to be released at the present rate they
would become established and become a pest. There is little doubt, according
to the son of Dr Fernandez, also Dr Fernandez and the present head of the
Veterinary Faculty at Maracay University, that birdkeepers had bought the
munias to breed with the local seed-finches for their song. Once the locals
realised that the munias did not sing, but just ate lots of seed, they released
them.
In those days the area between Maracay and Valencia had a large lake,
Lago de Valencia, and there were reedbeds and marshes at the edge. The
munia barely survived year to year, for the dry season in Venezuela produces
true drought conditions. The local seedeating birds move to other areas, but
the sedentary, non-migratory munia stayed, and most died. To compound
its misfortunes, the Lago de Valencia served as a reservoir for the big city
and too much water was extracted and what remained became polluted.
The marshes shrunk and the munia just about clung on. Those that made it
to the rice growing country to the south also died off during the drought,
rice being a very seasonal crop (as it is in Asia today). Then something
happened that dramatically changed the fortunes of the Tri-coloured Munia
in Venezuela. And it was because of another bird.
The North American Dickcissel Spiza americana was a migrant to
Trinidad (where Richard ffrench counted nearly three million at one time),
Venezuela and Colombia. It was becoming increasingly common in
Venezuela, so much so that it seemed as if the entire North American
population (to the relief of Trinidadian rice farmers) had discovered the rice
fields here in Venezuela and had made them its favourite destination. As a
result more was invested in rice production than almost anything else, leading
to the creation of irrigation systems that enabled Venezuela to grow rice all
year round, rotating crops month by month. This meant that instead of the
Dickcissels descending in their millions and wiping out the entire year's
crop, the damage was restricted to just the few months of the year the birds
were present before returning to the USA to breed. Nowadays, the entire
North American population winters in the rice growing area of Venezuela,
and the birds are persecuted mercilessly by the farmers.
I have a friend in Australia who had on his property a large amount of
unused land - a year-round marsh. He is a keen birdkeeper and the last time
I saw him, he was planning to build an aviary over the entire marsh and
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.554903" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500653" page_num="51" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - TRI-COLOURED MUNIA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997499" page_id="56500653"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
51
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9939145" page_id="56500653"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
plant it with rice. Once the rice was established he planned to release into
the aviary a small flock of Pytilia sp. and a few paradise whydahs Vidua sp.
At the time, and since then, I have often thought how ideal that set-up would
have been for a flock of Tri-coloured Munias, for under those circumstances
they would breed very well indeed. The rice growing area of Venezuela is
an ideal environment for the munias. They discovered the rice fields, but
unlike the Dickcissels they did not depart after a few months, but stayed and
found a munia paradise - ideal food and ideal breeding conditions - all year
round. As a result they have become possibly the most numerous resident
species in the rice growing areas of Venezuela. They are undoubtably a
pest, but for some reason, the farmers, obsessed with the Dickcissels, have
not yet become aware of the extent to which they have a potential monster
in their backyards.
Seedeating finches and smaller passerines in the Neotropics are quite
different in their breeding behaviour from those elsewhere. The native
finches breed after the rains have started. They breed only during the rainy
season. They have very small clutches of two or perhaps three eggs and
very short nestling periods. They usually have two clutches a season. The
young of the Blue-black Grassquit Volatinia jacarina fledge at nine or 10
days (but may leave the nest at eight days if disturbed) and Sporophila spp.
fledge at 11-12 days, or sooner. This is a survival strategy that works well,
for nest predation is very high indeed. Once the young fledge, their chances
of reaching adulthood and surviving to breed are quite high as predation
then is much lower. Compare this to temperate country species where nest
predation is much lower, but losses during the moult, migration and the first
winter are high. Temperate passerines tend to have larger clutches and longer
nestling periods. Clearly the situation with regard to nest predation and
survival of first year birds is also very different in the Old World tropics.
Clutches are larger, nest predation is lower, but predation of young birds
during their first few months is higher.
In Venezuela the Tri-coloured Munia has the best of both worlds. It
nests low down in reeds or rice, over water, where nest predation is lowest.
It has large clutches, and when there is ideal food all year round, it will
produce at least two clutches - that is 10-12 fledglings in a year, more than
double the number produced by local birds. Quite possibly it produces three
clutches in a year. The post-fledging behaviour of Tri-coloured Munias has
evolved to deal with predators in the Old World tropics, and so its survival
rate at this stage is at least as high as that of local birds, possibly higher. As
a result, there has in the last decade or so been a population explosion of
Tri-coloured Munia.
Whenever I have been working in the field in the rice-growing areas I
have mist-netted Tri-coloured Munia. About five years ago I decided to
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994802" page_id="56500652"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
52
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.865727" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500652" page_num="52" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - TRI-COLOURED MUNIA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.953859111111111" page_id="56500652"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
keep some to study, to see how they would settle and whether they would
behave differently from those I was familiar with from India and Sri Lanka.
They settled into a cage and aviary routine astonishingly easily. In the aviary
they behaved quite naturally. I have a modest outdoor flight that adjoins a
birdroom at one comer of the house. The flight reaches up to the eaves of
the house and my studio in which I paint looks out into it, and I can watch
the birds at leisure while I work. It has a small fish pond in the centre in
which a large stand of papyrus grows. Water Hyacinth also grow in the
pond, and every finch I have ever kept feeds on the leaves of this nutritious
plant. At the time, the aviary also had many tubs of Phyllostachys aurea
bamboo, known here as bambucillo, and very popular as a garden hedging.
It grew to about 3m (9ft 9in) in height.
There were seven munias in the group and a sort of hierarchy was
established with a dominant female and her mate. This dominant pair built
a nest, lm (approx.3ft 3in.) above the water, in the bamboo. It was a classic
ball of grasses and strips of leaves, with an entrance at the front that looked
out over the water. The nest was about 20cm (almost 8in) across. In the
wild, they use growing green grasses and reed stems, strips from palm leaves
and bamboo leaves to make the nest. The male brings the material and the
female builds the nest. The young in my aviary were reared entirely on
whatever seeds the adults selected from the canary and finch mixtures I
provided. I offered softfood and also mealworms, but never saw the munias
take either. By the time this happened I had acquired some local seedeaters
that I needed to study as part of my work at the Phelps Ornithological
Collection, so as soon as the five young fledged and were feeding themselves,
I released them all.
Here in Venezuela we also have established populations of Java Sparrow
Padda oryzivora and Village Weaver Ploceus cucullatus. I have not been
able to net either of these, but did buy a trio of the weavers from a villager
living on the edge of the marshes near Maracay. They were absolutely
indefatigable and were ideal aviary birds expect for the destruction they
wrought on every growing thing in their quest for materials to weave with.
I eventually had to release them for the same reason I had to release the
munias.
Robin Restall is a Research Associate, Phelps Ornithological Collection,
Caracas, Venezuela. E-mail: restall@cantv.net
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998458" page_id="56500651"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
53
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8435988" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500651" page_num="53" year="" vol="">
NEST ACTIVITY IN RHINOCEROS HORNBILLS Buceros
rhinoceros IN RELATION TO ARTIFICIAL RAINFALL
PATTERNS
by David A. Oehler
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991026628571429" page_id="56500651"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
The response of a pair of Rhinoceros Hornbills Buceros rhinoceros to
scheduled artificial monsoon rainfall and subsequent cessation of this
artificial rainfall was observed as it pertained to circannual behaviour
(behaviour occurring on an approximately annual basis; a rhythm or cycle
of behaviour of approximately one year) and resulting reproductive
behaviours. Examination of the relationship of reproductive success to the
provision of artificial rain and the scheduled discontinuation of the artificial
rain was conducted. Empirical data shows that nest activity behaviours
were non-existent prior to the provision of the rain patterns and egg laying
commenced within seven days after the cessation of the artificial monsoon
rain. Our study suggests that if natural-like cycles of rainfall are provided
as part of the management of the captive Rhinoceros Hornbill population,
successful breeding may result. The increase in captive breeding could have
positive ramifications in the future conservation of these hornbills.
Introduction
Hornbills of the genus Buceros belong to the group of Indomalayan great
hornbills, which can be characterised as large birds with pied plumage and
a broad black band across the white tail in most species. As well as having
distinctive black and white plumage, Rhinoceros Hornbills have large orange
mandibles with an upturned orange casque. These hornbills are distributed
within the forests of the Sunda Shelf landmasses (Kemp, 1995).
Circannual behaviours such as energy intensive reproductive activities
may increase daily energy requirements by 50% in birds. In the case of
males, courtship displays and territorial defence account for a significant
share of these activities, while in the case of females, the production of eggs
increases energy requirements (Cech et al. 2001). Where the annual
fluctuation in daily photoperiod is relatively slight or absent, seasonal rains
and the associated changes in food availability may be more important
environmental cues for the onset of breeding and may be the ultimate
breeding stimulus (Hudelson, 1996). In response to the increased energy
needs, most hornbills demonstrate circannual breeding behaviours, governed
mainly by extraneous factors such as the effects of rainfall on food supply
(Kemp, 1973,1976; Poonswad etal. 1987). Hornbills in Khao Yai National
Park in northern Thailand begin nesting activities at the end of the monsoon
when food supplies are at their peak (Tsuji, 1996).
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995889" page_id="56500650"  page_num="54" year="" vol="">
54
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.80353" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500650" page_num="54" year="" vol="">
OEHLER - RHINOCEROS HORNBILL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998861523809524" page_id="56500650"  page_num="54" year="" vol="">
As described by Galama et al. (2002) in the EAZA (European Association
of Zoos and Aquaria) guidelines, captive management includes providing
pairs with areas with minimal disturbance, warm ambient temperatures, light
regimes consistent with natural habitats (mainly between 30*N-30*S), high
humidity, sufficient space for flight, minimum enclosure height of 3m
(approx .9ft 9in), stable perching and nest sites that duplicate those used by
their wild counterparts. Utilization of sprinkler systems for Aceros hornbills
in European zoos, has persuaded personnel of the importance of artificial
rainfall in stimulating breeding pairs (Galama et al. 2002). Significant
correlation between sprinkling frequency, duration and breeding success of
Aceros hornbills was not revealed in data compiled by Galama in 1996,
although institutions with successful breeding pairs sprinkled their birds
more frequently throughout the year. American zoo personnel describe
probable critical factors leading to reproduction of Rhinoceros Hornbills as
enclosure size, placement and type of nest structure, and access to the nest
structure, but do not discuss amount and/or timing of rainfall (Hutchins,
1976; Shannon, 1993; Reilly, 1988; Kemp, 1975). Overall, the use of these
criteria has not provided the captive population of hornbills with a high
reproductive success or consistent enough reproduction to provide stocks
for conservation efforts such as future reintroductions (Wilkinson, 1992;
Kemp, 1995).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.894053">
Methods
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97563095" page_id="56500650"  page_num="54" year="" vol="">
Cinicinnati Zoo and Botanical Garden exhibited a wild-caught pair of
Rhinoceros Hornbills from 1988-1995 in a greenhouse display of the Bird
House. In 1996, the male and a new wild-caught female were placed in the
renovated Bird House, The Wings of the World Exhibit. This pair was
transferred in 1999 to a propagation area. The off-exhibit propagation
enclosure is 3.6m x 3.5m x 2.6m high (approx, lift 9in x lift 6in x 8ft 6in
high). Within this is a natural nest log 2.1m (approx. 6ft lOin) in
circumference x 2.4m (approx.7ft lOin) in length, with an opening 1.2m
(approx. 3ft 1 lin) long x 30cm (approx. 1ft) wide, approximately 1.5m (4ft
11 in) from the base of the log. There is also an artificial nest log and
horizontal perching 2m (approx. 6ft 6in) from each nest site and at centre
points of the enclosure. Environmental conditions provided included a
controlled photoperiod based on the seasonal schedule of 20*N and ambient
temperatures ranging from 25*C-30*C (77*F-86*F). Management of the
pair was modified in 2001 to include stimulated rain, via a sprinkler system,
daily for at least one hour from December-April and curtailment of the rainfall
drastically after this. The actual schedule consisted of rainfall for two hours
each day beginning at 9.00am in January, reduced to 15 minutes per day in
May and terminated June 2nd. Due to cleaning schedules this was modified
in 2002, to one and a half hours of rainfall twice a day (9.00am and 12 noon)
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.469202" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500649" page_num="55" year="" vol="">
OEHLER - RHINOCEROS HORNBILL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994623" page_id="56500649"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
55
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.958866" page_id="56500649"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
from December-March, decreased to 45 minutes per day on April 1st and
terminated April 22nd.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.925952">
Results
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9985601875" page_id="56500649"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
The pairs of Rhinoceros Hornbills at Cincinnati had demonstrated little
or no reproductive activity from 1988-2000. March 2001, however, the pair
began showing interest in the nest log, began bill fencing, and ritualized
mutual feeding. Aggressive behaviour by the male towards the keeper staff
was noted in May, as was plastering of the nest opening. On June 10th,
copulation was observed and within 24 hours, the female entered the nest
log and remained there for the next 91 days (Robbins and Miller, 2001).
One chick was produced and emerged from the nest log in early October,
118 days after the onset of incubation activities. During the 2002 season,
one egg was produced seven days after cessation of the artificial rain. The
egg was laid on April 29th, outside of the nest cavity and was discovered
broken in the enclosure pool. The female returned to the nest log within 12
hours and subsequently produced another egg. After remaining in the nest
log for 89 days, the female emerged and a chick was observed feeding at the
nest opening. This chick came out 133 days after the female first entered
and remained in the nest log.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.851311">
Discussion
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985204105263158" page_id="56500649"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
All available information indicates that the provision of proper
environmental conditions influence the rate of success in the propagation of
captive Rhinoceros Hornbills. Nest site preferences, warm temperatures,
natural light regimes and stable perching in a secure enclosure lead to nesting
activity in pairs of hornbills. We believe that the addition of scheduled
artificial monsoon rain further stimulate pairs to nest. The cessation of the
artificial monsoon rain corresponds to the relative abundance of food in the
wild, providing the additional energy required during courtship and egg
production observed at six to seven days post-monsoon. Comparison of the
years 1988-2002 in regard to the management of the Rhinoceros Hornbills
indicates that egg production resulted from the manipulation of the artificial
rainfall. Confirmation of this inference will require additional detailed studies
and analysis within the captive population of Rhinoceros Hornbills.
Conclusion
The importance of providing breeding pairs of Rhinoceros Hornbills
with a proper nest to elicit appropriate nest-related behaviours has been
well documented. Utilisation of known stimuli, augmented with scheduled
artificial monsoon rain has been demonstrated to further stimulate circannual
behaviour in the form of reproductive activities. The use of sprinkler systems
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.990712" page_id="56500648"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
56
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.795696" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500648" page_num="56" year="" vol="">
OEHLER - RHINOCEROS HORNBILL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.978105" page_id="56500648"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
to create artificial monsoon rain, particularly in indoor enclosures, has
resulted in egg production and viable offspring. Incorporation of this
management practice may lead to increased production within the captive
population of Rhinoceros Hombills to intensify future conservation efforts.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.69013" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56500648" page_num="56" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgement
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9989782" page_id="56500648"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
We are indebted to Edward Maruska for his appreciation and interest in
the exhibition and propagation of hornbill taxa at Cincinnati Zoo and
Botanical Garden. I would personally like to thank the aviculture staff for
the care and observations provided in reference to the Rhinoceros Hombills
here at the zoo.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.930805" genericHeader="references" page_id="56500648" page_num="56" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.744448235294118">
Cech, R., Dunning, J. B. and Elphick, C. 2001. Behavior. In: Elphick, C., Dunning, J. B. and
Sibley D. A. (eds.). The Sibley Guide to Bird Life &amp; Behavior. Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., New
York.
Galama, W., King, C. &amp; Brouwer, K. 2002. EAZA Hornbill Management and Husbandry
Guidelines. The EAZA Hornbill TAG, National Foundation for Research in Zoological Gardens,
Amsterdam.
Hudelson, K. S., DVM. 1996. A review of the Mechanisms of Avian Reproduction and their
Clinical Application. Seminars in Avian and Exotic Pet Medicine 5,4:189-198.
Hutchins, M. 1976. Breeding biology and behaviour of the Indian Pied Hornbill Anthracoceros
malabaricus malabaricus. International Zoo Yearbook 16:99-104.
Kemp, A. C. 1973. Environmental factors affecting the onset of breeding in some southern
African hombills, Tockus spp. Journal of Reproduction and Fertility , Supplement 19:319-331.
Kemp, A. C. 1976. Factors affecting the onset of breeding in African hombills. In: Proceedings
of the 16th International Ornithological Congress. Australian Academy of Science, Canberra.
Kemp, A. C. 1995. The Hombills. Oxford University Press.
Poonswad, P.,Tsuju, A. and Ngarmpongsai, C. 1987. Acomparative study of breeding biology
of sympatric hornbill species (Bucerotidae) in Thailand with implication for breeding in captivity.
In: Proceedings of the Jean Delacour/ International Foundation for the Conservation of Birds
Symposium on Breeding Birds in Captivity. International Foundation for the Conservation of
Birds, Los Angeles.
Reilly, S. E. 1988. The captive management and breeding of the Rhinoceros Hornbill Buceros
rhinoceros at the Audubon Park and Zoological Garden. International Zoo Yearbook 27:263-
269.
Robbins, A. &amp; Miller, M. 2001. Captive Propagation of Rhinoceros Hornbill at the Cincinnati
Zoo &amp; Botanical Garden. Unpublished manuscript.
Shannon, P. W. 1903. Rhinoceros Hornbill. In: Poonswad, P. and Kemp, A. C. (eds.). Manual
to the Conservation of Asian Hombills. Hornbill Project, Thailand.
Tsuji, A. 1996. Hombills. Masters of tropical forests. First edition. Sarakadee Press, Bangkok,
Thailand.
Wilkinson, R. 1992. Any hope for hombills? Avicultural Magazine 98,3:119-123.
David A. Oehler is Avian Conservation Program Manager ; Cincinnati
Zoo and Botanical Garden, 3400 Vine Street, Cincinnati, OH 45220-1399,
USA. Tel:513-475 6153/Fax 513-559-7790/ Website: www.cincyzoo.org/
E-mail: sinornis513@aol.com
</reference>
<page confidence="0.99723" page_id="56500647"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
57
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.991532" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500647" page_num="57" year="" vol="">
HORNBILLS IN THAILAND
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994655947368421" page_id="56500647"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
The Thailand Hombill Project has been conducting research on hombills
since 1978 and has lately expanded its research into the forests of western
and southern Thailand. In the southern provinces including Pattani,
Narathiwat and Yala, the project is receiving overwhelming cooperation
from villagers who previously earned money by taking hombill chicks from
their nests and selling them, but now receive payments for protecting the
nests and collecting research data.
Bushy-crested Hornbill at nest-hole.
As well as augmenting their meagre incomes, the project aims to create
an awareness of hombill conservation and the conservation of nature in
general among local people. The hombills being studied are the White-
crowned Berenicornis comatus, Helmeted Buceros vigil. Rhinoceros B.
rhinoceros. Great B. bicornis , Bushy-crested Anorrhinus galeritus and
Wreathed Aceros undulatus, the first three of which are considered to be
endangered.
In order for the project to succeed funding is crucial and money for it is
raised through the Hombill Family Adoption Project. To adopt a family of
hombills costs US$120 (about #75) a year. Adopters receive an end of year
report, with details of their hombills' breeding season, along with photos of
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996521" page_id="56500646"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
58
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993125" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500646" page_num="58" year="" vol="">
HORNBILLS IN THAILAND
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986127454545455" page_id="56500646"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
the birds, the villager who protected and observed the nest, and examples of
some of the types of food brought to the nest.
At the end of last year, following the society's adoption of a pair of
Bushy-crested Hombills, it received a letter and breeding report from Dr
Pilai Poonswad. Dr Poonswad wrote: "Thank you very much for your support
of the Hombill Family Adoption Program set up by the Hombill Research
Foundation in 2002. The staff of the Thailand Hombill Project and the
villagers of southern Thailand collect data throughout the year. The study
is ongoing and we are still collecting hombill data in this area. We need and
welcome the continuation of your support.
Nest observer, Mr. Haseng Kariya.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.96175" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500645" page_num="59" year="" vol="">
HORNBILLS IN THAILAND
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99181" page_id="56500645"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
59
</page>
<table confidence="0.287988" page_id="56500645"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
Dr Poonswad has provided the following results:
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.9724">
Table 1. Summary of hombill nesting in 2002.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.7507094" page_id="56500645"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
Hombill No. nests
Species in 2002
Female Successes Failures No data
entered
Great Hombill
</figure>
<page confidence="0.9311215" page_id="56500645"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
43
21
</page>
<figure confidence="0.953987" page_id="56500645"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
20
1
-
Rhinoceros Hombill
</figure>
<page confidence="0.6997485" page_id="56500645"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
34
11
</page>
<figure confidence="0.962103315789474" page_id="56500645"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
9
2
-
Helmeted Hombill
13
4
4
-
-
Wreathed Hombill
12
8
8
-
-
Bushy-crested Hombill
13
3
2
-
-
White-crowned Hombill
6
3
3
-
Wrinkled Hombill
3
1
1
-
-
Total
124
51
47
3
1
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.984515181818182" page_id="56500645"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
Information on the hornbill adopted by you:
Species of hombill: Bushy-crested Hombill Anorrhinus galeritus
Name of observer: Mr Haseng Kariya
Location of the nest: Budo Mountain, Raman District, Yala Province
Data of tree that the hornbill used for nesting:
Species of nest tree: Sindora echinocalyx
Diameter of nest tree at breast height: 101.8cm (3ft 4in)
Height of nest tree: 50m (approx. 164ft)
Height of nest above the ground: 20m (approx.65ft)
Size of nest hole entrance (w x 1): 12cm x 20cm (4 3 Ain x 8in)
Direction of nest hole entrance: 240*
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.991773" page_id="56500644"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
60
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.992539" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500644" page_num="60" year="" vol="">
HORNBILLS IN THAILAND
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9878452" page_id="56500644"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
Data of the nesting hornbill:
Date nest was found: July 6th 2002
Date female and chick came out of nest: September 8th 2002
Type of parental care: Cooperative care (the male
had four helpers to assist
feeding the brood throughout
the breeding cycle)
Food that the male brought to feed the female and chick:
Fruit species: Ficus sp. (size 0 &lt; 1cm) (0.3), Ficus sp. (size 0 l-2cm)
(2.6), Ficus sp. (size 0 &gt; 2cm) (2.3), Knema sp (4),
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.9776753" page_id="56500644"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
Sterculia sp (3.8), Dysoxylum sp. (0.8)
Aglaia spectabilis (0.7), Beilschmiedia sp. (0.2),
Artocarpus sp. (0.1), Oncosperma tigillarium (0.1)
Animal Locust (0.7), Walking stick (0.03), Leaf Insect (0.1),
species: Worm (0.3), Cicada (0.1), Beetle (0.03),
Earthworm (0.1), Millipede (0.3) Centipede (0.1),
Scorpion (0.4), Spider (0.1), Lizard (0.1),
Flying Lizard (0.2) Skink (0.1), Snake (0.4)
Period of data collection: July 6th - September 9th 2002
Breeding status: This nest was successful.
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.73784">
Table 2a. Duration of foods (fruits) which Bushy-crested Hornbill brought
to the brood during the 2002 breeding season at Budo Sungaipadi National
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.997029428571429" page_id="56500644"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
Park.
Type of food
July
August
September
Fruits
Ficus spp.
Knema sp.
^ &apos; '
W
Sterculia sp.
Dysoxylum sp.
W
&lt; \0x25BA
Aglaia spectabilis
Beilschmiedia sp.
Artocarpus sp.
Oncosperma tigillarium
*
w
*
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.962909" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500643" page_num="61" year="" vol="">
HORNBILLS IN THAILAND
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997861" page_id="56500643"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
61
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.811061">
Table 2b. Duration of foods (animals) which Bushy-crested Hombill brought
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.985804181818182" page_id="56500643"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
to the brood during the 2002 breeding season at Budo Sungaipadi National
Park.
At the Council Meeting held on Saturday April 5th at Blackbrook
Zoological Park, the decision was taken to continue for a further year to
support the study of the above pair of Bushy-crested Hombills and to adopt
a second pair of hombills of a different species, namely a pair of Rhinoceros
Hombills. Later, however, we were advised that it looked unlikely that the
pair of Bushy-crested Hombills was going to nest this year, so instead decided
to adopt a pair of Great Hombills. So for 2003 the Avicultural Society has
adopted a pair of Rhinoceros Hombills and a pair of Great Hombills.
Further information about the project can be obtained from: Dr Pilai
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.921226">
Poonswad, Secretary-General, Hornbill Research Foundation, do
Department ofMicrobiology, Faculty of Science, Mahidol University, Rama
6 Road, Bangkok 10400, Thailand. Tel: 66-2-201 -5532/Fax:66-2- 644-5411/
E-mail: scpps@mucc.mahidol.ac.th
</reference>
<page confidence="0.975908" page_id="56500642"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
62
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.571359" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500642" page_num="62" year="" vol="">
THE HAND-REARING OF A ST VINCENT PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.955025552631579" page_id="56500642"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
Amazona guildingii
by Roger G. Sweeney
The St Vincent Parrot Amazona guildingii is one of the largest and most
striking of the Amazon parrots. Adult St Vincent Parrots can measure up to
41cm (approx.16in) in length and weigh 550g-800g. Although no subspecies
are recognised, the general plumage is extremely variable in colour and
three distinct colour phases exist, green, bronze-brown and orange. The St
Vincent Parrot is endemic to the island state of St Vincent &amp; the Grenadines
in the eastern Caribbean, where it lives in remaining undisturbed forest areas
and is regarded as being of vulnerable conservation status (Snyder et al.
2000). It is the national bird of St Vincent &amp; the Grenadines and is widely
regarded as a national symbol of the countries independence. Popularly
known there as 'Vincie', it is also a nature conservation symbol.
A captive group of the St Vincent Parrot has been present on the nearby
island of Barbados since 1973. It was formerly housed at Ougheston Zoo,
but in 1998 the zoo closed and the group was moved and brought under the
management of the Graeme Hall Nature Sanctuary (Sweeney, 2001). At the
time that the birds were transferred it was noted that most of the older
individuals had become extremely obese. From January 2000 onwards the
birds were subject to improved husbandry to control their diet and promote
exercise, to bring about a return to improved physical condition and fertilty.
Although during the period 1999-2001 the four adult females laid numerous
eggs, none of these proved to be fertile. In the spring of 2002, all four
females laid again, producing a total of 15 eggs, which were removed for
artificial incubation. Only one proved to be fertile and this was incubated to
hatching and the chick was successfully hand-reared to independence.
Husbandry of adult pairs
Immediately upon their arrival, efforts were made to provide improved
accommodation for all of the St Vincent Parrots in the group, particularly
the adult pairs potentially capable of breeding. The four adult pairs are
maintained now in breeding cages measuring 7m long x 1.8m wide x 1.8m
high (approx. 23ft long x 5ft lOin wide x 5ft lOin high). These are suspended
on a solid wooden frame with the wire mesh floor of each cage some 75cm
(2ft 6in) above ground level to allow for easy daily cleaning beneath the
cages. The wooden framework encloses the wire mesh frame to provide
stability, as do the legs of the wooden frame which are cemented into the
ground. The cages are separated from each other by a barrier of plants in
order to reduce inter-male aggression caused by the sight and sound of other
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.763854" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500641" page_num="63" year="" vol="">
SWEENEY - ST VINCENT PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998836" page_id="56500641"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
63
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99831425" page_id="56500641"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
male birds. The food and water containers are placed in a specially designed
shelf enabling them to be serviced and cleaned from the front of each cage.
There are three horizontal perches across the width of each cage. There are
no branches running the length of the cages in order to encourage the birds
to fly from perch to perch rather than walk. All cages are regularly provided
with freshly cut branches for the birds to chew and other occupational items
such as natural fibre rope are also provided. Compared to the former
accommodation in which the birds lived for almost three decades, the new
cages allow for increased exercise, mental stimulation and a better standard
of hygiene
The dietary regime broadly reflects conventional husbandry protocols
for other species of Amazon (Stoodley, 1990; Sweeney, 1998). The feeding
protocols for the Barbados population of St Vincent Parrots have been
modified to manage the problem of severe obesity. The birds are now under
close dietary control to slowly restore them to healthy body weights. Soon
after their transfer to the management of Graeme Hall Nature Sanctuary, all
dry seeds and nuts were removed from the diet and replaced by fruits,
vegetables and low fat dietary pellets. The birds receive a mixed salad of
fruits and vegetables early each morning and the pellets in the afternoon.
Manufactured by Rolf C. Hagen, the pellets are called Tropi-mix and are
specially formulated for parrot species that are prone to obesity. Prime, a
vitamin supplement, is sprinkled over the morning feed of fruits and
vegetables. The pattern of weight loss of each bird is being monitored
regularly and discussed with our veterinary advisors.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.5513205">
Breeding management
The St Vincent Parrot is considered to be one of the least studied parrot
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999658266666666" page_id="56500641"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
species in the Caribbean (Snyder et al. 2000). In the wild it breeds annually
and produces a clutch of two to four eggs. The breeding season occurs at
the end of the annual dry period from March-July. The nesting site is usually
situated within a trunk cavity of a tall tree, particularly a Dacryodes excelsa.
Incubation takes 26 days and the chicks take 10 weeks to fledge. Sexual
maturity is achieved in the fourth year. There has been speculation that the
life expectancy of this species may be up to 80 years.
Pairing arrangements for birds of the captive population on Barbados
are determined by genetic relatedness and by assessment of individual
compatibility, opportunities for natural pair-bonding/free mate choice are
limited by genetic and practical constraints. The nest boxes measure 64cm
high x 46cm x 42cm (approx. 2ft l l Um high x 1ft 6in x 1ft 4V2in) and are
filled with clean wood shavings from untreated wood. The nest boxes are
left undisturbed during the incubation period unless the sitting female displays
problematic behaviour (e.g. prolonged periods out of the nest-box; agitated
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997623" page_id="56500640"  page_num="64" year="" vol="">
64
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.935526" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500640" page_num="64" year="" vol="">
SWEENEY - ST VINCENT PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98802495" page_id="56500640"  page_num="64" year="" vol="">
and/or aggressive behaviour). Closer observation of the nest-boxes begins
the day the first eggs are due to hatch. The appearance of each chick is
monitored to ensure good physical development (body mass is as expected
for its age and the eyes, skin, wings, legs, toes and feathers appear normal).
The chicks are also examined to ensure that they do not have ectoparasites,
such as mites, and there are no signs of parental aggression. Check are also
made to ensure that the chicks are being fed correctly by their parents.
In the spring of 2002 all four potential breeding pairs produced clutches
of eggs between March and the beginning of June. Three of the pairs each
produced a single clutch of eggs, while the remaining pair produced three
clutches during this period. A total of 15 eggs were removed for artificial
incubation. Because of long-term obesity and the resulting high levels of
infertility, the majority of these were removed soon after being laid to permit
examination for signs of fertility and to encourage the laying of replacement
clutches. The average egg size (15 eggs) was 41.9mm x 33.3mm.
Artificial incubation
The 15 eggs removed for artificial incubation were all placed in a
Grumbach incubator. Only one proved to be fertile. The parameters used to
artificially incubate eggs of the St Vincent Parrot at Graeme Hall Nature
Sanctuary are similar to those used for most other parrot species in captivity
(Harvey, 1990; Jordan, 1989; Sweeney, 1998,2001). A constant temperature
of 37.4*C (99.3*F) was maintained from the time the egg was placed in the
incubator until internal pip (when the chick&apos;s beak was seen to have pieced
the membrane of the air cell). The temperature was then reduced to 36.6*C
(97.9*F).
Air humidity in the incubator was maintained at 55% for most of the
incubation period and raised to above 80% after internal pip occurred. Weight
loss by the egg during incubation followed the expected pattern and no
adjustments to the air humidity level were required.
Throughout the incubation period up until the time of internal pip, the
egg was turned throughout the day by the automatic turning mechanism of
the incubator. Turning was discontinued after internal pip was observed.
The chick's emergence from the egg took place within 48 hours of internal
pip first being observed.
Hand-rearing
The chick was left to dry in the incubator for 12 hours before being
moved to a prepared brooder initially set at 36*C (96.8*F). This temperature
was maintained for the first five days of the rearing period and then slowly
lowered by about one degree every three days, this pattern of change being
dependant upon the chick's reaction. Physical signs that the temperature is
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.76389" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500639" page_num="65" year="" vol="">
SWEENEY - ST VINCENT PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99824" page_id="56500639"  page_num="65" year="" vol="">
65
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.895644714285714" page_id="56500639"  page_num="65" year="" vol="">
too high include panting and a brighter, more reddish skin coloration, while
signs that the temperature is too low include lethargy and paler than normal
skin coloration.
During its early development the chick was housed in a small container
padded with paper towelling to support its body. The towelling was changed
at every feeding period and the stainless steel container was routinely
sterilized. As the chick grew bigger it was transferred to larger containers
and either towelling or clean wood shavings were placed inside the container.
The first food was given to the chick approximately 18 hours after
hatching. The early feeds consisted simply of a hydration fluid (Infalyte).
Later in the day a commercial hand-rearing formula (Exact) was introduced
at a dilution of 10% solids to 90% Infalyte hydration fluid. The dilution of
the food was changed slowly over the first week as follows:
day 1 - 10% solids + 90% Infalyte
day 2 - 12% solids + 88% Infalyte
day 3-15% solids + 85% Infalyte
day 4-18% solids + 82% Infalyte
day 5 - 20% solids + 80% Infalyte
day 6-23% solids + 77% Infalyte
day 7-25% solids + 75% Infalyte
From the seventh day onwards a dilution of 25% solids was maintained
for the remainder of the hand-rearing period through to weaning. From the
eighth day onwards the Infalyte hydration fluid was replaced by bottled
water when preparing the hand-rearing food. The chick was fed throughout
the day from 6.00am - 11.00pm, with the crop being filled each time it
emptied.
Upon hatching the chick weighed 21.9g. The skin colour was pink with
long, thin strands of natal down lightly covering the body. The eyes and
ears were closed. At seven days old the chick weighed 53.8g and the ears
were open. At 14 days old the chick weighed 159g and the eyes were starting
to open, but were not fully open and looking around until day 17. At three
weeks of age the chick weighed 308g and pin feathers were appearing on
the body. The chick continued to grow well as can be seen from the
photographs and weight chart. Weaning proved to be slower than expected
compared to that of other species of Amazon parrot, almost certainly because
the chick was being reared alone without the benefit of interaction with
brood-mates. The chick took more than three months to become independent.
Summary
Although the poor level of fertility in 2002 remains disappointing, the
production of a fertile egg by one of the founder pairs that had previously
been infertile during its many years in captivity provides the expectation
that increased fertility may follow. With the four adult pairs of St Vincent
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.851744166666667" page_id="56500638"  page_num="66" year="" vol="">
66
SWEENEY - ST VINCENT PARROT
Aged one day.
Copyright Roger Sweeney
Copyright Roger Sweeney
Aged 15 days.
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.685535" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500637" page_num="67" year="" vol="">
SWEENEY - ST VINCENT PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.872759" page_id="56500637"  page_num="67" year="" vol="">
67
</page>
<figure confidence="0.75493925" page_id="56500637"  page_num="67" year="" vol="">
Copyright Roger Sweeney
Aged 33 days.
Copyright Roger Sweeney
Aged three months.
</figure>
<page confidence="0.998243" page_id="56500636"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
68
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.933327" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500636" page_num="68" year="" vol="">
SWEENEY - ST VINCENT PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.975820222222222" page_id="56500636"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
Parrots managed by the Graeme Hall Nature Sanctuary all showing gradual
weight loss and increased daily activity, we hope for improved breeding
success in future years.
Graeme Hall Nature Sanctuary has given the St Vincent Forestry
Department a commitment that it will manage the birds on a non-commercial
basis and will not move any of them without the knowledge and agreement
of the Forestry Department. Graeme Hall Nature Sanctuary will continue
to participate in the on-going DNA relatedness study being undertaken by
the Wildlife Conservation Society.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.941352" genericHeader="references" page_id="56500636" page_num="68" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.934862933333333">
Harvey, R. 1990. Practical Incubation. Birdworld, Surrey, UK.
Jordan, R. 1989. Parrot Incubation Procedures. Silvio Mattacchione &amp; Co., Port Perry,
Ontario, Canada.
Snyder, N., McGowan, P., Gilardi, J. &amp; Grajal, A. (eds.). 2000. Parrots: Status Survey and
Conservation Action Plan 2000-2004. IUCN, Gland, Switzerland and Cambridge, UK.
Stoodley, J. 1990. Genus Amazona. Bezel Publications, Channel Islands, UK.
Sweeney, R. G. 1998. Husbandry, breeding and European Studbook of the Red-spectacled
Amazon at Loro Parque. International Zoo News 45,6:352-362.
Sweeney, R. G. 2001. Pionus Parrots, a complete guide. Silvio Mattacchione &amp; Co., Port
Perry, Ontario, Canada.
Sweeney, R. G. 2001. Development of a management plan for the captive population of St
Vincent Amazon Parrots in Barbados. International Zoo News 48,7:430-436.
Roger G. Sweeney is Associate Director, Graeme Hall Nature Sanctuary,
Worthing, Christ Church, Barbados, West Indies. E-mail: rogergsweeney@
hotmail.com
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998011" page_id="56500635"  page_num="69" year="" vol="">
69
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.718075" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500635" page_num="69" year="" vol="">
CHESTER ZOO BIRD REVIEW 2002
by Roger Wilkinson
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997217105263158" page_id="56500635"  page_num="69" year="" vol="">
There were some exciting developments in the bird collection at Chester
Zoo in 2002. Highlights were the successful fledging of a Great Hombill
Buceros hicornis chick, a rare event in any zoo and only the second to be
reared in the UK, and the breeding of a Victoria Crowned Pigeon Goura
victoria and a Blue Crane Anthropoides paradisea. The successful rearing
of these birds was extremely satisfying not only in that they represented the
first time these had been bred at Chester but in that the bird staff had worked
hard to create the best conditions for these to breed.
The breeding of the Great Hornbill in particular gave us much pleasure
and satisfaction. In 2001 cameras were installed in all our hombill nest-
boxes and for the first time we were able to observe exactly what occurred
inside the boxes. The female Great Hombill of the pair in the aviary in the
Asian Elephant House was seen to remove from the nest barrel all the bark
chips provided as nest material. She then laid an egg directly on the flat
floor of the barrel and rather than cover the egg sat with it to one side of her.
As a result of this knowledge the nest barrel was modified. The size of the
entrance hole and the internal dimensions of the cavity were reduced and it
was provided with a concave bottom to prevent subsequent eggs from rolling
to one side.
As in previous years the pair of Great Hombills in the Elephant House
started showing signs of interest in each other very early in the year and the
birds were seen mating in late January. On February 13th the male was seen
feeding the female whilst she was inside the nest barrel and by February
21st the female was observed to be well mudded-in. The laying date was
not ascertained but the egg was noted to have hatched on March 30th and
the female was observed feeding mealworms, morio worms and small locusts
to the chick over the next few days. By April 4th the male was observed
taking pink rats and mice to the female in the nest. The chick grew rapidly
and on June 22nd the female broke the mud seal and emerged from the nest.
The chick fledged three days later when the male then surprisingly attacked
the female. She was removed and the male continued feeding the fledged
chick which he subsequently reared to independence. In late September the
male became aggressive towards the youngster which was removed and the
female reintroduced to the male.
Great though it was, this was the only hombill that was successfully
reared at Chester in 2002. The Tarictic Hombills Penelopides sp. nested
and laid four eggs but all of these were infertile. The pair of Wrinkled
Hombills Aceros corrugatus made no breeding attempts in 2002. This was
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994445" page_id="56500634"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
70
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.570286" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500634" page_num="70" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - CHESTER ZOO BIRD REVIEW 2002
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.968329142857143" page_id="56500634"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
much to my personal relief as the female appeared weary after her two
unsuccessful nesting attempts in 2001 and hopefully the rest should better
prepare her for this year. The Blue-winged Kookaburras Dacelo leachii
again bred and reared a chick. Lilac-breasted Rollers Coracias caudata
hatched five chicks but on this occasion reared only one. The turacos had a
better year with two Fischer's Turacos Tauraco fischeri, two Schalow's
Turacos T. schalowi, a Red-crested Turaco T. erythrolophus and a Violaceous
Turaco Musophaga violacea successfully bred.
The Parrot House has served Chester well as a breeding centre for rare
parrots. Parrots bred there have included Red-fronted Macaws Ara
rubrogenys, Blue and Gold Macaws A. ararauna. Thick-billed Parrots
Rhynchopsitta pachyrhyncha. Hawk-headed Parrots Deroptyus accipitrinus,
Golden Conures Guaruba guarouba. Blue-eyed Cockatoos Cacatua
ophthalmica , Leadbeater's C. leadbeateri and, most recently, Red-tailed
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.697672">
Amazons Amazona brasiliensis.
Roger Wilkinson
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987453375" page_id="56500634"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
Great Hornbill at six months old.
Standards continuously improve and the Parrot House aviaries now offer
less than we would wish in the future for their occupants and for our visiting
public. Therefore, we are in the process of relocating parrots to larger aviaries
in other areas of the zoo. A new development in 2002 was the opening of
the new South American Parrot Aviary in the area adjacent to the Tropical
Realm. This aviary complex is huge and includes two adjacent interlinking
flights and off-show areas within the upper story of the Tropical House.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.424824" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500633" page_num="71" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - CHESTER ZOO BIRD REVIEW 2002
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.949716" page_id="56500633"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
71
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.408543" page_id="56500633"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
.....
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.433348">
Roger Wilkinson
Victoria Crowned Pigeon.
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.978004" page_id="56500633"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
One of our two pairs of Hyacinth Macaws Anodorhynchus hyacinthinus
was received in 1992 as captive bred from the USA and housed in the Parrot
House. A second pair of Hyacinth Macaws was received in 2001. The birds
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997081" page_id="56500632"  page_num="72" year="" vol="">
72
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.572096" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500632" page_num="72" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - CHESTER ZOO BIRD REVIEW 2002
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.971179904761905" page_id="56500632"  page_num="72" year="" vol="">
of the first pair, although from unrelated parents, were raised together. It
was considered that this might have been one of the reasons they had shown
no breeding behaviour. When all four were moved into their new quarters
they were given the opportunity to re-pair but none of the birds chose to
select a new partner.
The original pair clearly appreciated the move to new quarters and
demonstrated this by laying eggs for the first time soon afterwards. Although
no chicks were hatched we feel this was an important step forward for this
pair. Another change has been to mix our Hyacinth Macaws with other
parrots, in this case a group of Blue-throated Conures Pyrrhura cruentata
and a pair of Blue-winged (Illiger's) Macaws Primolius ( Ara ) maracana.
With three parrots of very different sizes there is little obvious competition
between the three species and with careful positioning of the nest-boxes no
reason that this should also not succeed when it comes to breeding. One
bird, a Blue-throated Conure, was lost as the result of having been injured in
a collision in this new aviary but after 12 months this has been our only loss.
The Red-tailed Amazons again bred successfully with three fine chicks
reared. Yellow-backed Chattering Lories Lorius garrulus flavopalliatus also
bred. Disappointments included the Thick-billed Parrots that hatched a chick
but lost it when it was still in the nest.
The Golden Heart Pigeons Gallicolumba rufigula reared one chick and
following two unsuccessful attempts the Jambu Fruit Doves Ptilinopus jambu
also successfully fledged a chick. One Pink Pigeon Nesoenas mayeri was
also reared. The highlight was the breeding of a Victoria Crowned Pigeon
in the New Guinea large mixed aviary in the Islands in Danger exhibit. The
youngster has since been transferred to London Zoo. The White-naped
Pheasant Pigeons Otidiphaps nobilis aruensis that share this aviary with the
Victoria Crowned Pigeons spent much time calling but no eggs were laid
and there is now suspicion, judging by their behaviour, that they may be
two males. The Green-naped Pheasant Pigeons O. nobilis laid eggs but did
not hatch these because of disturbance by the aviary's other occupants, the
very inquisitive Red Birds of Paradise Paradisaea rubra . As the result of
that these two species no longer share the same aviary and we hope this
change may mean that the pheasant pigeons are successful this year.
Other pigeons bred included Speckled Pigeons Columba guinea and Rock
Doves C. livia. New to the collection were Socorro Doves Zenaida macroura
graysonii. We were pleased to receive a pair of these important doves through
Bristol Zoo and another from London Zoo. The Socorro Dove which is
extinct in the wild is the subject of a European Endangered Species Breeding
Programme (EEP) coordinated by Frankfurt Zoo.
West African Black Crowned Cranes Balearica p.pavonina were again
successful with four chicks reared. One difficulty we have had with these
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.443318" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500631" page_num="73" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - CHESTER ZOO BIRD REVIEW 2002
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998734" page_id="56500631"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
73
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998145142857142" page_id="56500631"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
cranes is that they breed late in the season. First clutches are normally laid
in the middle of July and if these are removed then second clutches, that are
usually laid about three weeks later, hatch in September when days are shorter
and our summer effectively over. These are not ideal conditions in which to
rear chicks outside. Moreover, if parents are left with their first clutch we
lose the opportunity to double clutch. In 2002 we allowed the parents to
hatch their first clutch and still got a second clutch from our breeding pair.
This was achieved by removing the first clutch of eggs for artificial incubation
then returning them after the second clutch had been laid. Having returned
the first clutch to the parents the second clutch was then placed in the
incubator. This worked because the re-lay interval is about a week shorter
than the incubation period. We further hedged our bets by returning only
two of the first clutch and hatching the third egg of the three-egg clutch
under a bantam, though in this case unusually, the bantam killed the chick.
The chick hatched by the parents was successfully reared by them, making
it Chester's first successful parent reared Black Crowned Crane. In previous
years chicks that had hatched under their parents had been lost before reaching
independence. The three eggs of the second clutch were artificially incubated
then divided between two bantams and made up the total of four chicks
reared.
Another first for Chester was the breeding of a Blue Crane Anthropoides
paradisea. For several years we have been artificially inseminating some
of the cranes at Chester Zoo. The Blue Cranes laid first in 2000 but the eggs
of both clutches proved to be infertile. Artificial insemination was attempted
in 2001 and although motile semen was obtained the timing was not perfect
and no fertile eggs resulted. In 2002 following the laying of the first egg the
female was artificially inseminated and the second egg was taken for artificial
incubation. This egg was fertile and was hatched under a bantam and foster
reared. Timing was better for the second clutch with the female inseminated
before the laying of her first egg. Two eggs were again laid and were replaced
with dummy wooden eggs whilst they were being artificially incubated.
Confident that the parents were sitting on the dummy eggs their own eggs
were returned to them a few days before they were due to hatch. Both
hatched but the novice parents appeared to spend more time patrolling the
boundaries of their enclosure than brooding or interacting with the chicks.
One disappeared and it was decided that as the second chick looked weak it
should be removed and fostered but despite this it failed to prosper.
Meanwhile the chick from the first clutch in the care of the bantam continued
to prosper and has grown into an excellent specimen.
Our Red-crowned Cranes Grus japonensis continue to lay eggs each
year but having successfully reared 13 chicks their offspring are now so
well represented in collections that unless we are requested to breed more
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998105" page_id="56500630"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
74
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.536249" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500630" page_num="74" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - CHESTER ZOO BIRD REVIEW 2002
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994296" page_id="56500630"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
we do not allow them to hatch their eggs. In contrast we continue to work
with our pairs of White-naped Cranes G. vipio and Wattled Cranes Bugeranus
carunculatus that despite artificial insemination continue to lay infertile eggs
each year. The male White-naped Crane is at least 54 years old. He was
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.418768" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500629" page_num="75" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - CHESTER ZOO BIRD REVIEW 2002
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.929158" page_id="56500629"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
75
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.5512375">
Schalow's Turaco.
Roger Wilkinson
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.724676" page_id="56500629"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
obtained by London Zoo from Mr Alfred Ezra in 1949 and was transferred
from Whipsnade to Chester in 1997. Despite this crane's age he still produces
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.989843" page_id="56500628"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
76
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.572833" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500628" page_num="76" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - CHESTER ZOO BIRD REVIEW 2002
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.981851647058824" page_id="56500628"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
motile semen so we will continue to work with him in the hope of improving
his founder representation in the breeding programme.
Another long term resident at Chester is the female Vermiculated Fishing
Owl Scotopelia bouvieri presented to the zoo in 1969. I have been told she
had flown onto a ship off the West African coast and was retrieved when the
ship docked in Liverpool. This owl is now at least 32 years old and was last
reported to have laid an egg in July 1999. However there is no opportunity
for breeding with her as no mate has been located for this bird which is
probably the only example of its species outside West Africa. The Great
Grey Owls Strix nebulosa did not nest in 2002 but the Spectacled Owls
Pulsatrix perspicillata reared one chick.
Our pair of Vietnamese Pheasants Lophura hatinhensis hatched and
reared two fine chicks which proved to be a male and a female. A Palawan
Peacock Pheasant Polyplectron emphanum was also reared. Other pheasants
fared less well and although Satyr Tragopans Tragopun satyra, Golden
Pheasants Chrysolophuspictus and Lady Amherst's Pheasants C. amherstiae
hatched chicks none of these were reared. A number of Roulroul Partridges
Rollulus roulroul were hatched but only one was reared.
The flamingos had another steady breeding season with eight Chilean
Flamingos Phoenicopterus chilensis and six Caribbean Flamingos P r. ruber
successfully reared. Twenty years ago Chester Zoo held just 19 Chilean
Flamingos and nine Caribbean Flamingos. Stock acquisitions, exchanges
and breeding increased the numbers to 28 Chilean and 41 Caribbean
Flamingos by the end of 1990. Since then a steady increase through the
number of chicks reared exceeding mortality of adults has allowed our flocks
to increase to 64 Chilean and 72 Caribbean Flamingos. This has been
extremely satisfying and I believe is a result of careful egg and colony
management by our bird staff. Although it is impossible to determine which
of our original wild caught flamingos is the oldest we know that one of our
Caribbean Flamingos, a female that was adult when she arrived from Chicago
in 1959, was continuing to lay eggs in 2000 when she was over 40 years old.
Ducks Unlimited... well almost! In 2002 we reared well over 100 ducks.
These included 19 Cuban Whistling Duck Dendrocygna arborea, 18 Marbled
Teal Marmaronetta angustirostris , three Falcated Teal Anas falcata, two
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.946100666666667">
Laysan Teal A. laysanensis , five Garganey A. querquedula, 14 Red-crested
Pochard Netta rufina, 22 Ferruginous Duck Ay thy a nyroca , seven Baer's
Pochard A. baeri , eight Mandarin Duck Aix galericulata, six Hooded
Merganser Mergus cucullatus and 11 White-headed Duck Oxyura
leucocephala. Three Red-breasted Geese Branta ruficollis , two Ross's Snow
Geese Anser rossii and a Black-necked Swan Cygnus melanocoryphus were
also bred.
Eleven Humboldt Penguin Spheniscus humboldti chicks were
successfully parent reared. A European Spoonbill Platalea leucorodia was
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.443435" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500627" page_num="77" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - CHESTER ZOO BIRD REVIEW 2002
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997554" page_id="56500627"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
77
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.79566452" page_id="56500627"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
hand-reared but unfortunately those chicks left with the parents failed to
survive.
In 2002 we re-paired our European Black Vultures Aegypius monachus.
Our female was transferred to Amsterdam and replaced by a new female
from Wassenar, which laid within less than three months of arriving here.
Although the egg was later found broken it gives us great encouragement
for the future.
In the free-flight area of the Tropical Realm new acquisitions included a
group of Java Sparrows Padda oryzivora from Rotterdam Zoo which to our
delight fledged at least six young. Pope Cardinals Paroaria dominicana
received from London Zoo also bred, rearing three young in their first year
at Chester. Softbills reared here and elsewhere in the collection, included
eight White-rumped Shamas Copsychus malabaricus, five Red-billed
Leiothrix (Pekin Robins) Leiothrix lutea, five Azure-winged Magpies
Cyanopica cyanea, four African Pied Starlings Spreo bicolor and two Bali
Starlings Leucospar rothschildi.
I had hoped for many years that we would be able to create suitable
enclosures at Chester to again house cassowaries. An opportunity arose in
2002 to develop an area previously used for some of our cats and our
carnivore team which assisted in planting and landscaping this area now
care for a magnificent Double-wattled Cassowary Casuarius casuarius. This
bird, a handsome female, was received from Paignton Zoo and we look
forward to locating a suitable mate for her. To breed cassowaries at Chester
- now that would be really exciting. That is what is so exciting about working
with birds, there is always another challenge.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.7963714">
Dr Roger Wilkinson, who was recently elected a Vice President of the
Avicultural Society, is Head of Conservation and Science, Chester Zoo,
Caughall Road, Upton-by-Chester, Chester CH2 1LH, UK. Tel:01244
380280IFax:01244 381352/Website:www.chesterzoo .org.uk/E-mail:
k .king sharp @ Chester zoo. co.uk
</reference>
<page confidence="0.994476" page_id="56500626"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
78
</page>
<table confidence="0.879776272727273" page_id="56500626"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
THE PURPLE-THROATED FRUITCROW Querula purpurata
by Malcolm Ellis
I felt sure that in the late 1950s, when I was working in the Bird House
at London Zoo, George Newmark had bought a male Purple-throated
Fruitcrow Querula purpurata , which he presented to the zoo. To my surprise
though, when I checked (London Zoo Notes by J. J. Yealland, Avicultural
Magazine Vol.64, No.3, pp.98-99 (1958)), I found that the bird had been a
Red-breasted or Scutated Fruitcrow Pyroderus scutatus, one of the larger of
the Cotingidae; a species never previously represented in the zoo collection.
Copyright Chris Brack
Male Purple-throated Fruitcrow Querula purpurata at Wuppertal Zoo.
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.9754008" page_id="56500626"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
The Purple-throated Cotinga is slightly smaller, being about 30cm (12in)
in length, compared to the Red-breasted which measures 42cm (16V2in). In
spite of its name, the male of the former, has a crimson rather than a purple
throat, while the female is all-black. According to Snow (1982), Querula
purpurata is a highly social forest species, which lives in closely knit family
groups with a social organisation that seems to be unique in the family.
Although it is geographically one of the most widespread of the family and
in some areas is quite common, it remains little known (or did when Snow
wrote his monograph in 1982). Snow based his observations on a three
month study he made in southern Guyana in 1970.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.507761" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500625" page_num="79" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - PURPLE-THROATED FRUITCROW
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997212" page_id="56500625"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
79
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998323903225807" page_id="56500625"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
Pearson and Beletsky (2000) describe it as living in highly social flocks
of five to ten individuals, while the caption to the illustration of the male
and female on plate 53, states family groups of four to six. According to
them the birds seldom leave the canopy of primary lowland forest in the
Oriente (or Amazon lowlands, Ecuador) and the moist coastal forests of
north-western Ecuador. They advise would-be observers to listen for its
distinctive calls, which are loud and slurred whistles interspersed with "rude
hacking noises, like someone getting ready to spit"; adding, that if you try
mimicking their whistles, you can attract them close to you as they investigate
what they believe may be an intruder in their territory.
The Purple-throated Cotinga usually feeds in the manner typical of
cotingas, i.e. by seizing its food, both fruits and insects, while on the wing.
However, in Guyana, Snow (1982) regularly watched them pluck fruits from
two trees, while perched. He witnessed courtship display on only one
occasion. When in an attempt to entice a female away from the nest she was
building to a new site he had chosen, a male followed her among the tree
tops, calling repeatedly, spreading his throat-fan and shivering his tail.
In the Guyana study, two nests were found; one 35ft (11m) up, near the
top of a slender tree and the second about 70ft (22m) up in a tree. The first
was a loose cup, consisting partly of twigs and partly of dry fruiting panicles
of a vine which hung down from a neighbouring tree and had been
incorporated into the nest so that the seeding heads hung down in a fringe
around the bottom of it. Only the female incubated the egg, which could be
seen against the sky through the bottom of the nest when the female was off
it. The egg hatched after 25 days. All four adults, two males, the female
and a fourth bird, brought food to the nest, though in unequal amounts.
The chick was fed almost entirely on insects, with (from day 12) a fruit
being observed being brought to the nest on only four occasions. The young
bird left the nest when it was 32 or 33 days old.
Raymond Sawyer had two males for many years and now has a pair
which have carried nesting material but has yet to build a nest.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.985841" genericHeader="references" page_id="56500625" page_num="79" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.99145325">
Pearson D. L. and Beletsky, L. 2000. Ecuador and its Galapagos Islands The Ecotravellers'
Wildlife Guide. Academic Press, London and San Diego.
Snow, D. 1982. The Cotingas Bellbirds, Umbrellabirds and their allies. British Museum (Natural
History) &amp; Oxford University Press, London and Oxford.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.991496" page_id="56500624"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
80
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.991736" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500624" page_num="80" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE WRINKLED HORNBILL Aceros corrugatus
AT PAIGNTON ZOO ENVIRONMENTAL PARK
</sectionHeader>
<author confidence="0.314838">
by Jo Gregson
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.256744">
Paignton Zoo Environmental Park succeeded in breeding the Wrinkled
</affiliation>
<bodyText confidence="0.995788805555556" page_id="56500624"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
Hombill Aceros corrugatus during 2002. The pair receive very similar care
to our pair of Papuan Wreathed or Blyth's Hombills A . plicatus, which
reared two chicks in 2001, a breeding which I described in the Avicultural
Magazine Vol.107, No.4, pp.165-166.
Getting our two Wrinkled Hombills to live together successfully was far
from straightforward. In our experience this is a difficult time for young
males and care needs to be taken. Our male was hatched at Chester Zoo in
1995 and was acquired by Paignton Zoo the following year. When it arrived
here in 1996 it was not yet old enough to place with our female, which
arrived in 1986, following a seizure by Customs &amp; Excise. We first
introduced them to each other in 1997, but this and subsequent introductions
during the following two years proved unsuccessful. Sometimes they would
stay together for a few months before the male began to lose condition and
had to be removed. The female was never seen to attack him, she simply
seemed to ignore him. At other times they were kept in separate aviaries
side by side, but the female continued to take no interest in him.
The pair was finally successfully introduced in 1999, when the male
was four years old and had more about him, though the female remained
dominant. She remained sealed in the nest-box for three months, however,
no eggs or chicks were ever seen. The following year there was no breeding
activity, as the pair was settling into new accommodation. This comprises
an outside aviary measuring 3m x 5m x 4m high (approx. 9ft 9in x 16ft x
13ft high) with an adjoining inside area measuring 2m x 3m x 4m high
(approx. 6ft 6in x 9ft 9in x 13ft high). All our Asian hombills prefer to nest
indoors and it is important that the inside area is as high or higher than the
outside area, also that the pop-hole between the inside and outside quarters
is at the highest point.
The nest-box is hung inside at a height of 2.5m (approx. 8ft 2m). It
measures 65cm x 40 cm x 50cm high (approx. 1ft l l hi n x 1ft 4in x 1ft Sin
high), and has a landing ledge measuring 20cm x 40cm (approx. Sin x 1ft
4in). The entrance hole measures 20cm x 20cm (approx. Sin x Sin) and is at
the centre of the narrower side. For plastering we supply a puddle clay
mixed with dry leaves and peat, the birds use some of this but mostly prefer
to use their own faeces and food.
Once settled into their new accommodation, the hombills' condition
improved greatly. Wrinkled Hombills are the 'grease monkeys' of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.729649" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500623" page_num="81" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - WRINKLED HORNBILL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997703" page_id="56500623"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
81
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.968565130434783" page_id="56500623"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
rainforest; it is not easy, even at the best of times, to get them into tip-top
condition. They are tacky to the touch and when in poor condition they
become even greasier and lose their waterproofing and insulation.
As a point of interest, we have found that our .male Wrinkled Hornbill
and male Rhinoceros Hornbill Buceros rhinoceros do not attain all their tail
feathers when their condition is not right. Obviously a bird with hardly any
or no tail feathers is not in the best of condition. Often a bird that looks
good, with only one or two tail feathers missing, has still not quite 'hit the
spot' and is unlikely to have a successful breeding season.
In 2001, the female was sealed inside the box by February. Keepers
reported hearing chicks during May, but when the box was inspected July
1st, there were no chicks inside, only an addled egg. Early in 2002 the birds
began plastering again and the female was sealed inside the box by the end
of February. A chick was heard on March 20th. May 30th one chick left the
nest-box. Six months later the female was continuing to feed the chick, but
the family behaviour had become more fractious and as a precaution the
chick was moved to an adjacent aviary. At nine months old it was showing
a few black feathers around the face, indicating that it is a female and not a
male as we had thought at six months old.
It was reared on a diet mainly of mice, pinkies at first, then fluffs, followed
later by small adult mice. The adults' diet consists of mixed chopped fruit,
mealworms, mice, cooked minced (ground) beef and boiled egg, all dusted
with SA37.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.64129025" page_id="56500623"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
Jo Gregson is Senior Head Keeper of Birds at Paignton Zoo
Environmental Park, Totnes Road, Paignton, Devon TQ4 7EU, UK.
Tel:01803 697500/Fax: 01803 523457/ Website: www.paigntonzoo.org.uk/
E-mail: jgregson@paigntonzoo.org.uk
</table>
<page confidence="0.995819" page_id="56500622"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
82
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9947405" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500622" page_num="82" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
BIRDS OF VENEZUELA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998408657894737" page_id="56500622"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
For those interested in the birds of Venezuela this book is essential. In
1978, Meyer de Schauensee and Phelps Jr. broke new ground in field guides
for South America with their Birds of Venezuela. At the time that book was
innovatory in many ways and became invaluable. Subsequent guides for
other South American countries soon equalled and then surpassed it, most
notably in the amount of behavioural detail and the percentage of species
covered.
Now, with this new book, Hilty has moved the bar higher once again. In
my opinion this is simply the best guide currently available to the birds of
any South American country. It is 875 pages of valuable and accurate
information, and it is hefty, weighing in at nearly 51bs (2.2kg), but is worth
any inconvenience this may cause. Entitled, Birds of Venezuela, Second
Edition , it is listed as a revised edition of the 1978 book. This is a rather
foolish understatement by the publisher for with the exception of the 34
plates by Guy Tudor from the first book, it is completely new and original.
There are now 67 plates mostly in colour, many of them competely new, by
John Gwynne mostly, with a few others by Sophie Webb and one by
Alexander Grajal. All are excellent. They show every single species in the
book, with many variations of plumage, such as females and juveniles where
noticeably different. In addition there are some 44 invaluable colour photos
of habitats. As well as coloured maps showing relief and vegetation zones.
The excellent graphics apart, it is really Hilty's book. Dr Steve Hilty is
an authority on Neotropical birds, his book on the birds of Colombia remains
the standard for that country and is unlikely to be surpassed. He has published
many scientific papers in ornithological journals and working as a bird tour
leader in the Neotropics has given him unrivalled experience of the subject.
The text sets a new standard in my opinion. Each family, subfamily and
genus usually has a short introduction, and a typical species account has the
English name, scientific name and local Spanish name. There follow sections
on Identification, Distinguishing it from similar species, Voice, Behaviour,
Status and Habitat, and Range. There is a map for each species showing its
expected or probable range, spots where it has been collected and sighted.
I have been working with this book during my researches for drafting
species accounts for a book on the birds of northern South America. Maybe
it is because I know Venezuela better than the other countries and know the
birds here often fairly well, that I have been so impressed by the wealth of
detail and the accuracy of the text. Steve Hilty went to great lengths in his
research for this book, as I saw when in the course of this research he visited
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909722" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500621" page_num="83" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998695" page_id="56500621"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
83
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.994890285714286" page_id="56500621"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
us here at the Phelps Ornithological Collection in Caracas. His
professionalism shows.
Birds of Venezuela (ISBN 0 7136 64185) is published in the UK by A &amp;
C Black (website: www.acblack.com). Price #40.00. it is available from
Hampshire Breeders and Books, 12 Inwood Road, Liss, Hampshire GU33
7LZ, UK. Credit card orders Tel/Fax :01730 301340. Price #45.00 including
postage in the UK.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.911561" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500621" page_num="83" year="" vol="">
Robin Restall
LOROS DE COLOMBIA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.976829225806452" page_id="56500621"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
Several important works on Neotropical parrots have been published in
the past few years. These include books on the parrots of Venezuela, Mexico,
Brazil and now Colombia. The importance of these works is that they are
by Latin American ornithologists, rather than North Americans or Europeans
who for so many years conducted much of the research on parrots in the
field, a fact only too evident by reviewing any of the major works on these
birds. Latin American ornithologists and field researchers are now making
a tremendous impact, bringing to light much new information and giving us
all a fresh look at parrots in the wild.
Some time ago, I reviewed a book on the parrots of Brazil, Ecologia e
conservacao depsittacideos no Brasil , edited by M.Galetti and M. A. Pizzo.
It is a masterpiece in my opinion. Loros de Colombia by Jose Vicente
Rodriguez-Camacho and Jorge Ignacio Hernandez Camacho, published
recently and the subject of this review, is another. As with the book on
Brazilian parrots, the only fault I can find is that there is no English summary.
An English edition or even a Spanish edition with an English summary
would have broadened considerably the market of this book.
Colombia has an extremely rich biota that includes 1,850 birds, 700
amphibians (100 of which have yet to be named), 520 reptiles, 3,200 fish
and 445 mammals. Its fauna - like its flora - is not yet fully investigated and
this becomes evident from reading the text. There is mention of a possible
new conure and of the probable existence of the Hyacinth Macaw
Anodorhynchus hyacinthinus in Colombia, given that it is known to the
Desana tribe in the Mapori River area (an affluent of the Vaupes River). Its
occurrence as in Paraguay probably represents migrants in search of food;
indeed the Desana name translates to "visitor".
The book deals with the origin of parrots, parrots in history (including
the origin of Spanish names), plumage art (encompassing tapirare or a method
employed by Indians to obtain coveted red and yellow feathers from
otherwise green birds), ethnozoology; there is a description of each species
(54) and a wealth of biological data.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996521" page_id="56500620"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
84
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.970645" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500620" page_num="84" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993703066666667" page_id="56500620"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
Data available from Amerindians is touched upon. This can shed light
on the biology of parrots, as well as possible causes of their decline and
even fascinating anecdotes. Folklore from the Department of Boyaca relates
the story of a waif Muisca girl named Mayavita, who collected feathers to
give creation to two birds (Scarlet Macaws Ara macao) to give herself flight.
These took her to an Eden and there they fed her - she in turn taught the
birds to talk. There is also reference to the Okina tribe using Orange-winged
Amazons Amazona amazonica for food, and of the sacrifice of birds trained
to talk so they can carry messages to the Sun God Sua.
This book offers such excellent information that I recommend purchasing
it, even if you are not fluent in Spanish (an appropriate dictionary will help).
The information is so fresh, so extensive and so interesting that the effort
will be worthwhile. Or, buy it simply for the excellent plates.
Loros de Colombia is published in Colombia by Conservacion
Intemacional and is available from Conservation International, Tropical Field
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.926702" page_id="56500620"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
Guide Series, 1919 M Street NW, Suite 600, Washington DC 20036, USA.
E-mail:jvrm@tutopia.com Price US$12.00 plus mailing.
Derian A. L. Silva Moraton
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.92788" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56500620" page_num="84" year="" vol="">
HUMMINGBIRDS OF COLOMBIA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998382631578947" page_id="56500620"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
As a fledgling photographer at the age of 12 Luis Mazariegos took his
first photographs in his native Colombia's Munchique Natural Park.
Gradually his photographic skills improved. Twenty years ago he met a
professional photographer who taught him the technique of stroboscopic
photography. A small Australian parakeet was the studio model for which
carefully timed flashes of light were used. Using the heavy electronic
equipment in the field was another matter. It did not take kindly to the heat
and humidity of steaming tropical forests. Mazariegos persevered, lugging
the equipment to remote parts of Colombia over mountain footpaths and
jungle trails. On one occasion his boat capsized on the Amazon and he
came close to losing his photographs - as well as his life.
The fascinating hummingbirds with their amazing variety of colours and
adornments were the subjects of his quests. Colombia has the enviable
number of more than 150 species of these avian jewels, whose very names
stir the imagination: Emerald-bellied Puffleg, Amethyst Woodstar, Great
Sapphirewing, Coppery Emerald, Rainbow-bearded Thombill. The reality
is often even more dazzling than the name. No other book on hummingbirds
has depicted so many species from one country. One hundred and ten species
have been captured by Mazariegos' lenses over a period of 20 years. They
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.90969" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500619" page_num="85" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996084" page_id="56500619"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
85
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.987591333333333" page_id="56500619"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
are all shown feeding on flowers (such as the incredible Palicourea with its
pink candyfloss blossoms), adding to the beauty of the pictures - as if the
hummingbirds themselves were not gorgeous enough.
Anyone who has tried to photograph hummingbirds in the wild knows
how difficult it is to capture the iridescence that characterises their plumage
(except that of the hermit hummingbirds) and to produce photographs in
which the wings are little more than blurs. Mazariegos art as a photographer
combined with the beauty of his subjects has resulted in one of the most
beautiful books I have ever seen.
The photographs are complemented by thoughtful articles written by
four Colombian biologists. They cover such subjects as the natural history
of hummingbirds, co-evolution of hummingbirds and flowers, and
biodiversity and conservation. There is a list of all the hummingbirds found
in Colombia with the region they inhabit, various maps of the country and
an appendix illustrating hummingbird flight.
Of course not all the species illustrated are endemic to Colombia, thus
the book shows more than 60% of Ecuador's hummingbirds, nearly 70% of
Venezuela's and 50% of the species in Panama. For me it was a glittering
reminder of some of the unforgettable species I have seen in the wild.
Hummingbirds of Colombia (ISBN 958-33-1632-6) is a large format
book of 356 pages. It is distributed in the UK by NHBS Ltd., 2-3 Wills
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.56061125" page_id="56500619"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
Road,Totnes, Devon TQ9 5XN. Tel:01803 865913 (International:+44 1803
865913)/Fax:01803 865280 (International: +44 1803 865280)/E-
mail:nhbs@nhbs.co.uk Price #38.50.
Rosemary Low
</table>
<page confidence="0.991603" page_id="56500618"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
86
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.973225" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500618" page_num="86" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
CONGRATULATIONS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8085385" page_id="56500618"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
Congratulations to The Avicultural Society of South Australia Inc.
which on February 10th celebrated its 75th Anniversary. Congratulations
also to Paradise Park Wildlife Sanctuary, Hayle, Cornwall, which this year
celebrates the 30th Anniversary of its opening in 1973. It is also home to the
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.700878" page_id="56500618"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
World Parrot Trust which was established there in 1989.
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.780754" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500618" page_num="86" year="" vol="">
ARACARIBRED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.92093225" page_id="56500618"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
London Zoo has succeeded in breeding the Black-necked Aracari
Pteroglossus aracari. It is almost certainly the first time this species has
been bred in the UK. The egg was artificially incubated and the chick was
hand-reared by the staff there.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.789513" page_id="56500618"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.712363" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500618" page_num="86" year="" vol="">
HYBRID TURACOS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.976190857142857" page_id="56500618"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
A recent paper in Alauda 70, pp.247-251, recorded the occurrence of
White-cheeked Turaco Tauraco /. leucotis x Prince Ruspoli's Turaco T.
ruspoli hybrids in southern Ethiopia. It is suggested that habitat degradation
and fragmentation may have led to hybridisation between these two species
which are normally ecologically separated. Prince Ruspoli's Turaco is a
globally threatened species and the occurrence of hybrids may have
implications for its conservation.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.848932" page_id="56500618"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.892218" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500618" page_num="86" year="" vol="">
FRUITFUL COLLABORATION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998493454545455" page_id="56500618"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
As the result of collaboration between Disney's Animal Kingdom Avian
Research Center (ARC) and San Diego's Avian Propagation Center (APC),
a total of 18 Long-tailed Broadbills Psarisomus dalhousiae were successfully
hand-reared in 2002. This cooperation began in 2001 when chicks were
hatched at both institutions, but unfortunately, the parents failed to rear the
clutches of up to eight chicks per nest. Hand-rearing was attempted, but out
of 26 chicks hatched only seven survived and these were in poor health.
Throughout 2002 all available rearing and developmental data, as well as
veterinary and nutrition advice, was shared between the two departments,
leading to this outstanding success. A template for future hand-rearing by
other institutions can be acquired by contacting Disney's Chelle Plasse by
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.6231655" page_id="56500618"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
e-mail:Chelle .Plasse@disney.com
* * *
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700245" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500617" page_num="87" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994023" page_id="56500617"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
87
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996705" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500617" page_num="87" year="" vol="">
AN IDEAL REFUGE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995521545454546" page_id="56500617"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
When it was feared that the Superb Lyrebird Menura novaehollandiae
might become extinct in New South Wales and Victoria, naturalists believed
that Tasmania's deep mountain gullies and fern glades might prove an ideal
refuge. So, in 1934, they took a pair from Victoria to central Tasmania.
Over the next 15 years a further 22 were released on the island. Successive
generations have gradually spread from the initial release sites and following
a rapid increase in the last decade, it is calculated that there may now be
some 8,200 Superb Lyrebirds in Tasmania.
Evidence is emerging that their powerful feet scratching for food on the
soft ground could slowly change the ecosystem in the island's World
Heritage-listed forests.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.826635" page_id="56500617"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.961161" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500617" page_num="87" year="" vol="">
CHRISTMAS ISLAND BIRDS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.977130625" page_id="56500617"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
Christmas Island is a remote Australian Territory in the Indian Ocean
covered by lush, tropical rainforest. This volcanic island is a haven for a
number of rare birds that nest there. Landbirds include two species found
nowhere else: the Christmas Island Imperial Pigeon Ducula whartoni and
the Christmas Island Hawk-Owl Ninox natalis. A subspecies of the Brown
Goshawk Accipiter fasciatus , the Christmas Island Goshawk A./, natalis is
found only on Christmas Island as is the Christmas Island Thrush Turdus
poliocephalus erythropleurus - a subspecies of the widespread Island Thrush
T. poliocephalus .
The above information comes from an envelope (produced by Australia
Post) on the front of which is a colour photo of the Christmas Island Thrush,
above the words - Christmas Island Birds. The Christmas Island Thrush is
also shown on one of the two stamps on the envelope, used by a friend in
Australia to send a number of newspaper cuttings and a postcard showing
the Southern Cassowary Casuarius casuarius johnsonii with the plea - Save
Me.
Only an estimated 1,500 are left in the wild. The postcard is addressed
to: The State Member of Parliament, c/~ CAFNEC, P0. Box 323N, North
Cairns, Queensland 4870. It points out that the survival of this bird, which
is the subject of international attention, is crucial to the survival of the
remaining tropical rainforests of the far north of Queensland. More than
1,100,000 hectares (over 2,000,000 acres) of native vegetation was cleared
in 1999-2001 and clearing continues unabated and is the biggest threat to
Queensland's unique and incredible biodiversity. It calls on The State
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.821574666666667">
Member of Parliament to support protecting the remaining habitat of the
Southern Cassowary in Queensland. -The card is published by the Cairns
and Far North Environment Centre Inc. (website: www.cafnec.org.au).
</reference>
<page confidence="0.997016" page_id="56500616"  page_num="88" year="" vol="">
88
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.982621" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500616" page_num="88" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
YEAR OF THE TROGON
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997276804878049" page_id="56500616"  page_num="88" year="" vol="">
In the Vogelpark Walsrode Inventory 2002, the VPW team report that
although the number of birds kept and bred was similar to that of 2001,
2002 proved to be an especially exciting year with an unusually high number
of first breedings. These were rather unexpected, as many changes had
been made, with small units having been combined into larger aviaries with
more naturalistic interiors matching species specific requirements with
particular regard to habitat preferences and social organization.
In January a pair of Javan Trogons Apalharpactes reinwardi showed
interest in a nest-box, which proved to be the beginning of a surprisingly
successful trogon breeding season. As well as Javan Trogons, Diard's
Trogons Harpactes diardii and Red-headed Trogons H. erythrocephalus
reared young. In addition, two pairs of White-tailed Trogons Trogon viridis,
a species bred first at Walsrode in 1995, laid eggs and four chicks were
raised. Unfortunately, the female Red-headed Trogon died later as the result
of egg binding. Walsrode now has small groups of all four species and
hopes to succeed in establishing self-sustaining populations of one or more
of these species.
In the Avicultural Magazine Vol.108, No.3, pp. 113-122 (2002), Dieter
Rinke and Bemd Marcordes described breeding the Blue-tailed or Banded
Pitta Pitta guajana at Vogelpark Walsrode. By the end of 2002, the two
pairs had produced an astonishing 31 young. There were many more eggs,
some of which were infertile or lost and a few young chicks disappeared.
The rearing of 31 young hopefully marks a major breakthrough in the captive
breeding of these birds only bred sporadically.
The Kagus Rhynochetos jubatus hatched two chicks at the beginning of
2002, then took a break until November, when both pairs started laying
again and another chick was hatched just before Christmas. Chicks were
reared of three of the less commonly bred species of crane, the Wattled
Bugeranus carunculatus , Black-necked Grus nigricollis and Black Crowned
Crane Balearica pavonina. At Walsrode they also succeeded in breeding
for the first time the Pink-eared Duck Malacorhynchus membranacea . This
small Australian species has specific feeding requirements and is rather
delicate, and its ducklings were particularly difficult to rear.
During 2002, Walsrode suffered a number of set-backs with its birds of
paradise. The breeding females of both the Greater Paradisaea apoda and
Red Bird of Paradise P. rubra were lost. The King Birds of Paradise
Cicinnurus regius produced several eggs, but none of the chicks were reared.
Its young female Superb Bird of Paradise Lophorina superba laid two
clutches of eggs, but possibly due to the male's age, all were infertile.
After several failures in 2001, the rarely kept White-crowned Hombills
Berenicornis comatus fledged a chick which went on to develop into a strong
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.699916" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500615" page_num="89" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996949" page_id="56500615"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
89
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.913496916666667" page_id="56500615"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
male bird. For the first time, Walsrode bred Golden Conures Guaruba
guarouba and Blue-headed Macaws Ara couloni. Keas Nestor notabilis
reared two chicks and the rarely kept subspecies Eclectus roratus riedeli
also fledged two chicks.
Walsrode's Madagascan birds continued to do well. Three pairs of
Madagascar Crested Ibis Lophotibis cristata between them fledged a total
of five young. The Crested Couas Coua cristata bred again but the survival
rate of the chicks was rather low in 2002. For the first time a pair of Sickle-
billed Vangas Falculea palliata, a rather delicate species, produced a clutch
of four eggs from which one chick was reared. It is the first vanga ever to
have been bred in captivity.
Long-tailed Ground-roller
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.991003" page_id="56500614"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
90
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.920934" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500614" page_num="90" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.988823083333333" page_id="56500614"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
New acquisitions by Project Tsimbazaza, a joint programme between
Parc Botanique et Zoologique de Tsimbazaza (PBZT) and Vogelpark
Walsrode, included both Long-tailed Uratelornis chimaera and Pitta-like
Ground-roller Atelornis pittoides, which seem never before to have been
kept in captivity. Two Long-tailed Ground-roller chicks were successfully
reared at PBZT, an outstanding event achieved with the cooperation of
Walsrode. Walsrode also cooperated in the complete renovation of the PBZT
bird centre, the training of staff, and the overall improvement of conditions
for the maintenance and breeding of indigenous Madagascan birds.
At Vogelpark Walsrode, 992 birds of 192 species were reared successfully
in 2002. The total number of birds held there at the end of 2002 was 3,241
individuals of 599 species and subspecies.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.232327" page_id="56500614"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
* * *
IN HEALTH AND DISEASE
Prof. John E. Cooper, FRCVS, has written from The University of the
West Indies, Faculty of Medical Sciences, School of Veterinary Medicine,
Trinidad, where he is teaching, to say how very much he and his wife,
Margaret, enjoyed reading 'Some famous aviculturists I have known' by
Raymond Sawyer ( AviculturalMagazine Vol.108,No.3, pp.100-109). They
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.970925888888889" page_id="56500614"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
enjoyed it all the more so because of the links to friends in East Africa. Also
of great interest was the reference (News &amp; Views p 142) to Dr Jean-Marie
Derscheid's notes and papers on the history of Rwanda, where John and
Margaret were working recently.
John has had another book published. Described as invaluable for
birdkeepers and vets - Captive Birds in health and disease - is a practical
guide for those who keep gamebirds, raptors, parrots, waterfowl and other
birds. Priced #25 (plus #2.50 p&amp;p UK and Eire/#3.50 continental Europe),
it is published by the World Pheasant Association, which moved recently to:
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.3675775" page_id="56500614"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
7-9 Shaftesbury Street, Fordingbridge, Hampshire SP6 1JF, UK. Tel: 01425
6571 29/Website:www.pheasant.org uk
* * *
IN BELGIAN NATIONAL BIOGRAPHY
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.886264428571429">
Daniel A. Reboussin, University of Florida, has written to say that he
has found an excellent biographical piece on Jean-Marie Derschied (see
above and News &amp; Views Vol. 108,No.3,pp 141-142 (2002)) in the Belgian
National Biography. He has provided the following reference: Brien, Paul.
1971. "De sc hied (Jean-Marie-Eugene-Leon-Charles)." Biographic
Nationale v. 37:211-235. Academic Royale des Sciences, des Lettres et des
Beaux-Arts de Belgique. (Supplement Tome 9, IV fasc.).
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700031" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500613" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.985114" page_id="56500613"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
91
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996614" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500613" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
IMPORTANT UK FIRST
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.979401285714286" page_id="56500613"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
Earlier this year Chester Zoo's female Red Bird of Paradise Paradisaea
rubra hatched and reared two chicks, mainly on a diet of waxmoth larvae,
locusts and fruit (the female proved to be especially partial to blueberries).
Received on breeding loan from Bronx Zoo, New York, in 1999, the male
and female hatched there in 1998. Now aged just over five years old, the
male only recently acquired tail streamers but otherwise remains in immature
plumage.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.863991" page_id="56500613"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.638045" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500613" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
DISAPPEARING HORNBILLS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9950165625" page_id="56500613"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
The Southern Ground Hombill Bucorvus leadbeateri has disappeared
from about 70% of its historical range in South Africa, where there is now
an estimated population of just 1,500-2,000 birds, and it is thought to be
suffering a similar dramatic decline in numbers over the rest of southern
Africa. This is due mainly to habitat alteration, the loss of large hollow
trees used for nesting, persecution by farmers and other landowners, and
indirect poisoning.
The female hombill usually lays one to two eggs and incubates them for
about 42 days. As the eggs are normally laid three to five days apart and
incubation begins as soon as the first egg is laid, there is a marked difference
in size between the chicks. The larger first chick normally out-competes its
younger sibling for food and within a few days the second chick dies.
Now, second-hatched chicks from nests in the Kruger National Park are
being rescued and reared, and along with birds in need of relocation from
farming areas, are being used in a project in which groups of these hornbills
are being reintroduced into suitable areas of wild habitat.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.805503" page_id="56500613"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
The Ground Hombill Research and Conservation Project started in 1999
on Mabula Game Reserve, near Warmbaths, in South Africa.
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.955819" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500613" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
GIANT IBIS FOUND
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996134333333333" page_id="56500613"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
When in 2000-2001 Wildlife Conservation Society (WCS) conservation-
ists in collaboration with Cambodia's Ministry of Agriculture, Forestry and
Fisheries and the Ministry of the Environment surveyed the northern plains
of Cambodia, closed to outsiders for 30 years by the Khmer Rouge, they
found the world's largest population of the Critically Endangered Giant Ibis
Pseudibis gigantea. They were able to describe the nest for the first time
and took the first photos of this rare species. The Cambodian Government
has now given protected status to a large area of the northern plains, centered
on what appears to be the heartland of this population.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995148" page_id="56500606"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
92
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9810755" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500606" page_num="92" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
OFF TO CAROLINA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993468714285714" page_id="56500606"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
On October 31st the National Bird of Prey Centre, Newent,
Gloucestershire, will close to the public and many of the birds will be moved
to the South Carolina Center for Birds of Prey, USA. Called originally the
Falconry Centre, the former was founded in 1967 by falconer Philip Glasier,
father of the present Director Jemima Parry-Jones MBE, who took over in
1985. Many birds of prey have been bred there, several for the first time,
one of the most notable being Verreaux's Eagle Aquila verreauxii in 1991.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.80208" page_id="56500606"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998342" genericHeader="general terms" page_id="56500606" page_num="92" year="" vol="">
ACTION PLAN FOR ENDANGERED PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.945122896551724" page_id="56500606"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
Classified as Endangered under lUCN/BirdLife International threat
criteria and listed on CITES Appendix II, the Cape Parrot Poicephalus
robustus is endemic to South Africa, where it is restricted to the fragmented
Afromontane forests of southern KwaZulu-Natal, Eastern Cape and Limpopo
Provinces. Key threats to its survival (the declining population is currently
estimated at approx. 650 individuals) are habitat destruction, seasonally
depleting food sources, shortage of suitable nest sites, illegal trapping for
trade, and psittacine beak and feather disease.
The Cape Parrot Working Group (CPWG), which aims to conserve the
Cape Parrot and its habitat in South Africa, was formed in 2001 following
research by the late Olaf Wirminghaus at the University of Natal. This
identified its major ecological requirements and conservation threats and
confirmed that it is a separate species, distinct from the Grey-headed Parrot
P.fuscicollis suahelicus and Brown-necked Parrot P.f.fuscicollis.
The major recommendations of the Action Plan, formulated at a three-
day workshop organised by the CPWG in conjunction with BirdLife South
Africa, are to provide alternative development opportunities for communities
living close to the forests within this parrot's range; develop environmental
education programmes; further ecological research; improve policy and the
legislation and law enforcement to support this; reduce the rate of the felling
of yellowwood trees ( Podocarpus spp. upon which it is heavily dependent
for food and nest sites); initiate the planting of food source trees; and develop
the CPWG into an organisation which has the resources to handle and carry
out the tasks detailed in the Action Plan.
Further information can be obtained from Louise Warburton (e-
mail:warburtonL@nu.ac.za) or Steven W. Evans (e-mail: iba@birdlife.
org.za). Should you wish to make a donation to help conserve the Cape
Parrot and its Afromontane yellowwood forest habitat, cheques should be
sent to: BirdLife South Africa, PO. Box 515, Randburg, 2125, South Africa.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700246" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500607" page_num="93" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.989543" page_id="56500607"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
93
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997677" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56500607" page_num="93" year="" vol="">
REDISCOVERED IN MYANMAR
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995429272727273" page_id="56500607"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
It is reported that the Critically Endangered Gurney&apos;s Pitta Pitta gurneyi
- named after John Henry Gurney (1819-1890), an English banker;
ornithologist and collector - has, after a great many years, been found again
in southern Myanmar (formerly Burma). The pitta was found at four lowland
forest sites, with a maximum of 10-12 pairs at one of these sites, all of
which are close to where this species has been collected in the past.
RirdLife International are urgently trying to identify the largest remaining
areas of suitable lowland forest habitat and hope to work with the relevant
authorities to develop an appropriate conservation strategy for them; and
will continue to work closely with the Thai authorities to protect the
dwindling population in southern Thailand.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.5918825" page_id="56500607"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
* * *
ONLINE INDEX
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.959488695652174" page_id="56500607"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
Some years ago when the late Harry Horswell was Hon. Secretary &amp;
Treasurer and Mary Harvey was Hon. Editor and the society was based at
Ascot, Dave Coles was encouraged to compile an index to the Avicultural
Magazine. On completion though, the job of typesetting it proved too
daunting and it was decided that the society could not at that time afford to
publish it.
Upon learning recently that it is still in existence and someone was typing
it out, the society was presented with an opportunity that was too good to
miss a second time around. Dave Coles was contacted and was keen to
update it so long as it would be made available this time. The council
enthusiastically agreed that upon it being updated it should be placed on the
society's website. The good news is that it will be completed following the
publication of Vol.109, No.4, and shortly afterwards will be available on
our website:www.avisoc.co.uk
Members (and non-members) wishing to consult back issues of the
magazine may be interested to know that there is a complete set (dating
back to 1894) in the library of the Zoological Society of London. It is
possible to purchase a one-day reference ticket to the library price #6.50, an
annual ticket price #17 or a student annual ticket price #12 (on production
of student ID). Proof of address is required on the first visit otherwise
admission will be refused. A photocopy service is also offered which has a
minimum charge of #4. Details can be found on the zoo website:www.zsl.org
The Natural History Museum, Akeman Street, Tring, Hertfordshire HP23
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.524551">
6AP (Tel:01442 824181), also has a complete set.
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.998286" page_id="56500608"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
94
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9829135" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500608" page_num="94" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
KEEPING CATS AWAY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986263142857143" page_id="56500608"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
Leading seed specialists and plant growers, Thompson &amp; Morgan of
Ipswich have recently introduced into the UK a plant which may prove to
be the first completely natural cat repellent. Coleus canina is a distant relative
of the popular house plant best known for its highly coloured and
extravagantly patterned leaves. Experiments indicate it could prove a
decorative and effective means of deflecting various unwelcome four-legged
visitors from gardens and the vicinity of aviaries. Cats apparently cannot
tolerate its pungent smell, and dogs and even foxes avoid it, while the human
nose is affected only when the plant is touched or handled.
Reaching a height of 38cm-45cm (15in-18in),it has excellent foliage and
small attractive spikes of blue flowers in summer. It prefers a position in
sun or part-shade and is ideal for bedding or borders. To be effective Coleus
canina needs to be established and well grown before its distinctive smell is
released. Plants can be up to 2m (approx. 6ft) apart. If they are planted in
containers they can be moved about when necessary to block off cat entry
points. They are not frost hardy and should be lifted in the autumn and
stored somewhere frost-proof and planted out again the following year.
Alternatively, cuttings can be taken in autumn and overwintered for planting
the following spring.
Coleus canina is available by mail order at #7.99 for six plants or
#12.99 for 12. Tel:01424 797877 (24-hour order line) or visit the Thompson
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.43059425" page_id="56500608"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
&amp; Morgan website:www.thompson-morgan.com
* * *
NEW LAGOON
In April San Diego Zoo's Caribbean Flamingos Phoenicopterus ruber
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.970782533333333" page_id="56500608"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
ruber took their first tentative steps into the completely redesigned Flamingo
Lagoon and apparently found it to their liking; for within days many of the
birds were engaged in nest building activities. Currently home to 71
Caribbean Flamingos, Flamingo Lagoon is designed to accommodate up to
100 birds, a number expected to be reached within the next few years as the
flock starts to breed. In the early 1980s, when a number of birds were
removed from the former Flamingo Lagoon, the remaining birds stopped
breeding for the next 14 years!
The Zoological Society of San Diego's Center for Reproduction of
Endangered Species (CRES) broke ground in June for a new US$22 million
state-of-the-art Arnold and Mabel Beckman Center for Reproduction of
Endangered Species, at San Diego Wild Animal Park. Expected to be in
operation late next year, it will incorporate the latest scientific technology
and serve as a workplace for international scientists to collaborate on
conservation research projects.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.691895" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500609" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.968185" page_id="56500609"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
95
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.923209" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56500609" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
WILDSOUNDS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8640687" page_id="56500609"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
Earlier this year, L. J. Driver of Bakersfield, Nottingham, wrote to say
that he thought members might be interested to know that some excellent
bird videos,&apos;along with CD-ROMs and sound recordings, are available from:
Wildsounds, Cross Street, Salthouse, Norfolk NR25 7XH, UK. Tel/
Fax:01263 741100/ Website: www.wildsounds.com/E~mail:sales
@ wildsounds .com
Wildsounds' latest catalogue offers a wide selection of atmosphere
recordings, sound guides, CD-ROMs, DVDs and videos, featuring birds
from various countries of the world. Also included in the catalogue is
recording equipment and a wide selection of bird guides.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.843565" page_id="56500609"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.918653" genericHeader="introduction" page_id="56500609" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
CORNCRAKE REINTRODUCTION PROJECT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9837094" page_id="56500609"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
This summmer a large number of Corncrakes Crex crex have been bred
at Whipsnade Wild Animal Park, Bedfordshire, and will be released from a
nature reserve in eastern England. The Corncrake is a migratory species
which winters in Africa and the following spring returns to breed in the
same area in which it hatched. Once common throughout the UK, its dramatic
decline was caused mainly by loss of habitat and agricultural intensification,
which led to the introduction of the combine harvester and earlier harvesting,
which resulted in the destruction of nests and birds. The Corncrake Project
is a joint venture between the Zoological Society of London, RSPB (Royal
Society for the Protection of Birds) and English Nature.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.5530635" page_id="56500609"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
* * *
SEABIRDS
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.983728625" page_id="56500609"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
There has been a marked increase lately in the keeping of seabirds. Here
in the UK, the #7 million (over US$10 million) Living Coasts complex
(part of Paignton Zoo Environmental Park), opened earlier this year in
Torquay, Devon. The exhibits include penguins, sea ducks, gulls and terns,
puffins and other auks. Loro Parque, Tenerife, Canary Islands, Spain, now
exhibits the largest group of Atlantic Puffins Fratercula arctica to be seen
in any European collection. With the permission of the Icelandic
Government, the birds were collected as nestlings last year in Iceland.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.794099">
Penguin and Puffin Coast, St Louis Zoo, Missouri, USA, opened May
23rd, is home to approximately 80 penguins - Humboldt Spheniscus
humholdti, Gentoo Pygoscelis papua, Rockhopper Eudyptes crestatus and
King Aptenodytes patagonica - and 30 puffins of two species - the Homed
F. corniculata and Tufted Lunda cirrhata - from the northern Pacific.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.994381" page_id="56500610"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
96
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.433383" page_id="56500610"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
w w w.eu-wildlifetrade .org
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993017" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500610" page_num="96" year="" vol="">
EASY ACCESS TO INFORMATION ON WILDLIFE
TRADE CONTROLS IN THE EU
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997289928571429" page_id="56500610"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
June 5th, TRAFFIC (the wildlife trade monitoring network of WWF
and IUCN) launched a website - www.eu-wildlifetrade.org - which provides
information on wildlife trade controls in the European Union (EU). Its aim
is to raise awareness of those involved in wildlife trade and inform them
about their legal responsibilities under EU Wildlife Trade Regulations.
In 11 EU languages it is an initiative of and financed by the European
Commission. The website was developed and is managed by TRAFFIC
Europe with support from the CITES management authorities of all EU
members.
Information on the website includes:
An explanation of the legal requirements for trade to, from and inside
the EU/ including the necessary documents and conditions to be observed.
Also specific provisions for trade in captive bom and bred animals.
Information on traders' and customers' obligations with regard to animal
welfare and especially the responsibility of traders in educating buyers of
exotic species. Links to other websites that offer advice and information
about the keeping and caring of commonly kept species and outlines of the
requirements applying to the transport and exhibition of live animals.
Marking requirements for certain live animals.
Details of legal obligations that apply to personal and non-commercial
use of wildlife.
More than 600 internet links to institutions, conventions, CITES materials
such as checklists and identification guides, nature conservation
organisations, hobbyist associations and commercial federations involved
in trade in exotic pets, zoological and botanical gardens.
The last page offers the opportunity to interact with website administrators
by making suggestions or comments and to ask questions should you have
specific enquiries.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.620334" page_id="56500610"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990522" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500610" page_num="96" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINES BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.943089333333333" page_id="56500610"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
A large stock is available including some early issues. Further details
are available from: The Membership Secretary, Stewart Pyper, 21 Primrose
Hill, Nunney, Frome, Somerset BAll 4NP, UK. Tel:01373 836293.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.735548692307692" page_id="56500611"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
DONATIONS RECEIVED 2000-2002
The society is most grateful to the following members for their generous
support:
R. Adams
Jan Louwman
S. Appleton
J. J. Mallet
D. R. Bayliss
G. Masson
R. A. Callaghan
G. Mulhaus
N. R. H. Dodds
N. O'Connor
</figure>
<construct confidence="0.92142245" page_id="56500611"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
K. W. Dolton
J. R. Padgett
Mrs W. Duggan
Ms. J. L. Pappas
Miss R. M. Ezra
A. Perkins
M. E. Fidler
P. J. Pheby
I. T. Forbes
A. J. Pittman
A. W. Gibbard
Dr H. Quinque
D. Goodwin
R. L. Restall
A. V. Griffiths
R. C. J. Sawyer
R. L. Henshaw
D. P. Shearing
Prof. J. R. Hodges
Dr K. C. Searle
</construct>
<figure confidence="0.974171615384615" page_id="56500611"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
H. Kapyla
J. Summers
R. Killingback
J. G. Thurlow
Koln Zoo
B. Tremlett
B. R. Kyme
J. Trollope
Ivo Lazzzeroni
J. K. Watson
Lars Lepperhoff
/Wi
Ackroyd's Australian Avitours
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.890101" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500611" page_num="" year="" vol="">
RAY ACKROYD&apos;S AUSTRALIAN BIRDWATCHING AND NATURALHISTORYTOURS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991587333333333" page_id="56500611"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
We offer adventure tours of the highest standard led by Ray Ackroyd a knowledgeable
and enthusiastic bush guide with 50 years outback experience.
Our tours are well priced and we travel with small groups for that exclusive personalised
service that is so hard to find in today's tourist industry.
Everybody has a window seat and our accommodation is modern and spacious.
So come down and discover Australia's unique fauna and flora, the tour of a life time:
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.924666">
Cockatoos, Parrots, Reptiles, Waterfowl, Kangaroos, Koalas, Wildflowers, Landscapes.
Many overseas aviculturists have travelled with us to date, all completely satisfied.
So please join Ray and our Hostess Beryl on the Australian Outback Tour of a Lifetime.
Enquiries for itineraries:
Ray Ackroyd's Australian Avitours, PO Box 44, Bringelly N.S.W., Australia.
Tel: 0247 748471 Email: cockatoosgalore@hotmail.com Fax: 029 8261639
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.986933" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500612" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION LIBRARIES
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.831080608695652" page_id="56500612"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
3 9088 01769 6501
The Tri-coloured Munia Lonchura malacca in Venezuela
by Robin Restall...49
Nest activity in Rhinoceros Hombills Buceros rhinoceros in
relation to artificial rainfall patterns
by David A. Oehler.53
Hombills in Thailand.57
The hand-rearing of a St Vincent Parrot Amazona guildingii
by Roger G. Sweeney.62
Chester Zoo Bird Review 2002
by Roger Wilkinson.69
The Purple-throated Fruitcrow Querula purpurata
by Malcolm Ellis.78
Breeding the Wrinkled Hombill Aceros corrugatus at Paignton Zoo
Environmental Park
by Jo Gregson.80
Book Reviews
Birds of Venezuela.82
Loros de Colombia.83
Hummingbirds of Colombia. 84
News &amp; Views.86
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</table>
</algorithms>
