<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.5799402" page_id="56260713"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 113
No. 1
2007
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260714" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990837" page_id="56260714"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2007 as for 2006: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.5855" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260714" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.972357" page_id="56260714"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, ARCADIA, THE MOUNTS, TOTNES, DEVON TQ9 7QJ, UK.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TN13 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail: Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998476" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260714" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982477333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.757519" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260715" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.229982" page_id="56260715"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 113 - No. 1 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2007
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.355428">
The Avicultural Society
</subsectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990856666666667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260715" page_num="" year="" vol="">
FOR THE STUDY OF BRITISH AND FOREIGN BIRDS
IN THE WILD AND CAPTIVITY
OFFICERS AND COUNCIL
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.6870576" page_id="56260715"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
As from September 16th 2006
President
Mrs R.M. Sawyer
Vice Presidents
F. Barnicoat (South Africa)
</table>
<construct confidence="0.944560428571429" page_id="56260715"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
J. M. Dolan Jr, PhD (USA)
C. J. S. Marler (UK)
The Rev. R. Noegel (USA)
Dr H. Quinque (France)
R. L. Restall (Venezuela)
R. C. J. Sawyer (UK)
Dr R. Wilkinson (UK)
</construct>
<figure confidence="0.96223719047619" page_id="56260715"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Honorary Editor
M. Ellis
Honorary Secretary - Treasurer
P. Boulden
Members of Council
R. S. Abrey
P. Convy
M. Curzon MBE
J. A. Ellis
Mrs L. Gardner
R. B. Girling
N. R. Hewston
G. Masson
S. Pyper
V. P. Sargent
P. G. Schofield
J. G. Thurlow
B. Tremlett
J. Trollope
Ms R. Wiseman
Chairman C.J.S. Marler
</figure>
<page confidence="0.890326" page_id="56260716"  page_num="2" year="" vol="">
2
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.542002" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260716" page_num="2" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE BLACK-THROATED BARBET
Tricholaema melanocephala
by Martin Davies
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998028085714286" page_id="56260716"  page_num="2" year="" vol="">
I acquired a pair of Black-throated Barbets from Phil Cleeton in early
summer 2006, with the intention of trying to breed this small East African
barbet.
The Black-throated Barbet is found in Sudan, Ethiopia, Somalia and
Kenya through to central Tanzania. It inhabits dry bush and woodland below
1,500m (approx. 4,925ft). In areas of slightly higher rainfall in Kenya and
Tanzania, it tends to be replaced by the very similar Spot-flanked Barbet T.
lachrymosa. Where their ranges overlap, the latter is mainly confined to
taller riverine vegetation. The Black-throated Barbet's call is very different
to that of the Spot-flanked Barbet, the former being more complex in make-
up and louder.
Like other African arboreal barbets the Black-throated species eats mainly
fruit, being particularly fond of figs. Insects also feature in its diet and are
taken from the surface of leaves and bark, it will also catch them on the
wing and will even hover to take insects. Caterpillars and shoots and buds
of acacia were among the food listed by Mackworth-Praed &amp; Grant (1957).
At the time I purchased my pair of Black-throated Barbets, I was in
close contact with Mike Curzon, who at the time had a pair of Spot-flanked
Barbets with successfully fledged young. Taking his advice and experience
on board, I set about making the flight for my Black-throated Barbets as
natural as possible. One of the keys to my breeding success was to provide
them with a well-rotted willow trunk (courtesy of Mike), so that the barbets
could make their own nest cavity. Within 24 hours of placing the log in the
flight both birds were busy excavating a hole in it. Interestingly, in a bid to
draw as little attention as possible to their nesting activity, the birds removed
the wood chips to the other side of the flight. Within four days the cavity
was complete and the pair began to roost in it each night.
Both birds were in great condition and got on together extreme well,
with no sign of aggression from either of them. The fact that they were both
in breeding condition at the same time was, I think, another key factor that
made my chance of breeding them so much stronger. In the past I have had
terrible trouble with tinkerbirds ( Pogoniulus ) not being in condition at the
same time and having to be separated from one another to stop fights
occurring. So, with both birds in good condition and the nest cavity made I
had high hopes.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.429288" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260717" page_num="3" year="" vol="">
DAVIES - BLACK-THROATED BARBET
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.900179" page_id="56260717"  page_num="3" year="" vol="">
3
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.31986">
Food
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.982867148148148" page_id="56260717"  page_num="3" year="" vol="">
At first the barbets fed almost exclusively on fruit and I discovered they
relished elderberries and pyracantha berries. Wax worms were also taken
but not in any quantity until the eggs hatched. Everything else supplied was
ignored.
Breeding
My notes on the breeding of this barbet are quite scant, as I was distracted
by my Black-capped Social Weavers Pseudonigrita cabanisi, which were
also breeding at the same time (see Avicultural Magazine Vol.l 12, No.3,
pp.l 19=122 (2006)). The barbets laid two eggs, one of which hatched and
the other was thrown out of the nest. The barbets were very vocal at this
time making a low-pitched "pee" whistle sound in short bursts and were
veiy bold and steady. The youngster was fed continually on the food provided
and flying insects caught on the wing by the parents. Mike had remarked on
how he had observed his Spot-flanked Barbets hawking flies and my Black-
throated Barbets did the same. After a surprisingly long time, 40 days, the
young barbet fledged successfully. The key differences between the parents
and the fledgling were the greater brightness of the yellow markings on the
fledgling's wings and the fact that it still lacked a serrated cutting edge to its
bill
At the time of writing (early January 2007) all three Black-throated
Barbets now reside with Mike Curzon, who has three species of small barbets
in his collection. If any member knows of other pairs of Black-throated
Barbets or odd birds, Mike and I would like to hear about them. We are
convinced that given the similarity between the Black-throated and Spot-
flanked Barbets, there may well be some other Black-throated Barbets that
were imported with other small barbets back in 2005, and perhaps their
owners have mistaken them for the Spot-flanked.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.51237" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56260717" page_num="3" year="" vol="">
Reference
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.9911148">
Mackworth-Praed, C.W. and Grant, C.H.B. 1957. Birds of Eastern and North Eastern Africa.
Vol. I. Second Edition. Longman, Green &amp; Co., London, New York, Toronto.
Martin Davies and Mike Curzon MBE are UK members who live in
Wiltshire. Mike Curzon can be contacted by Tel:01934 or E-mail:
mcurzonmbe@hotmail co. uk
</reference>
<page confidence="0.915427" page_id="56260718"  page_num="4" year="" vol="">
4
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.662085" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260718" page_num="4" year="" vol="">
CIRL BUNTING Emberiza cirlus
REINTRODUCTION PROJECT
by Jo Gregson
Overview
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.981985361111111" page_id="56260718"  page_num="4" year="" vol="">
The Cirl Bunting is a sedentary species that rarely strays more than a
mile (1.6km) or so from its winter and summer territories. Changes in
farming practises have caused small flocks of this species to become isolated
along the south Devon coastline. There is other suitable habitat along the
UK coastline but no corridors for the Cirl Bunting to move along. While
the Cirl Bunting has maintained and in many cases increased in number
there has been little expansion in its range.
During 2001 Paignton Zoo, the RSPB (Royal Society for the Protection
of Birds), The National Trust and English Nature combined forces to set up
the Cirl Bunting Reintroduction Project, with the aim of re-establishing the
Cirl Bunting in other parts of southern England. The first phase of the
project was to ascertain whether or not the Cirl Bunting could be hand-
reared from a young age without becoming imprinted and, of course, to
undertake research on the behaviour of the chicks in captivity. During 2001,
2003 and 2004 chicks were collected from the wild population (during 2002
the project was put on hold due to the outbreak in the UK of foot and mouth
disease). Over those three years the partners finely tuned their nest finding
and hand-rearing skills. They found that once independent the hand-reared
Cirl Buntings behave like wild birds and are very alert and quick to react to
any perceived threat.
Five donor sites were selected for the project. RSPB field workers closely
monitored the wild population to ensure that the birds were not under any
local pressures. Just one brood was taken from any one pair. Cirl Buntings
lay up to three clutches and the first brood of the year is invariably lost due
to heavy rainfall and lack of insect life, so this was the brood targeted. In
total 22 broods were harvested from a possible 67 pairs and it is unlikely
that the relocation had any effect on the south Devon population.
At the end of 2004 12 young Cirl Buntings were released in an area of
south Devon from where they had previously been taken. Prior to release
the birds were kept in an aviary and then soft-released, being fed at the site
each day until they eventually dispersed. They were closely monitored over
the winter and on into 2005. The birds mixed well with flocks of wild,
wintering, Cirl Buntings. During 2005 four of the released birds paired
with wild Cirl Buntings and three of those pairs produced young.
In 2006 the project really took off - 72 Cirl Buntings were reared and
later released in an area of Cornwall. Two aviculturists were employed to
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.863005" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260719" page_num="5" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - GIRL BUNTING
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.856992" page_id="56260719"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
5
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.98227105" page_id="56260719"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
undertake the hand-rearing and to release the birds. Several RSPB field
workers will continue to monitor the birds in the wild well into 2007. The
project will continue for the next three years, with at least 60 birds being
released annually. We hope the result will be that the Cirl Bunting once
again becomes self-sustaining along the Cornish coast and adjacent farmland.
Hand-rearing
We found that the ideal age to start hand-rearing the Cirl Bunting is at
six to seven days. When taken at eight days or older the chicks are less
confiding and more difficult to feed. Any younger than six days old the
chicks are very small and difficult to manage in a practical sense, though
chicks both older and younger have been reared successfully. The nestlings
are kept in their birth broods and placed in a brooder set at 28*C (82.4*F).
They are nestled in a round dish and bowled together using soft tissue paper
which prevents their legs from splaying. The chicks are not fed for the first
hour in order to allow them time to settle, after which they are fed every
f/ 2-2 hours from 6.00am until midnight.
The chicks are weighed every day and kept to a weight gain of
approximately 10%. Some older chicks have proved stubborn at feeding
times and to overcome this we use a soft bristle paint brush to tease open
their bills and place food in their mouths. Another trick we have used with
stubborn feeders is to feed another brood at the same time. When this is
done, the calls of the other brood of Cirl Buntings feeding is too much for
the chick to bear and it automatically opens its bill albeit somewhat
reluctantly.
The diet consists of 60% Mazuri Diet A pellets soaked until soft and
then mixed with 35% grated boiled egg. The remaining 5% is banana which
is added to the mix so that it can easily be formed into balls for feeding. A
light sprinkling of SA37 vitamin/mineral supplement is added. Mealworms
are offered throughout the day.
Baycox (Bayer) 2.5% Toltrazuril solution is added to the diet as a
prophylactic. The oral dose for passerines is 12.5mg/kg body weight, once
daily for two consecutive days each week. Throughout the rearing period
all chicks undergo regular visual and faecal checks. From our experience
during the 2004 release, when they showed many stress responses, we learned
that Cirl Buntings do not cope well with being handled after they have
fledged. Therefore, unless signs of disease are obvious, all checks are carried
out without handling the birds.
Equipment
Brinsea TLC 4 brooders were used for the rearing period. Fledging
birds were weaned in standard sized wooden double breeding cages. Once
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.966445" page_id="56260720"  page_num="6" year="" vol="">
6
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.965496" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260720" page_num="6" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - GIRL BUNTING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.982145342105263" page_id="56260720"  page_num="6" year="" vol="">
weaned the birds were placed in aviaries. These release aviaries are designed
with a release door at the front and another in the roof. During the first trial
it was noticed that some birds preferred to enter and leave the aviary via the
roof To prevent birds of prey entering the aviaries 2 i n (5 cm) mesh is placed
over both release doors. Fixed at the back of each aviary under a shelter is
a wooden breeding cage. The weaned chicks are kept in this small cage for
a couple of days before being let into the aviary. This gives them a chance
to take in their new surroundings before being given flight space. Hopefully
it has also reduced incidences of trauma. Each aviary is heavily perched
and positioned facing a thick hedgerow beyond which is an open stubble
field.
Fledging
The chicks are kept in brooders for only a short while. At 12 days they
start to show signs of fledging. At this time their appetite will drop and they
will not gain as much weight. They become more observant and will sit on
the edge of the nest bowl and even jump out if disturbed unexpectedly.
Between days 12-14 they are moved into standard sized wooden breeding
cages. As would be expected, on the first day of being moved the chicks
become quiet and subdued. They are moved early in the morning and are
watched closely throughout the day. If by the end of the day a bird is not
relaxed, it is placed back in the brooder for another night. A lot of changes
are made at this time. The cages are furnished with leafy branches to allow
the birds to perch and hide. Wild seeds and millet are added to the diet and
a dish of water is provided. Fledging is a very stressful time for all birds
and great care is taken to ensure that they are kept in a comfortable routine.
With stress can come disease, so this is a time when all birds can be at risk.
They must be kept pristine clean, but it is also a time when they make the
most mess, as they learn to feed themselves and jump in the food dishes.
Mixed seeds are gradually added to make up half of the diet.
Weaning
From about 16 days the chicks begin to pick up food. At first they will
pick it up only from the hand, but after a few days of repeatedly having had
the food dropped in front of them, they are eventually persuaded to pick up
the food from the floor or a dish. Livefood is not picked up until a few days
later, though dead livefood is taken. As they grow more independent they
become hand shy and weighing is stopped. The birds remain in cages until
all of them are feeding, bathing and preening efficiently. By day 25 they are
moved to the release aviaries.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.848171" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260721" page_num="7" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - GIRL BUNTING
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.966144" page_id="56260721"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
7
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.406931">
Release
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989784727272727" page_id="56260721"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
Once the birds have been released from the breeding cages into the
aviaries they become noticeable to predatory animals in the area. Several
methods were used to deter birds of prey and domestic cats. An electric
fence was placed around all 10 aviaries. More usually used to keep domestic
stock in, it worked very well at keeping cats out. A sonic sound device was
also used, but its effectiveness could not be measured, as the electric fence
was already in place. Several large balloons adorned with two large target
eyes were tied to trees and shrubs around the aviaries to put off any
Sparrowhawks Accipiter nisus.
Wild Cirl Buntings spend a lot of time foraging on the ground, so some
of the seed and mealworms are placed on the floor of the aviary. Most of
the food however is placed on the inside ledge of the escape hatch. During
this time the rearing mix is slowly withdrawn and replaced with a mixture
of millets and wild seeds. The birds spend about 12 days confined to the
aviaries after which, provided they are fit and healthy, the release hatches
are opened. All food is then placed on the outside ledge of the escape hatch
and after one week the birds are shut out of the aviary, but continue to be fed
on the ledge. As late as October some birds were still returning for food and
for this reason one aviary was left standing and used as a feeding station.
Seed is also scattered in the adjacent stubble field.
The project has been a great success thus far and all partners are eagerly
waiting to see if the released birds pair up successfully this spring.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.642346846153846" page_id="56260721"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
Products mentioned in the text
Mazuri Diet A: zoo food pellet supplied by Mazuri Zoo Foods, Witham, Essex CM8 3 AD, UK.
Website: www.mazuri.com
SA37: vitamin/mineral supplement supplied by Intervet UK Limited, Walton Manor, Milton
Keynes MK7 7AJ, UK. Website:www.intervet.com
Brinsea Brooders: supplied by Brinsea, Station Road, Sandford, N. Somerset BS25 5RA, UK.
Website: www.brinsea.com.
Mixed wild seeds: supplied by Rob Harvey Specialist Feeds, Kookaburra House, Gravel Hill
Road, Holt Pound, Famham, Surrey GU10 4LG, UK. Website:www.robharvey.com.
Mixed millet seed: supplied by John E. Haith, Park Street, Cleethorpes, Lines., UK.
Website: www.haiths.com
Aviaries: supplied by Grange Aviaries and Pet Centre, Woodhouse Lane, Botley, Southampton
S030 2EZ, UK. Tel:01489 781260.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.664974" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56260721" page_num="7" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.8888406">
Thanks to my fellow staff members involved in this project: Curator of
Birds Colin Bath and aviculturists Carl Laven and Julie Wallace.
Jo Gregson, Senior Head Keeper of Birds, Paignton Zoo Environmental
Park, Totnes Road, Paignton, Devon TQ4 7EU, UK. Website:www.
paigntonzoo. org. uk/E-mail:jgregson@paigntonzoo. org. uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.735485" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260722" page_num="8" year="" vol="">
THE BIRD COLLECTION AT WADDESDON MANOR
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98109025" page_id="56260722"  page_num="8" year="" vol="">
by Andrew Owen
Over the last few years the Aviary at Waddesdon Manor has undergone
many changes. As well as the complete refurbishment and painting of the
exterior of this unique ornate structure, all of the interiors of the aviaries
have been landscaped and replanted with tropical plants such as bamboos,
palms and tree ferns. Not only does this enhance the appearance of the
aviaries, it creates mini-environments and provides good nesting sites for
the birds. Several species have been replaced in the collection by new and
often more challenging birds. Whenever possible we are working with rare
and endangered birds, focusing on those from south-east Asia and Africa.
Turacos have always been well represented at Waddesdon and new
species include the White-crested Tauraco leucolophus, Schalow's 7.
schalowi and Fischer's T. fischeri. The beautiful White-crested Turaco is
rare in aviculture. Our two are a young unrelated pair that nested for the
first time in 2006. Unfortunately they showed their inexperience and failed
to rear their young themselves. The first two chicks were hand-reared by
keeper Ian Edmans and two further chicks were foster-reared under the
Fischer's Turacos.
Members will recall that we also keep the White-bellied Go-away Bird
Coryihaixold.es leucogaster and in 2005 were successful in breeding this
species, almost certainly for the first time in the UK (s qq Avicultural Magazine
Vol. 112, No.2, pp.62-70 (2006)). This grey and white species is delightful
to keep. Unlike other turacos that eat mostly fruit, the go-away birds eat
large amounts of greenfood and we feel that the abundance of cos (romaine)
lettuce, along with Hazel Corylus avellana , Hawthorn Crataegus nigra , Lime
Tilia sylvatica and honeysuckle Lonicera spp. leaves, were the key to the
rearing of the chicks.
Bearded Barbet Lybius dubius , Spot-flanked Barbet Trichoiaema
lachrymosa, Spotted Morning Warbler Cichladusa guttata (also known as
the Spotted Morning-Thrush and Spotted Palm-Thrush) and Snowy-crowned
Robin Chat Cossypha niveicapiila are among other African additions to the
collection. The first three species mentioned all reared young during 2006.
Large rotten logs from the estate grounds were provided for the barbets to
excavate their nest holes and the Spotted Morning Warblers were provided
with a dish of wet clay soil to make their cup-shaped nest. Both Spotted
Morning Warblers took turns to incubate the two bright turquoise eggs and
the young were reared on a variety of insects.
Breeding success has also been achieved with a number of south-east
Asian species. Nine Pekin Robins or Red-billed Leiothrix Leiothrix lutea
were bred in 2005 and it close relative the Silver-eared MesiaT. argentauris
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.982532" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260723" page_num="9" year="" vol="">
OWEN -WADDESDON MANOR
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.961039" page_id="56260723"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
9
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.991027" page_id="56260723"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
reared three young. We were less successful with these during 2006, rearing
only three Pekin Robins and failing to breed any Silver-eared Mesias. Several
of the species bred recently are rare in aviculture or in the wild. The Critically
Endangered Blue-crowned Laughingthrush Garrulax courtoisi, one of four
species of laughingthrushes we keep, arrived in 2005 and produced five
young during 2006. A clutch of three eggs was removed and artificially
incubated and the chicks were hand-reared. Soon afterwards a replacement
clutch was laid and the parents successfully reared two more young.
Formerly regarded as a subspecies of the Yellow-throated Laughingthrush
G. galbanus it is, following taxonomic changes, now recognised as a full
species (Collar, 2006) and classified as Critically Endangered in the wild in
China. The newly-named Sumatran Laughingthrush G. bicolor was formerly
regarded as a subspecies of the White-crested G. leucolophus , but is now
considered different enough to warrant full species status. Thought to be
very rare in the wild on Sumatra, it is currently classified as Vulnerable.
One of these, a male, was hand-reared here in 2005. It was, we believe,
the first time this species had been bred in the UK. Two further chicks were
hand-reared in 2006. Despite several nesting attempts we have been unable
to produce any parent-reared young. In addition to our breeding pair we
also have a bachelor group. At Paultons Park in Hampshire Geoff Masson
also has a pair and a female was hand-reared there in 2006. Between our
two collections, we are trying to establish this rare and beautiful
laughingthrush in captivity. We know of a few others in the UK, but these
are males. There is a paucity of females in the small population and we are
very keen to hear from anyone who keeps this species.
A pair of Red-tailed Laughingthrushes G. milnei arrived from Jersey
Zoo in 2005 and reared their first young in 2006. The fourth species of
laughingthrush we keep at Waddesdon Manor is the Chestnut-capped G.
mitratus. We have three here and a fourth out on loan with a private
aviculturist, but unfortunately all four are females. Although this species is
not rare in the wild, we would like to establish this lovely bird in captivity
and again would like to hear from anyone who keeps it.
True thrushes are represented in the collection by the Orange-headed
Ground Thrush Zoothera citrina, Chestnut Thrush Turdus rubrocanus and
Chestnut-backed Thrush Z. dohertyi. Three Chestnut-backed were parent-
reared at Waddesdon in 2006. This beautiful Indonesian thrush is being
bred by a number of dedicated aviculturists and a few zoos and other
collections in the UK, with the aim of establishing a self-sustaining captive
population.
Threatened studbook managed species at Waddesdon include the Bali
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.416376666666667">
Starling Leucopsar rothschildi , Omei Shan Liocichla Liocichla omeiensis,
Luzon Bleeding Heart Dove Gallicolumba luzonica and the aforementioned
Blue-crowned Laughingthrush.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.963634" page_id="56260724"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
10
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.6781625" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260724" page_num="10" year="" vol="">
OWEN -WADOE3BON MANOR
Andrew Owen
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98611125" page_id="56260724"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
Chestnut-backed Thrush.
Hand rearing is a useful way to increase the numbers of difficult and
rare species and a number of these have been bred over the past few years
using this technique. It is of course a very time consuming way to rear
birds, even for those working with them foil-time, as everything else has to
stop so that the chicks can be fed.
A highly successful hand-rearing diet for a variety of passerines has
proved to be two parts pinkie mice to one part papaya, blended to a fine
consistency with multi-vitamin powder added. Most will lay a replacement
clutch of eggs within a week or two of their young being taken for hand-
rearing, so there is every opportunity of them rearing a follow-up brood.
As well as those species mentioned above, we have also successfully
hand-reared Pekin Robins, Silver-eared Mesias, Grosbeak Starlings
Scissirostris dubium, Fairy Bluebirds Irena puella and Rufous-bellied
Niltavas Niltava sundara. In addition, seven Large Niltavas N. grandis
have been hand-reared in the past two years for Bob Jewiss, a private
aviculturist, in an attempt to build up the number of this lovely flycatcher in
captivity.
The construction of several off-show aviaries has helped us maintain
second and even third pairs of the same species and the secure, quiet
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.68687" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260725" page_num="11" year="" vol="">
OWEN -WADDESDON MANOR
</sectionHeader>
<figure confidence="0.91081425" page_id="56260725"  page_num="11" year="" vol="">
Andrew Owen
Male Rufous-bellied Niltava.
Andrew Owen
Sumatran Laughingthrush.
</figure>
<page confidence="0.994782" page_id="56260726"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
12
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996867" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260726" page_num="12" year="" vol="">
OWEN -WADDESDON MANOR
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.961911111111111" page_id="56260726"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
surroundings, have helped with the breeding of some of our more sensitive
birds.
Head Keeper Ian Hadgkiss said that 2006 was the best breeding season
at Waddesdon (for softbill species at least) with 14 species reared to
independence.
Cooperation between breeders is very important and we have developed
good links with a number of UK collections and private breeders, with whom
we exchange birds and place birds on breeding loan. We would welcome
contact with other aviculturists who keep any of the species mentioned above.
In this way we may be able to pair up individual birds and put other breeders
in touch with each other. Contact can be made with Head Keeper Ian Hadgkiss
or myself by Tel:01296 65386 or E-mail: Andrew.Owen@nationaltrust.org.uk
Reference
Collar, N. J. 2006. A partial review of Asian babblers (Timaliidae). Forktail 22:84-112.
Waddesdon Manor (website:www. waddesdon.org. uk) was built by Baron
Ferdinand de Rothschild. On a hilltop overlooking Aylesbury Vale, it has
one of the finest Victorian gardens in the UK, at the heart of which is the
Aviary.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998046" page_id="56260727"  page_num="13" year="" vol="">
13
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.736966" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260727" page_num="13" year="" vol="">
THE CORNCRAKE SPECIES RECOVERY PROGRAMME
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.971906743589743" page_id="56260727"  page_num="13" year="" vol="">
by Jamie Graham
Background and history
The Corncrake Crex crex is the only globally threatened bird species
that breeds regularly in the UK.
A land rail (order Gruiformes, family Rallidae), it measures 27cm-30cm
(approx. 10V2in-l PAin) in length. It has a relatively short pinkish bill, a
broad grey stripe above the eyes, a grey neck and breast and brown and
white barring on the flanks. The upperparts are mainly huffish, with a dark
centre to the feathers, especially those on the back. The bright chestnut
wing-coverts and inner flight feathers are fully revealed when the Corncrake
flies. It has pale flesh-pink coloured legs and feet.
Related species include the Spotted Crake Porzanaporzana, Water Rail
Rallus aquaticus. Moorhen Gallinula chloropus and Coot Fulica atra. Like
many rails the Corncrake is a difficult bird to see. The best time to spot this
secretive species is in late April and early May soon after it has arrived back
in the UK, when the vegetation is still low.
The Corncrake is more often heard than seen. It gets its scientific name,
Crex crex , from the male's loud, grating, repeated "crex-crex" call. Soon
after arriving back in the UK he starts to call from a small patch of higher
ground and continues to call until he has found a mate. Having found a
mate, he stops calling for about two weeks, then starts again to try to attract
a second mate. He sometimes calls during the day but is famed for calling
throughout the night.
In the nineteenth centuiy the Corncrake was found throughout most of
the UK and the population numbered hundreds of thousands. Yet by the late
1970s the UK population had suffered a drastic decline and there were only
a mere 1,000 calling males. The Corncrake's decline was due to modem
intensive farming methods, particularly the rapid introduction of mechanised
grass-cutting and the taking of repeated cuts of grass through spring and
summer for silage (winter feed) which deprived the Corncrake of its preferred
habitat. Earlier harvesting also led to the destmction of nests and the killing
of sitting birds and chicks.
North-west Scotland, especially the Hebrides, is now the only place in
the UK where the Corncrake continues to breed in any numbers. The reason
it survives there is that the crofters (small-scale tenant fanners) continue to
farm in a Corncrake-friendly, non-intensive manner. They do not cut the
grass before August 1 st and this gives the female Corncrakes enough time
to nest and raise their first brood and in many cases their second brood as
well. Furthermore, they always cut the fields from the centre outwards in a
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998667" page_id="56260728"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
14
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.831011" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260728" page_num="14" year="" vol="">
GRAHAM - CORNCRAKE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9863142" page_id="56260728"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
circle or in large strips so that any adults and/or chicks have enough time to
escape to the edges which are always left to grow wild.
Nineteenth century distribution.
The RSPB (Royal Society for the Protection of Birds) has produced a
leaflet which includes a five-point plan that lists the basic requirements of
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.952173" page_id="56260728"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
the Corncrake to breed successfully:
1. Early Cover - An area of vegetation sufficiently tall for Corncrakes
to find refuge in April and early May when they return from Africa.
First nests are in this habitat.
2. Provide Nesting Habitat - An extensive area of ungrazed meadow
(with grass for hay or silage) in which to feed in and in which the second
nest is made and in which the birds can remain concealed.
3. Manage Nesting Habitat - These meadows must be mown or grazed
no earlier than August 1st and preferably later to allow the Corncrakes
to successfully rear a second brood.
4. Corncrake Friendly Mowing - A method of cutting that minimizes
the chance of young birds being trapped or injured during harvesting.
5. Fate Cover - Areas of tall vegetation in which Corncrakes can hide
</listItem>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.427599" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260729" page_num="15" year="" vol="">
GRAHAM - CORNCRAKE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.986595" page_id="56260729"  page_num="15" year="" vol="">
15
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99074" page_id="56260729"  page_num="15" year="" vol="">
and feed after the hay and silage fields have been cut or grazed.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.63184">
The Zoological Society of London (ZSL), RSPB and Natural England
Species Recovery Programme (SRP)
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995581" page_id="56260729"  page_num="15" year="" vol="">
Although the number of Corncrakes is increasing in Scotland, it was
clear that it would find it difficult to gain a foothold in England again without
habitat protection. That was why a partnership was set-up between The
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.71994">
Zoological Society of London (ZSL), RSPB and English Nature (now Natural
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9995185" page_id="56260729"  page_num="15" year="" vol="">
England). The ultimate aim of the programme is to secure the future of the
Corncrake in the UK.
In 2000 an RSPB site on the fens north of Peterborough was identified
as being suitable for Corncrakes to breed. In February the following year
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.941632" page_id="56260730"  page_num="16" year="" vol="">
16
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.551871" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260730" page_num="16" year="" vol="">
GRAHAM - CORNCRAKE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.974217142857143" page_id="56260730"  page_num="16" year="" vol="">
15 captive-bred Corncrakes were imported from Germany. They were
quarantined at Chester Zoo and later transferred to specially designed
breeding pens at Whipsnade Wild Animal Park (WWAP).
The partners agreed that they would like to release 100 Whipsnade-bred
Corncrakes each year. In the first couple of years though only a handful of
birds were able to be released, due to the programme wanting to release
only parent-reared stock and having had too few breeding birds at the start
of the programme. In 2002 a further 15 were imported from Germany to
add to the breeding stock. This led to a more successful breeding season the
following year. The number released though was still short of the target of
100, but the longer the programme continues more experience is gained as
to how to maximise the breeding potential of our limited number of birds.
The 2003 breeding season was my first at Whipsnade Wild Animal Park.
By then some of the breeding birds were getting old. On average a wild
Corncrake has only one breeding season, yet some of our breeding stock
was heading for six to seven years old. In the spring of 2005, four wild-
caught males were imported from Poland and in late summer 11 second
clutch chicks were collected on the island of Coll in the Inner Hebrides,
north-west Scotland. These replaced the very old Corncrakes which were
lost over the winter.
Breeding
At the start of April the birds are placed in the breeding pens. We have 21
individual pens that measure approximately 2.5m sq (27sq ft). They contain
a mix of wild grass and nettles which is perfect for the birds, as they need the
grass to breed in amongst and also need the nettles as cover. Each bird is
housed separately until the males start to call regularly and the females appear
receptive. We have a very simple way of telling when each female is ready.
In each pen there is a small wooden table under which we place food and,
when the table becomes covered with faeces it shows that the female has been
standing on the table most of the night trying to locate a calling male.
When a male is placed with a female, he remains with her for about two
weeks before she starts to lay. In this time he must mate with the female and
make a nest that meets with her approval. He makes a scrape in the ground
and using the surrounding vegetation, usually long grass and nettles, he
swirls some of the grass around and creates a soft cup in which the female
lays the eggs. She will lay between seven to 12 eggs. After the fourth egg
is laid, the male is removed and plays no part in the incubation, which takes
16-20 days.
We do not allow the females to incubate the eggs for the full incubation
period. This is because the chicks become imprinted on their surroundings,
which were the females allowed to hatch the chicks, would include the night
sky at Whipsnade rather than that of the release site. It is thought that
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.429966" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260731" page_num="17" year="" vol="">
GRAHAM - CORNCRAKE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998956" page_id="56260731"  page_num="17" year="" vol="">
17
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.979090736842105" page_id="56260731"  page_num="17" year="" vol="">
Corncrakes migrate using star mapping as a navigation tool and studies have
shown that they return to within a mile (1.6km) of where they were hatched
and reared. Hand-rearing the chicks also helps us maximize the number
produced each year. In an ideal world we would prefer the chicks to be
parent-reared indoors here or outdoors at the release site, but we would still
need a much larger breeding stock to produce anywhere near the number
we are releasing at the moment.
Artificial incubation
With most of the hard work having been done by the females, the eggs
are usually collected at 15 days and placed in incubators, although recently
we have picked up fresh eggs and incubated them from scratch. The
incubators are set at 37*C (98.6*F) with 70% humidity. Although the
incubators are of the automatic tipping variety, we still turn the eggs five
times a day until internal pipping occurs. At this point we transfer the eggs
to a hatcher set at the same temperature but with slightly higher humidity of
75%. When the chicks hatch they are placed in a large drier set at 35*C
(95*F) for about 12-24 hours while the chicks absorb the rest of the yolk
sac. After this they are transferred to a large brooder to be reared. This
takes 10-12 days.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.587883">
Rearing
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998789428571429" page_id="56260731"  page_num="17" year="" vol="">
When the chicks hatch they are covered in black down and their eyes are
open and within 24 hours they have the ability to move around very well.
Unlike many other precocious chicks they need intensive rearing, as it can
take up to six days before they start to feed themselves. Therefore, up until
the time when they are feeding themselves they require hourly feeds from
8.00am-6.00pm then a late feed at 9.00pm. Then, dependent on the chicks'
feeding behaviour, the feeds are reduced to every two hours. The keeper's
hand and forearm are covered by a brown sock and the chicks are fed from
behind a screen using a pair of red plastic tweezers. This is to ensure that
the chicks do not become imprinted on humans. When they do see us we
make sure that they associate it with a negative experience, e.g. when we
catch them in order to clean their enclosures, we do not use the sock on the
hand and forearm, so that they never associate the sock with the keepers.
The chicks' growth rate is phenomenal. When they hatch they weigh
about 8g and by the time they leave us in 10-12 days time they weigh 60g-
80g. All of the chicks undergo health checks and faecal samples are taken
at four days old and at eight days old. After leaving us they spend three
weeks in outdoor pre-release pens at the release site at the RSPB's Nene
Washes reserve in Cambridgeshire. There they undergo a further health
check and are ringed (banded). Before they are released they must have
reached a specified weight which varies according to the age and sex of the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.960327" page_id="56260732"  page_num="18" year="" vol="">
18
</page>
<table confidence="0.3747838" page_id="56260732"  page_num="18" year="" vol="">
GRAHAM - CORNCRAKE
J. Graham
Corncrake nest at Whipsnade Wild Animal Park.
J. Baines
The release site on the RSPB's Nene Washes reserve.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.415691" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260733" page_num="19" year="" vol="">
GRAHAM - CORNCRAKE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.963536" page_id="56260733"  page_num="19" year="" vol="">
19
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.934184714285714" page_id="56260733"  page_num="19" year="" vol="">
Corncrake chicks.
J Graham
bird, but should be at least 120g. If they have not reached the correct weight
they are held back for another week or so.
All of the measurements of the chicks are recorded and they are weighed
and their weights compared on a chart to the weights of wild chicks of the
same age. At two weeks old the birds still have another two to three weeks
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.980969" page_id="56260734"  page_num="20" year="" vol="">
20
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.824498" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260734" page_num="20" year="" vol="">
GRAHAM - CORNCRAKE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.971454" page_id="56260734"  page_num="20" year="" vol="">
Author feeding chicks from behind a screen.
J. Baines
as sub-adults. They look like adult birds, the only differences are their weight
and the fact that the primary feathers are not fully grown. A very important
measurement is that of the remaining feather sheath left on the primaries
(Dr Rhys Green of the RSPB is an expert on this). The reason it is so
important is because the Corncrake migrates as soon as the primaries are
fully grown. The remaining feather sheath indicates how much longer the
bird will remain on the reserve before it migrates.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.430196" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260735" page_num="21" year="" vol="">
GRAHAM - CORNCRAKE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998135" page_id="56260735"  page_num="21" year="" vol="">
21
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.990359967741936" page_id="56260735"  page_num="21" year="" vol="">
Releases, migration and returning birds
They spend roughly two weeks on the reserve feeding and readying
themselves for the 1,500 mile (approx. 2,400km) flight to Africa for the
winter. Because of their secretive behaviour their winter range is imperfectly
known. It is believed that the majority of European (and Asiatic) birds
winter in sub-Saharan Africa, especially the eastern half of the continent.
The following spring wardens at the release site go out each evening to
listen for the calls of returning male Corncrakes. Sixty-three Whipsnade-
bred birds were released in 2003 but none of these were known to have
returned in 2004, in which year a further 72 were released. In 2005 a male
was heard calling at the release site and was caught and found to be one of
the birds released in 2004. It was the first proof that a hand-reared bird
could migrate to Africa and return the following spring, having undertaken
a round trip of approximately 3,000 miles (4,800km). In the 2005 season
78 Whipsnade-bred birds were released. In 2006 four males were heard
calling at the release site, three of which were birds released in 2005 and
one which was a wild bird which seemed not to have bothered to make its
way back to Scotland or more positively it may have been hatched on the
Nene the previous year. We regard this as a major success, as the males
exhibited behaviour that suggested they had all mated. The males call
continuously until they find a mate, after which they stop calling for about
two weeks and then start calling again. The birds that have returned have
done this twice which suggests they mated twice. The only drawback with
this method of Corncrake surveying is that it records only the males, we
have no idea how many females have returned.
At the time of writing (2006) we are drawing to the end of another busy
breeding season. With the success of the past two years of having birds
return and the introduction of new stock, the programme is looking very
healthy. There is though still a lot of work to do and it will be quite a few
years yet before there is once again a self-sustaining population of Corncrakes
in England.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.977374666666667">
Jamie Graham, Senior Keeper, Bird Section, Whipsnade Wild Animal
Park, The Zoological Society of London, Dunstable, Bedfordshire LU6 2LF,
UK, Website: www.whipsnade.co.uk.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.997005" page_id="56260736"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
22
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.89923975" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260736" page_num="22" year="" vol="">
KEEPING AND BREEDING THE GREATER BIRD OF
PARADISE Paradisaea apoda AT AL WABRA WILDLIFE
PRESERVATION, QATAR AND WALSRODE BIRDPARK,
GERMANY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.981230583333333" page_id="56260736"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
by Simon Bruslund Jensen
The Greater Bird of Paradise was bred in captivity for the first time at
Walsrode in Germany in 2001, unfortunately the female was later lost and
the breeding success was not repeated. However, methods first developed
at Walsrode were implemented at A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation (AWWP)
in 2002 and resulted in successful breeding that same year and to date 22
chicks have been hatched at AWWP in Qatar.
At Walsrode initially massive problems were encountered in the effort
to breed birds of paradise. Eggs were destroyed and/or were infertile.
However, much experience was gained over a period of three years and it
was learned that the males, when kept together with the females, would
consistently destroy the nests and eggs. When the males were separated
from the females, the females would lay eggs and incubate them, but these
often proved infertile due to the difficulty of judging the right time to place
the pairs together and quite frequently the female would destroy the nest
and eggs herself. Important lessons were learned on timing and in particular
the birds' sensitivity to disturbance. In June 2001 a single chick hatched in
an off-exhibit breeding aviary. It was successfully reared by the female and
proved to be a male. Unfortunately, the death of the female the following
winter ended any further hope of breeding the Greater Bird of Paradise at
Walsrode.
After working for three years as a keeper at Walsrode I took up the position
as Curator of Birds at A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation early in 2002. The
Greater Bird of Paradise is also maintained at AWWP and similar problems
had been encountered when trying to breed this species. Implementation of
the methods developed at Walsrode quickly led to the first breeding success,
when in May 2002 as a precaution an egg was removed for artificial
incubation and the chick was hand-reared. This was followed shortly
afterwards by another chick from a different pair. Our husbandry methods
were further developed and improved, not least by incorporating what had
been learned breeding other species of birds of paradise at the Bronx Zoo
(Hundgen, 1988,1991) and at San Diego Zoo (Rimlinger, 1984) in the USA.
Extensive health monitoring and documentation allowed for experimental
diet modifications that have effectively reduced the problems caused by
iron storage disease that almost completely depleted the population of Greater
Birds of Paradise at Walsrode (Marcordes pers. comment). Iron storage
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.71649" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260737" page_num="23" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND JENSEN - GREATER BIRD OF PARADISE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998816" page_id="56260737"  page_num="23" year="" vol="">
23
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.969527956521739" page_id="56260737"  page_num="23" year="" vol="">
disease was also the biggest health problem with captive birds of paradise
in other collections (Hundgen, 1938).
At AWWP a total of 22 chicks have hatched to date in a managed internal
breeding programme that seeks to represent as many founders as possible in
the population, with the aim of developing a long-term viable captive
population. This is achieved by interchanging breeding males and even by
restricting breeding by highly productive individuals and instead encouraging
non-breeding birds, so that all female founders are equally represented. So
far nine founder birds have reproduced and the first generation female showed
the first signs of breeding behaviour in 2006.
Simon Bruslund Jensen/AWWP
Lek of displaying male Aru Island Greater Birds of Paradise at AWWP.
Ongoing studies have produced some initial results from data collected
on the age at which young birds of paradise become mature: both when they
are able to reproduce and also when they develop full plumage. These seem
not to be entirely related to each other, for males are sexually mature before
they develop fill plumage which may take up to seven years. We have also
undertaking research on DNA-sexing and endoparasites. The latter have
proved to be a particular problem especially amongst parent-reared young,
which may suffer infections if they are not prevented in time (Schulz &amp;
Hammer et al. 2004).
A size variation was detected among the birds of the founder population.
Our birds were all purchased years ago in south-east Asia. Their exact origin
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998266" page_id="56260738"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
24
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.820753" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260738" page_num="24" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND JENSEN - GREATER BIRD OF PARADISE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997704941176471" page_id="56260738"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
is unknown but it is likely that they are all wild-caught birds. Not knowing
the locations they came from made it difficult to determine which of the two
recognised subspecies they might belong to. However, all of our birds were
measured and by comparing their measurements with those given by Frith
&amp; Beehler (1998), it was obvious that we have two distinct groupings within
the population and these match the sizes of the two recognised subspecies.
In addition to the measurements we were also able to determine that there
are marked differences in their weights, with no overlap whatsoever between
the adult birds of the two groupings.
As a result, the birds at AWWP are now managed as two separate
populations: the larger birds as the Aru Island Bird of Paradise P. a. apoda
group and the smaller birds as the Mainland Greater Bird of Paradise P. a.
novaeguineae group. Before the two groups were identified and separated,
a few hybrids were produced, but these were subsequently taken out of the
breeding programme. Interestingly the hybrid forms present intermediate
values both with regard to size and weight and have proved to be much
more vulnerable than the other offspring.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.991946">
Table 1. Average weights of adults based on 31 birds.
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.844487416666666" page_id="56260738"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
Aru Island Bird of Paradise
Male
365g (range 330g-429g)
Female
220g (range 205g-232g)
Mainland Greater Bird of Paradise
Male
229g (range 205g-255g)
Female
171 g (range 154g-193 g)
Husbandry
Feeding
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.9991395" page_id="56260738"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
The birds are fed twice a day, with the diet of the adult birds being
relatively simple and mainly fruit based. Large amounts of fruit, especially
papaya, are consumed, with mango, pear and apple also being offered daily.
This is varied regularly with mulberries, oranges, grapes, bananas,
watermelons and other fruits. Commercial pellets for fruit-eaters are also
offered twice a day, the amount varying depending on the size of the particular
bird. In the morning 7g-10g Ziegler(R) Bird of Paradise pellets are presented
to each bird and in the afternoon each bird receives 2g-4g Wittemolen(R)
Mynah G ranulate. Both of these products, which we have tested on a regular
basis in independent laboratories, have a steady iron content of less than
65ppm. Past experience with pellets containing higher measurable amounts
of iron than 1 OOppm, resulted in birds quickly showing symptoms of iron
storage disease. Livefood such as mealworms is fed once a week, when
each bird receives five. They are of course also able to catch insects that
</bodyText>
<bodyText confidence="0.35559" page_id="56260739"  page_num="25" year="" vol="">
BP. US LUND JENSEN - GREATER BIRD OF PARADISE
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995447" page_id="56260739"  page_num="25" year="" vol="">
25
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.98386195" page_id="56260739"  page_num="25" year="" vol="">
enter their flights. Feeding rations are tailored to suit each individual bird's
consumption and there is very little waste. Vitamins and minerals are
sprinkled over the food three times a week.
Housing
The birds are kept in large well-planted flights, each with access to a
climate controlled inside enclosure in which the birds are fed. Male Greater
Birds of Paradise become animated by observing each others' displays; in
contrast the females can be aggressive towards each other. Therefore two
males are often housed next to each other with the females in adjacent flights
each side. Pairs are allowed access to each other as long as the female
shows interest in entering the enclosure of the male, when this is not the
case they are kept separated most of the time. If a female shows interest in
a particular male and breeding behaviour such as mating or nest building is
observed, the birds are monitored more closely. To achieve a successful
breeding, timing is of the essence. It is important to allow the birds to
remain together long enough to mate, but not long enough for the male to
destroy the nest or egg. On some occasions females build their nests in very
exposed positions or have been proven to destroy their eggs. In such cases
the eggs are removed for artificial incubation. Due to the very hot summer
climate in Qatar we also remove eggs laid in the outside flights during the
hottest months. We do this not only to secure the eggs but also spare the
female from the strain of having to sit on the nest all day in the blazing sun.
Greater Birds of Paradise consistently lay single egg clutches and the egg is
incubated exclusively by the female. She will abandon the nest and egg if
she is convinced that the nest site has been compromised either by a keeper
or by a male bird. Not infrequently the female will eat the egg and even a
small youngster and will destroy the nest before it can be reached by an
intruder.
We provide the birds with open baskets and nest material in the form of
hay, fresh grasses, large dry leaves and thin sticks throughout the year. Only
rarely is the same nest site used twice and it has proven beneficial to change
the nest baskets or move them around when they are not in use. Most breeding
occurs In the spring from late February until July. Mid-summer the birds
normally start to moult and there is a halt in breeding activity until late
autumn when some birds may start breeding again.
Artificial incubation
Greater Bird of Paradise and other bird of paradise artificial incubation
records indicate that a comparatively high temperature and humidity produce
the best results. An incubation temperature of 37.8*C-37.9*C (100*F-
100.2*F) and a weight loss aim of 13.5% have been found to produce superior
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.989447" page_id="56260740"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
26
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.5594075" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260740" page_num="26" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND JENSEN - GREATER BIRD OF PARADISE
Simon Bruslund Jensen/AWWP
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97207805" page_id="56260740"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
Mainland Greater Bird of Paradise nest containing an infertile egg.
results. Eggs have been turned eight to 14 times a day with good results,
whereas an egg that was turned more than 24 times a day failed to hatch,
although the turning frequency could not be confirmed as the cause. The
incubation period for the single egg clutch is 16-17 days, with the vast
majority hatching on day 16. At internal pip the turning of the eggs is
normally discontinued, although the time between internal pip and the first
external pip is often exceedingly short and regularly the hatching process is
not detected until the external pip has started. The eggs are subsequently
transferred to the hatching unit and kept at a temperature of 37.5*C (99.5*F)
and relative humidity of about 80%. During the hatching period and the
first few days afterwards we have found it is very important to maintain the
correct temperature. Hatching can take 12-46 hours (average 29 hours). If
progress stalls we generally start assisting by chipping some of the shell
away about 36 hours after external pipping.
Hand-rearing
Soon after hatching chicks are weighed and the umbilicus area is
disinfected with iodine, then they are moved into a brooder. The temperature
in the brooder is maintained at 37.1*C (98.8*F). If the temperature is too
low the chick is likely to remain unresponsive at feeding time. The feeding
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.715318" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260741" page_num="27" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND JENSEN - GREATER BIRD OF PARADISE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.992148" page_id="56260741"  page_num="27" year="" vol="">
27
</page>
<author confidence="0.31673">
Simon Bruslund Jensen!AWWP
</author>
<bodyText confidence="0.99674452" page_id="56260741"  page_num="27" year="" vol="">
Five days old Aru Island Greater Bird of Paradise being hand-fed at AWWP. Note the
syringe holding a small amount of water which is given to the chicks after each feed.
response is stimulated by whistling softly or gently touching the chick.
Immediately after hatching the humidity is lowered to 65%-70% and then
gradually lowered to about 55% over the course of a few days. The
temperature in the brooder is lowered by approximately 0.5*C each day and
by the time the chick fledges the temperature is being maintained at about
29*C-31*C (84.2*F -87.8*F). After a further few days the chick can safely
be kept at room temperature without the need of additional heat.
Fluids in the form of Lactated Ringers solution mixed 1:1 with water are
given orally in very small amounts every hour after hatching. If the hatch
was prolonged or the chick appears weak a small amount of glucose is added
to the solution. Depending on the degree of absorption of the yolk sac the
first solid food is fed to the chick 12-20 hours after hatching and is limited
to one or two small pieces of high protein food such as cricket abdomen or
rat organs. It is essential to restrict food intake during the first few days
until the yolk sac has been fully absorbed and is no longer visible through
the skin of the abdomen. After that the chick is fed as much food as it will
accept in suitable bite sizes. We have used organs and muscle meat from
newborn mice and rats, soft white mealworms and pupae, cricket abdomens,
soft papaya, pear, banana, mango and grapes. During the first week mice,
rats and insects make up the larger portion of the diet, after which the amount
of fruit is gradually increased and by the time the chick leaves the nest,
about half the amount of food fed to it is fruit. The amount of insects and
meat is slowly decreased during the following months and by three to four
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997659" page_id="56260742"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
28
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.826181" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260742" page_num="28" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND JENSEN - GREATER BIRD OF PARADISE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997760407407407" page_id="56260742"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
months it is offered the same diet as the adults.
From the beginning the chicks are fed only during the daytime - in our
case a 14 hour day. Care is taken not to disturb the chicks during the night,
when it is essential they are allowed to conserve energy. Initially they receive
12-16 feeds a day at just under one hour intervals. When the chicks are
about two weeks old, the intervals are increased to two hours. On reaching
30 days they are fed five times a day and are encouraged to feed themselves.
By 50 days they should be fully weaned.
A faecal sac is normally produced after each feeding session. If one is
not produced following two or more feeds or if the membrane is fragile, it is
more often than not a sign of problems. The most frequently encountered
problem is stress or dehydration. Greater Bird of Paradise chicks are
particularly shy and easily become stressed when there is activity or noise
in the room. Keeping more than one chick in the same brooder unit has
consistently led to problems. Stressed chicks are very susceptible to
secondary infections.
The chicks are kept in plastic cups lined with tissue and a plastic mesh.
It is exceedingly important that the chicks can grip the lining of the cup with
their large feet. If they are unable to do this, deformities such as bent toes
and even twisted tarsus can quickly become irrevocable. Greater Bird of
Paradise chicks are in general more sensitive and difficult to rear than those
of other birds of paradise that have been hand-reared at AWWP. The chicks
are weighed and the nest cups are changed daily, however, due to the chicks'
nature and also the sensitivity of their legs it may be advisable to keep
handling of the chicks to a minimum. Young Greater Birds of Paradise
continue to grow long after they have become independent and males
continue to gain weight for at least one year.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.908369">
Table 2. Development stages of juvenile Greater Bird of Paradise.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.96692625" page_id="56260742"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
Days
Development stage
1-3
Blind and naked.
4
First growth of pin-feathers on the wings.
5-8
Pin-feathers developing all over body.
6-8
Eyes start slitting.
12
Feathers start breaking out of sheaves on wings.
15-19
Standing in nest, stretching and flapping wings.
18-20
Fledges and does not return to nest.
20-25
Immobile on perch waiting to be fed.
25-30
Starting to become active; approaches to receive food.
28
Almost fully feathered.
29-32
Starts feeding itself.
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.708822" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260743" page_num="29" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND JENSEN - GREATER BIRD OF PARADISE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.987629" page_id="56260743"  page_num="29" year="" vol="">
29
</page>
<table confidence="0.97565" page_id="56260743"  page_num="29" year="" vol="">
Am Island Greater Bird of Paradise individual weight
curves
All the above charted weights are for hand-reared chicks.
</table>
<page confidence="0.995817" page_id="56260744"  page_num="30" year="" vol="">
30
</page>
<table confidence="0.9901528" page_id="56260744"  page_num="30" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND JENSEN - GREATER BIRD OF PARADISE
Simon Bruslund Jensen!AWWP
Aru Island Greater Bird of Paradise aged approximately 10 days old.
Simon Bruslund Jensen!AWWP
Young recently fledged parent-reared Mainland Greater Bird of Paradise at 18 days.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.715658" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260745" page_num="31" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND JENSEN - GREATER BIRD OF PARADISE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998745" page_id="56260745"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
31
</page>
<table confidence="0.918235" page_id="56260745"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
Simon Bruslund Jensen/AWWP
Young Aru Island Greater Bird of Paradise starting to become mobile at 25 days.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.583595" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56260745" page_num="31" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.703921333333333" page_id="56260745"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
My thanks to the Bird Department staff at A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation,
in particular Dean Tugade, who spent many hours with me hand-rearing
birds of paradise. I also thank Sven Hammer, Director of Wildlife and
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.7244395" page_id="56260745"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
Veterinary Services at A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation and HE Sheikh Saoud
Bin Mohammad Bin Ali Al-Thani.
</table>
<page confidence="0.99858" page_id="56260746"  page_num="32" year="" vol="">
32
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.970758" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260746" page_num="32" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND JENSEN - GREATER BIRD OF PARADISE
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.984686375">
Bruslund Jensen, S. and Hammer, S. 2003. Breeding Birds of Paradise at A1 Wabra Wildlife
Preservation. International Zoo News 50, 5:276-279.
Bruslund Jensen, S. and Hammer, C. 2003. Paradiesvogel - ihre Haltung und Zucht im A1
Wabra Wildlife Preservation in Katar. Gefiedert Welt 127, 9:262-265.
Bruslund Jensen, S. 2005. Breeding Birds of Paradise at A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation, Qatar.
AFA Annual Conference Proceedings 2005:73-76.
Frith, C. B. and Beehler, B. M. 1998. The Birds of Paradise. Oxford University Press, Oxford,
New York, Tokyo.
Hammer, S., Jensen, S., Balzer, J. and Sandow, D. 2003. DNA Sexing in Birds of Paradise and
Bowerbirds. International Zoo News 50,3:156-159.
Hundgen, K. H. 1988. Propagation techniques for Birds of Paradise at the New York Zoological
Park. AAZPA 1988 Annual Proceedings : 14-20.
Hundgen, K. H. 1991. Management and breeding of the Red Bird of Paradise at the New York
Zoological Park. International Zoo Yearbook 30:192-199.
Rimlinger, D. 1984. Empress of Germany's Bird of Paradise. Zoonooz Feb. 1984:11-14.
Schulz, J., Bruslund Jensen, S., Arif, A., Taha, A. and Hammer, S. 2004. Indoparasite
</reference>
<table confidence="0.490126" page_id="56260746"  page_num="32" year="" vol="">
Management in Captive Birds of Paradise. Poster presentation, European Association of Zoo
and Wildlife Veterinarians (EAZWV) Meeting, Ebeltoft, Denmark.
After more than five years in charge of the bird collection at Al Wabra
Wildlife Preservation, Simon returned recently to Walsrode to take up the
position of Senior Curator. E-mail: simon.jenson@vogelpark~walsrode.de
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.968432" genericHeader="introduction" page_id="56260746" page_num="32" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.948776875" page_id="56260746"  page_num="32" year="" vol="">
The society has a large stock of back issues mostly from 1935 onwards
but there are also some earlier issues still available. They are priced #3.00
each (including p&amp;p). Please check availability before placing an order.
Overseas members may be able to pay by credit card through a PayPal
invoice, but this service is not available in all countries. All enquiries should
be addressed to: P. Boulden, Hon. Secretary/Treasurer, Avicultural Society,
Arcadia, The Mounts, East Allington, Totnes, Devon TQ9 7JQ, UK or
E-mail:admin@avisoc. co.uk
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999237" page_id="56260747"  page_num="33" year="" vol="">
33
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.704475" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260747" page_num="33" year="" vol="">
ON A VISIT TO CHESTNUT LODGE
by Fred Bamicoat
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993296710526316" page_id="56260747"  page_num="33" year="" vol="">
I have enjoyed reading the Avicultural Magazine for the greater part of
my lifetime, and my set - I am missing only four issues since November
1894 - is a treasured possession. The Avicultural Society's history is
fascinating, as is its reflection of over a century of avicultural history and, in
a way, even of world history. Of particular interest to me have always been
the accounts of the annual garden parties hosted by the President, Alfred
Ezra, at his superb home, Foxwarren Park, Cobham, Surrey, which was
destined to become an avicultural legend.
The first of these accounts was written by David Seth-Smith for May
16th 1925. Some 40 members had accepted the invitation of Mr and Mrs
Ezra, who had kindly provided a charabanc (a motor coach) for the party
departing at 3.00pm from Hyde Park Comer in central London. Foxwarren
Park extended over some 300 acres (approx. 120 hectares) of sandy soil,
very suitable for birds and mammals on account of its dryness, and the grand
house, surrounded by large and pretty flower gardens with ornamental pools
and fountains was in a commanding position overlooking Wisley Common,
with the Surrey Downs and beyond in the distance. The party moved down
through the lovely gardens in which Demoiselle Cranes Anthropoides virgo
and both Grey-winged Tmmpeters Psophia crepitans and Green-winged
Tmmpeters P. viridis walked free, to a well-lit birdroom in which innumerable
sunbirds, hummingbirds, starlings, fmitsuckers, niltavas, robin-chats, pittas,
etc. were tastefully displayed; then on to the range of very large aviaries
ideally sheltered from cold winds between two plantations of larch trees,
and bathed in sunshine. The avian gems they contained, and their breeding
triumphs, destined to become an on-going story for the next 30 years, are
far too numerous to mention here. Pride of place perhaps went to the unique
blue Alexandrine Parrakeets Psittacula eupatria , and, of course, the Pink-
headed Ducks Rhodonessa caryophyllacea, already nearing extinction,
happily swimming on their lovely lake. The party returned to the house
and, after a sumptuous tea, paid a visit to the extensive area of woodland
and open heather- and gorse-covered land, fenced into huge paddocks for
kangaroos, wallabies, Blaokbuok Antilope cervicapra and deer, with various
pheasants, including monals, cranes and chukor partridges roaming about,
and bmsh turkeys building their huge mounds of leaves to generate enough
heat to incubate their eggs. The farm with its Jersey herd, llamas and
Shetland ponies was also on view. Small wonder that it was past 8.00 pm
when the charabanc reached London with its well entertained and inspired
passengers.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997952" page_id="56260748"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
34
</page>
<table confidence="0.9677856" page_id="56260748"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
BARNICOAT - CHESTNUT LODGE
Cyril Laubscher
Helen Hughes, the Hon. Editor, Raymond Sawyer and Fred Barnicoat.
Cyril Laubscher
Caribbean or Rosy Flamingos.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.641444" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260749" page_num="35" year="" vol="">
BARNICOAT - CHESTNUT LODGE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.991359" page_id="56260749"  page_num="35" year="" vol="">
35
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.700545">
Daniel Shearing
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989358625" page_id="56260749"  page_num="35" year="" vol="">
Caribbean or Rosy and Greater Flamingos, the latter feeding a chick.
The accounts of these garden parties were almost annually repeated in
th q Avicultural Magazine. As Jean Delacour wrote in 1926: "Mr Ezra being
continually building new aviaries and extending his collections, it is rather
a difficult task to give an account of them which will not be out of date at the
time it is published." Whoever wrote about Foxwarren Park came under the
magical spell of the place, and between the lines, the same sort of wistful
sigh - "ah, Foxwarren Park" - is discemable.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996162" page_id="56260750"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
36
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.876439" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260750" page_num="36" year="" vol="">
BARNICOAT - CHESTNUT LODGE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.983083976190476" page_id="56260750"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
Soon after the death of Alfred Ezra OBE in 1955, the name of his daughter,
Miss Ruth Ezra, residing at Chestnut Lodge, Cobham, Surrey, appeared in
the Avicultural Society membership list. I had always assumed that Chestnut
Lodge was part of the Foxwarren Park estate, but it is in fact an entirely
separate property just a few miles (kilometres) away. Strangely enough,
when Ruth Ezra purchased the property, the address had already appeared
in the long annals of the Avicultural Society, for I have discovered Chestnut
[sic] Lodge, Cobham, Surrey, was the address of a Miss Florence E. Wigram
who was listed as a member from 1903-1908. This property has been destined
to play an enormously prominent role in the history of the Avicultural Society,
because here Ruth Ezra and Raymond Sawyer (Mr &amp; Mrs Raymond Sawyer
since April 14th 2004) have established one of the finest privately owned
collections of birds in the world. Ruth Ezra succeeded Jean Delacour as the
Avicultral Society President over 20 years ago, and the annual garden party
has continued to be the highlight of the society's year.
I live in Johannesburg, South Africa, and have not travelled very much
in my life, but in 2006 I was about to stay in England for a week with my
friends, the well-known bird photographer Cyril Laubscher and his wife, on
my way to the USA. I took the opportunity to write to Ruth Ezra and
Raymond Sawyer, asking if it might be possible to view their bird collection.
Imagine my excitement when by return of post I received such a kind
invitation for Cyril Laubscher and myself to have lunch with them on Friday
May 12th, and then view the collection. A further pleasant surprise was in
store for me, in that our current Hon. Editor, Malcolm Ellis and Helen Hughes,
a friend who had driven him to Cobham, were also invited, and I enjoyed
one of the most interesting days of my life.
England in May is exquisite, and the journey by car to Cobham was
through countryside in all its spring beauty. The house and grounds and
aviaries are beautiful. I shall never forget the warm welcome I received,
Raymond's delightful wit, the sumptuous lunch, the dining room table's
silver centrepiece representing the animals of the English countryside, from
the stag to the hedgehog, and Roland Green's original painting of the Pink-
headed Duck from living specimens (two males and a female) at Foxwarren
Park (published in the June 1932 issue of the Avicultural Magazine ), along
with numerous other bird paintings hanging in the hallway.
I refrain from going into detail of the birds in this wonderful collection,
as I could not do justice to it. Suffice it to say that it is in a way a microcosm
- albeit still a large and grand one - of Foxwarren Park. The house is in a
commanding position on high ground overlooking superb gardens. Opposite
its main entrance is a lovely lake with flamingos and other waterfowl. Cranes
still prance at freedom on spacious lawns and there is still a herd of wallabies,
including white ones. Very successful results are achieved breeding some
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.641784" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260751" page_num="37" year="" vol="">
BARNICOAT - CHESTNUT LODGE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998165" page_id="56260751"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
37
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.978701205882353" page_id="56260751"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
rare species of tortoise, for which heated quarters are provided for the winter,
and for which there is a huge demand from zoos.
The magnificent aviaries reflect Raymond's love of and expertise in
horticulture, and there are very successful attempts at particular aviaries
reflecting specific habitats, e.g desert plains or rainforest. The more delicate
and tropical softbills are provided with the comfort of hothouse conditions
with tasteful tropical plants. The main theme of the collection is exotic
softbills, so one gets to see many of the exquisite species of honeycreeper,
tanager, sunbird, robin-chat, roller, flowerpecker, cotinga, etc. Several
species of turaco have also bred well in the spacious, open aviaries. There
are also a number of species of wading birds, e.g. Avocets Recurvirostra
avosetta and plovers tastefully displayed in aviaries with ponds and close-
cropped lawns, as well as beautiful shrubs and cacti.
Perhaps for me the most interesting part of the visit was the time spent
looking through the old photograph albums of Foxwarren Park. The
magnificent house looked even more impressive to me than Chartwell, still
fresh in my mind from the previous day's unforgettable visit. There were
photographs taken of Alfred Ezra and his brother Sir David Ezra, who was
visiting from India. We reminisced about so many of the great characters in
the long history of the Avicultural Society, most of all Jean Delacour, arguably
the greatest aviculturist of all time, who loved visiting Chestnut Lodge to
enjoy the company and the gorgeous birds to be viewed in the collection.
He had celebrated his 90th birthday in this house, and had telephoned
Raymond from California on the day before his death at the age of 95 in
1985. There are numerous treasures in the house - Ruth's mother had
belonged to the highly distinguished Sassoon family - and memorabilia of
visits by royalty and other events that have taken place here, as well as
Raymond's many triumphs showing birds at the National Exhibition of Cage
and Aviary Birds in his more youthful days - when through the years he won
the Supreme Award at this most prestigious event more times than any other
exhibitor, and, of course, in later years was sought as a judge more often
than anyone else.
The time was so pleasant, it was gone in a flash. Ah, Chestnut Lodge!
May it last forever.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.286406" page_id="56260751"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.703175" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56260751" page_num="37" year="" vol="">
PRESIDENT'S GARDEN PARTY
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.884675666666667">
This year's President&amp;apos;s Garden Party will be held on Saturday July 14th
at Chestnut Lodge, Cobham, Surrey. Members are advised to book early for
this popular event.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998478" page_id="56260752"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
38
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.970389" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260752" page_num="38" year="" vol="">
TWO SPECIES OF COTINGIDAE BRED IN GERMANY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99941075" page_id="56260752"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
In the December 2006 issue of the German avicultural journal Gefiederte
Welt , pp.358-359, Dr Ulrich Schiirer, Director of Wuppertal Zoo reported
on the successful breeding of the Scarlet Cock-of-the-Rock Rupicola
peruviana and the Purple-throated Fruitcrow Querula purpurata.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.657425">
Copyright Chris Brack
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9923555" page_id="56260752"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
At just over IIV 2 months old, the male Scarlet or Andean Cock-of-the-Rock,
had started to acquire adult plumage.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.934039" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260753" page_num="39" year="" vol="">
TWO SPECIES OF COTINGIDAE BRED IN GERMANY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998214" page_id="56260753"  page_num="39" year="" vol="">
39
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9814954" page_id="56260753"  page_num="39" year="" vol="">
In 2004 two Scarlet or Andean Cock-of-the-Rocks were reared
successfully by the keeper of the Bird House, Thomas Rosner and his wife,
and the following year one was reared. In 2006 the Scarlet Cock-of-the-
Rocks bred again and this time the female was allowed to get on with it by
herself. The clutch consisted of two eggs. One was infertile but the other
hatched and the chick was very well looked after and reared successfully.
The Tropical Bird Hall was closed to visitors during the breeding. The
pair of rarely imported Purple-throated Fruitcrows had been kept in the same
hall and had tried to breed, but after the pair disturbed the breeding of the
Scarlet Cock-of-the-Rocks, the pair was removed and housed in an aviary
to which the public did not have access. There the pair nested and hatched
a chick which was reared by the bird keeper. It is believed to be the first
successful breeding of this species in captivity.
The report was accompanied by a photograph of the young fruitcrow,
whose black plumage was still covered by the remains of the buff-coloured
down, which may be useful as camouflage. This disappeared slowly. It has
never been photographed before. A more detailed report of both breeding
successes will be published shortly in the journal Der Zoologische Garten.
Our thanks to Dr Herbert Schifter for providing an English summary of
Dr Schurer's report.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.828995" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56260753" page_num="39" year="" vol="">
FUNDING SUPPORT TO CONTINUE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.966090333333333" page_id="56260753"  page_num="39" year="" vol="">
At the recent Council Meeting, held on Saturday March 31st at
Waddesdon Manor, it was agreed that the society will continue to support
the Hombill Research Foundation's Hombill Family Adoption Programme
in southern Thailand. It will also continue to support Prof. Fen-qi's study of
the Blue-crowned Laughingthrush Garrulax courtoisi (formerly considered
a subspecies of the Yellow-throated Laughingthrush G. galbanus) in China,
especially his search for G. c. simaoensis. Generous support will also
continue to be given towards the cost of distributing the Foreign Bird
Federation&amp;apos;s Breeding Register.
In addition, the society has agreed to provide funding towards research
aimed at learning more about the Bugun Liocichla Liocichla bugunorum,
the new species discovered recently in north-eastern India (see Avicultural
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.332844" page_id="56260753"  page_num="39" year="" vol="">
Magazine Vol.l 12, No.3, pp.123-124 (2006)).
</table>
<page confidence="0.990294" page_id="56260754"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
40
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9911665" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260754" page_num="40" year="" vol="">
NEWS ON THE CAPTIVE MANAGEMENT
OF LEAR'S MACAW Anodorhynchus leari
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.94706908" page_id="56260754"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
by David Waugh and Matthias Reinschmidt
Lear's Macaw, a CITES Appendix 1 species endemic to north-east Brazil,
is designated as Critically Endangered in the IUCN Red List (BirdLife
International, 2006) because it has an extremely small population which
breeds and is resident in one area (of 3,900sq km or approx. 1,500sq miles).
In its semi-arid habitat of the caatinga it has a close relationship with the
Licuri Palm Syagrus coronatus, which produces the hard fruits which form
the major part of this macaw's diet. Given that stands of Licuri Palms
formerly covered 250,000sq km (approx. 96,000sq miles) but have been
vastly reduced by livestock grazing, it is threatened by the degradation of its
habitat. It is further threatened by illegal trapping for trade (BirdLife
International, 2000, 2006) and macaws are occasionally shot by farmers
where attacks on maize crops occur.
Action for the conservation of the wild population and its habitat has
been underway for a number of years and a plan was published recently to
clarify and prioritise the necessary conservation measures (IBAMA, 2006).
The plan includes the use of captive breeding as an ex situ conservation tool
for the species. Loro Parque FundaQon of Tenerife, Spain, together with
the Brazilian Government agency IBAMA (Brazilian Institute of Enviroment
and Renewable Natural Resouces) and other partners, are contributing to
the field conservation project. Furthermore the LPF Curator, Matthias
Reinschmidt, is the international studbook keeper, with support from Onildo
Marini-Filho of IBAMA and Ryan Watson of A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation
(AWWP). This article presents current information about the captive
population.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.989462">
Table 1. Distribution of managed population.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.974033555555556" page_id="56260754"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
Participating institution
Countiy
Status*
A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation
Qatar
4.5.0
Crax - Wildlife Research Society
Brazil
1 . 1.0
Harewood Bird Garden
UK
1.2.0
Loro Parque Fundacion
Spain
2.2.0
Lymington Foundation
Brazil
2.4.0
Rio de Janeiro Zoo
Brazil
6.5.0
Sao Paulo Zoo
Brazil
3.5.0
* males, females, gender unknown.
Total
19.24.0
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.335076" page_id="56260755"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
WAUGH &amp; REINSCHMIDT - LEAR'S MACAW
</equation>
<page confidence="0.997489" page_id="56260755"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
41
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.980757" page_id="56260755"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
In the studbook (Reinschmidt, 2006) there are seven participating
institutions with a total of 43 officially incorporated birds (Table 1). These
currently form the managed captive population coordinated by IBAMA, the
birds being on deposit from the Brazilian Government. There is an additional
specimen confiscated in October 2006 by the competent authorities in Brazil,
which will be incorporated into the managed population. Two further females
are also likely to join the official population. In addition, there is an
undisclosed number of Lear's Macaws in Switzerland, for which there is no
definite prospect of inclusion in the officially managed population.
Demographically the managed population requires a breeding momentum
to add more young birds, as can be seen in the age pyramid (Fig. 1). An
improvement in the current sex ratio of 0.74, by the addition of more males
is also required. However, the breeding programme is still at an early stage.
Because most of the macaws were recruited into the population as confiscated
young birds taken in their first year of life, these are close estimates of their
ages, even though they are registered in the studbook as wild-caught.
Furthermore, endoscopic examination of the condition and stage of
development of the gonads of these birds reveal that at seven to eight years
of age they are only just reaching reproductive maturity (Crosta &amp; Timossi
in litt.). This coincides with the first studbook registered breeding which
occurred at A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation in Qatar, which has the oldest
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.727987">
birds.
Fig. 1. Age pyramid of the managed population of Lear's Macaw.
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.883214333333333" page_id="56260755"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
Age pyramid of the managed population of Lear's Macaws
Number of Specimens
4 , 3 ~ &amp;apos; &amp;apos;1 2 &amp;apos; 3 " &amp;quot; 4 ;IjS||Jf|
</figure>
<page confidence="0.995436" page_id="56260756"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
42
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.427759" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260756" page_num="42" year="" vol="">
WAUGH &amp; REINSCHMIDT - LEAR'S MACAW
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9760105" page_id="56260756"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
Given that 42 of the studbook registered macaws are wild-caught,
founders apparently constitute 97.6% of the captive population, a remarkable
and positive situation. However, given that these macaws were taken from
nests and often were confiscated together, there is a reasonable probability
that the founders (which by definition should be unrelated) include siblings.
However, despite this possibility, the genetic situation overall is favourable,
as can be demonstrated by the work in progress of Prof. Cristina Miyaki and
her team at the Institute of Molecular Genetics, University of Sao Paulo.
Prof. Miyaki has carried out DNA analysis from blood samples obtained
from these macaws and has been able to calculate a genetic similarity index
between all of the individuals. Thus, she has all possible pairings ranked
according to the statistical probability of genetic relatednes of the birds (in
five categories ranging from lowest relatedness = A - highest relatedness =
E).
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.791962">
Table 2. Pairings of Lear's Macaws in the managed population, with level
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.96417637037037" page_id="56260756"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
of genetic relatedness currently and after re-pairing within each institution.
Level of relatedness
Current
pairings
Re-pairings
No.
%
No.
%
Low (A, B)
5
29.4
11
64.7
Medium (C)
3
17.7
5
29.4
High (D, E)
9
52.9
1
5.9
Total
17
100.0
</figure>
<page confidence="0.676733" page_id="56260756"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
17
100.0
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.979328">
Table 3. Level of relatedness following possible re-pairings of Lear's
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.569244875" page_id="56260756"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
Macaws within each institution.
Participating institution
Relatedness of pairings
Al Wabra Wildlife Preservation
1A, IB, 2C
Crax - Wildlife Research Society
IE
Harewood Bird Garden
N/A
Loro Parque Fundacion
IB, 1C
Lymington Foundation
1A, 1C or 2B
Rio de Janeiro Zoo
4A, 1C
Sao Paulo Zoo
</table>
<page confidence="0.546437" page_id="56260756"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
3A
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9943435" page_id="56260756"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
In general terms (for scientific details see Miyaki et al. in prep.) this
indicates that the macaws sampled (17.21) have a total of 357 pairing
combinations, which show 115 (32.2%) in the low relatedness categories
(A, B), 131 (36.7%) in the medium category (C) and 111 (31.1%) in the
high categories (D, E). Currently all 17 males with known similarity indices
are paired with females with relative proportions of genetic relatedness as
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.334138" page_id="56260757"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
WAUGH &amp; REINSCHMIDT - LEAR'S MACAW
</equation>
<page confidence="0.999653" page_id="56260757"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9462273" page_id="56260757"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
shown in Table 2. The same table indicates the changes in these proportions
were re-pairing of macaws to take place within each institution, i.e. before
an interchange of macaws between institutions. The pairings according to
institution are shown in Table 3.
Given that in the first instance it be would be easier to manage populations
on a regional basis, it would make sense to exchange birds for further re-
pairings between the holding institutions in Brazil. From the 11.15 captive
Lear's Macaws currently in that country, it would be possible to form 11
low-relatedness (A) pairings. Any intention to re-pair these birds must take
into account the compatibility of the individuals within pairs, revealed
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.942586875" page_id="56260757"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
primarily by their behaviour, and the following precautions should be taken:
1. Birds not in successfully reproducing pairs, should be given the
possibility of freely choosing a mate from a choice of birds housed in a
group/flock. However, before breaking up non-reproducing pairs, the
age of the birds should be taken into consideration.
2. Genetically acceptable pairings should be the aim, but before breaking
up existing pairs, their breeding history and age should be taken into
consideration.
</listItem>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.911868" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56260757" page_num="43" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9925895" page_id="56260757"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
Our thanks to Prof. Cristina Miyaki for making available to us the
rankings of relatedness of possible pairings.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.94907" genericHeader="references" page_id="56260757" page_num="43" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.987880272727273">
BirdLife International. 2000. Threatened Birds of the World. Lynx Edicions and BirdLife
International, Barcelona and Cambridge, UK.
BirdLife International. 2006. Species factsheet: Anodorhynchus leari. Downloaded from http:/
/www.birdlife.org on 7/12/2006.
IBAMA. 2006. Management Plan for the Lear's Macaw ( Anodorhynchus leari). Endangered
Species Series 4. Brazilian Institute of Environment and Renewable Natural Resources, Fauna
Species Protection Coordination, Brasilia.
Reinschmidt, M. 2006. Lear's Macaw (Anodorhynchus leari) International Studbook, Annual
Report and Recommendations for 2006. Loro Parque Fundacion, Puerto de la Cruz, Tenerife.
Prof. David Waugh is Director of the Loro Parque Fundacion and
Matthias Reinschmidt is Curator at Loro Parque.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998026" page_id="56260758"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
44
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9900845" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260758" page_num="44" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEW
WATERFOWL ECOLOGY AND MANAGEMENT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.972434818181818" page_id="56260758"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
The first edition of Waterfowl Ecology and Management was published
in 1994. It was a mammoth compendium with more than 1,600 citations
and 12 chapters, covering every aspect of waterfowl ecology and
management, principally in North America. Additional research and
knowledge has now resulted in the original edition being revised and greatly
expanded. The second edition cites more than 2,600 works and is much
more international in scope.
Its 12 chapters cover the following headings: Introduction and historical
overview, Waterfowl classification, Courtship behaviour, mating systems
and pair-bond formation, Reproduction ecology, Feeding ecology, Nesting,
brood rearing and molting, Winter, Mortality and harvest management, Major
waterfowl habitats, Wetlands and wetland management, Waterfowl policy
and administration, Conclusion.
The book has several Tnfoboxes' with information about individuals,
species and even research facilities, all of which have played a part in
enriching waterfowl science. The individuals covered include Sir Peter Scott,
Jean Delacour and Janet Kear. The Tnfoboxes' describe the tremendous
contributions made by these aviculturists and these sections alone make the
book a worthwhile acquisition.
Each section is detailed and provides much food for thought. The authors
are open and admit that their views may not be the last word on topics such
as classification, noting that "...waterfowl taxonomy is a dynamic topic,
which constantly seeks to discover true relatedness, and hence new
information necessarily obliges updated classification..."
This book is not an avicultural treatise. There is, however, a considerable
amount of information likely to be helpful to aviculturists. There is, for
example, a description of the epizoology of botulism. I know of no other
book that so succinctly describes the cycle: toxin production, maggot
ingestion and die-off.
Photographs, charts and drawings adorn the pages. Although most would
expect colour images, I found the black and white ones most attractive and
in many cases, such as the old photographs of hunters, they place them in
perspective.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.97606025">
Waterfowl Ecology and Management , Second Edition, by G. A.
Baldassarre and E. G. Bolen (ISBN 1-57524-260-5) is published by the
Krieger Publishing Company, Malabar, Florida, USA.
Derian A.L. Silva Moraton
</reference>
<page confidence="0.997378" page_id="56260759"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
45
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9825675" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260759" page_num="45" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
EIGHTY-SEVEN YEARS OLD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991127166666667" page_id="56260759"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
Our distinguished member Derek Goodwin was 87 years old on February
26th 2007. Derek is not in the best of health, but is determined to remain
active and independent. He joined the Avicultural Society in 1945, and
appears to have been a member for longer than anyone else among our present
membership, followed by Prof. J. R. (Bob) Hodges who joined the society
in 1947.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8009415" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260759" page_num="45" year="" vol="">
* t *
CHESTER'S MASCARENES PROGRAMME
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.925623444444444" page_id="56260759"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
Chester Zoo continues to support several projects involved with the
conservation of endemic plants, birds and mammals on Mauritius and
Rodrigues and has recently added to its list, support for work on the predator-
free He aux Aigrettes - a small island off the coast of Mauritius.
Ninety Mauritius Fodies Foudia rubra have been introduced onto the
island and there are plans to add 25 Mauritius Olive White-eyes Zosterops
chioronothos. The zoo supports the in situ conservation programmes for
both of these Critically Endangered species, and the bird rearing experience
of its staff working on these projects has been integral to their success.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.851237" page_id="56260759"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.895587" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260759" page_num="45" year="" vol="">
BRUCE'S GREEN PIGEON BRED IN THE UK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9973628" page_id="56260759"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
In the weekly magazine Cage &amp; Aviary Birds January 25th, pp. 14-15,
2007, published here in the UK, Bill Daniel described breeding Bruce's
Green Pigeon Treron waalia. The breeding pair (two of four birds bought in
late 2004) built a substantial nest of twigs on a 15cm (6m) diameter circular
nest tray and the first egg was laid on January 13th 2006. The single egg
hatched successfully and the fledgling left the nest on February 23rd. During
2006, three chicks were reared, but several eggs and other chicks were lost
because young fledglings tended to try to roost on any new nest and would
beg the incubating bird for food and, in doing so, would knock the eggs or
small chicks off the nest.
Brace's Green Pigeon was named after The Reverend Henry James Brace
(1835-1909), an American missionary who worked in India from 1862 until
his death. Why, therefore, this species found in semi-arid country from
Senegal to Somalia, the island of Socotra and south-west Arabia was named
after him, is not immediately obvious.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996722" page_id="56260760"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
46
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9735525" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260760" page_num="46" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
PUBLISHER WITH PASSION FOR ORNITHOLOGY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9764934" page_id="56260760"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
Christopher Helm, a publisher whose passion for ornithology led to a
series of authorative and bestselling bird guides, many of which are frequently
used by aviculturalists, died on January 20th 2007, aged 69. His publishing
career, which began with Penguin and then Macmillan, began to blossom
after he teamed up with David Croom to start Groom Helm in 1972. Croom
Helm published many bird books including two, one an identification guide
to seabirds and another an identification guide to shorebirds, each of which
sold not far short of 100,000 copies worldwide. After Croom Helm was
taken over in 1986, he went solo and Christopher Helm (Publishers) Ltd
flourished for four years until it was sold to A&amp;C Black. Two years later, he
started again, this time with Pica Press, now also owned by A&amp;C Black.
Within 48 hours of Christopher Helm's death, reviewers were receiving
copies of Birds of Northern South America , the latest publication to carry
his name. Our Vice President Robin Restall has been heavily involved with
the last title.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.905787333333333" page_id="56260760"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
* * *
BOUGHT FROM A DEALER IN JOHANNESBURG
In November 2003, Isivuba Birds in South Africa, bought two males
and one female, long-tailed, White-crested Hornbills Berenicornis
( Tropicranus ) albocristatus. In the Field Guide to the Birds of East Africa,
p.246, Stevenson &amp; Fanshawe describe this mainly West African species,
which just reaches extreme western Uganda, as looking like "a giant wood-
hoopoe" Phoeniculus spp.
In Cage &amp; Aviary Birds March 22nd, p.21, 2007, Graeme Hoffman
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.880406285714286" page_id="56260760"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
described how the female first entered the nest box in August 2004. There
were two eggs, one was infertile and the other hatched but the chick was
found dead on the floor. The following year, the female had fully sealed
herself into the nest box by September 2nd and again laid two white eggs.
On December 11 th the female was heard tapping at the nest hole and having
enlarged the opening, emerged two days later, followed two hours afterwards,
by a single chick. The female had been in the nest box for 102 days. The
parents, especially the male, continued to feed the young hombill, thought
to be a male, until the end of February 2006.
I had previously heard of Graeme Hoffman from our recently elected
Vice President, Fred Bamicoat, who also lives in South Africa. Fred wrote
of Graeme's "new softbill collection" of "extraordinary quality" and said
that he (Fred) will try to get down to writing an article about it for the
Avicultural Magazine.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700588" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260761" page_num="47" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994426" page_id="56260761"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
47
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.988205" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260761" page_num="47" year="" vol="">
BIRDS IN AN AUSTRIAN ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.916035666666667" page_id="56260761"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
In International Zoo News Vol.54, No.l, pp.32-36 (2007), Gisela Bihler
wrote about the collection of birds and mammals at Raritatenzoo Ebbs in
Austria, established by Erich Eberl and his wife Amalie, that first opened to
the public in 1990.
Hombills kept there between 1997-2006 and the numbers reared (in
brackets), included White-crowned Berenicornis contains, Wrinkled Acer os
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.993856357142857" page_id="56260761"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
( Rhyticeros ) corrugatus ( 1), Red-knobbed Rhyticeros ( Aceros ) cassidix (7),
Papuan Wreathed or Blyth's P. ( Aceros ) plicatus, Malayan Rhinoceros
Hombill Buceros r. rhinoceros , Javan Rhinoceros Elombill B. r. silvestris,
Black-casqued Ceratogymna atrata, Yellow-casqued C. elata, Silvery-
cheeked Bycanistes ( Ceratogymna ) brevis and Trumpeter Hornbill B.
(i Ceratogymna ) bucinator (8). Eight Tarictic Penelopides sp. were also bred,
but as they proved to be hybrids, the breedings were halted.
After years of not showing any nest building acitivity, the colony of
Greater Flamingos Phoenicopterua ruber roseus raised six chicks in 2002,
and in subsequent years has produced five or six chicks each season. Other
species bred there have included the Common or Grey-winged Trumpeter
Psophia crepitans , Blue Crowned Pigeon Goura cristata and Victoria
Crowned Pigeon G. victoria.
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.709313" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260761" page_num="47" year="" vol="">
RARE FINCH CONSERVATION GROUP
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.853897333333333" page_id="56260761"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
A group of aviculturists in South Africa, which includes Fred Bamicoat,
Neville Brickell and Eelco Meyjes, along with Australian Russell Kingston,
has got together to found the Rare Finch Conservation Group (RFCG).
It is gathering information on wild and captive species, along with photos
of these birds, and the information and photos gathered so far can be found
on its website - www.rarefmch.co.za - which is still in its infancy. In addition,
the RFCG has launched a programme in Uganda, along with the Wildlife
Conservation Society, to undertake research on the little-known
crimsonwings Cryptospiza spp., of which Shelley's Crimsonwing C. shelleyi ,
the species chosen as the group's emblem, is of most concern. It is also
running a captive breeding programme for the Red-faced Crimsonwing C.
reichenovii. Other species kept by RFCG members include the Fawn-
breasted Waxbill Estrildapaludicola maixvitzi, Peters's Twinspot Hypargos
niveoguttatus, Green Twinspot Mandingoa nitidula chubbi and Western
Bluebill Spermophaga haematina.
If you would like to contribute information or photos, you should contact
Simon Espley by e-mail:simon@africageographic.com or Eelco Meyjes
at:editor@avitalk.co.za
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997786" page_id="56260762"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
48
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9780845" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260762" page_num="48" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
BRED REGULARLY AT CHESTER ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9934034" page_id="56260762"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
In 2006 Chester Zoo bred five West African Crowned Cranes Balearica
p. pavonina. The two clutches of eggs were taken from the birds and
artificially incubated in the zoo's incubation and rearing unit. Some of the
chicks were returned to their parents and others were reared by domestic
hens. Chester is one of the few European zoos regularly breeding this species.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.621499" page_id="56260762"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.592688" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260762" page_num="48" year="" vol="">
TWENTY-TWO QUETZALS RAISED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.719377" page_id="56260762"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
The Golden-headed Quetzal Pharomachrus auriceps was first bred at
Houston Zoo, Texas, in 1985, since when 22 offspring, both parent- and
hand-reared, have been raised successfully to adulthood.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.492645" page_id="56260762"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.403823" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260762" page_num="48" year="" vol="">
UP FOR THE CUP
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.893497571428572" page_id="56260762"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
In the Avicultural Magazine Vol.97, No.l, pp.9-13 (1991), W. D.
Cummings wrote about the 1990-1991 breeding season at Mitchell Park,
Durban, South Africa, the highlight of which had been the rearing of 22
Hartlaub's Ducks Pteronetta hartlaubii, all from one pair. The Crested
Guineafowl Guttera pucherani chicks had proved easy to rear and they were
pleased to have reared Cape Parrots Poicephalus robustus for the first time,
after years of trying. Others species bred had included Blue or Stanley
Crane Anthropoides paradisea , a wide variety of waterfowl and pheasants,
plus Sonnerat's Junglefowl Gallus sonneratii, Black-winged Starling Sturnus
melanopterus . Crested Myna Acridotheres cristate!lus and Jungle Myna A.
fuscus, Occipital Blue Pie Urocissa melanocephala , Pied Imperial Pigeon
Ducula bicolor and Black Crake Amaurornis flavirostris.
Little or nothing had been heard of this collection for a number of years,
until recently when concern was expressed about the derelict condition of
some of the enclosures. Now, Thembinkosi Ngcobo, the Municipality&amp;apos;s
Head of Parks, Recreation and Cemeteries, has announced that his department
is considering a proposal to allocate R30 million (approx. #2 million or
US$4 million) towards upgrading the park. This, it is suggested, could turn
Mitchell Park into a world class zoo and a major attraction for residents and
visitors ahead of the 2010 World Cup soccer tournament, which will be held
in South Africa.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998181" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260763" page_num="" year="" vol="">
SPECIAL INTEREST GROUPS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.977382555555556" page_id="56260763"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
It is vital now, more than ever before, that we establish self-sustaining
captive-breeding populations of as many different species as possible. With
this in mind, the Avicultural Society is supporting a number of Special Interest
Groups. These put keepers and breeders in touch with each other to exchange
information and birds, with the ultimate aim of forming the maximum number
of unrelated breeding pairs. Although all of the contacts listed below are
here in the UK, the Special Interest Groups are by no means confined solely
to UK aviculturists, but also welcome contact with aviculturists throughout
Europe, North America and elsewhere.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.671348166666667" page_id="56260763"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Contacts
Laughingthrushes Garrulax spp., Chestnut-backed Thrush Zoothera
dohertyi , Fairy Bluebird Irena puella , Rufous-bellied Niltava Niltava
sundara; Andrew Owen/Ian Hadgkiss - Tel:01296 653286/E-mail:
Andrew.Owen@nationaltrust.org.uk
Blue-crowned Laughingthrush Garrulax courtoisi; Laura Gardner - E-
mail:LauraGardner@leeds-castle.co.uk
Liocichlas Liocichla spp.; Nigel Hewston - Tel:01453 826944/E-
mail : nigelhewston@supanet. com
Barbets Capitonidae; Mike Curzon MBE - Tel:01373 824077/E-mail:
mcurzonmbe@ hotmail.co.uk
Fruit Doves, Ground Doves, Bleeding Hearts Columbidae; Rosemary
Wiseman - E-mail:ro.wiseman@virgin.net
Shamas and Magpie Robins Copsychus spp.; Barry Woodley - E-
mail :barry woodley @tiscali .co.uk
White-ramped Shama Copsychus malabaricus, Large Niltava Niltava
grandis, Spotted Morning Warbler Cichladusa guttata , Mockingbirds Mimus
spp.; Bob Jewiss - Tel:07910 353718/E-mail:bobby@blueyonder.co.uk
Corvids Corvidae, Hombills Bucerotidae, African Starlings Stumidae;
Geoff Masson - E-mail:geoffmasson@paultons.co.uk
Asian Starlings and Mynahs Stumidae; Rob Monk - Tel:01905 351649/
E-mail :rob@pickersleigh. co.uk
Toucans Ramphastidae; John Ellis - Tel:0207 4496436/E-mail:
john.ellis@zsl.org
</table>
<reference confidence="0.908229857142857">
Contacts are still required for the following: Yuhinas Yuhina spp., White-
eyes Zoster ops spp., Bulbuls Pycnonotidae, Robin-Chats Cossypha spp.,
Thrashes Turdidae, Pekin Robin Leiothrix lutea, Silver-eared Mesia L.
argentauris, Sibias Heterophasia spp., Rollers Coracias spp., Hoopoe Upupa
epops, Mousebirds Coliidae, Shrikes Laniidae, Sunbirds Nectariniidae,
Grosbeaks Fringillidae, BuntingsEmberizidae, Tanagers and Honey creepers
Thraupidae, Cardinals and Grosbeaks Cardinalidae.
</reference>
<bodyText confidence="0.6240505" page_id="56260764"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society. 1
Breeding the Black-throated Barbet Tricholaema melanocephala
by Martin Davies. 2
Cirl Bunting Emberiza cirlus Reintroduction Project
by Jo Gregson. 4
The bird collection at Waddesdon Manor
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.5849244375" page_id="56260764"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Andrew Owen.8
The Corncrake Species Recovery Programme
by Jamie Graham...13
Keeping and breeding the Greater Bird of Paradise Paradisaea apoda at
A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation, Qatar and Walsrode Birdpark, Germany
by Simon Bruslund Jensen. 22
On a visit to Chestnut Lodge
by Fred Bamicoat.33
Two species of Cotingidae bred in Germany.38
News on the captive management of Lear's Macaw Anodorhynchus leari
by David Waugh and Matthias Reinschmidt.40
Book Review
Waterfowl Ecology and Management.44
News &amp; Views.45
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</figure>
</algorithms>
