<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.596034" page_id="56259792"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 114
No. 1
2008
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259793" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.984827516129033" page_id="56259793"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2008 as for 2007: British
Isles #18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please).
The subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the
Society later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of
the AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, ARCADIA, THE MOUNTS, TOTNES, DEVON TQ9 7QJ,
UK.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TNI3 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail: Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have not
been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of a
particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history. Articles
should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the scientific
names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given. References
cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line drawings,
black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular point in
the article will be used where possible and should be clearly captioned. If
authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when submitting the
article and write their name on the back of each photograph. Tables and
graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be aware of
the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of the page
which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997594" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259793" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982475333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.757185" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259794" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.228894" page_id="56259794"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 114 - No. 1 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2008
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.355024">
The Avicultural Society
</subsectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.994182333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259794" page_num="" year="" vol="">
FOR THE STUDY OF BRITISH AND FOREIGN BIRDS
IN THE WILD AND CAPTIVITY
OFFICERS AND COUNCIL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.537372" page_id="56259794"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
As from April 5th 2008
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.302757">
President
</subsectionHeader>
<construct confidence="0.7636769" page_id="56259794"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
R. C. J. Sawyer
Vice Presidents
F. Barnicoat (South Africa)
M. Curzon MBE (UK)
J. M. Dolan Jr, PhD (USA)
C. J. S. Marler (UK)
The Rev. R. Noegel (USA)
Dr H. Quinque (France)
R. L. Restall (Venezuela)
Dr R. Wilkinson (UK)
</construct>
<figure confidence="0.979949571428571" page_id="56259794"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Honorary Editor
M. Ellis
Honorary Secretary - Treasurer
P. Boulden
R. S. Abrey
P. Convy
J. A. Ellis
Mrs L. Gardner
R. B. Girling
N. R. Hewston
G. Masson
S. Pyper
Members of Council
V. P. Sargent
P. G. Schofield
P. Stocks
J. G. Thurlow
B. Tremlett
J. Trollope
Ms R. Wiseman
Chairman C.J.S. Marler
</figure>
<page confidence="0.90912" page_id="56259795"  page_num="2" year="" vol="">
2
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.826243" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259795" page_num="2" year="" vol="">
THE NESTING BEHAVIOUR OF THE MUSOPHAGIDAE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.959783684210526" page_id="56259795"  page_num="2" year="" vol="">
by Myles Lamont
The Musophagidae are renowned for their poor nest making, with
their feeble attempts at nest construction often being likened to those of
the Columbiformes (Pigeons and Doves) (Payne, 1997; Isenberg, 1993;
Schroeder, 1991; Fry et al. 1988; Maclean 1985; Rowan, 1983; Berry
&amp; Todd, 1982; Britton &amp; Britton, 1976; Lamont, 2005; McLachlan &amp;
Liversidge, 1976; Stannard, 1971; Mackworth-Praed &amp; Grant, 1957; van
Someren, 1956; Courtenay-Latimer, 1942; Bannerman 1933; Friedman,
1930). Due to their poor nest building skills, most aviculturists do not
encourage natural nest building besides which most aviaries lack suitable
natural nest sites within their perimeters. This has in effect led to a gap
in our knowledge of the natural nest building behaviour of this family of
birds in captivity. There is also a lack of knowledge about this activity in
the wild.
Here at the Hancock Wildlife Research Center in Canada, each breeding
pair of turacos is provided with a nest platform measuring approximately
30cm x 20cm with a 7cm perimeter lip (12in x 8in with a 2%in perimeter
lip). This is similar to that used at other facilities (Bruslund Jensen,
2006; Lamont, 2006b; Paterson, 1993; Milne, 1991; Heston, 1987) and,
incidentally, is very similar in size to natural nest sites found in the wild
(Borghesio pers. comm. 2006; Rowan, 1983). In addition to a nest platform,
hanging or wicker baskets are used successfully, however, occasionally a
pair will decide to make its own nest.
Although a rather uncommon occurrence, natural nest construction has
occurred at the Hancock Wildlife Research Center and has resulted in some
interesting behavioural observations, most of which are described in more
detail later in this article.
There follows a summary of numerous published and some unpublished
records of nest observation of the Musophagidae compiled on a species by
species basis, both from the wild (in situ ) and in captivity (ex situ).
Nest observations
Species
Guinea or Green Turaco Tauraco persa
In the wild. Bannerman (1953) described the nest as roughly built
and bulkier than a dove's nest. That of I p. zenkeri was described by
Chapin (1939) as being a frail structure of dry twigs, placed in a low forest
tree and containing two eggs. Fry et al. (1988) described the nest as a
shallow platform 20cm-30cm (8in-lft) in diameter, made of sticks and
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.507087" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259796" page_num="3" year="" vol="">
LAMONT - MUSOPHAGIDAE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.941491" page_id="56259796"  page_num="3" year="" vol="">
3
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.976632285714286" page_id="56259796"  page_num="3" year="" vol="">
twigs interlaced together. It was said to be flimsy or compact but open,
with light showing through and looking reminiscent of a large dove's nest.
Nests were found 1.5m-3m (approx. 5ft-10ft) above the ground in a thick
portion of an isolated bush, a tree, and in a tangle of leaves and twigs on
the outer branches of a tree. Creepers are also used, but usually concealed
from view. Twigs are normally snapped from a tree and brought to the nest
one or two at a time. One nest took five days to complete. Payne (1997)
described the nest as a roughly built platform of twigs interlaced with finer
twigs and found in the thickest part of a bush or tree. He described it as
bulkier than a dove's nest.
In captivity. A flimsy platform of twigs, similar to that of other species
of turaco. A failed nesting attempt in thick ivy was also noted by Rutgers
and Norris (1972). A female T. persa x T. hartlaubi hybrid attempted to
nest in a clump of ivy, but did not complete the nest (Lament, 2006a).
The pair of T. p. buffoni kept by Home (1991) nested in a hanging basket
suspended in an elderberry bush.
Black-billed Turaco Tauraco schuetti
In the wild. Mackworth-Praed and Grant (1957) wrote of a stick nest
like that of other turacos in a thick tree or creeper. Chapin (1939) mentioned
that, "At Lukolela a female about to lay was collected on September 2nd,
and a nest was found under constmction in some dense second growth in
early December, but it was never completed." Referring to T. s. emini, he
wrote, "In the region of Medje we were shown nests on August 24th and
September 28th, frail stmetures of twigs, about 12ft (3.6m) up, in tangled
second growth." Fry et al. (1988) referred to a frail platform of twigs some
4m (approx. 13ft) above the ground in tangled growth in a tree. Payne
(1997) described the nest as a frail platform of twigs some 3m-5m (approx.
10ft-16ft) above the ground in tangled secondary growth.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.537837">
Schalow's Turaco Tauraco schalowi
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998822416666667" page_id="56259796"  page_num="3" year="" vol="">
In the wild. Mackworth-Praed and Grant (1957) described the nest
as a flimsy structure of sticks, some 10ft-30ft (approx. 3m-9m) above the
ground. Chapin (1939) made a brief mention of this species and described
the nest as, "...like a dove's, 12ft (3.6m) up in an acacia." Payne (1997)
wrote of a flimsy structure of sticks some 3m-10m (10ft-32ft) above the
ground in the thickest part of a tree or bush.
In captivity. Boehm (1967) wrote of this species building a "...much
more elaborate nest than has been observed in other turaco species we have
bred. The nest is more "jay-like" in its constmction. Not having experienced
nesting preparations of all turaco species, I cannot say definitely that this is
characteristic only of Schalow's." However, Roles (1973) wrote: "mating
was never observed and no form of nest building was seen to take place, the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.916556" page_id="56259797"  page_num="4" year="" vol="">
4
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.86702" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259797" page_num="4" year="" vol="">
LAMONT - MUSOPHAGIDAE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.94545925" page_id="56259797"  page_num="4" year="" vol="">
two dull white eggs being laid on April 13th 1972 on the totally unadorned
nest platform."
Fischer's Turaco Tauraco fischeri
In the wild. Britton and Britton (1976) wrote of a nest found 7.5m
(approx. 24ft) above the ground. It was described as a loose platform of
twigs with no lining or other nest material used. It was not taken as it could
only be removed in pieces. Fry et al. (1988) referred to a loose platform
of twigs placed 7.5m (approx. 24ft) above the ground in a Syzygium tree.
Payne (1997) described the nest as a frail platform of twigs placed 3m-10m
(approx. 10ft-32ft) above the ground in thick tree foliage.
In captivity. Milne (1991) described the nest as measuring 1 ft x 1 ft x 6in
deep (approx. 30cm x 30cm x 15cm deep). Twigs and grasses were placed
in the shallow box to help stimulate the pair to breed. Paterson (1993)
wrote that the nest box measured 1ft x 1ft x 1ft (approx. 30cm x 30cm x
30cm). The base was made of wire mesh and the front lip was 4in (10cm)
high; the roof had a 2in (5cm) overhang and slanted down towards the
front. The box was lined with apple tree twigs of uniform length (approx.
6in (15cm)) and thickness. The twigs were then reorganised by the birds.
Livingstone's Turaco Tauraco livingstonii
In the wild. The compact but transparent nest is a well woven mass
of large twigs with fine ones, usually in the top of a small tree and well
concealed (Mackworth-Praed &amp; Grant, 1957). Payne (1997) described it
as a well woven platform of sticks and twigs some 3m-10m (approx. 10ft-
32ft) above the ground in the thickest part of a bush or tree.
In captivity. Garsee (1992) noted: "I had an open platform with
6in (approx. 15cm) sides constructed and painted black. It was hung
approximately 6ft 6in (2m) high on the side of the aviary. I first placed
twigs in it for nesting, but they were not to their liking and were all thrown
out. They were replaced with natural wood fibre packing material and they
seemed to like this."
Knysna Turaco Tauraco corythaix
In the wild. Nests can be found at various heights from 3m-9m (approx.
10ft-30ft) above the ground, usually in a tangle of leafy twigs in the outer
branches of a tree; often among creepers and also in the crown of a tree fern.
Nests measure 20cm-30cm (8in-lft) across and are usually fairly flimsy
platforms of interlaced twigs with a shallow depression in the centre. Both
sexes seem to partake in nest construction, with one bird bringing twigs
to the nest site while the other works them into the nest (Rowan, 1988).
Stannard (1971) wrote: "Today I stood stock-still under the bougainvillaea
and by craning my neck, could see through the tangle of branches and
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.519856" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259798" page_num="5" year="" vol="">
LAMONT - MUSOPHAGIDAE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.90183" page_id="56259798"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
5
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.950798857142857" page_id="56259798"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
watch the birds come in, stand or sit on the nest and place their sticks right
inside the tangled mass of creeper." McLachlan and Liversidge (1976)
described the nest as a shallow platform of sticks placed in a tree or in thick
creepers.
Courtenay-Latimer (1942) described how he found a pair, "...building
in a Boerboon tree Scholia brachypetala approximately 12ft (3.6m) from
the ground. The nest was completed November 1st and measured roughly
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.588309">
1ft (30cm) in diameter, whilst the hollow or depression measured 4m-5in
(10cm-12.5cm) across. The foundation was built of fairly heavy sticks
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.98319070967742" page_id="56259798"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
with finer twigs towards the top and resembled a large dove's nest in
appearance." Maclean (1985) noted that the nest is a shallow platform of
sticks, like a large dove's nest, in a leafy tree or dense creeper. According
to Payne (1997), the nest is "...a shallow platform of sticks, much like that
of a large dove, 2m 9m (approx. 6ft 6m-7 9ft 6in) above the ground in a
leafy tree or among dense creepers."
In captivity. One nest was made in the top of a hawthorn tree where
a female took over a discarded nest of a Grey-winged Blackbird Turdus
boulboul and reared three young from two clutches. Further nests were
made in a basket in a pine tree (Everitt, 1965a). Payne (1963) wrote: "..at
the highest point in the shelter I put up a contraption made of thin saplings
and the last-year runners from the Russian vine made to resemble an open
nest, and into this saucer-like shape I put a handful of straw and rootlets."
At Cologne Zoo: "The eggs were laid in a wooden bowl, about 4ft 6m
(approx. 1.4m) above the floor of the inside cage. Little twigs which had
been placed on the floor for them had been used as nesting material" (Hick,
1964). Two young were reared in a nest that the parents built of pine
needles and green grass shoots in a shallow wooden tomato box in South
Africa. (Bamicoat, 1987).
Baenermae's Turaco Tauraco hannermani
In the wild. Payne wrote: "Nest a flimsy platform of twigs, well hidden
in thickest part of an isolated tree or bush among a tangle of creepers, or in
the thick foliage on outer branches at 1.5m 10m (approx. 5ft-32ft) above
ground in open forest or along forest edge."
Red-crested Turaco Tauraco erythrolophus
In the wild. The nest is assumed to be similar to that of other Tauraco
spp.
Yellow-billed Turaco Tauraco macrorhynchus
In the wild. Bannerman (1933) considered a nest found by Bates
(1909) and described as belonging to T. p, zenkeri , to actually be that of I
macrorhynchus. He went on to describe it as "placed in the thick top of
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.966764" page_id="56259799"  page_num="6" year="" vol="">
6
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.878513" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259799" page_num="6" year="" vol="">
LAMONT - MUSOPHAGIDAE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.982624675" page_id="56259799"  page_num="6" year="" vol="">
a low tree...and built of tiny dry twigs laid loosely together, so that it fell
to pieces when taken in hand." Fry et al. (1988) described the nest as a
flimsy platform of dry twigs, hidden in the thick foliage of a tree or creeper
7.5m-10m (approx. 25ft-32ft) above the ground. There was also mention
of a nest that was apparently located on the ground. Payne (1997) wrote:
"Nest a flimsy platform of dry twigs, well hidden in tree foliage, 7mT0m
(approx. 23ft-32ft) above the ground, reports of ground nesting on Bioko
require confirmation."
White-cheeked Turaco Tauraco leucotis
In the wild. The nest is a rather thick platform of dry twigs, very loosely
put together, with a slight hollow at the top (Mackworth-Praed &amp; Grant,
1957). Payne (1997) also described it as a rather thick platform of dry
twigs, loosely constructed with a slight depression at the top, built some
7m-10m (approx. 23ft-32ft) above the ground.
In captivity. Thomson (1991) stated that the birds did not make
substantial nests, rather more a gathering of flexible twigs placed randomly
together in a thick part of a tree or bush. Foxall and Burton (1975)
noted that a 9ft (approx. 2.7m) high section of a felled Lawson Cypress
Chamaecyparis lawsoniana was erected in a well-lit shelter. A nesting
platform was placed in the cypress and furnished with some small twigs,
but this arrangement was apparently ignored. The cypress twigs were still
green, but dry and brittle and it was these that the birds used to make their
own nest, 7ft (approx. 2.1m) above the ground in the cypress itself. When
completed the nest was quite substantial and measured approximately
8in-9in (20cm-23cm) in diameter and 4in (10cm) thick at the centre. A
pair in the Boehm aviaries nested successfully 10ft (approx. 3m) up in a
White Pine Pinus strobes. The nest of twigs, which was quite fragile, fitted
into a crutch in the branches and owing to its insecure appearance, was
supported by a wire-netting basket. The nest was prepared by the female
alone (Everitt, 1965a).
Rutgers and Norris (1972) noted that a pair of T. 1. donaldsoni had
nested approximately 9ft (2.7m) above the ground in a poplar tree Populus
sp. and laid three successive clutches of two eggs in the nest.
Prince Ruspoli's Turaco Tauraco ruspoli
In the wild. The nest is assumed to be similar to that of other Tauraco
spp.
Hartlaub's Turaco Tauraco hartlaubi
In the wild. A very pigeon-like flat, transparent tray of sticks, placed
among dense creepers in a bush or tree and usually within 15ft (4.5m) of the
ground (Mackworth-Praed &amp; Grant, 1957). The nest had previously been
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.48807" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259800" page_num="7" year="" vol="">
LAMONT - MUSOPHAGIDAE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.988324" page_id="56259800"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
7
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.993232512195122" page_id="56259800"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
described by van Someren (1956) as being comparatively low down and
characteristically near thick foliage and fine twiggy branches. It was said
to be loosely constructed of twigs, interlaced to form a shallow platform,
like a pigeon's nest. He noted that it is often so transparent that the eggs
can be seen from below. Finer twigs are sometimes used to line the nest,
which is usually on a horizontal branch.
Nests have been found in dense tangles of bush. They were quite thick
and approximately 20cm (8in) across and were cup-shaped (Borghesio
pers. comm. 2006). Fry et al. (1988) described the nest as, &quot;... a shallow
platform of loosely interlaced twigs, sometimes lined with finer twigs; eggs
showing through. Always built amongst fine, twiggy branches with thick
foliage, high in e.g. Rhus or thorny Chaetacme tree. Nest added to during
nestling period." According to Payne (1997) the nest is a platform of loose
sticks and twigs, sometimes lined with finer twigs. It is usually 3m-8m
(approx. 10ft-26ft) above the ground among thick tree foliage.
In captivity. Risdon (1954) wrote: "...we fixed up a bunch of twigs in
a comer of the flight. The middle of this was flattened out and a shallow
dish-shaped piece of wire netting was fixed to form a platform. On this
some coarse hay was shaped to form a foundation for a nest." Rutgers and
Norris (1972) described the nest as a platform of twigs, usually built among
creepers enveloping bushes or low trees and seldom more than 15ft (4.5m)
from the ground.
White-crested Turaco Tauraco leucolophus
In the wild. The nest is a saucer-like platform of dry twigs (Mackworth-
Praed &amp; Grant, 1957). It is built of small, dry sticks and twigs interwoven
into a saucer-like shape some 15cm (6in) in diameter, according to Fry et
al. (1988). One nest was located in some forked branches 7m (approx.
22ft) high in an acacia-like savannah tree, while another was found 3m
(approx. 10ft) above the ground in a small tree (Fry et al. 1988). Payne
(1997) described the nest as a flimsy saucer-shaped platform of interlaced
twigs and sticks 3m-7m (approx. 10ft-22ft) above the ground, often in an
acacia.
In captivity. Brown (1971) witnessed an unusual nesting attempt, in
which the pair nested on the floor and only sat at night. Unsurprisingly,
nothing came of the eggs.
Purple-crested Turaco Tauraco porphyreolophus 1
In the wild. Rowan (1983) described the nest as a flimsy, unlined
platform of intertwining twigs, through which the eggs can often be seen
from below. Favoured sites are among matted creepers and in dense
parasitic growth. Maclean (1985) described the nest as a platform of sticks
in a tree or creeper, up to about 4m (13ft) above the ground, often in an
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.885284" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259801" page_num="8" year="" vol="">
LAMONT - MUSOPHAGIDAE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97322485" page_id="56259801"  page_num="8" year="" vol="">
isolated thicket or at the edge of a forest. According to Fry et al. (1988) the
nest is a flimsy platform of interwoven twigs 3m-9m (approx. 10ft-30ft) up
in a tree, well concealed in a matted creeper or in parasitic growth. Both
sexes are involved in its construction. The nesting tree is usually isolated
on an open savannah or is part of a dense thicket. Payne (1997) described
it as a flimsy, unlined platform of twigs 3m-9m (approx. 10ft-30ft) above
the ground, well concealed in a tree among matted creepers or in dense
parasitic growth.
In captivity. Jarvis and Currie (1974) described how a cut pine tree was
fixed upright in the enclosed section of the aviary and a wire mesh platform
90cm (almost 3 ft) in diameter was placed in it lm (approx. 3 ft 3in) from
the earth floor. The platform was covered with pine needles which the
birds later rearranged. An empty orange box with an open top, prepared
with a layer of fresh hay, to which the birds added a few small sticks, was
also used successfully by this species (Raison, 1992).
Rwenzori Turaco Ruwenzorornis johnstoni 1
In the wild. Fry at al. (1988) described the nest as being a small platform
of sticks built lm-3m (approx. 4ft-10ft) above the ground in a clump of
bamboo. Payne (1997) also described it as being a small platform of sticks,
often in a clump of bamboo, but gave the height as being some 3m-5m
(approx. 10ft-16ft) above the ground.
Violet Turaco Musophaga violacea
In the wild. The nest was described by Mackworth-Praed and Grant
(1957) as a slight structure of twigs in a bush 10ft-12ft (approx. 3m-3.6m)
from the ground. Fry et al.(l 988) described it as being a fragile pigeon-like
nest of twigs and sticks in a leafy tree some 6m (20ft) up.
In captivity. Nests are usually made on a typical nest platform of the
type described earlier or in a basket. They have also been made by placing
sticks in the comer of a square frame designed for ibis and spoonbills to
nest on. This species has also built its nest in a Berberis sp. (Gomis pers.
comm. 2006). Nests consisting of fragile stick platforms, so transparent
and flimsy that the eggs could be seen through the bottom, 6.7m (approx.
22ft) above the ground, were noted by Bent (1988); who further noted that
the pair were seen carrying twigs broken from a Ficus sp. and taking them
l I have followed The Clements Checklist of the Birds of the World, Sixth
Edition (2007) and listed the Purple-crested Turaco in the genus Tauraco
and the Ruwenzori Turaco in the genus Ruwenzorornis. Some other recent
publications have placed both of them in the genus Gallirex and they may
also be found listed in the genus Musophaga or with the Ruwenzori Turaco
listed in the genus Tauraco with the Purple-crested species . - Ed.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.484196" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259802" page_num="9" year="" vol="">
LAMONT - MUSOPHAGIDAE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.931246" page_id="56259802"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
9
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.951174682926829" page_id="56259802"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
into artificial rock planters full of vegetation, which were approximately
6m (20ft) off the ground.
Ross's Turaco Musophaga rossae
In the wild. Mackworth-Praed and Grant (1957) described the nest
as a pigeon-like platform of sticks and Maclean (1985) described it as
a platform of sticks and twigs in a tree. Fry et al. (1988) gave a more
detailed account, describing it as a pigeon-like platform of sticks up to
60cm (almost 2ft) long, lined with twigs (375 in one nest) and 20cm-21cm
(approx. Sin -8%in) in diameter. It is built by the male and female 2m-16m
(approx. 6ft 62ft) above the ground, in a clump of thick foliage, mistletoe
or creepers, usually in an isolated tree. It takes the birds five to 16 days,
working mainly in the morning.
In captivity. Rutgers and Norris (1972) described the nest as a
flimsy platform of twigs fairly high above the ground. Some interesting
observations of nesting at Disney's Animal Kingdom were provided by
Congdon (2000). The nest was approximately 30ft 35ft (9m-10m) off the
ground in a clump of bamboo B ambus a sp. It consisted largely of sticks
approximately Vsin (2mm) in diameter and of various lengths. They were
not observed to be picked up off the ground, but were broken from three
branches. They also appeared to come from another tree, possibly a Chinese
Elm Ulmus parvifolia. There was also a large amount of leafy foliage.
Both the male and female took part in the nest building. Approximately
a month after the above observations were made, the nest was inspected
again and did not have so much leafy material but consisted mainly of
twigs and sticks. Plasse (pers. comm. 2006) noted that the birds apparently
succeeded in building the nest so that several stalks of bamboo were pulled
together by the twigs, leaves and rootlets that had been accumulated to
make the nest platform.
Royston (1974) noted that her birds made their nests partly of bunches
of long grass fixed high up in secluded places in bushes and trees in the
aviaries, the birds adding a few sticks and using the same nest for a second
brood. Steel (1973)&apos;wrote: "I hurriedly spent a whole afternoon erecting a
large log at the far end of the flight, up against a south-facing wall, hoping
that this might be a suitable home for them but not, they took no notice
of it whatsoever, but preferred to carry stupid pieces of stick to some
dangerously insecure branches in the greenhouse. I \0x25A0 endeavoured to help
them by putting some flat, dry laurel branches and leaves horizontally, but
for all their industrious stick carrying, everything fell to the ground again.
I then wove in a piece of wire netting upon which I thought they could lay
their sticks more securely." Eventually, a modified shopping basket with a
concave bottom, placed 6ft (1.8m) above the ground, was utilised as a nest
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.988266" page_id="56259803"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
10
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.86741" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259803" page_num="10" year="" vol="">
LAMONT - MUSOPHAGIDAE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.992886048780487" page_id="56259803"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
site.
Ellis (1975) mentioned a letter from Syd Downey in Kenya, in which
Mr Downey wrote: &quot;... the pair of Ross's Turacos had nested again and
hatched two chicks, but for some reason neither survived." They appeared
to have been sat on too heavily and, Mr Downey, wondered, if the nest
which he arranged for them, was too cup-shaped. He added, he knew that
in the wild the nest is a bare, flat platform. Milne (1990) described how
this species successfully used a bowl-shaped, thick wicker basket, 1ft 2in
(35.5cm) in diameter and Tin (17.5cm) deep.
Grey Go-away Bird Corythaixoides concolor
In the wild. Mackworth-Praed and Grant (1957) stated that this species
makes a stick nest like that of a pigeon, usually in dense creepers or high on
an acacia. Rowan (1983) provided further information, stating that the nest
is always built in a tree, most commonly a thorny species, and is usually
placed high in the crown. There may be a scant attempt at concealment,
as the chosen tree often has little or no foliage. The height of the nest
can vary from 1.5m-20m (approx. 5ft-65ft), but is most commonly 3m-
10m (approx. 10ft-32ft) above the ground. It is a platform of interlaced
twigs resembling a dove's nest in its simple and often flimsy construction.
It is usually 18cm-24cm (approx. I&apos;m-Wiin) across and about 3cm (l!4in)
thick. McLachlan and Liversidge (1976) described it as the usual dove-
like structure, often so thin that the eggs can be seen from below. It is up
to about 25ft (7.6m) from the ground, according to them, in a thorn tree or
sometimes a soft-foliage tree.
Maclean (1985) called it a scanty platform of sticks and twigs in a fork
or crown of a tree (usually thorny) or in a clump of mistletoe or matted
creeper 1.5m-20m (approx. 5ft-65ft) above the ground. A flimsy pigeon-
like nest measuring 18cm-24cm (approx. Tin^Ain) in diameter, with the
eggs visible from below, was how Fry et al. (1988) described it. Both sexes
partake in nest construction, building it 3m-20m (approx. 10ft-65ft) up in a
tree, usually an acacia. They may also build in a non-thomy species of tree
and in clumps of mistletoe and dense matted creepers.
In captivity. A pair at Busch Bird Park laid three eggs on a ledge of
a steel support beam (Young, 1975). Further notes by the same author
indicated that a flimsy nest of bamboo twigs was constructed in a clump
of bamboo, against the wire side of the enclosure approximately 20ft (6m)
above ground level and 8ft (approx. 2.4m) above the top of a waterfall.
Roles (1970) noted that a female at Jersey Zoo carried hawthorn twigs to
a wire nesting platform on a conifer branch, about 7ft (2.1m) above the
ground. The female and her mate built the nest entirely of hawthorn twigs;
oak and various other twigs lying in the aviary were left untouched.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.483204" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259804" page_num="11" year="" vol="">
LAMONT - MUSOPHAGIDAE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998066" page_id="56259804"  page_num="11" year="" vol="">
11
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.961333625" page_id="56259804"  page_num="11" year="" vol="">
Bare-faced Go-away Bird Corythaixoides personatus
In the wild. A round, loosely made stick nest in the fork of a tree,
generally an acacia (Mackworth-Praed &amp; Grant, 1957). "A shallow platform
of loosely interwoven sticks, sometimes lined with rootlets and dry grass,
in a fork or near the top of a tree, usually an acacia" (Fry et al. 1988).
In captivity. A wire platform designed for Threskiomithidae (Ibis and
Spoonbills) has been used, with sticks and twigs being placed in the middle
of the wire square, to make a poorly built nest (Gomis pers. comm. 2006).
White-bellied Go-away Bird Corythaixoides leucogaster
In the wild. A bare platform of sticks, which is usually almost
transparent, some 10ft-20ft (approx. 3m-6m) from the ground (Mackworth-
Praed &amp; Grant, 1957). The nest is usually placed in the crown of a tall
acacia tree. Friedman (1930) described the nest as a mere lattice of sticks,
10m (approx. 32ft) above the ground, near the end of a horizontal bough
of a large thorn tree. Built of twigs and thorns, it resembles a large dove's
nest and is so loosely constructed that an observer can look up through it
and see if it contains eggs or young. Fry et al. (1988) described the nest as
an untidy, thin and flat structure built of twigs, 3m- 12m (approx. 10ft-32ft)
above the ground in an Acacia xanthrophloea or other thorn tree.
In captivity. Isenberg (1993) found that the nest made by his birds
was worse than the most loosely built dove's nest and as a result the eggs
kept dropping out, until an artificial nest was woven for them using fruit
tree twigs. At Houston Zoo a second nest platform (smaller than the
first) contained a handwoven framework of dried vines over straw. This
was fixed to the shelter wall a short distance below the older nest which
contained only straw (Todd et al. 1985).
Western Grey Plantain-eater Crinifer piscator
In the wild. The nest was described by Fry et al. (1988) as a substantial
platform of dry, thin sticks, that was some 30cm (approx. 11 3 Ain) in diameter
and 12cm (4 3 /4in) deep. It was some 4m-10m (approx. 13ft-32ft) above the
ground in a leafy tree. Khaya senegalensis and Acacia albida have been
used.
Eastern Grey Plantain-eater Crinifer zonurus
In the wild. Mackworth-Praed and Grant (1957) described it as a large
nest of loose sticks and Fry et al. (1988) described it as a substantial nest
made of sticks, built near the top of a tree.
Great Blue Turaco Corythaeola cristata
In the wild. The nest, generally built high in a tree, was described by
Mackworth-Praed and Grant (1957) as a loose platform of small sticks,
appearing ridiculously small for the bird. This was contradicted by Chapin
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.993303" page_id="56259805"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
12
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.880613" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259805" page_num="12" year="" vol="">
LAMONT - MUSOPHAGIDAE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994546964285714" page_id="56259805"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
(1963), who noted that the nest of Corythaeola is the largest built by any
turaco and is composed mainly of dry sticks, some of which may be nearly
lm (3ft 9in) in length. The nest is said to often be in the forked branches
of a tree, some 20m (approx. 65ft) or more above the ground. Sites chosen
though can vary in height from 10m-16m (approx. 32ft-52ft) and may be
hidden in a clump of semi-parasitic mistletoe or in a creeper covered tree
(Candy, 1984).
Fry et al. (1988) provided the most complete description of the nest,
describing it as a well constructed to flimsy and insecure platform of dry
sticks, measuring 31cm x 51cm (approx. 1ft x 1ft 8in) with a shallow rim.
The base is made of sticks up to 61cm (2ft) long, with smaller twigs used
to line the nest. It is constructed by both sexes usually over a period of
a week, some 8m-25m (approx. 26ft-82ft) above the ground in a tall tree
covered with creepers or in dense foliage and often in a clump of mistletoe.
Old nests may be re-used. Payne (1977) described the nest as usually being
a platform of dry sticks with a shallow rim, built by both sexes at 8m-25m
(approx. 26ft-82ft) in a tall leafy tree. The nest is often over water.
In captivity. It is relatively rare, hence there is a lack of information on
its captive breeding behaviour. It has been known to use nesting baskets
and has used a natural nest site, using leaf material in a clump of Cissus
antarctica (B. Macordes pers. comm. 2006).
The second part of the above article - Further notes on the White-
cheeked Turaco T. I leucotis - will be published in the next issue of the
magazine. The author, Myles Lamont, Avian Manager, Hancock Wildlife
Research Center, 19313 Zero Avenue, Surrey, British Columbia V3S 9R9,
Canada, would like to hear from those aware of other reports of turaco
nesting behaviour, either published or unpublished. E-mail:myles@
hancockwildlife. org
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.691588" page_id="56259805"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.956067" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259805" page_num="12" year="" vol="">
BATES'S FIREFINCH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9916988" page_id="56259805"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
Writing about additions to the London Zoo collection, Arthur Prestwich
(A.A.P.), Avicultural Magazine Vol.53, No.5, p. 191 (September-October
1947), listed among the "more interesting arrivals," Bates's Firefmch
Lagonosticta rubicata virata , a bird new to the collection, from "Kulikoro,
French Sudan." Described by Bates in 1932, it is, of course, now accorded
full species status and known as the Mali or Kulikoro Firefmch L. virata.
It was first bred in the UK by Ian Hinze, who described the breeding
in the Avicultural Magazine Vol. 107, No.l, pp.27-34 (2001). Ian was
subsequently awarded the society's medal for the first UK breeding of this
West African firefmch.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.984243" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259806" page_num="13" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE RUFOUS-COLLARED SPARROW
</sectionHeader>
<keyword confidence="0.308461">
Zonotrichia capensis
</keyword>
<page confidence="0.999377" page_id="56259806"  page_num="13" year="" vol="">
13
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.993912162162162" page_id="56259806"  page_num="13" year="" vol="">
by Jim Jen ai d
According Clements (2007) the Rufous collared Sparrow Zonotrichia
capensis has 28 subspecies, whereas Howard &amp; Moore (1980) listed
25. Not surprisingly perhaps, it has a wide geographical distribution,
being found from the highlands of southern Mexico southwards to Cape
Horn. The four other members of the genus, the White-crowned Sparrow
Z. ieucophrys , White-throated Sparrow Z alhicollis , Golden-crowned
Sparrow Z atricapilla and Harris's Sparrow Z. querula , breed in North
America.
The sexes of the Rufous-collared Sparrow look alike, so I was pleased
to purchase a proven pair at the Stafford Show in spring 2006. During the
summer of that year I had no luck with the pair, only clear eggs were laid
- nine in all. So in September I caged the pair for the winter and fed the pair
seed only until the following February. I then began to feed some livefood
to the pair and, by March, the female was ripping up the paper covering the
floor of the cage and the male was starting to sing.
On March 14th I put the two into a flight measuring 9ft x 3 ft x 6ft
(approx. 2.7m x 0.9m x 1.8m) and supplied them with dry grass, dog hair
and sisal. On April 5th the female began to build in an open nest box, about
5ft (1.5m) above the ground. The first egg was laid on April 10th and was
followed by a further two. The female began to incubate on April 12th and
10 days later two chicks hatched. The other egg was clear. The chicks
were ringed (banded) at seven days old by my friend Sean Fitzpatrick and
left the nest on May 3rd, aged 11 days old.
On May 6th, the female laid again and, on May 8th, was once more
incubating a clutch of three eggs. As the male was continuing to feed the
two young from the first nest, I left them with their parents. Unfortunately,
they harassed the female while she was sitting and perhaps as a result of
this, the eggs became addled and were abandoned on May 15th.
I removed the two young on May 17th. The female cleaned and relined
the nest and laid again on May 24th - a further clutch of three eggs. All
three hatched on June 6th and when the chicks were seven days old they
were ringed by Sean Fitzpatrick. When they were 23 days old I removed
them from their parents.
Following their removal, the female went to nest yet again, this time
choosing a slightly higher nest site. There was a clutch of four eggs, which
should have hatched on July 24th, but when tested on the 26th, proved to
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99884" page_id="56259807"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
14
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.796583" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259807" page_num="14" year="" vol="">
JERRARD - RUFOUS-COLLARED SPARROW
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995667107142857" page_id="56259807"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
be clear. Fortunately, I was able to use this to my advantage, as in the next
flight a pair of buntings Emberiza sp. 1 were nesting and, that same day,
I noticed some eggshells on the floor, one of which had a chick stuck to
it. On inspecting the nest, I found it contained a chick and an egg. I left
things as they were and went to get some livefood, however, on my return I
found the remaining chick on the floor. It was cold, but by holding it in my
cupped hands and using my warm breath, I managed to revive it.
I immediately transferred it and the remaining egg to the nest of the pair
of Rufous-collared Sparrows, while doing so removing their clear eggs.
When I checked the nest again less than half an hour later, I was delighted
to discover that the buntings' egg had hatched and the nest now contained
two chicks. The foster parents made quite a commotion, but all went well
and both chicks were reared successfully. They were ringed at seven days
old and left the nest at nine days.
It was the first time I have bred the Rufous-collared Sparrow, and I
found the species very easy to cater for. The nests were very deep and
the eggs were stony-grey, heavily blotched and streaked rusty red at the
large end. In the past, when I kept this species, the eggs that were laid
were similar in coloration to those of the Blackbird Turdus merula (i.e.
usually bluish-green or greenish-blue speckled and mottled light reddish-
brown). My Rufous-collared Sparrows are very lively birds but are shy
and would leave the nest and hide when I entered the flight, as did the
young. The latter had brown backs, grey underparts heavily streaked with
brown and lacked the rufous collar and well defined head markings. The
five Rufous-collared Sparrow chicks and the two bunting chicks the pair
fostered were all reared on buffalo worms, small crickets and, after the
first week, waxworm larvae. The young of both species were ringed with
TO.A. rings size D.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.3645855">
1 The identity of Jim Jerrard's buntings has been the subject of a
number of letters between the two of us. He is convinced that his birds are
</footnote>
<reference confidence="0.777601222222222">
Somali Golden-breasted Buntings E. poliopleura, but I am not so sure and
think it more likely that they are the more wide-ranging Golden-breasted
Bunting E. flaviventris. A colour photo of the buntings can be seen in the
Avicultural Magazine Vollll, No.4, p.162 (2005). If they prove to be the
Somali Golden-breasted Bunting, he will be the first person in the UK to
have bred this species.- Ed.
Jim Jerrard, who lives in south Yorkshire, here in the UK, would like to
hear from anybody who breeds foreign buntings. He can be contacted via
the Hon.Editor.
</reference>
<table confidence="0.461995" page_id="56259808"  page_num="15" year="" vol="">
PARENTAL BEHAVIOUR BY TWO PAIRS OF
GUAM MI C RON ESI AN KINGFISHERS
Halcyon cinnamomina cinnamomina
</table>
<page confidence="0.933901" page_id="56259808"  page_num="15" year="" vol="">
15
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.974595583333333" page_id="56259808"  page_num="15" year="" vol="">
by Jennifer J. Elston, Christy Sky, Glorieli Quinones,
Jennifer Carney, Chelle Plasse and Tammie Bettinger
Introduction and background
Historically, the Guam Micronesian Kingfisher Halcyon c. cinnamomina
- hereafter referred to as the Micronesian Kingfisher - existed throughout
the forested regions of Guam 1 (Fry et al. 1992). The population of this
subspecies was decimated following the unintentional introduction of
the Brown Tree Snake Boiga irregularis to the island and by 1986 the
Micronesian Kingfisher was extinct in the wild (Savidge, 1987; Wiles et
al. 2003). Today, the Micronesian Kingfisher survives only in captivity
as part of a captive propagation programme. The birds are spread among
11 institutions in the USA and one on Guam (Bahner, 2006). The goal of
the propagation programme is to increase the population through captive
breeding for release in the future on Guam or other appropriate sites (U.S.
Fish and Wildlife Service, 2004).
Despite the accomplishments of the programme in keeping this
subspecies alive, breeding the birds in captivity has presented challenges,
including that of the failure of the parents to rear their offspring (Bahner et
al. 1997), resulting in the majority of offspring being hand-reared (Bahner,
2006). The hand-rearing protocol has been instrumental in increasing the
population of Micronesian Kingfishers, because chicks that may otherwise
have perished through parental inexperience or neglect, have survived by
being hand-reared. In addition, when their eggs are removed from the nest,
the females lay a further clutch (Oehler, 1990), so maximum egg production
can be encouraged during the breeding season. As a result of the extensive
need to hand-rear the chicks, little is known about the parental behaviour
of the Micronesian Kingfisher. A larger more stable population of these
birds needs to be established in captivity before reintroduction attempts
occur, and information regarding parent-rearing behaviour is necessary so
that avian managers can feel confident that these birds are sufficiently able
to care for their offspring. Parent-rearing experience gained in captivity
may better prepare the birds for reproductive success in the wild (Wallace,
1994).
During the 2005 and 2006 breeding seasons, we had the opportunity
to study parental activity by two pairs of Micronesian Kingfishers housed
at Disney's Animal Kingdom, Lake Buena Vista, Florida, USA. Our
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996818" page_id="56259809"  page_num="16" year="" vol="">
16
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.854847" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259809" page_num="16" year="" vol="">
ELSTON ET AL - GUAM MICRONESIAN KINGFISHER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9026995" page_id="56259809"  page_num="16" year="" vol="">
objectives were to record the frequency and duration of parental visits
to the nest log during incubation and nestling periods and to establish
a preliminary database documenting parent-rearing behaviour by the
Micronesian Kingfisher.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.985346">
Materials and methods
Subjects and housing
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997038514285714" page_id="56259809"  page_num="16" year="" vol="">
Two pairs of Micronesian Kingfishers were housed in separate off-
display, outdoor aviaries. Both pairs had visual access to other birds in the
facility, but did not have visual access to other Micronesian Kingfishers.
Other birds in the facility, including additional Micronesian Kingfishers,
were audible. The aviaries measured 6m x 6m x 2m (approx. 20ft x 20ft
x 6ft 6in) and 6m x 3m x 2m (approx. 20ft x 9ft 9in x 6ft 6in) and each
contained two or three decayed queen palm logs that could be used for
nesting.
One pair of Micronesian Kingfishers (a mature pair) consisted of a seven
year-old parent-reared male and a six-year old hand-reared female. The pair
had resided together for two years. Neither bird had prior experience of
parent-rearing a chick, but had previously incubated and hatched an egg in
2004. The 2004 chick was removed from the log three days after hatching
and hand-reared, after it was determined that the chick was not gaining
weight. The second pair of Micronesian Kingfishers (a novice pair) was
hatched and hand-reared at Disney's Animal Kingdom in 2004. At the
time of the study, the two birds were approximately two years old. The
pair had been housed together since fledging and had no prior experience
of breeding.
During reproductive periods food was provided ad-lib at least four
times a day. The diet consisted of pinkie mice, anoles, crickets, large
mealworms, superworms and waxworms (Crissey and Toddes, 1997).
Vitamin E (Roche, Nutley, New Jersey, USA) and chitin (Fisher Scientific,
Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA) supplements, manufactured in powdered
forms, were also offered to the birds daily in 2cm ( 3 Ain) plastic capsules that
were inserted in the pinkie mice or anoles (one capsule per bird each day).
Vitamin E was provided to enhance fertility and chitin was supplied in order
to replicate the insect exoskeletons in the natural diet. Supplementation
ceased when offspring were present in the nest log to avoid the risk of a
chick choking if an adult attempted to feed a capsule to it and resumed after
the chicks fledged. Because the aviaries are outside a variety of natural
foods, including insects, anoles, frogs and toads, were also available.
Mature pair
In July 2005 the mature female produced her third clutch of the season,
consisting of two eggs. The eggs from the previous two clutches had been
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.603684" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259810" page_num="17" year="" vol="">
ELSTON ET AL - GUAM MICRONESIAN KINGFISHER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.987582" page_id="56259810"  page_num="17" year="" vol="">
17
</page>
<author confidence="0.672458">
Christy Sky
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.489981">
Female Guam Micronesian Kingfisher chick aged 27 days in nest log.
</affiliation>
<bodyText confidence="0.997930625" page_id="56259810"  page_num="17" year="" vol="">
removed from the nest log for the chicks to be hand-reared. In the case
of the third clutch, one egg was removed so that the chick could be hand-
reared and the second egg was left with the parents to incubate. Daily
video recordings were made at the nest log from the day the chick hatched
until it fledged. The chick was weighed when the opportunity arose up
until day nine, when its size and behaviour made it difficult to remove it
from the nest log.
In early summer 2006 a bullet camera was inserted inside the cavity
the pair had excavated in the nest log. In June 2006 the mature female
produced her third clutch of two eggs inside the nest log. Similar to the
2005 breeding season, the eggs from the previous two clutches were
removed from the nest log for the chicks to be hand-reared. With this
clutch, however, one egg was removed for the chick to be hand-reared and
the other egg was left in the nest log for the pair to incubate. All parental
activity inside the nest cavity during the day was recorded. The chick was
weighed when the opportunity arose up until the time it was removed from
the log to be hand-reared. Because the chick was removed from the log,
data were recorded only for the incubation and early brooding periods.
Novice pair
In July 2006 the novice female produced her fourth clutch of the season,
which consisted of two eggs. The eggs of the previous three clutches had
been removed from the nest log for the chicks to be hand-reared. With
the fourth clutch, one egg was left in the nest log for the pair to incubate
and the other egg was removed for the chick to be hand-reared. Video
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99783" page_id="56259811"  page_num="18" year="" vol="">
18
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.855098" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259811" page_num="18" year="" vol="">
ELSTON ET AL - GUAM MICRONESIAN KINGFISHER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.980321322580645" page_id="56259811"  page_num="18" year="" vol="">
recordings were made at the nest log from the day the chick hatched until it
fledged. It was weighed when the opportunity arose until day 10, when its
size and behaviour made it difficult to remove it from the nest log.
In August 2006 the novice female produced her fifth clutch. It consisted
of a single egg and the pair was given the opportunity to incubate it. Daily
video recordings were made of all parental interaction at the nest log.
The egg was hatched successfully and the chick was weighed when the
opportunity arose, up until the time that it was removed from the nest to be
hand-reared.
Data collection
All video recordings were made using VCRs between approximately
06.30-20.30hrs. Tapes were scored for all behaviours (behavioural
sampling: Martin &amp; Bateson, 1993) exhibited by the birds while at the nest
log (see Table 1), as well as the number of visits to the log, the time of
the visits, length of the visits and the sex of the bird. During the 2006
incubation and nestling periods the daily temperature and relative humidity
were recorded by HOBO data loggers (Onset Computer Corporation,
Bourne, Massachusetts, USA) that were positioned on the outside of each
pair's nest log. After fledging the young birds were sexed based on feather
coloration (i.e. males have a cinnamon coloured breast; females have a white
coloured breast) and feather/tissue analysis (Avian Biotech International,
Tallahassee, Florida, USA). Egg and chick data for both pairs during the
2005 and 2006 breeding seasons are presented in Table 2.
During incubation periods a total of 269.5 hours of video was recorded
for the mature pair (June 2006) and a total of 239.3 hours of video for
the novice pair (August 2006). During nestling periods a total of 274.8
hours of video was recorded for the mature pair (July 2005) and a total of
337.6 hours of video was recorded for the novice pair (July 2006). Food
provision was not scored for the mature pair, because the position of the
camera made it difficult to observe whether a bird had food in its beak
when it arrive at the nest log.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.909559">
Results
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998514444444444" page_id="56259811"  page_num="18" year="" vol="">
Incubation and early brooding periods
Mature pair - July 2006 and novice pair - August 2006
There was some variation between the two pairs in the percentage of
time birds spent in the nest log per day during the incubation period (see
Table 3). Birds spent time in the nest cavity throughout the day and on
average fewer than 15 minutes elapsed without a bird being present in the
nest log. Both pairs hatched their chicks after an incubation period of 25
days. The bullet camera in the mature pair's nest log made it possible to
determine that the chick began hatching in the morning at 09.07hrs and
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.609582" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259812" page_num="19" year="" vol="">
ELSTON ET AL - GUAM MICRONESIAN KINGFISHER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998849" page_id="56259812"  page_num="19" year="" vol="">
19
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9749661" page_id="56259812"  page_num="19" year="" vol="">
36.2 minutes later the majority of the chick's body was freed from the
shell
Staff determined that each pair's chick was not gaining weight after
hatching (see graph below). As a result, the mature pair's chick was
removed from the nest log on day three and the novice pair's chick was
removed for hand-rearing on day four. During the first few days after
the chicks hatched and before they were removed from the nest logs, the
mature pair and the novice pair spent a large amount of time in their nest
logs (85.46% and 72.13% of time per day, respectively). In addition, both
pairs made visits to their chick during this time (the mature pair 4.37 visits
per hour; the novice pair 2.83 visits per hour), however, food provision
was observed only twice in the case of the mature pair and three times in
the case of the novice pair. Both chicks were females. The average daily
temperature was 26.6*C (79.9*F) and the average relative humidity was
81.3% during the incubation and early brooding periods.
Fig. 1. Both parent-reared chicks fledged from the nest log and both early
brooded chicks were removed from the nest log for hand-rearing at three
and four days old.
Nestling period
Mature pair - July 2005 and novice pair - July 2006
The mature pair's chick hatched after an incubation period of 23 days
and the novice pair's chick after an incubation period of 24 days. Keepers
provided a small amount of supplementary food (chopped pinkie mice)
once a day for the first two days after hatching for the mature pair's chick
and for the first eight days after hatching for the novice pair's chick. Both
chicks gained weight steadily during the first few days after hatching (see
graph).
The mature pair entered the nest log on day one of the chick hatching,
however, only the female was observed entering the nest log after the first
day and neither bird was observed entering the nest log after day four.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.986802" page_id="56259813"  page_num="20" year="" vol="">
20
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.853962" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259813" page_num="20" year="" vol="">
ELSTON ET AL - GUAM MICRONESIAN KINGFISHER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999777642857143" page_id="56259813"  page_num="20" year="" vol="">
The novice pair entered the nest log on day one of the chick hatching and
continued to enter the nest log until day nine. Both pairs made chick visits
throughout the day. On average these occurred more than once per hour
and lasted fewer than 10 seconds (see Table 3). The mature male and
female made an equal number of chick visits during fledging (0.82 visits
per hour), however, the novice female made approximately twice as many
chick visits as the novice male (1.03 vs 0.44 visits per hour, respectively).
When food provision occurred, parents presented whole items of food to
the chicks. Both pairs began drilling new holes in their nest logs before the
chicks had fledged. The mature pair's chick fledged at 31 days and was a
male. Seventeen days after fledging it weighed 60.Og. The novice pair's
chick was a female. It fledged at 33 days and weighed 65.2g on the day
of fledging. The average daily temperature was 28*C (82.4*F) and the
average relative humidity was 69.1% during the 2006 nestling period.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.968253">
Discussion and conclusions
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99976388" page_id="56259813"  page_num="20" year="" vol="">
Incubation of the eggs and care of the chicks was undertaken by both
sexes, which signifies the importance of the participation of both parents
in the incubation of the eggs and the survival of the chicks. This finding
is similar to the natural behaviour recorded for other species of kingfishers
in the wild, in which male and female kingfishers are monogamous and
both participate in the excavation of the nest cavity and the rearing of the
chicks (Davis &amp; Graham, 1991; Fry et al. 1992). Oehler (1990) reported
the participation of both sexes in parental care by three different species of
kingfisher in captivity. Even though the novice male visited the nest log less
frequently than his partner during the nestling period, he was comparable
to the female in providing food for the chick when he did visit the nest log
(35.37% of visits by the male vs 28.94% of visits by the female), indicating
that he was sharing responsiblity for care of the chicks.
During the incubation phase, birds spent on average fewer than 15
minutes between visits. Because predation pressure was absent and external
disturbance (e.g. weather and humans, etc.) were miminal, the relatively
continuous time spent in the nest cavity may reflect the importance of
maintaining the proper temperature for the successful incubation of the
eggs. During the nestling phase, both pairs visited the nest log slightly more
than once per hour on average. Because chick visits occurred throughout
the day, it is important that food sources are readily available so that parents
can provide for their chicks.
Despite some variation between pairs regarding the percentage of time
spent inside the nest cavity during the incubation periods in 2006 (mature
pair's third clutch and novice pair's fifth clutch), both pairs successfully
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.609727" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259814" page_num="21" year="" vol="">
ELSTON ET AL - GUAM MICRONESIAN KINGFISHER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997793" page_id="56259814"  page_num="21" year="" vol="">
21
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997771961538462" page_id="56259814"  page_num="21" year="" vol="">
hatched their chicks, indicating that the amount of time each pair spent
inside their nest log was sufficient for successful hatching to occur.
However, even though both pairs successfully incubated and hatched their
eggs and were observed visiting their nest logs and brooding their chicks,
the decision was taken to remove the hatchlings for hand-rearing because
of the lack of weight gain during the first few days after hatching. In both
instances in which the parents successfully reared their chicks, far less time
was spent inside their nest logs after the chick hatched than during the
occasions when it was necessary to remove the chicks for hand-rearing.
It appears that in both of the latter cases the parents failed to switch their
roles from incubation/brooding to more actively caring for the hatchlings
(i.e. food provision). In the case of the Micronesian Kingfisher, there are
probably many factors that contribute to the ultimate success or failure of
a clutch, and successful incubation and/or fledging of offspring by a pair
during one attempt does not always mean that the pair will be consistently
successful in future reproductive attempts.
This study provides evidence that hand-reared birds can successfully
incubate and hatch their own eggs and parent-rear their own offspring,
which is encouraging for the propagation programme and future plans for
reintroduction to the wild. However, when a pair is given the opportunity
to parent-rear a chick, regardless of the individual parents' own parent- or
hand-rearing background, or even their previous success at rearing chicks,
careful monitoring of the chick should occur and supplementary feeding
by keepers may sometimes be necessary. Although the sample size of the
study was small, it provides information that can be used when giving pairs
the opportunity to incubate their own eggs and rear their own offspring.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.989551">
Table 1. Ethogram used during the reproductive periods 2005 and 2006.
</tableCaption>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.3192435">
Behaviour
Description
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.920786375" page_id="56259814"  page_num="21" year="" vol="">
Entered nest log
Bird moved its entire body through the entrance hole
and into the nest log.
Chick visit
Bird landed at nest log entrance hole and placed its
head inside the hole; maybe accompanied by shaking
of the body; occurred when offspring was present
inside log.
Food provision
Visit made to the chick by a parent with an item of food
visible in its bill and the food was deposited inside the
nest log.
Drilling 1
Bird flew at nest log and struck it one or more times
with its bill.
Adapted from Bahner et al. 1997.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994639" page_id="56259815"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
22
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.502841" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259815" page_num="22" year="" vol="">
ELSTON ET AL - GUAM MICRONESIAN KINGFISHER
</sectionHeader>
<tableCaption confidence="0.97434">
Table 2. Egg and chick data 2005 and 2006.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.988716470588235" page_id="56259815"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
Pair
Year
No. of
clutches
No. of
eggs (i)
No.
hatched
No.
fledged 00
Success
rate (iii)
Mature pair
2005
7
12(1)
4
4(1)
33.33%
Mature pair
2006
5
8(1)
4
2(0)
25.00%
Novice pair
2006
5
9(2)
7
6(1)
66.67%
(i) Number in parentheses indicates number of eggs incubated by parents.
(ii) Number in parentheses indicates number of parent-reared offspring.
(iii) Number fledged/number of eggs.
Table 3. Parental activity during incubation and nestling periods 2005 and
2006.
Activity
Mature pair
Novice pair
Incubation periods 2006
Average percent of time spent
inside nest log per day
62.34
45.48
Average length of time spent
inside nest log per visit
16.76mins
12.53mins
Average length of time between
nest log visits
9.75mins
13.97mins
Nestling periods 2005 and 2006
Average percent of time spent
inside nest log per day 1
28.06
24.59
Average number of chick visits
per hour
1.79
1.50
Average length of chick visits
5.85secs
3.97secs
Percent of chick visits that
food was provided
</figure>
<page confidence="0.412452" page_id="56259815"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
30.58
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.506042" page_id="56259815"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
1 Refers to the four days after the mature pair's chick hatched and the nine
days after the novice pair's chick hatched.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.929376" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56259815" page_num="22" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9925145" page_id="56259815"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
We wish to thank the Aviary Team and Animal Research and Technology
Team at Disney's Animal Kingdom for their cooperation during this study.
Special thanks are extended to Cheryl Tybor for video recording and care
of the birds, Jennifer Gaudio and Ginger Stanley for project support and
Sue DuBois for assistance with video equipment. Christy Sky took the
photograph.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.610174" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259816" page_num="23" year="" vol="">
ELSTON ET AL - GUAM MICRONESIAN KINGFISHER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996224" page_id="56259816"  page_num="23" year="" vol="">
23
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.974465" genericHeader="references" page_id="56259816" page_num="23" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.9635792">
Bahner, B. 2006. North American regional Guam Micronesian kingfisher Halcyon cinnamomina
cinnamominia studbook. Zoological Society of Philadelphia, Philadelphia.
Bahner, B., Baltz, A., Diebold, E. 1997. Micronesian kingfisher species survival plan
husbandry manual.
Crissey, S., Toddes, B. 1997. Diets for Micronesian kingfisher Halcyon c. cinnamomina. In:
Micronesian kingfisher species survival plan husbandry manual pp.41-54. Bahner, B., Baltz,
A., Diebold, E. (eds.).
Davis, W. J-, Graham, D. J. 1991. The influence of food on reproductive strategies in a
monogamous kingfisher (Chloroceryle amazona ). Auk 108:780-789.
Fry, C. H., Fry, K., Harris, A. 1992. Kingfishers, Bee-eaters and Rollers. Princeton University
Press, Princeton, New Jersey.
Martin, P., Bateson, P. 1993. Measuring behaviour an introductory guide, second edition.
Cambridge University Press, New York, N.Y.
Oehler, D. A. 1990. Successful propagation of three Halcyon kingfisher species at Cincinnati
Zoo. Avicultural Magazine 96,1:1-9.
Savidge, J. A. 1987. Extinction of an island forest avifauna by an introduced snake. Ecology
68:660-668.
U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service. 2004. Draft revised recovery plan for the Sihek or Guam
Micronesian kingfisher (Halcyon cinnamomina cinnamomina). Portland, Oregon.
Wallace, M. P. 1994. Control of behavioral development in the context of reintroduction
programs for birds. Zoo Biology 13:491-499.
Wiles, G. J., Bart, J., Beck Jr., R. E., Aguon, C. F. 2003. Impacts of the brown tree snake: patterns
of decline and species persistence in Guam's avifauna. Conservation Biology 17:1350-1360.
Jennifer J. Elston, PhD, Christy Sky, Glorieli Quinones, Jennifer
Carney, Chelle Plasse and Tammie Bettinger, Disney s Animal Kingdom,
PO. Box 10000, Lake Buena Vista, Florida 32830, USA. Contact: Chelle
Plasse, Assistant Curator of Birds, Disney s Animal Kingdom. Tel:(+1) 407
939-7339 /E-mail: Chelle.Plasse@disney.com Jennifer Elston is currently
Curator of Conservation and Behavior, Fort Worth Zoo, 1989 Colonial
Parkway, Fort Worth, Texas 76110, USA. Tel:(+1) 817 759-7315/Fax:(+l)
</reference>
<page confidence="0.703669" page_id="56259816"  page_num="23" year="" vol="">
817 759-7501/E-mail:jelston@fortworthzoo.org
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.878365" page_id="56259816"  page_num="23" year="" vol="">
l The island of Guam is about 30 miles (48km) long and 4 miles (6.4km)
to 10 miles (16km) wide. It is a US territory in the Mariana Islands and
is about 1,300 miles (2,100km) east of the Philippines. The Clements
Checklist of the Birds of the World, Sixth Edition (Christopher Helm,
2007), lists the Micronesian Kingfisher as Todiramphus cinnamominus
cinnamominus. - Ed.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998159" page_id="56259817"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
24
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.882676" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259817" page_num="24" year="" vol="">
GOLDIE'S LORIKEET: HAND-REARING
AND PARENT-REARING
by Rosemary Low
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998595888888889" page_id="56259817"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
During the 1970s many species were imported that previously were
virtually unknown in aviculture and while importations continued and
some breeding successes occurred, they were popular and easily acquired.
However, numbers gradually, almost imperceptibly, declined until, at the
end of the 1990s, people were asking: "Whatever happened to...?" Goldie's
Lorikeet Trichoglossus goldiei fell into this category but, fortunately, it is
one of the species that is making an avicultural recovery in Europe. It
originates from New Guinea, where is occurs in the main central mountain
ranges up to 8,500ft (approx. 2,500m). An ideal avicultural subject because
it is small, quiet, relatively inexpensive and a free breeder, it will nest in a
cage or aviary, indoors or outdoors. What more could one ask?
Our late member Stephanie Belford imported the first commercial
consignment into the UK in 1977. There were 30 birds and, under her care,
every one survived. The three pairs Bob Grantham and I bought from her
each took one year to enter a nest box! This is unusual for lorikeets who
normally roost in their nests. The first UK breeding occurred in 1979 and
mine first reared young in 1980. Today many breeders fail to realise there
were certain difficulties associated with breeding wild-caught birds - from
Australian parakeets to lorikeets - notably that they were very choosy over
nest sites.
I will now fast-forward nearly 30 years to March 7th 2007, when due
to the sad death of the owner, a pair of Goldie's Lorikeets arrived at my
home at quite short notice. I had been told there was a chick or chicks in
the nest box. Inspection revealed a downy little chick, with its eyes closed,
that I estimated to be 11-12 days old. It weighed 20g. I could not take the
risk of leaving it in the nest box in case due to the strange surroundings
the pair might fail to re-enter the nest box. I placed the pair in a totally
covered aviary measuring 8ft long x 4ft wide (2.4m long x 1.2m wide) in a
very sheltered position. The pair seemed to settle down very quickly and
within two hours had eaten a piece of pomegranate from a fruit holder and
consumed the nectar.
The chick was placed in a brooder with the temperature set at 94*F
(34*C). It was in a small container on a bed of tissues below which was a
facecloth; the tissues were packed around it as, of course, it was used to the
feeling of being brooded by the female. (After a few days it was moved
into a 8in (20cm) wide tub.)
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.579566" page_id="56259818"  page_num="25" year="" vol="">
LOW - GOLDIE'S LORIKEET
25
(c) Rosemary Low
At 24 days (and weighing 34g) the chick's tail feathers were starting to
erupt.
(c) Rosemary Low
Aged 28 days.
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.95025225" page_id="56259818"  page_num="25" year="" vol="">
It fed readily from a teaspoon with bent sides. The first couple of days
I fed it every two hours between 6.15am-10.45pm. The food consisted of a
fairly thin solution of Nekton Lory. After two days the food was changed
to Lory CeDe which makes up to a slightly thicker food. This was offered
every 2Vi hours. Throughout the rearing period a pinch of Nekton MSA was
given at one feed daily. This is my favoured source of calcium, minerals
and amino acids for growing parrot chicks.
For the purpose of this article I am assuming that the chick was 12 days
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.988974" page_id="56259819"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
26
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.59552" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259819" page_num="26" year="" vol="">
LOW - GOLDIE'S LORIKEET
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998614317073171" page_id="56259819"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
old when I received it. Three days after it arrived I ringed (banded) it with a
size N (5.35mm) ring. I think this is slightly too large for Goldie's Lorikeet
but size M (4.4mm) would probably have been too small.
By day 18 the chick's eyes were wide open. This usually occurs several
days after the eyes start to slit. By day 19 green feathers were starting
to erupt on the breast and sides. Two days later its ears were just open
(though difficult to discern). There was a red blush on the forehead where
the feathers were developing and prominent wing quills that had not yet
emerged. By day 23 it was quite thickly covered with grey down and the
growing tail feathers were just visible. The forehead and cheeks were dark
with growing feathers.
By day 25 its underparts were one third feathered and the red feathers
on the forehead were starting to erupt. Growth of the wing and tail feathers
was then rapid. By day 28 the underparts were half covered with striped
feathers but most of the upperparts were still very downy. By day 30 it was
flapping its little wings and its nails were very sharp and useful for clinging
on. I suspect that in the wild chicks might start to climb towards the nest
entrance at this stage.
It was just over 4in (11cm) in length and its tail measured nearly lin
(2cm) in length by day 33 and it was calling to be fed even before its crop
was empty. It had grown too large for the tub and was free to move about
in a large plastic container - within the brooder - with a floor of very small
gauge soft plastic mesh. At this age it was extremely appealing with its big
dark eyes and pretty markings.
By day 36 its underparts were fully feathered and the violet feathers
of the forehead were erupting. It had started to preen itself. A couple of
days later it would run about when removed from the brooder. The nape
was still downy and conspicuously bare of feathers and this also applied to
the area under the wings. By day 42 it was folly feathered except for the
nape, although down protruded through the wing feathers. It was perching
on a small twig. On day 43, when it was taking nectar from a small, very
shallow container on the floor of the brooder, it was moved to a small cage.
From now on I will refer to the young lorikeet as her, as the bird's low peak
weight and small beak suggested to me that the bird was of the gentle sex
and, she had too much personality, to be thought of as "it".
Rearing this little bird was almost a new experience for me. At one time
I had 24 consecutive years of hand-rearing parrots. At times it was intense
and very hard work, along with the other tasks of running a collection.
During the past 11 years I had hand-reared only about a dozen chicks and
none since 2000. I thought I had put away my spoon forever, partly because
I had virtually stopped breeding from my pairs and because my attitude to
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.235822" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259820" page_num="27" year="" vol="">
LOW - GOLDIE'S LORIKEET
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996909" page_id="56259820"  page_num="27" year="" vol="">
27
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998885804878049" page_id="56259820"  page_num="27" year="" vol="">
hand-rearing has changed to the point where I consider it advisable only to
save the life of a healthy chick. To be able to focus on a single chick and
to watch very closely its development - physical and psychological - was
interesting and rewarding.
Awareness of her surroundings came first, then the desire to climb. The
next stage (at 38 days) was running when placed on a flat surface. At 40
days came the need to flap her wings and to test surfaces with her tongue.
At 43 days she started to preen herself. At 45 days she was " cheeping " and
wanting to fly. The next day she took off and the following day she flew
to me and landed on my head. Within two more days she could control her
landings perfectly and fly very strongly. Small lorikeets fly very fast and
presumably have to learn quite quickly to keep up with the flock when it
is on the move visiting food trees. Contrast this with larger parrots which
are at first quite clumsy in flight and take a while to learn how to control
their landings. After mastering the art of flight she liked to sit in a hibiscus
plant and nibble at its leaves. It was not until day 55 that she roosted on a
perch at night.
It was a wrench to part with the young Goldie's Lorikeet at the age of
nearly eight weeks. She was weaned and I was going away two days later.
She was becoming too attached to me and needed a new home where she
could be with others of her own species. She loved to fly but after a couple
of circuits of the room she would return to me like a boomerang and perch
on my head. If she perched up high (on a pelmet or light shade), she would
fly down when I called her.
I wanted her to lead a normal life with her own species. Fortunately,
someone I knew had two Goldie's Lorikeets fledge just before she was
weaned. As he is that rarity, one of the few breeders intent on setting up
more pairs, rather than selling the young, I agreed that she should go to a
small aviary with these two youngsters
Meanwhile, the adult female of my pair laid the first of two eggs on
March 26th. On April 9th a ball hit the aviary by the nest box and the
female deserted. I gave one of the two eggs to an incubating Stella's
Lorikeet Charmosynapapou stellae but after three or four days it had gone.
About three weeks later the female Goldie's Lorikeet laid two more eggs.
They, too, were deserted and I suspected that the larger lories living nearby
were making them nervous.
On May 17th I moved the pair of Goldie's Lorikeets to a small
'detached' aviary with a fence and a buddleia behind it. The female laid
again at the end of June. After incubation commenced it was rare to see
the male or female outside the nest box. However, on July 21st the male
was out of the nest, trying to attract my attention by nibbling at a piece of
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99289" page_id="56259821"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
28
</page>
<table confidence="0.62227475" page_id="56259821"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
LOW - GOLDIE'S LORIKEET
(c) Rosemary Low
Aged 36 days. Note especially the pin-feathers on the head.
(c) Rosemary Low
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.9679862" page_id="56259821"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
At 50 days old it still had some down.
the previous day's Chickweed Stellaria media . I guessed he was trying to
tell me he needed more greenfood and possibly a more varied diet. The
chicks must have hatched! I found him some Chickweed, seeding grasses
and a golden flowering head of Smooth Hawk's Beard Crepis capillaris
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.235447" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259822" page_num="29" year="" vol="">
LOW - GOLDIE'S LORIKEET
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.990722" page_id="56259822"  page_num="29" year="" vol="">
29
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.871098" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259822" page_num="29" year="" vol="">
(c) Rosemary Low
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998045272727273" page_id="56259822"  page_num="29" year="" vol="">
Parent-reared chicks at 34 days. One weighs 51g and the other 60g.
The day before they left the nest. The difference between the
male (right) and female (left) is apparent by the size and colour of
the head. Note also that young birds have a pale coloured cere.
from my garden. Dandelions Taraxacum officinale had temporarily halted
flowering and although hawk's head beard contains less pollen, the flowers
were eagerly accepted
I cautiously checked the nest the next day, when both birds were out
and found two very small chicks covered in white down. Within about
five days both adults were eating quite a lot of seeding dock Rumex sp.
at the green stage and millet spray. (When the young fledged they lost
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.993795" page_id="56259823"  page_num="30" year="" vol="">
30
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.599202" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259823" page_num="30" year="" vol="">
LOW - GOLDIE'S LORIKEET
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.904592951219512" page_id="56259823"  page_num="30" year="" vol="">
interest in seeding dock but, with the young, eagerly consumed Chickweed,
Dandelion flowers and spray millet.) I started to give them a little Nekton
Lory as well as the usual nectar mixture. All of my lories get small cubes
of Madeira cake, some sweet com kernels daily and a few soaked sultanas
a couple of times a week. All of these items were readily eaten by the
Goldie's Lorikeets along with the nectar.
I knew nothing of the breeding history of this pair, other than the fact
that the pair had fed the single chick for up to about 12 days, which was
when the pair and the chick were moved to my aviaries. I was therefore
quiet and rapid with my nest inspections every four days or so, which were
carried out only when both parents had left the nest. When the chicks were
about nine days old I removed the wet nest litter from the comers of the
nest and replaced it, leaving intact the dry litter on which the chicks were
resting. I did not touch them.
Two days later I removed the chicks and changed more of the litter, and
ringed (banded) the largest, although there was little difference between
them in size. I deliberately ringed it a day or so early, so that if the female
took a dislike to the ring she could remove it without injuring the chick's
foot. For the same reason I ringed only one of the chicks. I normally
have no qualms about ringing chicks but without knowledge of the pair's
breeding behaviour, I was cautious. The female has a silver coloured ring
on her left leg so she is familiar with rings. Two days later the chick's ring
had come off so I ringed it again and, on August 5th, ringed the second
chick, noting it had no food in its crop. The grey second down was then
tinged with yellow at the tip. On August 11th the ring had come off so I
re-ringed the chick - just in time. The parents showed no concern when I
removed the chicks to clean out the nest - and carried on feeding on dock.
The parents were especially keen on consuming pollen-filled blossoms
such as Dandelion, which were again available, and on eating Chickweed
and seeding dock. They became quite vocal when they saw me, apparently
inviting me to give them different foods. They were spending quite a lot of
time out of the nest, as the weather had become warmer (after a long cool,
wet spell).
By mid-August they entered the nest only to feed the chicks, and at
night. In the evening I often saw them nibbling at the leaves of a passion
flower Passiflora sp. that grew over the front of the aviary. This was
interesting because they were not short of seeding dock. I was handling
the chicks every second or third day when I changed the litter in the comer
of the nest box. On September 7th the young ones weighed 59g and 65g
and started to climb up the aviary mesh when I put them on the floor! The
parents, who were normally nonplussed when I handled their chicks, were
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.235854" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259824" page_num="31" year="" vol="">
LOW - GOLDIE'S LORIKEET
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999731" page_id="56259824"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
31
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.981977" page_id="56259824"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
very concerned and started to climb down to their young, so I quickly put
them back.
The first young one left the nest on the morning of September 10th.
It was flying and perching well. At dusk I returned it to the nest box but
it would not stay there with its sibling, so I placed it in the small shelter
where it stayed for the night. Early the next morning the second young one
fledged. The day was sunny, the sky clear and the night was set to be cool,
so I tried unsuccessfully to return the young one to the nest and to place
it in the shelter. I was worried about it - especially when my next-door
neighbour started a bonfire at 9.00pm close to the aviary. Thankfully, the
next morning all was well.
By September 17th both young were nibbling at apple. A couple of days
previously they had started to spend a lot of time in the shelter with their
parents, so they might also have been taking nectar, although the parents
were still feeding them. None of the family went near the nest box after
the second youngster fledged, which is unusual behaviour for lorikeets. At
night they slept on a perch with overhead cover.
Some days before they fledged I knew that the oldest was a male and the
youngest was a female. The male had a larger head and beak and slightly
more extensive red on the forehead. With adults the head and beak of the
male are usually larger and he generally has more extensive red markings
on the head.
At the time of writing (October 31st 2007) they are still with their
parents - and I intend to leave them there indefinitely. I could spend hours
watching this delightful family group. Observing the interactions between
individual birds and their young at play is, for me, the most rewarding part
of aviculture.
Postscript
On November 13th when they were moved indoors for the winter their
weights were as follows: adult male 58g, adult female 53g, young male
52g; the young female was not weighed.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99859" page_id="56259825"  page_num="32" year="" vol="">
32
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.992475" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259825" page_num="32" year="" vol="">
NEWS FROM WALSRODE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999097256410257" page_id="56259825"  page_num="32" year="" vol="">
In 2007 the first attempts were made to set-up a gull colony in one of
the large flight aviaries. Walsrode started off with 11 Grey-headed Gulls
Lams cirrocephalus and two Mediterranean Gulls L. melanocephalus , two
species which exhibit classic colony-based breeding behaviour. In the past
it had been reluctant to display large groups of gulls due to their copious
and corrosive droppings. However, the liveliness of the birds and the fact
that visitors are able to observe their natural behaviour, outweigh the fact
that some boulders have white blotches that are difficult to remove, along
with the realisation that these are as much part of life in a gull colony as the
loud calls and lively intrigues between pairs.
Staff had fairly high hopes that such a large group of birds would breed
and increase in numbers and, the first eggs were laid early, but shortly
thereafter went missing and later clutches also disappeared without trace.
They wondered if this problem might have been due to a Weasel Mustela
nivalis and carefully observed the colony to rule out the fact that the gulls
may have been stealing each others eggs. To their surprise, the culprits
proved to be two young Siberian Cranes Grus leucogeranus sharing the
exhibit with the gulls. Each day the cranes would swim to the gull colony
and systematically 'sweep' the ground for fresh eggs. Staff only managed
to secure a few eggs before the end of the breeding season, but having
identified the culprits, will be better prepared this year. The concept of a
gull colony has proved popular with visitors and gulls alike.
Until now Walsrode's pair of Congo Peafowl Afropavo congensis had
restricted breeding status within the EEP (European Endangered Species
Programme) studbook and as such was not allowed to breed due to risks
related to inbreeding. Instead the pair was given chickens' eggs to hatch
and was allowed to rear the chicks as a form of enrichment and to keep the
pair in practise in case it might be required to foster young of another pair
of Congo Peafowl or some other species. The most recent edition of the
studbook, however, takes into consideration the fact that very few founders
now remain and it is unlikely that new bloodlines from the wild will
become available. This year, therefore, the pair will be allowed to breed
and staff at Walsrode are hopeful that the pair will produce fertile eggs
and healthy chicks. Within the captive population, a number of problems
occur, all likely related to inbreeding. These include poor feather quality,
poor fertility and the tendency for chicks to suffer from metabolic bone
disease. The recent diagnosis of type A diabetes in a male Congo Peafowl
at Walsrode is also of concern. It is the first time that this mainly inherited
disease has been diagnosed in a Congo Peafowl.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.958816" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259826" page_num="33" year="" vol="">
NEWS FROM WALSRODE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999078" page_id="56259826"  page_num="33" year="" vol="">
33
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998368878048781" page_id="56259826"  page_num="33" year="" vol="">
The Crested Guineafowl Guttera pucherani produced quite a few
chicks in 2007. Walsrode's birds have the characteristic face and neck
coloration of the nominate subspecies G. p. pucherani , sometimes called
the Kenya Crested Guineafowl, but consistently have a black collar,
a characteristic of other subspecies such as G. p. verreauxi and G. p.
barbata. It is unclear whether Walsrode's birds represent a colour morph,
originate from a population in which two subspecies had intergraded,
are a previously unrecorded geographical variant, or there is some other
explanation. Walsrode's Crested Guineafowl can be traced back to birds
imported from Kenya in the 1960s. They were identified originally as
G. edouardi grand (a subspecies found in eastern Tanzania) but later the
taxonomy was reviewed and this subspecies was renamed G. pucherani
grand. Following a further review grand is no longer recognised as a valid
subspecies. Walsrode Birdpark also has Vulturine Guineafowl Aery ilium
vulturinum and tries to simulate their behaviour in the wild by keeping
them in a group outside the breeding season and letting pairs form within
the group and then isolating them in a separate aviary in April or May
depending on the weather.
The Laughing Kookaburras Dacelo novaeguineae reared two single
chick clutches in 2007 and as expected the chick from the first clutch assisted
in rearing the second chick. By keeping these birds in such groupings
as opposed to only in pairs, Walsrode hopes to present this interesting
kingfisher in a much more active and dynamic fashion. The difficulty for
the keepers, however, is to determine when it is time for the young to be
removed in order to avoid aggression. Once a bird has been away from
the group for more than a few days it is impossible to reintroduce it back
into the group. Therefore, If a bird is removed for treatment its isolation is
likely to become permanent until a new home can be found for it in another
collection.
The Hoopoes Upupa epops reared their first clutch unnoticed in a
nesting chamber that was intended for the Carmine Bee-eaters Merops
nubicus. The latter failed to breed successfully in 2007, probably due to the
rather skewed sex ratio within the colony, rather than the presence of the
Hoopoes. In the aviary there are a number of very old male Carmine Bee-
eaters, several of which are almost 20 years old and no longer breeding. It
seems that males live longer than females and these old males spend a good
deal of time harassing younger pairs that are attempting to breed. This year
the colony has been split up into a bachelor group and a breeding group
with an even sex ratio.
A pair of Homed Guans Oreophasis derbianus arrived from Mexico
as part of an international breeding project. After release from quarantine
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998223" page_id="56259827"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
34
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.992498" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259827" page_num="34" year="" vol="">
NEWS FROM WALSRODE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9887155" page_id="56259827"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
the two birds proved to be a very compatible pair. The pair is housed
in one of the off-exhibit breeding complexes. Thanks to donations the
Walsrode Birdpark Foundation has been able to commit to a parallel in
situ conservation project, for at least the next five years, to benefit this
Endangered species in the wild.
Six Black Munias Lonchura stygia were received from a breeder in
Flensburg, Germany. This New Guinea species is under threat in the wild
due to habitat loss. The Black Munia is rare in aviculture in Europe and
Walsrode is pleased to have found a dedicated breeder of this species.
All of the birds arrived closed ringed (banded) and with exemplary
documentation.
On a Sunday evening in October 2007, it became clear that Walsrode
would have to say goodbye to one of its oldest and most charismatic cranes.
The old female Hooded Crane G. monachus had been suffering from age
related gout for sometime and was no longer able to stand. So the difficult
decision was taken to put her down for humane reasons. Several keepers
share fond memories of this old and rather eccentric bird. She must have
been at least 40 years old, as she was already in adult plumage when she
arrived at Walsrode unexpectedly in a shipment of Demoiselle Cranes
Anthropoides virgo from Mongolia in 1969. She was for a long time
the only Hooded Crane in Europe. After considerable effort, a male was
brought in from the USSR in 1987 and the following year the pair produced
a chick. It was possibly the world's first captive breeding of this species.
In 2007 Walsrode Birdpark again reared Hooded Cranes and now
has a third generation. In Europe Hooded Cranes are currently kept only
at Walsrode and in one zoo, whereas in North America, the breeding
programmes for this small crane are more successful and it is kept in at
least 10 zoos.
Madagascar programmes
Walsrode Birdpark has been involved in projects with the unique
avifauna of Madagascar for more than a decade. Staff first travelled to
Madagascar in 1998 and there have been expeditions to Madagascar most
years since then. An aim of the Madagascar programmes has been to
collect founder stocks of species that have never before been maintained in
captivity. Establishing captive populations at both the zoo at Tsimbazaza
in Madagascar and at Walsrode in Germany have helped provide valuable
information about several little known birds, as well as creating safe
populations in case of ecological disasters in their natural but endangered
habitats. All birds have been collected as young or even at the egg stage,
ensuring that the minimum impact is made on the wild populations.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.958861" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259828" page_num="35" year="" vol="">
NEWS FROM WALSRODE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996791" page_id="56259828"  page_num="35" year="" vol="">
35
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998162048780488" page_id="56259828"  page_num="35" year="" vol="">
All three species of couas or silky-cuckoos at Walsrode Birdpark bred
successfully in 2007. The Crested species Coua cristata first arrived at
Walsrode from Madagascar in 1998, since when more than 60 young have
been reared and distributed to zoos around the world. The propagation of the
Blue species C. caerulea has proved considerably more difficult. Between
2003-2006 only a single chick was successfully reared to independence.
Following a review, a few changes were made in 2007, including higher
brooder temperatures and the use of bee larvae in the rearing food, which
may have provided the solution, as following the changes eight young were
reared to independence. After several infertile clutches the Giant species
C. gigas finally produced a fertile egg last year and the youngster was
hand-reared in the nursery. It is the first of its species to be reared in
captivity and as the captive population consisted of just two males and
a single female, it was hoped that it would turn out to be a female, but
unfortunately it turned out to be a male. The breeding success does though
provide hope that this impressive cuckoo can be bred again in the future.
One of the main species in Walsrode's Madagascar programmes is the
Crested Ibis Lophotibis cristata. Eleven were reared in 2007 and will be
integrated into the international breeding programme that is managed by
Walsrode Birdpark. Madagascar Crested Ibis hatched at Walsrode can be
seen in zoos around the world and breeding success has been achieved in
the USA, Switzerland and Japan. Hand-reared birds from Walsrode, whose
parents were hand-reared in Madagascar, have successfully reared their
own young. A third generation of this species is now breeding in captivity
and hopes are high that it will become firmly established in captivity.
As well as collecting endemic species, the Madagascar expeditions
have also been involved in in situ conservation efforts aimed at conserving
the Madagascar Pond-Heron or Madagascar Squacco Heron Ardeola idae ,
financing research on this species which is believed to be threatened by the
invasion of the closely related African Pond-Heron or Squacco Heron A.
ralloides. Since the arrival on Madagascar of the first humans about 2,000
years ago, the landscape of this once completely forest covered island has
been continually changing and becoming a more open habitat that may
favour the African species. Recently there were the first indications that the
two species might be hybridizing in the wild. Therefore, a small number
of young were collected in 2003 from nests attended by Madagascar Pond-
Herons in one of the last colonies where this species is known to breed.
They were brought back to Walsrode and later started to breed. However,
based on morphological and genetic studies it is now obvious that some
of these birds carry genes of the African Pond-Heron. In future staff at
Walsrode will aim to breed towards the phenotypes of the Madagascar
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996549" page_id="56259829"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
36
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.992308" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259829" page_num="36" year="" vol="">
NEWS FROM WALSRODE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97186078125" page_id="56259829"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
Pond-Heron and continue to investigate the relationship between the two
species.
Only recently accorded full species status the Blue-eyed Ibis
Threskiornis bernieri was previously regarded as a subspecies of the
Sacred Ibis T. aethiopicus. Following its upgrading to full species status,
a review of its conservation status showed that although there is only
limited data available, it can be said with a good degree of certainty that
the world population numbers fewer than 2,500 birds. It is therefore now
listed as Endangered by BirdLife International. Walsrode Birdpark has
for sometime been developing a conservation project for this ibis. Habitat
destruction poses the main threat to its survival. It is strongly tied to the
mangrove and coastal forests of western Madagascar, which in common
with all forest habitats in Madagascar, are in severe decline. Hunting is
also a major problem and in areas where some of the largest breeding
colonies are located almost all of the nestlings are collected for human
consumption.
The Perschke-Voronosy Project, initiated by Walsrode Birdpark
Foundation employee Mario Perschke, who unfortunately died in
Madagascar in 2007, aims to increase the awareness of local people to the
legacy of this unique species and develop a protected area and encourage
the participation of local communities in its development. The project
has the support of several other institutions that have come together under
the conservation organisation Stiftung Artenschutz. The zoos at Munster,
Landau, Duisburg and Berlin are involved and further support in the form
of [euro]20,000 (approx. #15,000 or US$29,000) was granted to the project from
the proceeds of the European Association of Zoos and Aquaria (EAZA)
Madagascar Campaign 2007.
The above report is based on information contained in two press
releases from the Walsrode Birdpark Foundation and Walsrode Birdpark,
D-29664 Walsrode, Am Rieselbach, Germany. The press releases were
issued by Zoological Director Simon Bruslund Jensen. E-mail:simon.
jensen@vogelpark-walsrode. de
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.991436" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259830" page_num="37" year="" vol="">
THE SPRING SOCIAL MEETING
AT THE HAWK CONSERVANCY, APRIL 2008
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99645" page_id="56259830"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
37
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.979382864864865" page_id="56259830"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
by Philip Schofield
Opened as Weyhill Zoo with a general collection in 1966, this
establishment then became Weyhill Wildlife Park and specialised for a time
in European fauna and also kept other animals, before becoming the Hawk
Conservancy in 1981. The leopards, wildebeest and hyenas are all long
gone, as are the bears and wolves. Run by the Smith family throughout
(Ashly Smith is now Chief Executive), this is now a bird of prey and owl
collection, that is also widely involved in conservation, education and
rehabilitation. The hospital facilities cater for up to 200 birds annually.
There is also a sponsored nest box scheme which caters for local wild owls
and Kestrels. For many years the conservancy bred Common Buzzards for
release, which provided helpful experience for a similar exercise with Red
Kites, which started in 2002. In recent years it has been involved with
vulture studies in Africa and the Weyhill collection houses a number of
White-headed and White-backed Vultures that were confiscated from the
illegal side of the international bird trade.
There was a Council Meeting, followed by the AGM and then lunch,
after which Avicultural Society members and their guests joined other
spectators for the first of two flying displays. An early highlight of the first
display was an African Fish Eagle, which was dive-bombed by the local
nesting pair of Kestrels and eventually went off to sit on the top of an aviary
out of their line of vision. This was followed by the familiar but always
impressive high speed expertise of a Peregrine and the 'canting' flight of
a juvenile Bateleur. Attention was drawn to how this short tailed species
steers with its wings, in contrast to the fish-like steering with the tail of the
local Red Kites. One of the latter joined with a group of six Black Kites
competing for food shot high in the air from a catapult. Both species 'stood
on their tails' in their attempts to snatch the projected morsels. (Wild
Common Buzzards also sometimes join the flying displays.) While the
kites performed high above, four Hooded Vultures flew back and forth low
over our heads. The display culminated in a huge female American Bald
Eagle flying to her handler from a valley in the middle distance where she
had been awaiting the signal to fly in, a spectacle eclipsed only by seeing
the pair of these eagles performing the same exercise during a previous
visit. It was not possible on the day of the society's visit, because the wind
was in the wrong direction and would have led to the male eagle flying off
hunting rabbits rather than sticking to his display schedule. Apparently he
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998463" page_id="56259831"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
38
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.976095" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259831" page_num="38" year="" vol="">
SOCIAL MEETING - HAWK CONSERVANCY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987842961538462" page_id="56259831"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
makes a habit of this.
A static feeding display of Gymnogenes (African Harrier Hawks) in an
aviary, showed off their double-jointed dexterity in retrieving food from
holes in posts and artificial weaver birds' nests. In the wild, these birds
hang with one foot onto the underside of weavers' nests, while using the
other foot to feel inside for nestlings. While I did not find time between
the flying displays for a detailed study of the aviary population (most
of the display birds are loose in aviaries rather than tethered when 'off-
duty'), I did notice two female Andean Condors and a pair of Steller's
Sea Eagles - the first Steller's Sea Eagles I have seen. This Far Eastern
species is a size larger than our own White-tailed Sea Eagle, known in
some birdwatching circles as the 'flying bam door'. At the other end of the
scale were the charming Ferruginous Pygmy-Owls, which always suggest
to me a carnivorous Budgerigar.
In contrast to the open meadow setting of the earlier display, the second
display took place in a woodland setting and began with a Pariah Kite
picking up food out of a pond. Next we saw the huge Milky or Verreaux's
Eagle Owl, the first I have seen flown free. The even larger Siberian Eagle
Owl gave us a demonstration of its silent wing-beats, when it flew by us
at close quarters. On an earlier visit I admired a group of South American
Red-backed Hawks (with this dimorphic species the male has a grey back)
which had arrived at Weyhill after having been confiscated by the customs
authorities. On this occasion we were able to watch one of these, apparently
taken from the wild as an adult, flown free among the trees.
The Hawk Conservancy is situated in Sarsons Lane, Weyhill, Andover,
Hants. SP11 8DY. Website:www.hawk-conservancy.org
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.570307" page_id="56259831"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.969489" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259831" page_num="38" year="" vol="">
AUTUMN SOCIAL MEETING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997171888888889" page_id="56259831"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
The society's Autumn Social Meeting will be held on Saturday,
September 6th 2008 at Exmoor Zoological Park, South Stowford, Bratton
Fleming, Barnstaple, Devon EX31 4SG. It was the first collection in the
UK to breed the White-browed Coucal and has also succeeded in hand-
rearing this species. The Bare-faced Currasow and Blue-throated Conure
have also been bred there. Head Keeper Derek Gibson's accounts of these
breedings will be published in future issues of the magazine. Paul Boulden,
our Hon. Secretary/Treasurer, says it has an up-and-coming bird collection,
and mentioned the cranes and breeding Abyssinian Ground Hornbills,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998442" page_id="56259832"  page_num="39" year="" vol="">
39
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9948185" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259832" page_num="39" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
RARE BIRDS YEARBOOK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995705294117647" page_id="56259832"  page_num="39" year="" vol="">
The Rare Birds Yearbook 2008 is the first of what is intended to be
an annual publication describing those of the world's birds that are most
threatened with extinction - that is those listed as Critically Endangered by
the IUCN.
The main part of the book is a directory of the 189 bird species named
on the 2007 IUCN Red List as Critically Endangered. The information in
the accounts largely follows that provided by BirdLife International and
available on the worldwide web on the IUCN Species Survival Commission
Red List (http://www.iucnredlist.org/) and is profusely supplemented with
photographs or illustrations of each species. The photographs are the first
I have seen of many of the species and these really are an important feature
of the book. I had never before seen a photo of the enigmatic White-
eyed River Martin and had no idea what a stunning little bird the Araripe
Manakin (only discovered in 1988) really is. In the case of species, such as
the Cebu Flowerpecker and Kinglet Calyptura, good quality photos remain
to be taken and these birds are illustrated with paintings.
In the case of the species with which I am most familiar, the accounts
seem already out of date, but then information often changes rapidly with
the changing status of so many endangered birds. For some species this
is very positive - for example the Echo Parakeet, which up until 2006 was
considered Critically Endangered, no longer ranks as such, as increased
conservation effort, including avicultural support, has resulted in the wild
population increasing to over 300 birds and the downlisting to Endangered.
In the case of other Critically Endangered Mauritian birds, such as the
Olive White-eye and Mauritius Fody, the use of avicultural techniques is
already showing benefits, with recently released hand-reared birds breeding
on predator-free offshore islands. These new developments and the new
survey data that suggest a wild population of over 1,000 Philippine Rufous-
headed Hombills, rather than the 120-160 indicated previously, remain in
technical reports and are yet to be assimilated into the general body of
conservation knowledge and indicate the value of this publication being
updated annually.
Many of the birds listed as Critically Endangered are species held in
captivity. These include the Northern Bald Ibis, Laysan Duck, Philippine
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.962674">
Cockatoo, Yellow-crested Cockatoo, Blue-throated Macaw, Grey-
breasted Parakeet, Bali Starling, Montserrat Oriole and Blue-crowned
Laughingthrush. Four species - the Alagoas Curassow, Socorro Dove,
</reference>
<page confidence="0.989845" page_id="56259833"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
40
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.964997" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259833" page_num="40" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97481504" page_id="56259833"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
Spix's Macaw and Hawaiian Crow - survive only in captivity. The Kakapo,
largely because of intensive management on offshore islands of New
Zealand onto which it has been introduced, is now categorised as Critically
Endangered, having previously been considered by the IUCN to have been
Extinct in the Wild.
Additional chapters include feature articles on preventing extinctions,
the work of BirdLife International and its partnerships, ornithologists
who have made new bird discoveries, migration studies, climate change,
ecotourism and in-depth articles on selected critically endangered species
including the Madagascar Pochard and Balearic Shearwater. There are also
chapters on extinct species and for those interested in seeing these critically
endangered species for themselves there is a list of tour operators and a bird
checklist. Keen birdwatcher that I am it frightens me to think of the cost in
terms of cash, time and carbon footprint, that an attempt to see even a small
proportion of these birds would cost - but if funds generated by ecotourism
really can be made available to support the conservation of these critically
endangered birds, this can be an important tool for conservation.
Anyone with an interest in birds will enjoy this book. It is the most up
to date, readily available published source of information about the world's
rarest birds and is worth the price, for the excellent colour photographs
alone.
Rare Birds Yearbook 2008 (ISBN 978-0-9552607-3-5; edited by
Erik Hirschfeld, paperback, 276 pages, is published by MagDig Media
Limited in association with BirdLife International. Price #18.95, of which
#4.00 goes to support BirdLife International's conservation work. It is
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.948481">
available through a number of organisations as well as the website :www.
rarebirdsyearbook.com
</footnote>
<table confidence="0.519275714285714" page_id="56259833"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
Roger Wilkinson
INTRODUCTION TO JAPANESE BIRDS
A Photographic Guide to the Birds of Japan and North-East Asia by
Tadao Shimba, closely follows the same format as the guides to the birds
of India, south-east Asia and Indonesia, which I reviewed in the Avicultural
Magazine Vol.109, No.3, pp. 137-138 (2003).
The Japanese Official Bird List (2000) listed 542 bird species as having
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.9971506" page_id="56259833"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
occurred on the islands of Japan, to which the author added a further 82
species, resulting in approximately 620 species, of which he selected 554
to feature in the main text. The objective is to provide a comprehensive
introduction to Japanese birds, along with those of the wider region of north-
east Asia, which for the purpose of this guide is considered to include the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909711" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259834" page_num="41" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998548" page_id="56259834"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
41
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.950180275" page_id="56259834"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
Korean Peninsula, north-east China (the provinces of Jilin, Heilongjiang
and Liaoning) and the Russian Far East (east of 120*E) north to the Arctic
coast, incorporating Ussuriland, Sakhalin, Kamchatka and Chukotka,
Opening the guide for the first time and flicking through the pages -
there are one or two species per page, illustrated by one, two, three of more
good colour photographs - I was surprised to discover just how many of
the birds are the same or very similar to those that occur in Europe and
North America. Many of the others are instantly recognisable, none more
so than the Mandarin Duck. In the past a good many others figured in
western aviculture, Including the Ryukyu (or Loo Choo) Robin and Lidth's
(or the Loo Choo) Jay. A Ryukyu Robin owned by Raymond Sawyer
won the class for flycatchers, robins, etc., at the National Exhibition of
Cage Birds and Aquaria in London in 1958, and the same bird won again
the following year, London Zoo received a Lidth's Jay in 1957 and this
species bred at Paignton Zoo in 1964. Photos of the Narcissus and Blue-
and-white Flycatchers and those of birds such as the Black-naped Oriole
and Varied Tit recalled for me the late 1950s, when consignments of
such birds, often including species that were new to the zoo collection,
frequently arrived at the Bird House as gifts to London Zoo from Dr K. C.
Searle in Hong Kong (who remains a member of the society, living now in
Portugal). I recognised the Greater and Lesser Sand Plovers in the guide
as winter visitors to East Africa and thought I also recognised the Oriental
Plover as another winter visitor. However, although in the guide it has
the scientific name Charadrius asiaticus (the same scientific name as the
Caspian Plover), other recent works list it as C. veredus, separating it from
the Caspian Plover, a migrant to East Africa.
There are sections on habitats, migration, conservation, photographing
birds and where to see birds in north-east Asia. It recommends, for
example, Arasaki, Kyushu, where thousands of cranes can be seen at close
range and Geocheonnam Lake, Haenam, where enormous flocks of Baikal
Teal congregate. Miyaki-jima, easily reached by overnight ferry from
Tokyo, is recommended as a popular destination to see the endemic Izu
Islands Thrush. Appendices list rarer vagrants not included in the main
text, extinct or presumed extinct species, those extirpated from the region
and English and Japanese names of species.
A Photographic Guide to the Birds of Japan and North-East Asia by
Tadao Shimba, paperback, 504 pages, nearly 600 species and over 1,500
colour photos, is published in the UK by Christopher Helm, an imprint of
A&amp;C Black (website www.acblack.com). Price #24.99. In the USA it is
published by Yale University Press (website:www.yalebooks.com).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.215123">
Malcolm Ellis
</subsectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.990795" page_id="56259835"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
42
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.590953" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259835" page_num="42" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
NEW PRESIDENT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.514737625" page_id="56259835"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
Raymond Sawyer was elected the new President of the Avicultural
Society at the recent Council Meeting held on Saturday April 5th at the
Hawk Conservancy, Weyhill, Andover, Hants. He succeeds his late wife,
Ruth, and is the tenth President in the Avicultural Society's 114-year history.
At the same meeting, Mike Curzon MBE was elected a Vice President and
Peter Stocks was elected a Council Member. Prof. J. R. (Bob) Hodges,
who joined the society in 1947, was elected an Hon. Life Member, in
recognition of his many years of work for the society.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.44291" page_id="56259835"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.925429" page_id="56259835"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
FOUNDED IN ADELAIDE 80 YEARS AGO
The Avicultural Society of South Australia Inc. (website:www.
birdkeepinginaustralia.com), Australia's oldest avicultural society and
thought to be the fourth oldest in the English-speaking world, celebrated
its 80th Anniversary on February 10th 2008. It was founded in Adelaide in
1928 by a group of South Australian aviculturists who were concerned by
the then Commonwealth Government's proposal to ban the importation of
birds (which eventually happened 21 years later).
Its magazine, which is called Bird Keeping in Australia, recently (Vol.50,
No.3/4, Winter/Spring 2007, pp.38-41 &amp; Vol.51, No.l, Summer 2008,
pp.8-9) reprinted Fred Lewitzka's 1973 account of breeding the Orange-
bellied Parrot Neophema chrysogaster. His pair reared two young in 1973
and a single youngster the following year, shortly after which any further
success was curtained by the South Australian National Parks &amp; Wildlife
Service (NPWS), that ordered him to surrender his birds, which were then
released into the wild. Had he been allowed to continue, a captive breeding
population might have been established far earlier. He bred the birds in his
private aviaries at his home and was also in charge of the Bird Department
at Adelaide Zoo, where this species is now being bred as part of a recovery
programme.
Forty-eight birds at 18 locations was described in Birds Australia's
quarterly publication Wingspan Vol.17, No.4, p.7, December 2007, as a
"conservative estimate" of the number of Orange-bellied Parrots found
wintering on the Australian mainland during last year's annual count.
Sixty-seven birds were counted at 20 sites in 2006. The 2007 shortfall is
attributed to smaller sized flocks at most of the key sites. The reasons for
this are unclear, but it appears to have been an ongoing trend since the late
1990s. South-west Victoria still appears to be the current stronghold (with
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700116" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259836" page_num="43" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99973" page_id="56259836"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.880715666666667" page_id="56259836"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
16 birds last winter). Results from The Coorang were encouraging, with
nine birds being sighted, the most recorded in South Australia for some
years.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.598421" page_id="56259836"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.805835" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259836" page_num="43" year="" vol="">
COUAS IN CAPTIVITY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.825936857142857" page_id="56259836"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
In International Zoo News Vol.55, No.l (2008), pp.13-17, Pierre de
Chabannes and Simon Bruslund Jensen wrote about identifying the couas
- non-parasitic members of the Cuculidae family found only on the island
of Madagascar - and summarized their history in captivity.
Of the nine living species, four can be seen in European zoological
collections, one of which has also been kept and bred in North America.
As mentioned earlier in this issue of the Avicultural Magazine (p.34),
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.383040769230769" page_id="56259836"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
60 Crested Couas Coua cristata have been bred at Walsrode Birdpark
in Germany. Several have been sent to other collections, notably Zurich
Zoo, where this species now breeds regularly. They have also been sent
to Wuppertal and Cologne Zoos. Walsrode birds have been bred at San
Diego Zoo and San Diego Wild Animal Park, and birds from there have
been sent to Central Park Zoo, Bronx Zoo, Disney's Animal Kingdom and
Lowry Park Zoo, Tampa, Florida. Two male Reynaud's or Red-fronted
Couas C. reynaudii are on show at Zurich Zoo and a pair live in an off-
exhibit aviary at Wuppertal Zoo. In 2006 an adult male Blue Coua C.
caerulea was sent from Walsrode to Cologne Zoo to be displayed in its
new Madagascar exhibit. At present the Giant Coua C. gigas is kept only
at Walsrode Birdpark. The remaining five species have never been seen
alive outside Madagascar.
</listItem>
<table confidence="0.586577" page_id="56259836"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
* * *
THREE IN A NEST
Loro Parque Fundacion is collaborating with Fundacion ProAves of
Colombia and Fundacion Jocotoco of Ecuador to conserve the Golden-
plumed Parakeet Leptosittaca branickii, which has a fragmented distribution
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.998538" page_id="56259836"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
in the Andes of Colombia, Ecuador and Pern, where it inhabits temperate
cloud forest to paramo at 2,400m-3,400m (approx. 7,800ft-11,000ft) and is
threatened by widespread habitat loss.
An essential part of the project is monitoring reproductive activity in
nests, including in nest boxes installed because of the scarcity of natural
nest cavities. While doing this, biologists in Colombia discovered a
hitherto unrecorded aspect of parental care by this species - the occupation
of a nest box by three individuals, probably a pair and a 'nest helper'. The
latter is presumed to have been a bird reared the previous breeding season,
gaining experience by assisting with the rearing of three young siblings.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997688" page_id="56259837"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
44
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.924607" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259837" page_num="44" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.992425666666667" page_id="56259837"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
Another surprise was finding that pairs occupying two nest boxes, having
fed their own chicks, then entered two nest boxes occupied by other pairs
in the same patch of forest and fed the chicks and females in those nests. A
third surprise was the discovery that well-feathered young in the nest, turn
onto their backs and strike upwards with their feet, defensive behaviour
also seen in macaws and a few conures.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.826295" page_id="56259837"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.862223" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259837" page_num="44" year="" vol="">
GOVERNMENT VET RETIRES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991972571428571" page_id="56259837"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
At the end of February, Avicultural Society Council Member Graham
Thurlow retired from the post of Chief Advisor to DEFRA's (Department
for Environment, Food &amp; Rural Affairs) Animal Welfare Division. Graham,
who last year wrote about breeding Layard's Black-headed Weaver Ploceus
cucullatus nigriceps (paroptus) (see Avicultural Magazine Vol.113, No.3,
pp. 119-121 (2007)), hopes his slightly early retirement will allow him to
devote more time to his avicultural interests.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.512425" page_id="56259837"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
* * *
REGRETTABLE LOSS
In the Avicultural Magazine Vol.59, No.6, p.216 (November-December
1953), John Yealland ended his London Zoo Notes by mentioning the
"regrettable loss" of the Spix's Macaw Cyanopsitta spixii that had lived
in the gardens for 23 years. It was presumably one of the pair that Arthur
Prestwich saw living in an outside aviary of the Parrot House in 1943
(Avicultural Magazine Fifth Series, Vol.VIII, No.6, p. 161 (November-
December 1943)).
* * *
UNUSUAL ACHIEVEMENT
Leipzig Zoo in Germany bought a pair of Turquoise Tanagers Tangara
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.986354" page_id="56259837"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
mexicana brasiliensis in 1999. Six months later the pair started to breed.
Using mainly coconut fibres, the pair nested in a 5cm (2in) diameter basket,
in a dense bamboo. By 2007, no fewer than 59 chicks had been hatched, of
which 31 fledged. Nineteen of the offspring were given to other collections.
Last year the female died, probably of old age, but fortunately the zoo still
had three of her female offspring. A male was obtained from a private
breeder and this enabled the zoo to form two new pairs, one consisting of
two completely unrelated birds.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997531" page_id="56259838"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
45
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.980111" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259838" page_num="45" year="" vol="">
OBITUARIES
DEREK GOODWIN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997513" page_id="56259838"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
Derek's note on the Mistle Thrush's feet (Avicultural Magazine
Vol.113, No.3, pp. 130=131 (2007)) was, sadly, his last contribution to the
magazine, for he died on May 14th, aged 88. He had supposed that it
would be the last of his many contributions to the Avicultural Magazine,
but following its publication, in his last letter (January 5th), he wrote that
he was contemplating a short article on the folly of changing eminently
descriptive English names into "ridiculous" ones. Among the examples he
gave was how much more descriptive were the old names Brown and Wood
Owl than the modem Tawny Owl. "THE TAWNY OWL HAS NO TAWNY
PLUMAGE", he wrote in bold block capitals. He also ridiculed the use of
the name Blue-capped Cordon-bleu instead of the more descriptive Blue-
headed Cordon-bleu.
Such was Derek's standing, that he was the subject of an obituary in The
Times newspaper (May 24th, p.79). It began with a limerick Derek wrote
at the age of 76:
There was an old man who said:
"My! What a beautiful bird I espy"
When they asked: "Is it rare?"
He replied: "I don't care,
so long as it pleases my eye."
I have repeated it here, because as the obituary stated, it summed up
succintly Derek's attitude to birds. He took as much, if not more, delight in
common birds - such as the feral pigeon, Wood Pigeon, Magpie, Jay, Carrion
Crow, Golden and Lady Amherst's Pheasants - as he did in observing rare
birds.
I learned from the obituary that he was bom Richard Patrick Goodwin
on February 26th 1920 in Woking, Surrey. However, for reasons he never
fully understood his parents called him Derek and he was known as Derek
until the day he died.
It recorded that he survived the siege of Tobmk, when serving with the
Royal Artillery in North Africa during the Second World War. Yet, almost
invariably, his wartime reminiscences were about the birds he saw rather
than the horrifying experience of battle.
It also recorded how our magazine came to play a pivotal role in Derek's
life. In th q Avicultural Magazine Vol.109, No.3, pp. 130-132 (2003), Derek
himself described how in 1945 he returned home, as a soldier of 25, from
service in Egypt, Libya and Malta and was granted four weeks leave. While
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997071" page_id="56259839"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
46
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.932953" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259839" page_num="46" year="" vol="">
OBITUARIES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.966327634146341" page_id="56259839"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
home he visited Gamages store in London, where he saw on sale some
back issues of the magazine. The one which caught his eye contained an
article on the Common Bronzewing Pigeon by T. H. Newman, illustrated
by a beautiful painting of this species by H. Goodchild. He purchased this
and several other back issues and the assistant who served him gave him
the address of the Hon. Editor, Miss Phyllis Barclay-Smith, who then had
rooms at the British Museum (Natural History) in South Kensington.
Derek joined the Avicultural Society in 1945 and when he was demobbed
the following year, found himself wondering whether to try to find a more
congenial job than his pre-war one in a mail-order business. Derek soon
realised there were very few jobs connected with birds for someone like
himself who had no formal educational qualifications. It was then that
Miss Barclay-Smith stepped in and introduced him to J. D. Macdonald,
who was in charge of the Bird Room at the museum.
To his great surprise Derek was offered a job as temporary assistant
and subsequently was taken onto the permanent staff, something that
would not have been possible a few years later. Despite his lack of formal
qualifications Derek eventually rose to Principal Scientific Officer.
As part of his work at the museum Derek wrote four books, including
his three best known and most referred to works: Crows of the World
(1976), Pigeons and Doves of the World (1967) and Estrildid Finches of
the World (1982). In all, he wrote six books and countless articles, many of
which were published in the Avicultural Magazine. Derek is also credited
as having been the first person in the UK to breed the Lanceolated Jay
(1954).
When I was a young keeper at London Zoo, Derek was a frequent
visitor to the Bird House. On one memorable occasion, when observing
the feeding behaviour of a Red-billed Oxpecker, Derek produced a razor
blade and as Curator of Birds John Yealland looked on aghast, proceeded
to cut his finger and when it began to bleed offered it to the bird, which
"appeared excited" and consumed the blood with "frantic haste and then
nibbled avidly at the wound." A few minutes later Derek made a fresh
incision and repeated the experiment, noting that whereas only very little
blood oozed from the original wound, after the oxpecker nibbled at it for
some moments the blood welled up more freely and in larger quantity!
According to the obituary in The Times , Derek eventually resigned
from the RSPB (Royal Society for the Protection of Birds) in protest at its
perceived lack of support for his campaign to save the introduced Golden
and Lady Amherst's Pheasants. However, as I recall, he resigned over its
support for the plan to cull the Ruddy Duck population here in the UK,
fearing that if the Ruddy Duck was exterminated, his beloved Mandarin Duck
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.825829" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259840" page_num="47" year="" vol="">
OBITUARIES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998513" page_id="56259840"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
47
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.95626248" page_id="56259840"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
would be next, followed by the Golden and Lady Amherst's Pheasants. As
I recall, he had been made an Hon. Life Member of the RSPB and received
its magazine free, but resigned his Hon. Life Membership and insisted on
paying for the magazine and continued to write long letters criticising the
society's policies. He was convinced that it wants to exterminate these
introduced species, while at the same time it is encouraging the spread
of the Red Kite, White-tailed Sea Eagle and, worst of all, the Northern
Goshawk.
Dr Cliff Frith in Queensland, who knew Derek for over 40 years, has
written to say that he is devastated to learn of the death of his friend and
former colleague. Robin Restall felt the obituary in The Times failed to
touch on "the eccentric man of many passions," he knew. Another long
time friend, Jeff Trollope, recalled the story of a pompous friend staying
overnight with Derek, who when asked what he wanted for breakfast,
asked for a small, poached egg. He got up the next morning to find that
Derek had poached a waxbill's egg, which he put on a postage stamp-sized
piece of toast and placed before him. On the first occasion Derek visited
Jeff and his wife Pat, they watched him come in the garden gate, but then
became puzzled why he had not come in the front door which they had left
open for him. When they looked out the window, Derek was in their rather
overgrown front garden, collecting Poa annua (Annual Meadow Grass)
for his waxbills. At a meeting of the British Ornithologists' Club, Jeff was
astonished by Derek's knowledge of birds in the Bible. He was also said
to be able to quote at length references to birds from Shakespeare - French
poetry - and other literature.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.646203" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259840" page_num="47" year="" vol="">
ANTHONY J. MOBBS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970372769230769" page_id="56259840"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
Anthony J. Mobbs died on February 5th 2008 following a short illness,
reports Bryan Reed. Tony, who lived in Walsall in the West Midlands,
joined The Avicultural Society in 1968. Most of his life he kept birds,
including British species, parrots, softbills, nectar-feeders and Australian
finches, and had many other interests.
As Bryan wrote, older members will perhaps best remember Tony for
the wonderful hummingbirds he used to keep. He frequently wrote about
these in the magazine and illustrated his articles with his photographs;
see for example, his coloured photo frontispiece of the Frilled Coquette
and his notes on keeping this species (Vol.78, No.3, pp.77-79 (May-June
1972)). Amongst the many other hummingbirds he kept and wrote about
in the magazine were the Tourmaline Sunangel, Homed Sungem, Reddish
Hermit, Black-tailed Trainbearer, Long-billed Starthroat, Golden-tailed
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997904" page_id="56259841"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
48
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9251" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259841" page_num="48" year="" vol="">
OBITUARIES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.879108545454546" page_id="56259841"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
Sapphire and Velvet-purple and Chestnut-breasted Coronets. Tony wrote
a book about hummingbirds, The Complete Book of Australian Finches
and books about the Star Finch, Bicheno (Double-barred) Finch and
the Gouldian Finch. In 1981 he wrote about breeding the Blue-winged
Parrotlet (Avicultural Magazine^ 61.87, No.2, pp.65-69 (April-June 1981)).
By 1984 he specialised in breeding Gouldian Finches, but to add a little
more interest, also kept and bred other Australian species.
His last two articles for the magazine were on breeding Gouldian Finches
(Avicultural Magazine Vol.102, No.3, pp.99-102 (1996)) and the Star Finch
(Avicultural Magazine Vol. 104, No. 1, pp. 10-12(1998)). Up until the time
of his death Tony was Cage &amp; Aviary Birds&apos; Australian finches expert.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.615331" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259841" page_num="48" year="" vol="">
PAT WISNIEWSKI
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.977182363636364" page_id="56259841"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
For many years Frank Woolham and I spoke to each other on the
phone two or three times or more a week and Frank often talked about
Pat Wisniewski and what was happening at Martin Mere, the Wildfowl &amp;
Wetlands Centre in Lancashire. It was not until April of this year though
that I had any direct contact with Pat, when he and co-author J. Meldrum,
submitted an account of the unusual breeding of Eurasian Goosander x
European Eider hybrids at Martin Mere. Sadly, less than a month later, I
had an early morning phone call from Frank's wife, Meg, who told me that
they had heard from their son Michael at Banham Zoo, that Pat had died.
The account of how the hybrid ducks came to be bred will be published in
a future issue of the magazine along with, it is hoped, a fuller obituary.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.96474" genericHeader="general terms" page_id="56259841" page_num="48" year="" vol="">
JOHN LEONARD MARTYN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99474825" page_id="56259841"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
John Martyn, the owner of S P Press, who had printed the Avicultural
Magazine since 1995, was tragically killed in a road traffic accident on
May 22nd. I am sure members will join with us to extend our sympathies
to his widow, Anne, and his sons Darren and Richard.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997668" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259842" page_num="" year="" vol="">
COMPLICATED HORNBILL TAXONOMY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995744" page_id="56259842"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Ongoing studies into their genetics, distribution, ecology, behaviour and
calls, suggest that at least three or possibly four subspecies of the Red-billed
Hombill Tockus erythrorhynchus might better be regarded as separate (full)
species. While most authors cautiously await the conclusion of these studies,
others such as Sinclair &amp; Ryan in Birds of Africa south of the Sahara (Struik,
2003), already treat them as five separate species: the Northern Red-billed
Hombill T. erythrorhynchus , Damara Red-billed Hombill T. damarensis,
Southern Red-billed Hombill T. rufirostris, Tanzanian Red-billed Hombill
T. ruahae and Western Red-billed Hombill T. kempi. Hockey, Dean &amp; Ryan
in Roberts Birds of Southern Africa , Seventh Edition (The Tmstees of the
John Voelcker Bird Book Fund, 2005), presently treat only damarensis as
a separate species, while elsewhere ruahae may be treated as a subspecies
of kempi or erythrorhynchus. In addition, some birds in northern Kenya
have have a pale coloured iris and may represent a form that has yet to be
formally described.
All can be distinguished visually by the colour of the bare skin around
the eyes, the colour of the iris and the facial and breast coloration. With this
in mind, Walsrode Birdpark and the EAZA Hombill TAG Group (European
Association of Zoos and Aquaria Taxon Advisory Group) are keen to
determine the status of red-billed hombills in zoos and private collections.
A questionaire has been distributed to many zoos in Europe and North
America, with illustrations by Thomas Eichler, aimed at helping distinguish
the various forms. Holders are asked to identify which type or types they
keep and how many; have they bred successfully since 2002; and do they
have any known wild-caught founder birds?
It also asks for information about hybridization between different forms.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.546117" page_id="56259842"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Details should be sent to Simon Bmslund Jensen, Zoological Director,
Vogelpark Walsrode. E-mail:simon.jensen@vogelpark-walsrode.de
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.692019" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259842" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ONE OF TWO REMAINING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9824196" page_id="56259842"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
One of Taronga Park, Sydney, Australia's longest and oldest residents
has been retired from exhibition. The bird, one of two Chilean Flamingos
Phoenicopterus chilensis remaining in Australia, will spend the rest of its
days on its own custom-built off-exhibit pool. It arrived at the zoo in 1948
and has outlived the other 52 flamingos in the flock.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.768805" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259843" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.891741444444444" page_id="56259843"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
3 9088 01383 4015
J
The Avicultural Society . 1
The nesting behaviour of the Musophagidae
by Myles Lamont.2
Breeding the Rufous-collared Sparrow Zonotrichia capensis
by Jim Jerrard.13
Parental behaviour by two pairs of Guam Micronesian Kingfishers
Halcyon cinnamomina cinnamomina
by Jennifer J. Elston, Christy Sky, Glorieli Quinones,
Jennifer Carney, Chelle Plasse and Tammie Bettinger...15
Goldie's Lorikeet: hand-rearing and parent-rearing
by Rosemary Low. 24
News from Walsrode. 32
The Spring Social Meeting at the Hawk Conservancy, April 2008
by Philip Schofield.37
Book Reviews
Rare Birds Yearbook.39
Introduction to Japanese Birds.40
News &amp; Views.42
Obituaries
Derek Goodwin.45
Anthony J. Mobbs.47
Pat Wisniewski.48
John Leonard Martyn. 48
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</table>
</algorithms>
