<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.7137226" page_id="56253544"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 113
No. 4
2007
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253545" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.984827516129033" page_id="56253545"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2007 as for 2006: British
Isles #18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please).
The subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the
Society later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of
the AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, ARCADIA, THE MOUNTS, TOTNES, DEVON TQ9 7QJ,
UK.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TN13 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail: Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have not
been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of a
particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history. Articles
should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the scientific
names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given. References
cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line drawings,
black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular point in
the article will be used where possible and should be clearly captioned. If
authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when submitting the
article and write their name on the back of each photograph. Tables and
graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be aware of
the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of the page
which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997594" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56253545" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982475333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8789015" genericHeader="method" page_id="56253546" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.924412" page_id="56253546"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 113-No. 4 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2007
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.964952333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56253546" page_num="" year="" vol="">
SUNNING BEHAVIOUR BY KORI BUSTARDS Ardeotis kori
AT THE SMITHSONIAN'S NATIONAL ZOOLOGICAL
PARK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.746137" page_id="56253546"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Nandita. Fernandes and Sara Hallager
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.901252" genericHeader="method" page_id="56253546" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97452148" page_id="56253546"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
In this paper we examine the sunning behaviour of seven Kori Bustards
Ardeotis kori over a period of 15 months at the Smithsonian's National
Zoological Park in Washington DC, USA. We found that sunning was most
\0x25A0 prevalent when the temperature was between 50*F-90*F (10*C-32.2*C),
between 10.00am - 1.00pm, during the months of August-October; when the
ultraviolet index was between five and eight. At such times the birds showed
preferences for particular areas and that birds sunned on average for eight to
12 minutes before moving to the shade to preen. We conclude that -sunning
is important for Kori Bustards to maintain good feather condition and zoos
and other collections that exhibit this species should provide sunny areas
in which their birds have the opportunity to exhibit this necessary feather
maintenance behaviour.
Introduction
Bustards are medium to large-sized terrestrial birds, that chiefly inhabit
open plains in either arid or seasonally dry regions of the Old World. The
largest species, the Kori Bustard is indigenous to grasslands and lightly
wooded savannahs in eastern and southern Africa. The nominate subspecies
A. k. kori occurs in Botswana, Zimbabwe, Namibia, southern Angola, South
Africa and Mozambique (Johnsgard, 1991), while A. k. struthiunculus occurs
from Ethiopia to north-west Somalia, south-east Sudan and north-east
Uganda, south through Kenya to northern Tanzania (Clements, 2007).
An ethogram for the Kori Bustard has been developed (Lichtenberg &amp;
Hallager, 2007) but additional observations of birds in the wild are needed
to supplement the descriptions. Sunning behaviour by Kori Bustards was
observed at the Smithsonian's National Zoological Park (SNZP). Sunning
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999214" page_id="56253547"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
146
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.601753" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253547" page_num="146" year="" vol="">
FERNANDES &amp; HALLAGER - KORI BUSTARD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.976932615384615" page_id="56253547"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
is behaviour in which a bird deliberately positions itself in the rays of the
sun while often assuming a special posture (Simmons &amp; Prytherch, 1986.).
There are numerous theories on the function of sunning, ranging from it
being a pleasurable stimulus connected with heat absorption, to it increasing
the mobility of ectoparasites which can then be preened out, drying wet
plumage, producing vitamin D, aiding moulting and increasing preen gland
Fig. 1. Sunning posture of Kori Bustards
secretion (Kennedy, 1969). With Kori Bustards sunning occurs strictly on
the ground with one or both wings spread out (Fig. 1). Sunning behaviour by
Kori Bustards is examined by us in this paper with the aim of understanding
the behaviour and its significance to the species. Because of the importance
of sunning to captive Kori Bustards, we include it in guidelines for the
management of these birds in captivity.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.919232">
Method
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996936428571428" page_id="56253547"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
Observations at the Smithsonian's National Zoological Park commenced
in June 2004 and concluded in September 2005. A total of 230 hours (122
hours in 2004 and 108 hours in 2005) was observed by one recorder, trained
in Kori Bustard behaviour. Over the course of the study a total of seven
adult birds (one male and six females) were observed three days a week from
11.00am-1.00pm. The hours of the study were determined by examining
nearly 2,000 hours of observation data by volunteer Kori Bustard watchers
during 2000-2005, which found that sunning occurred most often between
11 .OOam-l.OOpm (Fig. 3). Data was not collected on days of precipitation or
heavy cloud cover when sunning behaviour was unlikely to be observed. The
exhibit consisted of nine quadrants each visually distinguished by physical
markers such as bushes, trees and fence lines. Six of the seven birds were
wild-caught and one was hatched in captivity. All the birds were fitted with
coloured leg bands for identification purposes.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.329075" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253548" page_num="147" year="" vol="">
FERNANDES &amp; HALLAGER - KORI BUSTARD
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998826" page_id="56253548"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
147
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.874188652173913" page_id="56253548"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
The observer stood in front of the exhibit and recorded behaviours using
binoculars and the naked eye. A stopwatch was used to record the duration
of the sunning behaviours. The ambient temperature was recorded prior to
the start of each watch. The orientation, posture (wings tucked in or spread
out) and the location of each bird were also recorded.
Fig. 2. Preferred sunning temperature from 11.00am - 1.00pm.
Preferred orientation
The male sunned the most when he was facing west, whereas females
sunned most when facing north.
Preferred temperature
In our study which examined sunning behaviour between the hours of
11 .OOam-l.OOpm, we found that four birds sunned most when the temperature
was 80*F-90*F (26.7 0 032.2*C), while three birds sunned most frequently
at 50*F-60*F (10*C-15.6*C) (see Fig. 2).
Duration of sunning and posture
Birds sunned on average for eight to 12 minutes. The sunning posture,
with wings spread, was observed 20% of the time. The most commonly
observed posture was with the wings tucked in.
Ultraviolet (UV) index
Sunning was most prevalent when the UV index was between five and
eight.
Preferred sunning locations
Although each bird showed a definite preference for a particular sunning
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998493" page_id="56253549"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
148
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.6224" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253549" page_num="148" year="" vol="">
FERNANDES &amp; HALLAGER - KORI BUSTARD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970110833333333" page_id="56253549"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
area, most birds occasionally sunned in other areas of the exhibit. Two areas
of the exhibit were not used as sunbathing spots by any of the birds.
Preferred sunning times and months
Using data collected from 2001 -2005, we determined that birds prefer to
sun from 10.00am-l .00pm (see Fig. 3), during the months of August-October
(see Fig. 4), when the temperature is between 60*F-89*F (15.6*C-31.7*C)
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.7868872">
(see Fig. 5).
Fig. 3. Preferred sunning hours (2000 - 2005).
8.00am 9.00am 10,00 am 11.00am 12 noon 1.00pm 2.00pm 3.00pm 4.00pm
Time of day
Fig. 4. Preferred sunning months (2000 - 2005).
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.6644005" page_id="56253549"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
Mar Apr May Jun Jut Aug Sep Oct Nov Dec
Month
Discussion
Feather maintenance is crucial to the survival of all birds. Birds care for
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.816861" page_id="56253549"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
their feathers by frequent preening and other activities such as water bathing,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.328596" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253550" page_num="149" year="" vol="">
FERNANDES &amp; HALLAGER - KORI BUSTARD
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997686" page_id="56253550"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
149
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.767157666666667">
Fig. 5. Preferred sunning temperatures (2000 - 2005).
anting, dust bathing and sunning. Each of these behaviours, while not
performed by all birds, have the function of helping maintain the plumage in
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.980368458333333" page_id="56253550"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
top condition. Sunning, the behaviour by which a bird deliberately positions
itself in the rays of the sun, according to hypothesis, increases the mobility
of ectoparasites which can then be preened out, dries wet plumage, produces
vitamin D, aids moulting and increases preen gland secretions (Simmons
&amp; Prytherch, 1986). Sunning behaviour has been reported in nearly 200
species (Simmons &amp; Prytherch, 1986) including the bustard family Otididae.
Kori Bustards as young as three weeks old have been observed sunning
(Hallager pcrs obs.)
As an adaptation to the arid environment in which they live, Kori
Bustards have loosely packed feathers and lack a preen gland, producing
instead powder down which helps waterproof their plumage. There are no
reports of sunning behaviour by Kori Bustards in the wild. This may be
due to the lack of observers, the short duration and/or infrequency of the
behaviour, the ability of Kori Bustards to blend in with their surroundings
while they are sunning, or the intensity of the African sun eliminating the
need to sunbathe.
Our observations of captive birds, demonstrated that Kori Bustards
at the SNZP, always sunned near a small bush or clump of grass, thereby
successfully camouflaging themselves. Kori Bustards at the SNZP were
observed sunning with one or both wings out four times less often than with
their wings tucked in. Outstretched wings increase the body surface of the
bird exposed to the sun, but may increase the likelihood of predation due to
increased visibility. Sunning near a bush or clump of grass may limit the
ability of a predator to detect the bird, but also probably decreases the ability
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.992867" page_id="56253551"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
150
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.62006" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253551" page_num="150" year="" vol="">
FERNANDES &amp; HALLAGER - KORI BUSTARD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99917135" page_id="56253551"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
of humans to observe the behaviour in the wild. As there are no recorded
observations of sunning by wild Kori Bustards with which to compare our
findings, in our paper we focus on the possible functions of sunning by
captive Kori Bustards and its importance to the overall management and
welfare of Kori Bustards in zoos.
Orientation of the birds
We found that the majority (six out of seven) of the Kori Bustards faced
north when sunning. As sunning occurred primarily during the middle of the
day in the warmer months when the sun was directly overhead, orientation
to the north was of undetermined significance as the sun's rays fell strictly
on the back of the birds (Hallager pers. obs.). We noted that the birds often
turned one eye skywards. Simmons and Prytherch's (1986) hypothesis was
that this may be a method of monitoring the position of the sun or an anti-
predator precaution.
Preferred temperatures, UV and social activity
Deliberate sunning behaviour is a strictly seasonal event in temperate
climates (Simmons &amp; Prytherch, 1986) and Kori Bustards at the SNZP clearly
followed a seasonal pattern of sunning frequency. In common with Simmons
and Prytherch (1986) and Stainton (1982), we found sunning occurred most
often in direct sunshine, at the highest UV intensities, at the hottest times of
the day, during the hottest months of the year and at favoured locations. Like
Hauser (1957) and Simmons and Prytherch (1986), we noted that multiple
birds sunned at the same time.
We noted that birds sunned the most when the ultraviolet (UV) index
was between five and eight. The UV index is an international standard
measurement of how strong the ultraviolet radiation from the sun is at a
particular place on a particular day, with one being the lowest intensity level
and 11+ the highest (US EPA). The UV index in Washington DC never
exceeded eight during our study. In the wild, Kori Bustards are regularly
exposed to UV indices of 11 or more, which may be high enough to keep
ectoparasites in check, thereby eliminating the need to sunbathe.
Duration of sunning and preening
We determined the mean sunning duration during our study to be eight
to 12 minutes. This appeared to be enough time for the birds to derive
maximum benefit from the sunning activity. Following a bout of sunning,
birds moved to the shade and preened. The fact that Kori Bustards sunned
when temperatures were at their highest and when UV indices were at
their highest, lends support to the notion that sunning by Kori Bustards is
related to feather maintenance and ectoparasite removal, as sunning did
not occur during the winter months when feather mites would be predicted
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.329" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253552" page_num="151" year="" vol="">
FERNANDES &amp; HALLAGER - KORI BUSTARD
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99857" page_id="56253552"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
151
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.987188048780487" page_id="56253552"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
to be minimal. The lack of sunning during the winter months negates
thermoregulation as a reason for sunning by Kori Bustards.
However, Houston (1979) questioned the effectiveness of ectoparasite
removal due to sunning. He argued that the small amount of time a bird
is engaged in sunning is insufficient for the sun to penetrate the layers of
plumage. Houston stated that the chief reason for sunning is to achieve
optimum feather maintenance, purporting that it is the heat and its effect on
the restoration of feather shape that is the reason for sunning. However, as
Kori Bustards are infrequent and only short distance fliers, the importance of
feather shape is not as critical to them as it is to birds that spend more time
in the air. Hauser (1957) though explained that numerous birds have their
feathers erect while sunbathing. This would result in greater exposure of
the skin and serve to evict ectoparasites to the outer layers of the plumage,
from where they could be removed by the bird. Erection of feathers by Kori
Bustards was observed during this study, lending support to ectoparasite
control being a plausible reason for sunning by captive Kori Bustards.
We often noted that birds sunned themselves to the point where they were
panting heavily. Heavy panting continued for up to five minutes after they
had moved into the shade (Hallager pers. obs.). Simmons and Prytherch
(1986) and Blem and Blem (1993) suggested that remaining in the sun to
the point of nearly overheating is an act that deliberately increases the body
temperature in an effort to eradicate ectoparasites. Like Mueller (1972)
and Kennedy (1969), we noted that birds habitually preened shortly after
sunbathing.
Preferred sunning locations
We determined that each bird had a particular location it sunned in. This
could have been due to a variety of reasons, such as the camouflaging nature
of certain bushes and shrubbery (Teager, 1967) or the territorial nature of the
bird. Probably due to their shady nature, two areas of the exhibit were not
used as preferential sunbathing spots by any of the birds. The vegetation in
these areas was therefore thinned out and the birds have now been observed
sunning in these locations (Hallager pers. obs.). We noted that two of the
three most dominant birds in the group (the male and one of the two alpha
females) sunned more than all the other birds in the study. The other alpha
female sunned most often at the back of the exhibit in an area farthest away
from zoo visitors. Blem and Blem (1999) mentioned the need of Violet-
green Swallows Tachycineta thalassina to sunbathe at a particular site, even
though there were various other locations available.
Conclusion
Our study demonstrated that the act of sunbathing plays an integral role
in the health and feather condition of captive Kori Bustards and suggests
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998749" page_id="56253553"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
152
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.614606" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253553" page_num="152" year="" vol="">
FERNANDES &amp; HALLAGER - KORI BUSTARD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993510375" page_id="56253553"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
that the control of ectoparasites is the most plausible cause of sunning by
captive Kori Bustards. When designing exhibits for this species, areas of the
enclosure that provide suitable areas for sunning during the middle of the day
should be included in sufficient numbers to give every bird the opportunity
to sunbathe. Areas of shade should also be provided so that the birds can
move to these areas after sunning themselves. Additional observations are
needed of birds in the wild to further elucidate the significance, frequency
and occurrence of sunning by Kori Bustards.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.941785" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56253553" page_num="152" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.95865" page_id="56253553"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
Our special appreciation is extended to Juliana Ohlrich for painstakingly
and patiently contributing to the collection of data for this study. We are
also grateful to the volunteer watchers who, from its inception in 2000,
contributed their time and energy to the Kori Bustard behaviour watch at the
SNZR Without their dedication, many of our conclusions would not have
been possible. Thanks are also extended to Sheila Franco for her assistance
with data analysis.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.871836" genericHeader="references" page_id="56253553" page_num="152" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.860620133333333" page_id="56253553"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
Blem, L. B. and Blem, C. R. 1993. Do swallows sunbathe to control ectoparasites? An
experimental test. The Condor 95,3:730-734.
Blem, L. B. and Blem, C. R. 1999. Effects of some meterological variables on basking behaviour
in violet-green swallows. Journal of Field Ornithology 71,2:339-344.
Clements, J. F. 2007. The Clements Checklist of the Birds of the World. Sixth Edition. Cornell
University Press, USA.
Hauser, D. C. 1957. Some observations on sun bathing in birds. Wilson Bulletin 69:78-90.
Houston, D. C. 1979. A possible function of sunning behavior by griffon vultures, Gyps spp.,
and other large soaring birds. The British Ornithologists' Union 122:366-369.
Johnsgard, P. A. 1991. Bustards, Hemipodes and Sandgrouse, Birds of Dry Places. Oxford
University Press.
Kennedy, R. J. 1969. Sunbathing behaviour of birds. British Birds 62:249-259.
Lichtenberg, E. M. and Hallager, S . 2007. A description of commonly observed behaviors for
the Kori Bustard (Ardeotis kori). Journal of Ethology (currently available online only).
Mueller, H. C. 1972. Sunbathing in birds. Z. Tiersychol 30:225-336.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.988432111111111">
Simmons, K. E. L. and Prytherch, R. 1986. The sunning behaviour of birds. A Guide for
Ornithologists. Bristol Ornithological Club.
Stainton, J. M. 1982. Timing of bathing, dusting and sunning. British Birds 75:65-86.
Teager, C. W. 1967. Birds sun-bathing. British Birds 60:361-363.
United States Environmental Protection Agency website: http://www.epa.gov/sunwise/uvwhat.
html
Sara Hallager, Biologist, Birdhouse, National Zoological Park , PO Box
37012 MRC 5507, Washington DC 205560, USA. Tel:202 633 3088/E mail:
hallagers@si. edu/Website: http://nationalzoo.si. edit/
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.835232666666667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56253554" page_num="153" year="" vol="">
MANAGING THE ORANGE-HEADED GROUND
THRUSH Zoothera citrina nielli AT PAIGNTON ZOO
ENVIRONMENTAL PARK
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999084" page_id="56253554"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
153
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.984421305555555" page_id="56253554"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
by Jo Gregson
The genus Zoothera comprises 36 species, about half of which are
considered to be threatened or vulnerable. They are characterised by their
short tails and relatively long beaks, an adaptation for spending most of the
day foraging under scrubby vegetation.
The Orange-headed Ground Thrush has 12 subspecies (Clements, 2007).
Z. c. melli is the one most often available to aviculturists nowadays. It is
easily identified by its two black face stripes and orange throat; Z. c. cyanota
has the two face stripes combined with a white throat. Young birds can be
sexed in the first year. The male's wings are slate grey in colour while those
of the female are olive green. These are quite sociable though shy birds.
Provided with the right environment though they will become confident and
make ideal understory birds for mixed exhibits.
Here at Paignton Zoo we have two males and three females in our tropical
house and these live happily together as a group. In addition we have 20
breeding aviaries behind the scenes, five of which hold individual pairs of
Orange-headed Ground Thrushes. Each pair is separated from the next
pair by another species such as the Chestnut-backed Thrush Z. dohertyi and
Grey-backed Thrush Turdus hortulorum.
These off-show aviaries are of very simple construction and are easily
managed without causing much disturbance to the occupants. Built on a
concrete plinth, each aviary is 16ft long x 4ft wide x 7ft high (approx. 4.8m
long x 1.2m wide x 2.1m high). They are in blocks of four. We also have
smaller aviaries measuring 10ft long x 4ft wide x 7ft high (approx. 3m long
x 1.2m wide x 2.1m high). Thrushes breed in both sizes of aviaries.
Each has a shelter directly opposite the keeper's access door. The shelters
measure 4ft x 2ft 6in x 3ft 6in high (approx. 1.2m x 0.8m x 1 m high) and are
3ft 6in (approx, lm) above the floor. There is a small pop hole at the lower
front centre with a landing ledge. The shelters are floorless, allowing the
birds to enter and leave through the open bottom, which they often do. They
were designed in this way to cut down on the amount of cleaning and the
birds are more inclined to use a shelter from which they can easily escape.
Each aviary has a few high, straight perches and large amounts of scrubby
vegetation. The floors of the aviaries are left bare all winter. Then just
before the breeding season an abundance of nesting material is supplied, so
that the floor of the aviary is covered with materials such as moss, leaves
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999697" page_id="56253555"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
154
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9279105" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253555" page_num="154" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - ORANGE-HEADED GROUND THRUSH
(c) Jo Gregson
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.961237533333333" page_id="56253555"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
Block of four off-show aviaries with a safety porch at the
front and the shelters at the rear.
(c) Jo Gregson
Simple shelter with pop-hole at lower front centre and no
floor.
and dry grasses. This is replaced several times during the season. The nest
pans measure 6in x 6in x 3in deep (approx. 15cm x 15cm x 7.5cm deep) and
are similar to the containers used by supermarkets for mushrooms. Lower
sided boxes have sometimes caused young birds to fledge prematurely.
Breeding birds have never built in a bush, preferring instead to rise the nest
pans described above.
Heating is supplied by an electric tubular heater hung half-way up the
back wall of the shelter. These measure 2ft (61 cm) long and are of the type
often used in greenhouses. A strip of !4in (6mm) wire mesh is fixed a few
inches (5cm or so) above the heater to prevent birds roosting directly on
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.839612" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253556" page_num="155" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - ORANGE-HEADED GROUND THRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997859" page_id="56253556"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
155
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.424991" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56253556" page_num="155" year="" vol="">
(c) Jo Gregson
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9740049" page_id="56253556"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
Approximately 11 days old.
top of it.
Food is placed in a dish hung high up at the front of the aviary. A piece
of Perspex (Plexiglas) covers the feeding area. The diet consists of mixed
fruits, Sluis, boiled egg and minced (ground) beef The food is sprinkled with
SA37 and a few mealworms are given to the birds each day. As the breeding
season approaches, chopped pinkies are added to the diet and the number of
mealworms is stepped up. When there are chicks in the nest, mealworms are
scattered in the aviary several times each day. The mealworms are 'loaded'
with cuttlefish bone, stinging nettles, dandelion leaves and bran.
They usually lay four eggs but sometimes there are just three. The
incubation period is 14 days and the chicks fledge at about 12-14 days.
Chicks selected for hand-rearing are removed from the nest at five to six
days old unless there is a more immediate problem. They are kept in bowls
lined with soft tissue to prevent splayed legs and are fed every VA hours on
a diet of chopped pinkies and papaya (pawpaw). Water is given by syringe
a couple of times each day. They are weaned after about 20 days and are
then moved to a larger pen. They can be sexed at that time after the first
moult. As we have not observed the adults driving them before this stage,
chicks are removed from the breeding aviaries at about 30 days.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.491283" genericHeader="introduction" page_id="56253556" page_num="155" year="" vol="">
Reference
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.979745666666667">
Clements, J. F. 2007. The Clements Checklist of the Birds of the World. Sixth Edition.
Christopher Helm, London.
Jo Gregson.is Senior Head Keeper of Birds at Paignton Zoo Environ-
mental Park, Totnes Road, Paignton, Devon TQ4 7EU, UK. Tel: 01803
697500/Fax:01803 523457/Website:www.paigntonzoo.org.uk/E-mail:
jo.gregson@paigntonzoo. org. ak
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999584" page_id="56253557"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
156
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.956567" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253557" page_num="156" year="" vol="">
MIXED FORTUNES WITH THE CHESTNUT-BACKED
THRUSH Zoothera dohertyi
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970698851851852" page_id="56253557"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
by Jim Jerrard
I obtained a pair of2006-bred unrelated Chestnut-backed Thrushes from
my friend Gary Bralsford, who was first to breed this beautiful Indonesian
thrush in 2003 (see Avicultural Magazine Vol.109, No.4, pp. 150-153).
In March when the male started to sing, I provided a couple of nest sites
in their flight and in the second week of April the female started to build a
nest, using dry grass and moss, and lined the cup with bits of paper, sisal
and fibres. The nest was completed by April 18th and the first egg was laid
on April 21st, followed by a second egg. One egg hatched on May 2nd but
the chick died the same day. The other egg was clear. No further nesting
attempts were made and the male stopped singing. There was heavy rain,
wind and cold weather, but things continued to go well with my other birds,
though I did lose a few chicks.
When the bad weather died away at the end of June, the male Chestnut-
backed Thrush started to sing again and the female started to rebuild, but
did not lay until August 11th. This time she laid a clutch of three eggs, two
of which hatched on August 26th. The other egg was clear. The two chicks
were reared on earthworms and crickets and fledged on September 8th.
On September 17th the female laid again. This time she laid a clutch
of two eggs. One hatched on October 1st and the other the following day.
By then though the days were getting shorter and the nights were getting
longer and it was getting cold, it was not surprising therefore perhaps that
the chicks failed to survive past the fourth day. Had they reached seven
days old, I would have ringed (banded) them, as I had ringed the two earlier
chicks, then hand-reared them, but it was not to be.
The society supports a Special Interest Group for keepers and breeders
of the Chestnut-backed Thrush. The UK contacts are Andrew Owen and Ian
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.421196" page_id="56253557"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
Hadgkiss - Tel:01296 653286/E-mail:Andrew.Owen@nationaltrust.org.uk
</table>
<page confidence="0.999128" page_id="56253558"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
157
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7335435" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253558" page_num="157" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE GUIANAN TOUCANET Selenidera culik
by Beogt Larsson
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999362702702703" page_id="56253558"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
The Guianan Toucanet is distributed in lowland forests from eastern
Venezuela, through the Guianas to northern Brazil. It is common in the
wild but rather scarce in aviculture. Before 1990 it was almost unknown in
captivity. Jerry Jennings in California bred it for the first time in captivity
that year. Subsequently he and other private breeders in the USA were
successful several times with different pairs. In Europe I had until recently
only found records of it having been bred by Leif Rusmussen, a private
breeder in Copenhagen and at Aalborg Zoo, Denmark, both having raised
eight to 12 young to independence in the 1990s. Leif Rusmussen kept a
pair of the young through to the following year and unexpectedly the pair
bred successfully in the birds' first year.
As small numbers were regularly imported into Europe during the past 10
years, I suspected that there might be others and earlier this year discovered
that this species has been bred at Olomouc Zoo in the Czech Republic and
arranged an exchange of birds. According to the ISIS website there are not
many Guianan Toucanets kept in zoos, though many large collections are
not on the ISIS website.
The species of the genus Selenidera are unusual among members of
the toucan family in showing marked sexual dimorphism, a characteristic
they share with four species of the genus Pteroglossus . Despite their rather
dull coloration - predominately black, grey and mossy green - the male and
female Guianan Toucanet are both extremely attractive birds, with their
contrasting colours of yellow, red and chestnut. The light blue skin round
the eyes is almost shining. The beak is black and dull red. They are the
size of a jay and weigh 150g.
Members of the toucan family are intelligent birds, not unlike crows, and
need some kind of environmental enrichment. Their temperament is very
calm and they only show aggressive behaviour during the breeding season
and even then never towards each other in my experience, though I have
heard of other breeders who have experienced fighting between the sexes.
My Green Aracaris P. viridis are much more nervous and need more space
in order to feel comfortable. Members of the toucan family are best kept in
pairs and not with other species. It is certainly not advisable to keep them
with other breeding birds and never with birds smaller than themselves. In
the wild, toucans often rob other birds' nests. They eat fruits and berries from
a great variety of plants and, besides eggs and nestlings of other birds, the
bigger species are capable of catching small birds on the wing. A friend of
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998922" page_id="56253559"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
158
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.712897" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253559" page_num="158" year="" vol="">
LARSSON - GUIANAN TOUCANET
(c) Bengt Larsson
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.5889635" page_id="56253559"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
Unusual coloured young male with female-like grey breast, with black feathers
emerging. This was the breeding male.
(c) Bengt Larsson
At 14 days old the chick's eyes have probably not yet opened.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.616771" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253560" page_num="159" year="" vol="">
LARS SON - GUIANAN TOUCANET
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.982894" page_id="56253560"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
159
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.513644" page_id="56253560"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
The breeding female.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.41658" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56253560" page_num="159" year="" vol="">
(c) Bengt Larsson
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.867283" page_id="56253561"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
160
</page>
<figure confidence="0.581628" page_id="56253561"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
LARS SON - GUIANAN TOUCANET
(c) Bengt Larsson
Heel pads of 14 days old nestling.
(c) Bengt Larsson
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.776968666666667" page_id="56253561"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
At 23 days old the chicks' pin feathers are in uniform lines, like in an illustration taken
from a school book on bird anatomy. Note the chicks have no down and the parents
had removed all the peat from inside the box before laying the eggs.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.588633" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253562" page_num="161" year="" vol="">
LARS SON - GUIANAN TOUCANET
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.935484" page_id="56253562"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
161
</page>
<table confidence="0.7510705" page_id="56253562"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
Twenty-three days old.
(c) Bengt Larsson
(c) Bengt Larsson
At 30 days old the black feathers emerging on the breasts reveal that they are males.
</table>
<page confidence="0.998612" page_id="56253563"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
162
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.933739" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253563" page_num="162" year="" vol="">
LARSSON - GUIANAN TOUCANET
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.992162073170732" page_id="56253563"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
mine had a pair of Swainson's Toucans Ramphastos amhiguus swainsonii that
caught and ate a Bengalese that escaped and got into the toucans' aviary.
At the end of May 2003, I exchanged a female Keel-billed Toucan R.
sulfuratus for an old pair of Guianan Toucanets. I put the pair in a covered
outdoor aviary measuring lm x 2m x 2m high (approx. 3ft 3in x 6ft 6in x
6ft 6in high). It was furnished with standing, small, full-branched trees
and horizontal perches at different levels. The pair enjoyed using even the
thinnest branches of the trees. After two weeks, high up in the aviary I put
a nest box measuring 60cm x 20cm x 20cm (approx. 2ft x 8in x 8in). I filled
the nest box with peat and it did not take more than 15 minutes before the
male entered the nest box and started removing the peat. This method of
triggering nesting works with many hole-nesting softbills (e.g. see D. Rinke's
accounts of breeding trogons at Walsrode Birdpark, Germany). Within a
few days the box was completely empty and a week later the female laid the
first egg. Incubation commenced following the laying of the first egg, after
which the female laid another egg each day until there was a clutch of four
eggs. The male did 70% of the incubating during the day. The eggs did not
hatch and I removed them five days after the expected hatching date.
Three weeks later the female started laying a fresh clutch of eggs. This
time one of the eggs was punctured and the other three hatched after 16
days. When the chicks were just over 20 days old it suddenly turned very
cold and one night the temperature dropped to below freezing point. In the
morning the parents were in the nest box but when I came home from work
and planned to take them inside, both parents were out of the nest box and
the three chicks were dead. At the time the pair was upwards of 12 years old
and last year produced a clutch of eggs when probably over 15 years old.
The following two years were spent building two new bird houses and
aviaries. Although no breeding activity was expected, a few fertile clutches
were laid, despite much disturbance and movement between aviaries. At the
beginning of20041 had the opportunity to buy two more pairs from a dealer.
All the pairs were given nest boxes measuring 60cm x 20cm x 20cm (approx.
2ft x 8in x 8in) hung at an angle of 45* and with a 10 cm (4in) entrance tube
of natural cork. Often they could be heard inside working on the walls of
the nest boxes, confirming their close relationship to the woodpeckers. They
slept in the boxes every night.
One of the new birds had a female-like grey breast but a yellow band
on the nape like a male and later proved to be a male. None of the breeders
I have been in contact with in Denmark and the USA have ever seen such
a bird, although Miguel Rochas in California bred a female with a yellow
nape band that disappeared later.
Nothing much happened until the spring of 2006. By then I had lost
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.626691" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253564" page_num="163" year="" vol="">
LARS SON - GUIANAN TOUCANET
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99944" page_id="56253564"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
163
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999632951219512" page_id="56253564"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
patience with the new pairs and was planning to change the males around.
Used to the very obvious courtship behaviour of parrots, I found that of the
toucanets much less obvious. They never sit close together, seldom preen
each other and I have never observed them mating. The male does though
frequently feed the female. What I have learned is that it is more important
to listen to them than watch them. The male feeds the female while making
a characteristic "chopping" sound, unlike any other, and often in the nest
box, in which I believe that mating occurs.
One day the water bowl had been made messy with material from the nest
box, behaviour I recognised from the older pair. Two weeks later there were
two eggs. At least one more was laid but it was punctured. As scheduled
they hatched with one day in between, following a 16 day incubation period.
The chicks developed rapidly and their weight increased tenfold in four
weeks. They were fed mostly Zophobas larvae and grasshoppers during
the first two weeks. The parents kept the nest box perfectly clean. After
42 days one of the chicks was out in the aviary but returned to the nest box
the same day. Two days later both of them were out in the aviary and after
that only returned to the nest box at night. Once they were fully feathered it
was obvious that they were two males. I let them remain with their parents
for four months.
The parents never showed any aggression towards me but became more
confident and took insects from my hand. The breeding male of the older
pair hates me and attacks my hand when I am feeding it. He lost his tongue
as the result of a fight through the wire with a male Green Aracari and I have
to catch him a few times each year and clean his bill.
I feed my toucans and hill mynahs chopped fruits, berries and vegetables
of at least five different kinds each day, using papaya, banana, apple, pear,
grapes, elderberries, redcurrants, green peas, maize (sweet com), peppers,
squashes, eggplant (aubergine) and other low acid foods. Because of the
serious danger of iron storage disease I use only universal food and pellets
with a declared low iron content of less than 85ppm or mg/kg, such as
Nutribird T16 pellets, TO VO and Orlux universal food. The ratio of fruit
to universal food/pellets is about 58:38 with the remaining 4% consisting of
livefood. They have never eaten slugs, earthworms, pinkie mice or crickets
but enjoy grasshoppers, Zophobas morio larvae and some mealworms. They
get 10-20 Zophobas worms per day, increased to 40 a day during the breeding
season and occasionally get grasshoppers. The numbers are increased when
they are raising young.
From the end of March to the end of May 2007, the young breeding
pair produced five clutches, each of three or four eggs. All of them though
were damaged and later disappeared. After the first clutch was damaged I
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999415" page_id="56253565"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
164
</page>
<table confidence="0.921006" page_id="56253565"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
LARS SON - GUIANAN TOUCANET
Pair with newly fledged young.
(c) Bengt Lursson
(c) Mogens Stig Andersen
Male at four months old.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.741832" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253566" page_num="165" year="" vol="">
LARSSON - GUIANAN TOUCANET
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999003" page_id="56253566"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
165
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.944347947368421" page_id="56253566"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
started to give the pair more vitamin D? and water soluble calcium (Orlux
CalciLux) unsuccessfully. It may be that the eggs have naturally thin shells.
There is also the danger of them being damaged when the pair move about
in the nest box and it is important that the birds are not disturbed at night.
The nest box should be fixed at an angle, so that the birds do not jump down
onto the eggs and there should preferably be some material in the bottom of
the box to keep the eggs in place. This is difficult though, as the pair remove
any loose material from the nest box.
This species is easy to keep and relatively undemanding and it should
be possible to establish a self-sustaining population in captivity. I think it
is high time we started a European group to cooperate over the breeding of
members of the toucan family and I invite anyone interested to contact me:
bl@skanskbyggtjanst.se
Postscript
Since the above account was written, Bengt Larsson has travelled to
the Czech Republic and exchanged one of his males bred last year for a
female bred earlier this year at Olomouc Zoo. Olomouc Zoo now (October
2007) has 3.3, 1.3 bred there. Unfortunately, the zoo's breeding female
died after the second clutch of young was reared. Bengt Larsson now has
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.656127">
4.4 unrelated birds and a friend of his in Sweden has 2.2, which includes a
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.734714" page_id="56253566"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
male from the author.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.611865" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56253566" page_num="165" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.5755616">
My thanks to Leif Rusmussen and Aalborg Zoo in Denmark and Jerry
Jennings, Amado Summers and Miguel Rochas in the USA.
Bibliography
del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A. and Sargatal, J. 2002. Handbook of the Birds of the World. Vol.7.
Jacamars to Woodpeckers. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona.
ISIS. International Species Information System. Website:www.isis.org
Rinke, D. Breeding Trogons in Captivity. In: Gefiederte Welt and Avicultural Magazine.
Roots, C. 1970. Softbilled Birds. John Gifford Ltd.
Short, L. and Horn, J. 2001. Toucans, Barbels and Honey guides. Oxford University Press.
Vince, M. 1996. Softbills - Care, Breeding and Conservation. Hancock House.
</reference>
<bodyText confidence="0.9939674" page_id="56253566"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
The author is a biologist and a consultant to several Swedish zoos. For
three decades he bred several species of lories and lorikeets and in 1980 was
among the first aviculturists to breed Duyvenbode s Lory. He later started
to keep softbills. Bengt was recently appointed Editor of Fagelhobby, the
Swedish national avicultural magazine.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99922" page_id="56253567"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
166
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.840033" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253567" page_num="166" year="" vol="">
HAND-REARING A WHITE-BROWED COUCAL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.947411736842105" page_id="56253567"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
Centropus superciliosus AT EXMOOR ZOO
by Derek Gibson
Our White-browed Coucals having successfully parent-reared their
offspring over the past two years (see Avicultural Magazine Vol. 112, No.2,
pp.49-52 (2006)), it came as somewhat of a surprise when we found a three
or four day old chick lying dead on the aviary floor. Up until then we had
found the coucals most obliging parents that took great care of their young.
When we inspected the nest, however, we found a further two chicks, very
cold, but still alive, a clear egg and a second dead chick. The two surviving
chicks were transferred to the zoo's Incubation and Rearing Station.
The first chick weighed 27g whereas the second chick weighed only 7g.
Both were placed in a small pot lined with kitchen towel and small twigs
to prevent any problems with splayed legs, and then placed in a brooder set
at 33*C (91.4*F). The larger chick's eyes had started to open. We quickly
pooled ideas with staff at the Cotswold Wildlife Park, where the White-
browed Coucal had previously been successfully hand-reared. The chicks
were offered pinkie mice, rat pups, waxmoth larvae, mealworms and papaya,
plus a vitamin supplement, Ace-High, a Vetarc product that has been used
at the zoo over the past three years.
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.646542">
Fig. 1. Growth rate of hand-reared coucal.
</figureCaption>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.492316" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253568" page_num="167" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-BROWED COUCAL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998948" page_id="56253568"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
167
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.982762" page_id="56253568"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
Unfortunately, the second chick died almost immediately, but the first
chick went from strength to strength (as can be seen from the accompanying
growth rate graph and hand-rearing record) and by day 21 was observed
feeding itself and by day 27 was weaned
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.952594">
Table 1. Hand-rearing record days seven to 27.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.9877894" page_id="56253568"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
Age
(days)
Date
Weight
Observations
</figure>
<page confidence="0.5235305" page_id="56253568"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
7
04.05.07
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.696798" page_id="56253568"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
27g
Placed in brooder set at 33*C
(91.4*F), along with a bowl of water
to increase the humidity.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.726288" page_id="56253568"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
8
</page>
<figure confidence="0.962864837837837" page_id="56253568"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
05.05.07
26g
From 7.30am - 5.30pm fed on
pinkie mice soaked and cut into
quarters and waxworm larvae
(killed).
9
06.05.07
29g
Eyes three-quarters open.
10
07.05.07
34g
Fed crickets and mealworms.
11
08.05.07
42g
f!
12
09.05.07
46g
If
13
10.05.07
51g
ft
14
11.05.07
59g
tt
15
12.05.07
65g
?f
16
13.05.07
70g
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.885007" page_id="56253568"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
Rat pups and minced (ground) meat
added to diet. Feathers developing
on the breast.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.7007685" page_id="56253568"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
17
14.05.07
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.71245875" page_id="56253568"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
77g
Stopped continual begging and
started to make more characteristic
coucal sound.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.8319285" page_id="56253568"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
18
15.5.07
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9306365" page_id="56253568"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
83g
Transferred to exercise cage and
given fruit, insectivorous food and
minced (ground) meat.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.982588" page_id="56253569"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
168
</page>
<figure confidence="0.9556235" page_id="56253569"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-BROWED COUCAL
Derek Gibson
Eleven days old.
Age
(days)
Date
Weight
Observations
</figure>
<page confidence="0.7742205" page_id="56253569"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
19
16.05.07
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.539666" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253569" page_num="168" year="" vol="">
9 1 g
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.859848" page_id="56253569"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
Food no longer placed in chick's
mouth, instead we wait for the chick
to make the first move.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.511149" page_id="56253569"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
20
</page>
<figure confidence="0.98327753125" page_id="56253569"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
17.05.07
90g
Soaked Zoo A given at feed.
21
18.05.07
88g
Started to feed itself, taking
mealworms and locusts.
22
19.05.07
87g
If
23
20.05.07
82g
ft
24
21.05.07
83g
ft
25
22.05.07
85g
Yen!
26
23.05.07
85g
ft
27
24.05.07
93g
Weaned.
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.491883" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253570" page_num="169" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-BROWED COUCAL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997293" page_id="56253570"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
169
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.785071">
Derek Gibson
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.972153272727273" page_id="56253570"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
Fifty days old.
Upon being weaned it was housed in a large flight cage and upon
determination of its sex will, it is hoped, go to make up a second pair here
at Exmoor. At the time of writing (summer 2007), the breeding pair is
incubating a further three eggs and, hopefully, this time will successfully
rear the young and take us a few steps further forward in establishing a self-
sustaining captive-breeding population of White-browed Coucals.
Derek Gibson is Head Keeper at Exmoor Zoological Park, South
Stowford, Bratton Fleming, Barnstaple, Devon EX314SG, UK. Tel: 01598
76335/E-mail: Derek.r.gibson@btinternet.com. It was the first collection in
the UK to breed the White-browed Coucal.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.989662" page_id="56253571"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
170
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.395405" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253571" page_num="170" year="" vol="">
THE ORIOLE FINCH IS A STRANGE FINCH
by Simon Espley
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995365540540541" page_id="56253571"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
The Oriole Finch Limirgus olivaceus is a secretive and seldom seen
species from the forests of west, central and east Africa. I have spent days
craning my neck staring up into the gloom of central African equatorial
forest canopies, during my many birdwatching trips to that part of the world,
hoping in vain to catch a glimpse of this elusive species. Although so far I
have had no luck, I intend to keep trying.
Imagine my interest therefore when during 2006 I heard that a few pairs
were to be imported into South Africa, and that I had secured one of these
pairs. I could barely conceal my excitement as I made my way to the airport
to pick up my prized pair.
The male Oriole Finch is a really stunning looking bird that does indeed
resemble a miniature black-headed oriole Oriolus spp. The female Oriole
Finch is a more sober coloured bird. The large head and sturdy looking beak
of the Oriole Finch appear to be an adaptation for a specific diet, but reference
books do not shed much light on this subject. As a matter of fact, reference
books do not have much to say about this species. Its body is marginally
smaller than that of our Bully or Brimstone Canary Serinus sulphuratus but,
unlike most Fringillidae, the Oriole Finch is mostly silent.
It has a large range, estimated at 180,000sq km (approx. 70,000sq miles),
covering a large area of west, central and east Africa. The size of the global
population has not been quantified, but it is believed to be substantial, as
the species is described as locally common in at least parts of its range. Its
preference is for tropical, subtropical and moist montane forests.
I set off for home with my two birds, which sadly were the only two to
survive the importation. There I set about settling them down in my Cape
Town aviaries in the hope that the pair would breed. I housed them on their
own and left them pretty much to their own devices in a thickly planted
aviary measuring 2m x 5m x 2.5m high (approx. 6ft 6in x 16ft x 8ft high).
Clear fibreglass sheeting covers 80% of the aviary roof. The sides consist
of 80% shade cloth to prevent visual contact with birds in neighbouring
aviaries. All my aviaries are covered externally with 6mm x 6mm (approx.
!4in x !4in) welded mesh and are therefore mouse-proof. Food is provided
through a door, without the need to enter the aviary. Fresh drinking water
is dispensed into a shallow baking tray four times a day via a timer. A twice
daily fine mist spray that keeps the plants happy in summer is also on a timer.
The plants include tall reeds, wild grasses, herbs and various weeds. The
Oriole Finches remain very secretive and spend much of their time in the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.708297" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253572" page_num="171" year="" vol="">
ESPLEY - ORIOLE FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998566" page_id="56253572"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
171
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99820765" page_id="56253572"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
depths of the reeds or hiding in the slangbos.
They have interesting dietary requirements and have settled on the
following: a seed mix including oily seeds (niger, linseed, canary and rape),
shelled sunflower seeds, papaya, cucumber, fresh and soaked dried figs,
grated broccoli and com, fresh seeding grasses, sprouting seeds, wild flowers
such as dandelions, thistles and daisies, mealworms, termites, soaked softbill
pellets with Pro Nutra added. The seed gets a weekly dose of cod liver oil
and wheatgerm oil and powdered calcium, before being discarded the next
day. My birds ignore all the usual finch seeds such as millet and manna.
Much to my delight, within three months, the pair produced three
chicks. As far as I am aware, this is the first recorded captive breeding in
South Africa and possibly anywhere in the world. (In his First Breeding
Records for Birds Reared to Independence under Controlled Conditions in
the United Kingdom , Dave Coles lists it as having been bred by Peter Paris
in 1974. To the best of my knowledge though Simon Espley's is the first
published account of breeding the Oriole Finch. - Ed.) Neville Brickell
of the Indigenous Bird Breeders' Group (Southern African Region) recalls
Oriole Finches being brought into South Africa in the mid-1900s on boats
that came down the east African coast, but cannot recall any breeding
claims. I know of no data on captive breeding and very little is available on
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998768" page_id="56253573"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
172
</page>
<table confidence="0.981676333333333" page_id="56253573"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
ESPLEY - ORIOLE FINCH
Juvenile at 24 days.
(c) Simon Espley
(c) Simon Espley
Juvenile Oriole Finch aged 47 days old. This is the bird hatched in November 2007.
Note that it still has a black bill.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.698953" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253574" page_num="173" year="" vol="">
ESPLEY - ORIOLE FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.983277" page_id="56253574"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
173
</page>
<figure confidence="0.639978" page_id="56253574"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
Simon Espley
Male Oriole Finch. The coloration of the male varies slightly from subspecies to
subspecies.
Male Oriole Finch (right) and female (left).
Simon Espley
</figure>
<page confidence="0.999552" page_id="56253575"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
174
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.916559" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253575" page_num="174" year="" vol="">
ESPLEY - ORIOLE FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.975781185185185" page_id="56253575"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
its breeding habits in the wild. My birds' cup-shaped nest was made from
coconut fibres, hessian and various plant fibres gleaned from plants in the
aviary. The nest was placed in hanging slangbos. Three eggs were laid on
consecutive days. They were white, shaded with light blue/green, and had
reddish brown pinprick sized speckles to blotches 2mm in diameter. The
young left the nest 21 days after hatching.
A further pair of Oriole Finches found its way into South Africa earlier
this year and I was lucky enough to secure this pair. I have paired the two
with my youngsters and now have three unrelated pairs and a spare bird. At
the time of writing (June 2007) these are the only Oriole Finches in South
Africa, but I hear some more may arrive later this year.
Postscript
The same pair subsequently produced a further chick in November
2007, that at the time of Simon's recent e-mail (December 18th 2007) was
independent and "learning about life" in a nursery aviary along with recently-
bred Red-faced Crimsonwings Cryptospiza reichenovii. Lavender Waxbills
Estrilda caerulescens and Red Siskins Carduelis cucullata. Simon confirmed
that a number of wild-caught Oriole Finches found their way from Tanzania to
South Africa in early 2007, but so far as he is aware, no successful breedings
have resulted from the importation of that batch of birds.
Simon Espley, the author of the above article, which was publishedfirst
in the South African magazine Avizandum (June 2007), is a founder-member
of the Rare Finch Conservation Group (website :www.rarefinch.co.za). The
postscript was sent just after Simon had returned from a trip to south-west
Uganda to search for Shelley s Crimsonwing C. shelleyi and visit the Rare
Finch Conservation Groups s Crimsonwing Project in Uganda. He can be
contacted by e-mail at: simon@africageographic.com
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99647" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56253575" page_num="174" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.90099525" page_id="56253575"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
The society has a large stock of back issues mostly from 1935 onwards
but there are also some earlier issues still available. They are priced #3.00
each (including p&amp;p). Please check availability before placing an order.
Overseas members may be able to pay by credit card through a PayPal
invoice, but this service is not available in all countries. All enquiries
should be addressed to: Paul Boulden, Hon. Secretary/Treasurer, Avicultural
Society, Arcadia, The Mounts, East Allington, Totnes, Devon TQ9 7JQ, UK
or E-mail:admin@avisoc.co.uk
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999089" page_id="56253576"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
175
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.970504128205128" page_id="56253576"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
ORNITHEA 2007 - A SHOW OF SUPERLATIVES
by Tony Pittman
The beginning of November each year is for me Omithea time. This
unique show organised by the aviculturists' club in Cologne, Germany, never
ceases to amaze me and this year's show - open to the public from Thursday,
November Ist-Sunday, November 4th - was no exception; in fact the club
members surpassed themselves.
The club was formed in 1961 and has some 50 members. It has a
clubhouse in a suburb of Cologne and the members meet there regularly
to exchange information on keeping and breeding all types of birds, have
a communal meal and drink the popular local beer. Sometimes they invite
a speaker, which is how I got to know about the club and later became a
member.
The show is held in the hall of a local secondary school, which the club
takes over for two weeks for a peppercorn rent. The lay-out is carefully
planned and all the members are involved in the build-up to the show and
help clear everything away at the end.
This year, some 500 birds of 182 species and subspecies, bred locally
and in perfect condition, were displayed in 123 decorated aviaries for larger
birds and large exhibition cages for smaller birds. All the cages and aviaries
were planted and some had water features and rock formations. Also, every
cage and aviary had detailed information about the occupants.
The centrepiece of this year's show was an astonishing swamp landscape
with a painted background, rock face, waterfall, pool, shrubs, grasses,
boulders and a large tree. Housed in it were seven species of birds, including
egrets, avocets, plovers, gulls and two species of ibis, with no wire netting
or any other form of barrier between the birds and the public.
Ornithea 2007 attracted some 6,000 visitors, including many from
neighbouring countries such as the Netherlands, Belgium and Switzerland.
Among them were many children, who were thrilled to have such a great
opportunity to see close-up in naturalistic settings, native birds such as the
Wren Troglodytes troglodytes , Robin Erithacus nubecula, Pied Wagtail
MotacUla alba yarrelli , Grey Wagtail M cinerea , Hoopoe Upupa epops ,
Kingfisher Alcedo atthis and Lesser Spotted Woodpecker Dendrocopos
minor.
There were 57 species of parrots, ranging from hanging parrots through
to conures and lories, Amazons, cockatoos, macaws and the Kea Nestor
notabilis. There were 10 species of owls, as well as a wide range of finches
and softbills. Bali Starlings Leucopsar rothschildi were on show again this
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998841" page_id="56253577"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
176
</page>
<equation confidence="0.267333" page_id="56253577"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
PITTMAN - ORNITHEA 2007
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.993505518518518" page_id="56253577"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
year in a large, beautifully planted aviary with lush vegetation and tropical
flowers.
On the Saturday there was a well attended all-day symposium. Bemd
Marcordes, formerly of Walsrode Birdpark and now Curator of Birds at
Cologne Zoo, spoke on cockatoos, Lars Lepperhoff from Switzerland
described his recent expedition to the Congo to see Grey Parrots Psittacus
erithacus and Norbert Hebei spoke about keeping and breeding Amazon
parrots. Other speakers included Jos Hubers, who gave a presentation
on lories and Simon Bruslund Jensen, formerly of A1 Wabra Wildlife
Preservation and now at Walsrode, who spoke about his experiences at A1
Wabra and Walsrode Birdpark. I gave a presentation on the Slender-billed
Conure Enicognathus leptorhynchus in the wild and in aviaries. At the end
of the symposium I was very pleased to be invited to accept from Norbert
Hebei organiser of the symposium and Walter Grau, chairman of the club,
a donation of 1,000 Euros (approx. #750 or US$1,500) for the Hyacinth
Macaw Anodorhynchus hyacinthinus project in Brazil.
On the Sunday morning the local special interest group held a meeting
on breeding conures, at which Thomas Arndt gave an illustrated presentation
on the many recent changes to the taxonomy of the conures.
In addition to the show, there was an area where the work of bird
artists was displayed and there was an informative display by the customs
authorities. There was a bookshop in the hall and a tombola. Food and
drink, organised by the club members, was available throughout the day in
a side-room and there was a barbecue just outside.
The airport at Cologne is very close to the suburb where the show takes
place and several low-cost carriers fly to it.
Tony has the website:www.bluemacaws.org
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.5205615" page_id="56253577"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
* *
*
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.679942" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253577" page_num="176" year="" vol="">
LONG-LIVED GLOSSY STARLING
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.8064972">
Chris Brack has sent news from Germany of a long-lived Greater
Blue-eared Glossy Starling Lamprotornis chalybaeus (Hohes Alter eines
Griinschwanz-Glanzstares, Gefiederte Welt August 8/2007, p.226). The bird
lived in a private aviary for 24 years and eight months. As it was an adult
when purchased, they estimate it may have been 27 or 28 years old.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9698735" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253578" page_num="177" year="" vol="">
THE SOCIETY'S VISIT TO WALSRODE BIRDPARK,
GERMANY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998009" page_id="56253578"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
177
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.926453529411765" page_id="56253578"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
by Andrew Owen
Early in October, 44 members and guests spent three highly enjoyable
days at the world-famous Walsrode Birdpark in northern Germany. The visit
was made an even more memorable experience, thanks to the wonderful
hospitality of the park's Curator Simon Bruslund Jensen. Simon took us
on an extremely thorough tour of the park, which included a look behind
the scenes at all the off-show facilities. Walsrode has one of the finest bird
collections in the world, and the skill and dedication of Simon and his staff
were clear for all to see.
The park covers approximately 30 hectares (74 acres) and is beautifully
landscaped with mature trees, shrubs and manicured lawns. There are some
5,000 birds of approximately 600 species, so the full three days of our visit
were needed to try to see everything. All the aviaries and enclosures were
immaculately maintained and spotlessly clean, something for which the park
has become well-known.
It is difficult to pick out favourite birds and areas of the park, but one
of the highlights for me was the collection of Madagascan birds, many
of which must be unique in aviculture. The Blue Couas Coua caerlea ,
Crested Couas C. cristata and Giant Couas C. gigas (non-parasitic members
of the cuckoo family) were a wonderful sight, with the first two species
breeding well. The Madagascar Blue Pigeon Alectroenas madagascariensis,
Madagascar Crested Ibis Lophotibis cristata , Long-tailed Ground-Roller
Uratelornis chimaera , Cuckoo-Roller Leptosomus discolor and the lovely
Pitta-like Ground-Roller Atelornis pittoides are all spectacular birds. We
visited the hand-rearing room and were privileged to see the first Blue-eyed
Ibis Threskiornis bernieri ever hatched in captivity. This is a Critically
Endangered species, yet Simon told us that the original birds were found
on sale in a meat market in Madagascar and were bought by the kilo - and
saved from the cooking pot! Conservation clearly plays an important role
in the work being done at Walsrode with species from Madagascar being
the focal point of this, although Walsrode also works with numerous other
threatened species from around the world.
There are two most impressive tropical facilities, the first of which has
a range of indoor aviaries housing a multitude of wonderful avian gems
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.949676666666667">
including Andean Cock-of-the-Rock Rupicola peruvianas, Golden-headed
Quetzal Pharomachrus auriceps. Hooded Pitta Pitta sordida , Banded Pitta
P. guajana, Spangled Cotinga Cotinga cayana. Carmine Bee-eater Merops
</reference>
<page confidence="0.988654" page_id="56253579"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
178
</page>
<table confidence="0.43304575" page_id="56253579"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
OWEN - WALSRODE BIRDPARK
Walsrode Birdpark Archive
Horned Guan.
Karen Heath
</table>
<author confidence="0.591861">
Christopher Marler, Andrew Owen, Simon Brusland Jensen and Raymond Sawyer.
</author>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.531389" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253580" page_num="179" year="" vol="">
OWEN - WALSRODE BIRDPARK
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.935411" page_id="56253580"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
179
</page>
<figure confidence="0.867356" page_id="56253580"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
Walsrode Birdpark Archive
Blue Coua.
Andrew Owen
Shoebill.
</figure>
<page confidence="0.994914" page_id="56253581"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
180
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.862574" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253581" page_num="180" year="" vol="">
OWEN - WALSRODE BIRDPARK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9674186" page_id="56253581"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
nubicus and a number of fruit doves, such as the Beautiful Ptilinopus
pulchellus and Pink-headed P porphyreus , to name but a few.
Pigeons and doves are something of a speciality at Walsrode, which must
have one of the most impressive collections of these birds. They are one of
the main groups housed in the other tropical house - the Indonesian exhibit.
Victoria Goura victoria and Southern Crowned Pigeons G. scheepmakeri
were an impressive sight strolling along the paths amongst the visitors in the
company of Pheasant Pigeons Otidiphaps noblis , Sulawesi Ground-Doves
Gallicolumba tristigmata , Emerald Doves Chalcophaps indica and Thick-
billed Ground-Pigeons Trugon terrestris. This tropical house is huge and we
saw different species each time we visited it during the three days. A female
Giant Pitta P. caerulea sitting quietly in the undergrowth, a Black-capped
Babbler Pellorneum capistratum with its unusual walking gait, a noisy flock
of Chestnut-backed Scimitar Babblers Pomatorhinus montanus and a Banded
Pitta digging in the soil by my feet were among the highlights for me.
Cranes, pelicans, ibises and storks are among other groups well
represented in the collection, with the amazing Shoebill Balaeniceps rex
vying for the title of strangest looking bird on the planet! Impressive birds of
prey included Harpy Eagle Harpia harpya, Lammergeier Gypaetus barbatus ,
Steller's Sea-Eagle Haliaeetus pelagicus, Great Grey Owl Strix nebulosa
and Hawk Owl Sarnia ulula and, in their off-show aviary, Secretary Birds
Sagittarius serpentarius with a well-grown youngster.
It was nice to see European birds displayed in really well thought-out
aviaries, one of which has Red-backed Shrike Lanius collurio , Hawfinch
Coccothraustes coccothraustes and Corncrake Crex crex. There is a
comprehensive display of parrots, of which the highlights for me were
the Homed Parakeet Eunymphicus cornutus, (Tahiti) Blue Lorikeet Vini
peruviana and Desmarest's Fig Parrot Psittaculirostris desmarestii.
I would recommend a visit to Walsrode to everyone with an interest
in keeping birds. There is so much to see and leam and, where else can
you see Kagu Rhynochetos jubatus , Horned Guan Oreophasis derbianus ,
Greater Bird of Paradise Paradisaea apoda , Harlequin Duck Histrionicus
histrionicus, Siberian Crane Grus leucogeranus and Roadmnner Geococcyx
californianus , together with some 594 other species, all in the same place?
Meeting new friends and catching up with old ones (some of them
very old!), sharing thoughts and ideas with like-minded bird keepers and
seeing one of the best collections of birds anywhere in the world, was a
great experience. A big thank you must go to Mike Curzon for organising
everything and helping to make this Avicultural Society visit such an
enjoyable one.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998452" page_id="56253582"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
181
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995422" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253582" page_num="181" year="" vol="">
LETTER TO EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.981475903225807" page_id="56253582"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
Prof. J. R. (Bob) Hodges has long had a special interest in the Orange-
bellied Parrot or Parakeet Neophema pulchella and recent developments
have prompted the following letter from him:
I had almost forgotten the exciting day on which I flew from Hobart
to their breeding area in virtually unexplored south-west Tasmania where
I was able to see and photograph several specimens and their nests. They
were extraordinarily beautiful with grass-green plumage and a large bright
orange patch on the abdomen, contrasting with a few I had seen some years
previously when Australian parrots were being smuggled into the UK. These
were pale and unattractive looking like faded Elegant Parrots or Parakeets
N. elegans.
Apparently several attempts have been made to reintroduce and re-
establish the species in its normal habitat by liberating small numbers of
aviary-bred birds that have not been successful and the species is still listed
as Critically Endangered with fewer than 150 birds in the wild. Biologists in
the Environment Departments of Tasmania and Victoria blame the situation
on the loss of habitat in Victoria where they spend their non-breeding
season. Anyone who has visited at intervals, as I have, this particular area
of 'countryside' around Melbourne will have noticed that during the last 40
years much of the 'pastoral area' has changed to large industrial estates and
their supporting towns. I cannot imagine that the parrots will adapt their
behaviour and adopt this new habitat.
In October this year (2007) about 80 birds, reared in Hobart, Adelaide Zoo
and at Healesville, were released in their Tasmanian breeding area. I hope
that this major effort to re-establish the species in the wild will be successful
but I am not optimistic. I consider that an enormous amount of money and
effort has been wasted. I think that the organisers of this effort will be very
disappointed, and should have involved the cooperation of well-known
aviculturists who would almost undoubtably have established them in their
aviaries. Healthy specimens in appropriate aviaries are far more attractive
than lifeless, stuffed and withering creatures in museums.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998631" page_id="56253583"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
182
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990596" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253583" page_num="182" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
PEKIN ROBINS AND SMALL SOFTBILLS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997688" page_id="56253583"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
Peter Karsten was bom in Germany and, following the completion of his
formal education in Germany and Sweden, emigrated to Canada in 1962.
After a 30-year career with Calgary Zoo, for 20 years of which he held the
positions of Zoo Director and Executive Director, he retired in 1994 and
turned his attention to small softbills, keeping and breeding Pekin Robins
Leiothrix lutea for the past 10 years. (An article by Peter Karsten on keeping
and breeding the European Robin Erithacus rubecula will appear in a future
issue of the Avicultural Magazine. - Ed.) His professionalism and hands-
on avicultural skills shine through in his delightful book, Pekin Robins and
Small Softbills - Management and Breeding.
There is a dearth of good quality, up-to-date books on bird husbandry,
particularly relating to softbills, so this well thought-out personal account
of managing these charming birds will be welcomed by bird keepers. The
17 colour plates, 60 high quality photographs and numerous line drawings
by the author help make this book even more endearing.
It is clear that Peter Karsten has a real passion for these birds and he
covers in fine detail every aspect of their husbandry. A really practical
and useful book, it has chapters covering biology, housing, general care,
acquisition, breeding, hand-rearing, feeding and health care, as well as
cultivating livefood.
Packed with information gathered through personal experience, Peter
Karsten's book is a mine of information for beginners and experienced
aviculturists alike. The section on the determination of sex is of particular
interest. Although the Pekin Robin (or Red-billed Leiothrix) is frequently
kept, it continues to surprise me how many aviculturists are unable to sex
their birds accurately. This no longer needs to be the case, as the author
resolves this tricky problem.
I am very impressed by his coverage of subjects such as aviary design,
predator prevention, health care and cultivating livefood, with his line
drawings, used throughout the book, enhancing his coverage of each subject.
Although the author lives in Canada, all of the techniques described are
applicable here in the UK and probably elsewhere as well. The climate is
similar to that of the UK and northern Europe and, although the predators
may be different, the methods of keeping them out of our aviaries are much
the same wherever we live.
There is a chapter on other softbill species, which gives brief descriptions
and useful management tips. The Pekin Robin is the main focus of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909704" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253584" page_num="183" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999309" page_id="56253584"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
183
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.841224125" page_id="56253584"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
book, but the author's practical ideas and common sense approach highly
recommend Peter Karsten's book to serious aviculturists caring for just about
any other species of aviary birds.
Pekin Robins and Small Softbills - Management and Breeding (ISBN
978-0-88839-606-8) by Peter Karsten, hard cover, 252 pages, 17 colour
plates, 60 colour photographs and 240 line drawings, is published by Hancock
House Publishers, 1431 Harrison Ave., Blaine, WA 98230-5005, USA.
Price US$49.95 plus s/h. It can be ordered by Tel:(604) 538-1114/Fax:(604)
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.8430895" page_id="56253584"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
538-2262/Toll Free Tel:800-938-1114/Fax:800-983-2262/E-mail: sales@
hancockhouse.com/Website:www.hancockhouse.com
Andrew Owen
THE LAPWING
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.994228222222222" page_id="56253584"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
The Lapwing by Michael Shrubb is the latest addition to the well
established series of Poyser monographs. It is about the ecology, behaviour,
breeding biology and conservation of the Northern Lapwing Vanellus
vanellus. A retired farmer who has studied the Lapwing on his farm and
elsewhere for over 40 years, the author is well placed to have written this
monograph, which is both very readable and well researched.
A brief introductory chapter sets the Northern Lapwing in context as one
of 24 species of the genus Vanellus - one of which the Javanese (or Sunda)
Lapwing V macropterus has not been recorded for over 60 years and may
be extinct. The following five chapters focus on information and analysis
of the breeding and winter distribution, habitats, habitat use and population
changes of the Northern Lapwing in the UK and Europe. Over 90% of the
Lapwings in the UK now breed on agricultural land, which is also their
main winter habitat.
A chapter is devoted to the Lapwing's food and feeding behaviour
and, a further five chapters, cover all aspects of its breeding behaviour
and biology, followed by a chapter on chick rearing and fledging success.
The section on the chick's diet - invertebrates mainly, with earthworms
and beetles, being amongst the more important food items - should be of
interest to aviculturists. The chapter on movements and mortality describes
the spectacular movements of large flocks of Lapwings in response to cold
weather. In really severe winters all of the Lapwings may leave the UK.
The final chapter is entitled - Conservation and the future - and looks at
the problems facing the Lapwing related to habitat loss, with reductions of
wet grassland, increasing agricultural intensification and changes in farming
practises. Recovery will require habitat restoration and the promotion of
less intensive agriculture.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999555" page_id="56253585"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
184
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.97004" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253585" page_num="184" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985640615384615" page_id="56253585"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
Appendices document changes in the breeding population and range of
the Lapwing in Europe and list breeding habitats, diets and the scientific
names of species referred to in the main text. As befits such a well researched
book, the bibliography has 18 pages of references.
Each of the 14 chapters is graced by monochrome illustrations by Robert
Gillmor which really capture the spirit of the Lapwing in a way that only
he can. These for me are the "icing on the cake" of this well written and
carefully produced book that is readable yet includes good science.
The Lapwing (ISBN 978-0-7136-6854-4) by Michael Shrubb, 232 pages,
eight colour plates which include 29 photographs of Lapwings and their
habitat, monochrome illustrations by Robert Gillmor, plus tables, etc., is
published by T &amp; A D Poyser, an imprint of A &amp; C Black Publishers Ltd
(website:www.acblack.com). It is a hardback price #40.00 in the UK.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.37604">
Roger Wilkinson
</subsectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996949" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56253585" page_num="184" year="" vol="">
WATERBIRDS AROUND THE WORLD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97285875" page_id="56253585"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
Albatrosses, flamingos, swans, geese, ducks, cranes, waders, gulls, terns,
auks and, other waterbirds, are among the world's most threatened birds.
They share a dependency on the world's wetlands, seas, coasts, estuaries,
lagoons, lochs, rivers, marshlands, swamps, tundra and other peatlands, and
have come to symbolize the changing, fragile nature of our planet.
With this in mind, more than 450 conservation scientists from 90
countries attended a conference entitled - Waterbirds around the world -
held in Edinburgh, Scotland, in 2004. The papers, more than 240 of them,
preceded by The Edinburgh Declaration, the address by HRH The Prince
of Wales and those by government ministers and other officials, etc., have
now been published in Waterbirds around the world - a global overview
of the conservation, management and research of the world's waterbird
flyways, which describes the global efforts being made to halt the decline
in waterbird populations.
Edited by Gerard Boere, Colin Galbraith and David Stroud, Waterbirds
around the world (ISBN 0 11 497333 4), hardback, 940 pages, over 250
colour photos and more than 500 graphs, tables and maps, is published by
The Stationary Office, 71 Lothian Road, Edinburgh EH3 9AZ, UK. It can
be ordered from there by Tel:+44 (0)870 606 5566/Fax:+44 (0)870 606
5588/E-mail:enquiries@tsoscotland.com/Website:www. tsoshop.co.uk
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.285533">
Malcolm Ellis
</subsectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99873" page_id="56253586"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
185
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.771571666666667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56253586" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
SUCCESSFULLY REARED
Loro Parque Fundacion's Lear's Macaw Anodorhynchus leari hatched
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9878584" page_id="56253586"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
earlier this year (see News &amp; Views Vol. 113, No.2, p.93 (2007)),was reared
successfully by its foster parents, a pair of Green-winged Macaws Ara
chloropterus . A second chick was reared by a second pair of Green-winged
Macaws and fledged in October. A third chick being reared by its parents
was about to fledge.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.847956" page_id="56253586"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.626609" genericHeader="method" page_id="56253586" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
IMPORTANT NEW ARRIVALS AT CHESTER ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.949857090909091" page_id="56253586"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
After a long wait Chester Zoo is delighted to have finally got a new
female Red Bird of Paradise Paradisaea rubra. She is said to be the only
female Red Bird of Paradise in Europe and has joined the three males in
the zoo's Islands in Danger exhibit. After almost two years of hard work
and negotiations the zoo has also finally imported four pairs of Endangered
Visayan Tarictic Hombills Penelopides panini panini from Panay Island
in the Philippines. It is hoped they will form the nucleus of a European
breeding population. Chester Zoo has long supported field conservation in
the Philippines and the breeding centre there where the birds were bred. It
is assisting with plans for trial reintroductions of this species and several
others endemic to the Philippines.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.60402825" page_id="56253586"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
* * *
CONTINUING TO BREED
Bernard Sayers whose autobiographical profile was published in the
Avicultural Magazine Vol AW, &amp;apos;No. 4, pp. 147-160 (2005), has written to say
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.911112" page_id="56253586"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
that although his collection is now full of geriatrics, with many of his birds
having been in his collection for over 20 years, a few for over 30 years and
one for over 40 years, nevertheless, a few still bred successfully during 2007.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.792370666666667">
Seven Indian Scops-Owls Otus bakkamoena were raised, five Burrowing
Owls Athene cunicularia , six Boobook Owls Ninox boobook, three Chaco
Owls Strix chacoensis, one Northern White-faced Scops-Owl Ptilopsis
(formerly Otus) leucotis, one Tropical Screech-Owl Megascops choliba,
three Crested Bronzewing Pigeons Geophaps lophotes and one Princess of
Wales' Parakeet Polytelis alexandrae.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999363" page_id="56253587"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
186
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9826545" genericHeader="method" page_id="56253587" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
GROWING CONCERN IN AUSTRALIA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999119285714286" page_id="56253587"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
There is growing concern among Australian aviculturists over the fact
that dealers have been visiting bird sales around the country and buying up
all the Australian-bred Cuban Finches (Grassquits) Tiaris canorus they can
get their hands on. The birds are exported to the USA and, according to
one report, onto Canada, leaving Australian aviculturists fearful that their
established stocks of these sought-after birds will be left severely depleted
and could even lead to their disappearance from Australian aviaries.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.713843" page_id="56253587"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
* * *
EXCITING DISCOVERY
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.982956923076923" page_id="56253587"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
Since 1995 the Bolivian organisation Armonia (BirdLife International's
partner in Bolivia) and Loro Paraque Fundacion of Spain have been working
together on a conservation programme for the Critically Endangered Blue-
throated Macaw Ara glaucogularis. Loro Parque Fundacion recently
donated a new vehicle to the programme and almost immediately this led
to the exciting discovery of a further 70 Blue-throated Macaws at a single
roost on a ranch to the west of the main river, the Rio Marmore. Other new
sites each with a few macaws were discovered in the same region. As a
result of these discoveries the estimated size of the overall population of the
Blue-throated Macaw has been revised upwards from 150-250 birds to 250-
350 birds. The programme team works with local cattle ranchers and law
enforcement agencies developing and implementing protection measures,
as no officially protected area yet exists for this species.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.510157" page_id="56253587"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.478921" genericHeader="method" page_id="56253587" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
PROBABLY ANOTHER FIRST
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.949685777777778" page_id="56253587"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
Raymond Sawyer has succeeded in breeding the Long-toed Lapwing
Vanellus crassirostris. Three eggs were laid of which two hatched and
both chicks were reared. It is believed to be the first time that this African
lapwing has been bred in the UK.
Raymond has added a number of birds to his collection, including some
more Harlequin Ducks Histrionicus histrionicus and has obtained a Victoria
Crowned Pigeon Goura victoria as a mate for his unpaired bird that was
sharing an avairy with the Southern or Scheepmaker's Crowned Pigeon G.
scheepmakeri.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700009" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253588" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995753" page_id="56253588"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
187
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.988087" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56253588" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
TRACKING THE NORTHERN BALD IBIS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.965144222222222" page_id="56253588"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
Eight Critically Endangered Northern Bald Ibis or Waldrapp Geronticus
eremita were hand-reared earlier this year at Chester Zoo. Later they were
transferred to Jerez Zoo in Spain (where this species is also being hand-
reared), prior to being released into the wild in southern Spain. Chester Zoo's
Curator of Birds and Mammals, Mike Jordan, said: "Hand-rearing the birds
is the only way to ensure their successful release into the wild. By doing it
this way, we can show the birds the safest places to live and the best feeding
sites and food once we release them. Every bird released will be fitted with
a radio transmitter so their movements can be tracked."
In 2002, a previously unknown small breeding colony of Northern Bald
Ibis or Waldrapp was discovered in the desert in Syria. Two males and a
female were trapped, ringed (banded) and fitted with satellite transmitters.
These birds later flew south to Yemen, then across the Red Sea to the
highlands of Ethiopia, where they were found along with an unmarked
fourth bird wintering on the shore of a small, remote pond. It was hoped
that others might be found wintering nearby. Mystery still surrounds where
the young birds go between fledging and returning to the colony to breed,
about two years later.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.749209" page_id="56253588"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
* * *
UNUSUAL BREEDINGS
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.983029777777778" page_id="56253588"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
It was reported in Cage &amp; Aviary Birds November 1st 2007, p.5, that
three female Southern Ground Hombills Bucorvus leadbeateri had been
hand-reared and a male chick had been parent-reared at The Wildlife Park
at Cricket St Thomas, Chard, Somerset. The latter is said to be the first
Southern Ground Hombill chick to be parent-reared in the UK. It will
remain at Cricket St Thomas and the three females will be used to establish
new breeding pairs in other collections.
In the issue for December 27th 2007, pp. 14-15, Stephen Dew described
how earlier in the year he had succeeded in breeding the Grey-sided
Laughingthrush Garrulax caerulatus. The pair had lived in his old aviary
for six or seven years, but it was not until he had a new aviary built and the
Grey-sided Laughingthrushes were transferred to it, that the pair started to
build a nest the very next day! The first breeding attempt failed, but after
adding some more dry leaves and making other adjustments to the deep,
cup-shaped nest, the pair made a second attempt. This time the female laid
a clutch of three eggs, which hatched on May 1st. The first chick fledged
on May 18th, followed later by the other two. They were reared on "pinkie
maggots" (greenbottle larvae Lucilia sp.) and mealworms.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998751" page_id="56253589"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
188
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9759545" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253589" page_num="188" year="" vol="">
OBITUARIES
PETER LOWE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970376428571429" page_id="56253589"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
We have belatedly learned of the death of Peter Lowe, who died on June
6th 2007, aged 71. Peter's father was the Rev. Canon J. R. Lowe, who joined
the Avicultural Society in 1927.
Peter appears to have joined the society in 1969, in which year it was
reported that he had been appointed Curator of Newquay Zoo, here in
Cornwall, which hoped to open in June of that yean Richard Meyer recalls
visiting him there and finding him "very charming" and "of the 'old school 5
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.679248" page_id="56253589"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
- polite, courteous, welcoming and humourous." Peter had previously worked
at Chester Zoo and later worked at Cricket St Thomas and in a number of
other collections in the UK and abroad.
</listItem>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.581947" genericHeader="general terms" page_id="56253589" page_num="188" year="" vol="">
LAWRENCE (LEN) CAHILL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.847612217391304" page_id="56253589"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
Another former member who died earlier in the year was Lawrence (Len)
Cahill Len joined the society in 1960, a few years after being appointed
Superintendent of Paignton Zoo, having previously worked at London Zoo.
He later worked at Dudley Zoo, the Department of Zoology, University of
Ife, Ibandan, Nigeria and held a senior post at Toronto Zoo in Canada, before
retiring and moving with his wife to Spain. Avicultural Society Council
Member Jeff Trollope started working at London Zoo in 1949, which is
where he first met Len. He got to know him when they worked together on
the animal rides, when on summer afternoons, after having finished work
on their sections, younger keepers were expected to 'volunteer' for riding
duties - there were not just donkey and pony rides, but a pony carriage,
Llama carts, camel and elephant rides. Len was, Jeff recalls, "that rarity,
a good practical zoologist, with a wide academic knowledge." He left the
zoo in 1958 to further his career. Jeff and his wife Pat, saw Len on several
occasions during visits to Toronto Zoo and Len and his wife Mathilde, visited
them when they returned to the UK to see relatives. They last saw Len and
his wife in the UK on the week-end of the society's visit to Paignton Zoo
in September 2005. It was a final nostalgic visit for Len, recalling the time
when he was Superintendent of Paignton Zoo.
DR KENNETH C. PARKES
Dr Kenneth C. Parkes, who joined the society in 1956, has died. He
joined the Carnegie Museum of Natural History in Pittsburgh in 1953 and
was Curator of Birds from 1965 until 1996, when he retired.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999037" page_id="56253590"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
189
</page>
<table confidence="0.937026375" page_id="56253590"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
Contributors to Volume 113 - 2007
Bamicoat, Fred
On a visit to Chestnut Lodge.........33
Bosco Ferraz, Joao, Schetini de Azevado, Cristiano
and Faggioli, Angela Bemadete
Deterring sinantropic animals:
two bird feeders developed for this purpose at Belo Horizonte Zoo.85
Bruslund Jensen, Simon
Keeping and breeding the Greater Bird of Paradise Paradisaea apoda
at A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation, Qatar and Walsrode Birdpark,
Germany.........22
Bruslund Jensen, Simon, Watson, Ryan and Hammer, Sven
Keeping and hand-rearing Lear's Macaw Anodorhynchus leari
at A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation.....57
Davies, Martin
Breeding the Black-throated Barbet Tricholaema melanocephala ..2
</table>
<figure confidence="0.728530055555556" page_id="56253590"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
Espley, Simon
The Oriole Finch is a strange finch............ 170
Fernandes, Nandita and Hallager, Sara
Sunning behaviour by Kori Bustards Ardeotis kori
at the Smithsonian's National Zoological Park.... 145
Gibson, Derek
Hand-rearing a White-browed Coucal Centropus superciliosus
at Exmoor Zoo ..............166
Goodwin, Derek
The Mistle Thrush's feet, an overlooked adaptation.. 103
Graham, Jamie
The Corncrake Species Recovery Programme......13
Gregson,Jo
Cirl Bunting Emberiza cirlus Reintroduction Project.... 4
Managing the Orange-headed Ground Thrush
Zoothera citrina melli at Paignton Zoo Environmental Park.153
Hall, Sylvia
Farewell.............. 101
</figure>
<page confidence="0.997926" page_id="56253591"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
190
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.948018" page_id="56253591"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
Contributors to Volume 113 - 2007 (cont'd)
He Fen-qui, Lin Jian-sheng, Gardner, Laura, Richardson, Mary,
Wilkinson, Roger
Searches for the Blue-crowned Laughingthrush
Garrulux courtoisi simaoensis in south Yunnan, south-west China.78
Hill, Brian A. G.
Memoir, notes and anthology arising from a visit to Brazil.49
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.956013260869565" page_id="56253591"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
Jerrard, Jim
Mixed fortunes with the Chestnut-backed Thrush Zoothera dohertyi... 156
Jeffreys, Christopher (Lord Jeffreys)
Ruth Muriel Sawyer (nee Ezra) - A Eulogy.......... 99
Marler, Christopher
Ruth Sawyer (nee Ezra) - June 13th 1919-August 21st 2007.................. 97
Meyer, Richard
Mike Reynolds - A Personal Appreciation.. 95
Owen, Andrew
The bird collection at Waddesdon Manor...8
The society's visit to Walsrode Birdpark, Germany..... 177
Piper, Ray
Notes on a visit to Papua New Guinea......73
Pittman, Tony
Omithea 2007 - a show of superlatives.....175
Scott, Colin
Notes on a trip to Sri Lanka.......122
Stevens, Michelle
Husbandry guidelines for hand-rearing
the Pink-backed Pelican Pelecanus rufescens ....... 104
Larsson, Bengt
Breeding the Guianan Toucanet Selenidera culik .. 157
Thurlow, Graham
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.8994172">
Breeding Layard's Black-headed Weaver
Ploceus cucullatus nigriceps ............ 119
Waugh, David, Reinschmidt, Matthias
News on the captive management
of Lear's Macaw Anodorhynchus lean... ...... 40
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998811" page_id="56253592"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
191
</page>
<table confidence="0.9113171875" page_id="56253592"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
Index to Volume 113 \0x25A0 2007
Anodorhynchus lean, captive management............................................. 40
Anodorhynchus leari, keeping and hand-rearing..................................... 57
Ardeotis kori , sunning behaviour........................................................... 145
Barbet, Black-throated, breeding............................................................... 2
Bird of Paradise, Greater, keeping and breeding..................................... 22
Book Reviews
A Century of Parrots............................................................................90
Albatrosses, Petrels and Shearwaters of the World.......................... 136
Birds of Northern South America....................................................... 89
Pekin Robins and Small Softbills... 182
The Meinertzhagen Mystery:
The Life and Legend of a Colossal Fraud........ ......... ...134
The Lapwing..................................................................................... 183
Waterbirds around the world............................................................ 184
Waterfowl Ecology and Management................................................ 44
</table>
<reference confidence="0.708853941176471">
Brazil, memoir, notes and anthology arising from a visit - Part 2........... 49
Bunting, CM, reintroduction project.......................................................... 4
Bustard, Kori, sunning behaviour.......................................................... 145
Centropus superciliosus, hand-rearing at Exmoor Zoo ......................... 166
Corncrake, species recovery programme................................................. 13
Cotingidae, two species bred in Germany ............................................... 38
Coucal, White-browed, hand-rearing at Exmoor Zoo............................ 166
Crex crex , species recovery programme .................................................. 13
End of an era.......................................................................................... 102
Farewell.................................................................................................. 101
Finch, Oriole, keeping and breeding in South Africa............................ 170
Foreign Bird Federation Register of Birds Bred in the UK
under Controlled Conditions for the Years 2002-2005 .......................... 138
Garrulax courtoisi simaoensis, searches for it in south-west China ....... 78
Ground Thrash, Orange-headed, management and breeding ................ 153
Hombills in Thailand - 2006.................................................................. 132
Laughingthrush, Blue-crowned, searches for in south-west China ......... 78
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999018" page_id="56253593"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
192
</page>
<table confidence="0.94257" page_id="56253593"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
Index to Volume 113 - 2007 (cont'd)
Linurgus olivaceus, keeping and breeding in South Africa.. 170
Macaw, Lear's, captive management...... 40
Macaw, Lear's, keeping and hand-rearing................... 57
News &amp; Views.....45,93,140,185
Obituary, Mike Reynolds.....94
Obituaries, Peter Lowe, Lawrence Cahill, Dr Kenneth C. Parkes......... 188
Officers and Council Members, as from September 16th 2006...1
Omithea 2007, annual show in Cologne, Germany.175
Papua New Guinea, notes on a visit to...... 22
Paradisaea apoda , keeping and breeding...........73
Pelecanus rufescens, husbandry guidelines for hand-rearing.104
Pelican, Pink-backed, husbandry guidelines for hand-rearing.. 104
Ploceus cucullatus nigriceps (paroptas ), breeding.......119
Reynolds, Mike, a personal appreciation.......95
Sawyer, Ruth Muriel (nee Ezra) - A Eulogy..........99
Sawyer, Ruth (nee Ezra) - June 13th 1919-August 21st 2007.. 97
Sawyer, Ruth Muriel, President, Avicultural Society - 1986-2007......98
Selendera culik, breeding.. 157
Sinantropic animals, two bird feeders to deter such animals.. 85
Special interest groups, contacts...inside back cover, No.l
Special interest groups, corrections and additions.56
Sri Lanka, notes on a visit to.......... 122
Thrush, Chestnut-backed, mixed fortunes with.......... 156
Thrush, Mistle, feet, an overlooked adaptation.......130
Toucanet, Guianan, breeding..........157
Tricholaema melanocephala , breeding...... 2
Turdus viscivorus , feet, an overlooked adaptation...130
Waddesdon Manor, the bird collection.........8
</table>
<reference confidence="0.5868705">
Walsrode Birdpark, Germany, visit by the society........................ 177
Weaver, Layard's Black-headed, breeding........ 119
Zoothera citrina melli , management and breeding...... 153
Zoothera dohertyi , mixed fortunes with .. 156
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995927" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253594" page_num="" year="" vol="">
LATE HATCHED CHICKS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.982398818181818" page_id="56253594"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
After a pause of several years, Loro Parque has again succeeded in
breeding the Lesser Vasa Parrot Coracopsis nigra , a species which is rarely
bred in captivity. The pair raised a single youngster, which by October had
fledged and was difficult to distinguish from its parents. Other late hatched
chicks included three Chestnut-fronted Macaws Ara severa , some Scarlet
Macaws A. macao and Blue-and-Yellow Macaws A. ararauna , along with
several Blue-throated Macaws A. glaucogularis . A new male Golden-fronted
Parakeet Bolborhynchus aurifrons had been transferred from quarantine to
the breeding station and paired with a female that had been hatched there
and, late in the year, the pair had produced eggs and hatched and reared
two chicks.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.454113142857143" page_id="56253594"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
* * *
DISAPPOINTING RESPONSE
Andrew Owen was rather disappointed by the initial response to the
Special Interest Groups (see Avicultural Magazine Vol.113, No.l, inside
back cover &amp; Vol.113, No.2, p.56 (2007)). In the case of the Special
Interest Groups he is involved with - laughingthrushes Garrulax spp.,
Chestnut-backed Thrush Zoothera dohertyi, Fairy Bluebird Irena puella
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.971396636363636" page_id="56253594"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
and Rufous-bellied Niltava Niltava sundara - Andrew only heard from one
person regarding the Fairy Bluebird and did not hear from any other keepers
of the Chestnut-backed Thrush. He was contacted by a few laughingthrush
keepers and through his own enquiries and word of mouth, succeeded in
locating about 250 laughingthrushes of some 23 species. Quite a lot of
these are kept in large enough numbers, that with good management and
cooperation between keepers, they could be established in captivity. Andrew
is also concerned that a lot of these birds have not been DNA-sexed and
urges everyone with species that are not sexually dimorphic, to get their birds
sexed, as it can save years of frustration and disappointment wondering why
your birds are not breeding.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.602035" page_id="56253594"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.963442" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56253594" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THREAT TO AFRICAN VULTURES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998685714285714" page_id="56253594"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The veterinary drug diclofenac, whose widespread use led to the deaths
of millions of vultures in India, Pakistan, Nepal and other south Asian
countries, has been licensed for use in Tanzania. Since the patent for the drug
expired it has been produced in generic form by hundreds of manufacturers
worldwide and is sold under dozens of different names. The manufacturer
of the brand found in Tanzania exports the drug to 15 African countries. It
is a development that could prove disastrous for African vultures.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997136" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253595" page_num="" year="" vol="">
SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION LIBRARIES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.80551225" page_id="56253595"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENT. 3 9088 01383 2308
Sunning behaviour by Kori Bustards Ardeotis kori
at the Smithsonian's National Zoological Park
by Nandita Fernandes and Sara Hallager.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.772948" page_id="56253595"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
.145
</page>
<figure confidence="0.529879033333333" page_id="56253595"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Managing the Orange-headed Ground Thrush Zoothera citrina melli
at Paignton Zoo Environmental Park
by Jo Gregson.153
Mixed fortunes with the Chestnut-backed Thrush Zoothera dohertyi
by Jim Jerrard.156
Breeding the Guianan Toucanet Selenidera culik
by Bengt Larsson.157
Hand-rearing a White-browed Coucal Centropus superciliosus
at Exmoor Zoo
by Derek Gibson. 166
The Oriole Finch is a strange finch
by Simon Espley.
.170
Omithea 2007 - a show of superlatives
by Tony Pittman.
.175
The society's visit to Walsrode Birdpark, Germany
by Andrew Owen.
.177
Letter to Editor.181
Book Reviews
Pekin Robins and Small Softbills.182
The Lapwing.183
Waterbirds around the world.184
News &amp; Views.185
Obituaries.188
Contributors to Volume 113 - 2007.189
Index to Volume 113 - 2007.191
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</figure>
</algorithms>
