<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.9114344" page_id="56337051"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
oil
A4S1
6lW
AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990762" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337052" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.96460475" page_id="56337052"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2012: British Isles #21.00:
Overseas #24.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the
Society later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of
the AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.687655" page_id="56337052"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, SHERATON LODGE, STATION ROAD, SOUTHMINSTER,
ESSEX CM0 7EW, UK.
</construct>
<bodyText confidence="0.94756275" page_id="56337052"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Barclays Bank, Burnham-on-Crouch Branch. Please
quote Account No. 13296954, Sort Code 20 54 30, and ensure you send your
name as the account reference, or else we cannot match payments. In case
of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and Treasurer at the address
above, or e-mail: otusscops@talktalk.net
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have not
been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of a
particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history. Articles
should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the scientific
names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given. References
cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line drawings,
black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular point in
the article will be used where possible and should be clearly captioned. If
authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when submitting the
article and write their name on the back of each photograph. Tables and
graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be aware of
the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of the page
which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997594" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56337052" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982475333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8121865" genericHeader="method" page_id="56337053" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.312326" page_id="56337053"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 118 - No. 3 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2012
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.85259" genericHeader="method" page_id="56337053" page_num="" year="" vol="">
REARING COUAS AT WELTVOGELPARK WALSRODE
IN GERMANY
by Anne Hoppmann
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996416068965517" page_id="56337053"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Here in Europe we are all acquainted with the Common Cuckoo Cuculus
canorus , a highly migratory species which visits Europe each spring and lays
its eggs in the nests of other species of birds and leaves them to incubate its
eggs and rear its young. What is perhaps less well-known is the fact that
out of the 136 species of Cuckoo (Cuculidae family) only 53 species are
brood parasites (like the Common Cuckoo), the rest build their own nests,
incubate their own eggs and rear their own young.
Among the many non-parasitic cuckoos are the couas. All belong to
the genus Coua and are endemic to the island of Madagascar, where they
inhabit different types of forest. One of the 10 species, the Snail-eating or
Delalande's Coua C. delalandei is extinct, leaving nine existing species: the
Giant Coua C. gigas , Coquerel's Coua C. coquereli , Red-breasted Coua C.
serriana. Red-fronted or Reynaud's Coua C. reynaudii , Red-capped Coua
C. ruficeps , Running Coua C. cursor , Crested Coua C. cristata, Verreaux's
Coua C. verreauxi and Blue Coua C. caerulea.
In 1998, in cooperation with Tsimbazaza Zoo on Madagascar,
Weltvogelpark Walsrode obtained its first species of coua - the Crested Coua.
In 2003, another species the Blue Coua was added to the bird collection at
Walsrode. Then in 2006, the largest living species of coua, the Giant Coua
was added to the collection and visitors can now see three species of couas
at Weltvogelpark Walsrode. All three species have been bred here with
great success for the first time outside of Madagascar. The first success was
achieved in 2000, when young Crested Couas were reared successfully. The
Giant Couas bred successfully after only a year at Walsrode and the Blue
Couas bred for the first time two years after arriving here. Since then they
have produced several young each year.
The Blue Coua lives in habitat with dense vegetation and its lifestyle
remained largely unknown until 2001, when an expedition from
Weltvogelpark Walsrode found nests of this species for the first time. The
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99659" page_id="56337054"  page_num="98" year="" vol="">
98
</page>
<figure confidence="0.744755666666667" page_id="56337054"  page_num="98" year="" vol="">
HOPPMANN - COUAS
Weltvogelpark Walsrode
Adult Crested Coua,
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.586774" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337055" page_num="99" year="" vol="">
HOPPMANN - COUAS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.95596" page_id="56337055"  page_num="99" year="" vol="">
99
</page>
<table confidence="0.867009666666667" page_id="56337055"  page_num="99" year="" vol="">
Adult Blue Coua.
Weltvogelpark Walsrode
Adult Giant Coua.
</table>
<figure confidence="0.9484175" page_id="56337056"  page_num="100" year="" vol="">
100
HOPPMANN - COUAS
Weltvogelpark Walsrode
Showing the different palate and tongue markings of the Blue Coua chick (right) and
Giant Coua chick (left).
_____ t &amp;apos; - L--___--;- \0x25A0\0x25A0\0x25A0\0x25A0\0x25A0.
Weltvogelpark Walsrode
Palate and tongue markings of a Crested Coua chick.
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.61055" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337057" page_num="101" year="" vol="">
HOPPMANN - COUAS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999289" page_id="56337057"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
101
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998600066666666" page_id="56337057"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
natural habitat of Madagascar was and remains degraded through the logging
of large parts of the rainforest. At the moment couas are not threatened
but they are perfect flagship species for the endangered flora and fauna of
Madagascar.
The rearing of couas in captivity is a considerable challenge for couas are
sensitive birds which are susceptible to stress. Thus, the pairing of the birds
is done by experienced members of our staff. In addition, the enclosures
must be heavily planted and equipped with enough branches so that the
birds can hide and avoid each other if need be. Asa general rule they are
not aggressive towards other species of birds.
Last year (2011) we again succeeded in raising young behind the
scenes. Four Blue Couas chicks were hatched and needed to be fed and
cared for throughout the day. The Blue Coua is a very beautiful bird with
magnificently coloured plumage. In addition, the eyes are surrounded by a
striking oval-shaped area of light blue bare skin. The Blue Coua is endemic
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999184" page_id="56337058"  page_num="102" year="" vol="">
102
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.899798" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337058" page_num="102" year="" vol="">
HOPPMANN - COUAS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994712757575757" page_id="56337058"  page_num="102" year="" vol="">
to Madagascar, where it inhabits the subtropical or tropical moist rainforests
in the east and north-west of the island. It is an arboreal species that moves
among the branches of trees and is rarely seen on the ground. The Blue
Coua can be seen in Europe only at Weltvogelpark Walsrode and Koln Zoo,
which received it birds from Walsrode. In contrast to the other species of
couas, the Blue Coua lays only one egg per clutch, whereas the Giant Coua
lays four eggs and the Crested Coua lays two eggs.
Several times we have tried to let the Blue Couas incubate their own
eggs and rear their own young, but have found that the embryos died during
incubation or if the eggs did hatch, the chicks failed to survive. Therefore,
all of the young hatched at Walsrode are hand-reared by our experienced
staff. The eggs are incubated for approximately 14 days. Like the adults,
young couas are also very sensitive and susceptible to stress. During the
first few days the chicks are fed up to eight times a day, beginning early in
the morning and continuing through until late in the evening. They are fed
the innards of day old pinkie mice, pieces of fruit and drone maggots. The
amount of food and its composition is adjusted as the chicks grow bigger,
until they receive the same food as the adults, namely pieces of fruit, meat,
pellets (for fruit-eating birds) and livefood.
After hatching each chick is placed in a small bowl with a layer of
bedding in place of the real nest. It is especially important that the chicks
are not able to spread their legs. We use wood-wool to line the bowl so
that the young have something on which they can get a good grip. Shortly
before fledging at the age of three to four weeks old the chicks are moved
to larger boxes. They are still relatively small and wobbly. They are fully
grown after eight to 10 weeks.
Conspicuous characteristics of all couas are the markings of the palate
and tongue which differ from species to species. In the wild these are used
to frighten off enemies and in addition also encourage the parents to feed the
chicks. With these markings being different and unique to each individual
species, a coua carries its own 'identity card.'
Anne Hoppmann is Bird Registrar at Weltvogelpark Walsrode which this
year is celebrating its 50th Anniversary.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9780115" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337059" page_num="103" year="" vol="">
MIXED FORTUNES FOR SOCIETY'S ADOPTED
HORNBILLS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999679" page_id="56337059"  page_num="103" year="" vol="">
103
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999283" page_id="56337059"  page_num="103" year="" vol="">
In 2011 the society adopted a pair of White-crested Hombills Berenicornis
comatus and a pair of Wreathed Hombills Aceros ( Rhyticeros ) undulatus as
part of the Hombill Family Adoption Program, mn by the Hombill Research
Foundation, based at Mahidol University, Bangkok, Thailand.
The female White-crested Hornbill - the bird in the background with the black neck
and underparts - broke out of the nest cavity on April 4th and did not return. The
cavity had previously been used by a pair of Rhinoceros Hombills.
On March 25th 2011 the female White-crested Hombill began to seal
herself into a cavity 6m (almost 20ft) above the ground in a 60m (approx.
196ft) tall Shorea curtisii. Throughout the period the female was in the nest
cavity, the male brought fruits ( Ficus chartaceae , F. caulocarpo, Artocarpus
rigida and Horsfieldia tomentosa ) to the nest about every 10-15 minutes.
However, the female broke out of the nest cavity on April 4th 2011 for an
unknown reason and did not return. Although we did not know at the time
we chose this pair, it has failed to produce chicks since 2009. The nest
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.8639916">
cavity on Budo Mountain, part of Budo-Sungai Padi National Park, Kapo
District, Pattani Province, Thailand, had previously been used by a pair of
Rhinoceros Hombills Buceros rhinoceros.
Messrs Masuding and Arbus Seeba, who have been field assistants since
1994 and 2007 respectively, are the guardians of the above nest. They
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999703" page_id="56337060"  page_num="104" year="" vol="">
104
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995025" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337060" page_num="104" year="" vol="">
ADOPTED HORNBILLS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986679097560975" page_id="56337060"  page_num="104" year="" vol="">
are responsible for monitoring six Great Hombill B . bicornis nests, three
Rhinoceros Hombill nests, two White-crowned Hombill nests and two
Bushy-crested Hombill Anorrhinus galeritus nests. More than 40 chicks
have fledged from these nests since they have been looking after them.
The pair of Wreathed Hombills fledged a single chick. On April 2nd
2011 the female began to seal herself in a cavity 33m (approx. 108ft) above
the ground in a 46m (approx. 150ft) tall Syzygium sp Of the food brought
to the nest 99.6% consisted of fruits. Three species of fig (Ficus sundaica , F
deltoidea and F benjamina) made up 51.3% of these fruits, while 48,7% were
non-fig species (Dysoxylum macrocarpum, Canthium glabrum , Polyalthia
clavigera and Horsfieldia tomentosa). The remaining 0.4% consisted of
centipedes and millipedes. The length of the nesting period, measured from
the sealing in by the female to the fledging of the chick, was approximately
104 days. Data were collected from April 3rd-July 16th. This pair, which
also nested on Budo Mountain, part of Budo-Sungai Padi National Park,
but in Ruso District, Narathiwat Province, has produced at least nine chicks
since 1999.
The guardian of the above nest is Hawa Kajay, who has been a field
assistant since 1999. He is responsible for three Great Hombill nests, three
Rhinoceros Hombill nests, two Wreathed Hombill nests and a Helmeted
Hombill B. vigil nest. More than 20 chicks have fledged since Hawa, who
also acts as an instmctor for the foundation's education and conservation
programs, has looked after these nests.
During 2011 the six species of hombills on Budo Mountain raised a total
of 16 chicks: six Great Hombill chicks, seven Rhinoceros Hombill chicks,
one Wreathed Hombill chick and two Bushy-crested Hombill chicks. The
White-crested and Helmeted Hombills failed to produce any young.
One hundred and ninety-two nests belonging to six species of hombill
were recorded on Budo Mountain during the period 1994-2011. Twenty
of these nests (10.4%) belonged to Wreathed Hombills and 10 (5.2%) to
the White-crested species. A total of 536 chicks were produced by the six
species, of which 42 (7.8%) were Wreathed Hombill chicks and 11 (2.1%)
were White-crested Hombill chicks.
Pilai Poonswad, Acting President of the Hombill Research Foundation,
has written to thank the society for supporting the Hombill Family Adoption
Program in 2011. Despite incidents of unrest in Thailand's southernmost
provinces and prolonged heavy rain and storms in the south of the country,
the Hombill Family Adoption Program continued, with some interruptions,
and the Hombill Research Foundation is grateful for our support in assisting
to conserve these fascinating birds in Thailand and needs and welcomes our
continued support.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8690905" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337061" page_num="105" year="" vol="">
THE SOUTHERN SCREAMER Chauna torquata
AT PAIGNTON ZOO ENVIRONMENTAL PARK
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999166" page_id="56337061"  page_num="105" year="" vol="">
105
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.986874945945946" page_id="56337061"  page_num="105" year="" vol="">
by Jo Gregson
The three species of screamer (Anhimidae family), which are closely
related to waterfowl, are found in South America. The Northern (Black-
necked) Screamer C. chavaria occurs in northern Colombia and north-
west Venezuela; the Homed Screamer Anhima cornuta , the most widely
distributed of the three, occurs over a large area northern tropical South
America; and the Southern (Crested) Screamer C. torquata occurs from
south-east Peru, northern Bolivia and southern Brazil, southwards to
Paraquay, Umguay and northern Argentina. Their favoured habitats are open
wetlands, flooded fields and marshland. Screamers are good swimmers and
take to deeper water in search of food. They sit high in the water due to
the many air sacs beneath their skin and their very light pneumatic bones.
They are adaptable birds that occasionally visit dry agricultural fields where
they can damage farmers' crops and become pests. Currently there are no
notable conservation issues concerning any of the three species (the Homed
Screamer is considered to be extinct on the island of Trinidad, on which it
formerly bred), however, as with many other species, threats are likely to
occur as wetlands are drained to make way for livestock and crops.
Their small head, large rounded body, long, partly-webbed toes and
rather ungainly appearance may deceive the casual observer into believing
that they are docile. However, they move quickly through the water
when they need to and can fly remarkably high considering their lack of
aerodynamics.
Their diet consists of water vegetation, roots, shoots and green leaves.
They also use this type of vegetation to build their build their nests in
shallow water or at the water's edge. The nests are attended regularly and
built higher each day, thereby, helping to keep them water resistant and
above the water level.
They usually lay four eggs but as many as seven have been recorded.
The chicks are nidifugous and can swim very well from a few days of age.
Most of their time is spent in water often hiding amongst water plants and
never straying too far from their parents until they fledge at about 10 weeks
of age. Screamers are very attentive parents and the chicks rarely leave their
sight. The claw on the bend of each wing may be used to fend off predators
that are threatening them. They also possess a piecing alarm call which can
be heard up to 3km (approx. 1.8 miles) away and often other screamers will
join in to alert other birds to the presence of a skulking hunter.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999127" page_id="56337062"  page_num="106" year="" vol="">
106
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.772735" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337062" page_num="106" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - SOUTHERN SCREAMER
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.548526">
Ray Wiltshire
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.965647" page_id="56337062"  page_num="106" year="" vol="">
Parent and a chick aged just over one week old.
Screamers which have been hand-reared can become imprinted very
easily in the same way that geese do. Some South American poultry keepers
like to have tame screamers running with their flocks of poultry as their alarm
calls are so effective at warning other birds of approaching predators.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.752106" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337063" page_num="107" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - SOUTHERN SCREAMER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99957" page_id="56337063"  page_num="107" year="" vol="">
107
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.982589828571429" page_id="56337063"  page_num="107" year="" vol="">
Here at Paignton Zoo Environmental Park we have a pair of Southern
Screamers. The two 2006-hatched birds made their first breeding attempt in
2010. Caution is needed when pairing screamers, as males can bully females
if they are housed in a small enclosure. Our birds were housed in adjacent
aviaries for a few weeks before being placed together.
Screamers spend a lot of time on the ground but also like to sit in trees
and on top of bushes watching over their family. For this reason our birds are
kept full-winged in a large netted aviary. Screamers can still fly high even
when they have had one wing clipped and those kept on open paddocks need
to be routinely checked to see how quickly the new feathers are growing.
Nest building begins about April and continues through May, therefore,
we supply our screamers with green vegetation and dry straw and grasses
towards the end of April. Due to the rainfall at this time of the year, dry
material is offered each day.
There is a long incubation period which lasts about 45 days, with both
birds taking turns to incubate the eggs. Once the chicks have hatched the
nest may be dismantled and rebuilt a short distance away, then a few days
later it will be moved back to the first site. Both parents brood the chicks
and have no fear of the zoo visitors and make excellent exhibits which show
how birds care for their young.
The diet fed to our adult birds is very simple. It consists of large quantities
of lettuce, grated carrots and apples and chopped cabbage. The food is dusted
with the vitamin/mineral supplement Vionate. They also graze on grass
and other vegetation. When the chicks hatch we add mealworms and chick
crumbs to the diet. After being guided by both parents for a few days the
chicks learn very quickly which items of food to select. The family group
live and forage together until the next breeding season, when the male begins
to drive the young birds away.
In the wild screamers form large wintering flocks which can contain
hundreds of birds. The loud alarm call of the screamer helps to keep the
birds safe during the winter months. Farmers and hunters in some areas
shoot screamers, but they are rarely eaten as their spongy flesh and network
of air sacs makes their flesh unsavory and therefore not a popular choice
for the dinner table.
Jo Gregson is Curator of Birds at Paignton Zoo Environmental Park,
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.9801988">
Totnes Road, Paignton, Devon TQ4 7EU, UK. She is Vice Chair of the EAZA
(European Association of Zoos and Aquaria) Ratites TAG (Taxon Advisory
Group) and Vice Chair of the EAZA Pigeons and Doves TA G, as well as EEP
(European Breeding Programme) Coordinator for the Wrinkled Hornhill
Aceros corrugatus. E-mail:jo.gregson@paigntonzoo.org.uk
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999572" page_id="56337064"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
108
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.991765" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337064" page_num="108" year="" vol="">
RELEASING MACAWS IN COSTA RICA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993050717948718" page_id="56337064"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
by Bryan Andrews
I am privileged to be both living and working in a Costa Rican rainforest
tucked in against the Panamanian border and continue to feel wonderment at
the biodiversity which surrounds us and have no idea just how much animal
and plant life we are looking at. The figures given by La Selva Biological
Station for this area of Costa Rica include 1,668 species from 121 families
of vascular plants including trees, shrubs, herbs, epiphytes and lianas, but
excluding introduced species; these are what we see when we look for an
equally diverse group of mammals, birds, amphibians and insects. There is
nothing, absolutely nothing, which compares with being in a tropical lush
evergreen rainforest and yet the indigenous people and long-term residents
of the areas in which these forests exist are, due to the advent of ecotourism,
excluded from these very forests by virtue of the ever increasing entrance
fees to the national parks and the unbelievably high costs of staying at the
privately owned ecotourist lodges. If, and it is a big if, some of the income
generated were to be fed back into genuine conservation research, not only
that undertaken by scientists from the temperate zones but also by students
of the two fine universities in Costa Rica, then a better and more justified
use of at least part of the income derived would have been found. Of even
greater help long-term would be an environmental educational programme
for local school pupils from the age of eight, to help build-up their pride in
the conservation of the fauna and flora around them.
Although the above is of great concern to me, it is the reintroduction of
the Scarlet Macaw Ara macao into the area in which I live, that has enabled
me to fuel my passion for birds. This emblematic species was abundant in
this area of Costa Rica bordering the Pacific Ocean until the mid-1950s. It
was during this period that fragmentation of the rainforests occurred as a
result of the need for pasture to accommodate the production of beef cattle
to satisfy the stomachs of North America, leaving just 20% of original forest
cover, which coupled with increased poaching for the pet trade reduced the
number of macaws in this region to nil.
While the concept of reintroducing captive-bred birds will remain
controversial, my belief is that to stand back and do nothing is far more of
a sin. We now have enough knowledge to overcome the arguments against
reintroductions and thereby stem the dwindling numbers of parrots. During
the past 20 years, aviculturists have with varying degrees of sophistication
managed to perfect the breeding of both the Scarlet Macaw and the Great
Green Macaw A. ambignus. It is this coupled with well documented field
studies which have enabled the project that I have been with for the past
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.80208" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337065" page_num="109" year="" vol="">
ANDREWS - RELEASING MACAWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999498" page_id="56337065"  page_num="109" year="" vol="">
109
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.992459414634146" page_id="56337065"  page_num="109" year="" vol="">
three years to begin in 2002 a programme of releasing small groups of
Scarlet Macaws at approximately three-and-half years of age. These birds
are bred and reared at a complex in the Central Valley of Costa Rica, where
a large captive population is kept containing enough individual bloodlines
to ensure as greater genetic diversity as possible. None of the birds at the
centre were taken directly from the wild, thereby impairing the conservation
of the wild stock, but were accumulated via customs officials and the police,
who handed them over to what was once a privately owned bird sanctuary
started 26 years ago. The collection grew and developed and 12 years ago
turned into a project, the aim of which is the reintroduction into the wild of
the captive-bred progeny. To date (April 2012) a total of 74 Scarlet Macaws
have been released, all of whom were photographed prior to release and their
unique pattern of yellow wing feathers recorded, in addition to which each
was fitted with a closed ring (band) with an individual number. This makes it
relatively easy to visually monitor the birds. They are identified by a process
of elimination, depending on whether they have a ring (band) on the left or
right leg, whether it is a flat or round type and then if the number cannot
be read through binoculars, we resort to checking the aformentioned wing
patterns. Birds without a ring (band) are whenever possible photographed
and recorded as having been hatched in the wild during the previous three
years, as the earlier released adults become sexually mature. Due to the
young hanging about with the parents for as long as 18 months it is often
possible to identify which young belong to which parents. However, it is
all too easy to become bogged down describing the various methods used
to monitor the birds, suffice to say that a pair of legs, some binoculars and
the patience of a saint are all that are required. Any spare time is spent
wondering why we cannot see a brilliant red and yellow bird 86cm (approx.
2ft lOin) in length, with a wingspan of 115cm (approx. 3ft 9in), probably
sitting in a tree right in front of us.
To ensure the well-being of the birds, they undergo a series of regular
health checks, which are carried out at the same time as they are routinely
wormed at the breeding centre. Further checks are made prior to the birds
being moved to the release site, with blood samples being taken under
veterinarian supervision. A strict protocol has to be followed to comply
with the rules of Minae the government body in Costa Rica which deals
with all environmental issues and is responsible for the granting of all the
licences that are required before any releases can even be contemplated.
The rules include making available to its office completed records for each
and every bird at the breeding centre, showing where they originated from,
all subsequent movements within the centre and, should they die, this must
be documented and a post mortem report included along with the complete
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997602" page_id="56337066"  page_num="110" year="" vol="">
110
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.967241" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337066" page_num="110" year="" vol="">
ANDREWS - RELEASING MACAWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998638952380952" page_id="56337066"  page_num="110" year="" vol="">
The release cage is at the top right-hand side of the aviary above the safety porch.
medical history of the bird, etc; moreover, this all has to be translated into
Espanol.
Photographs show the release aviary being built. Each of the steel
panels weigh 90kg (almost 200lbs) and have to be transported into the
primary rainforest at an altitude of 1,600ft (approx. 490m). Upon being
assembled the sections are sunk approximately 20cm (8in) into the ground
and corrugated sheeting is needed to deter snakes from entering the aviary,
which was a problem encountered with the previous aviary, which had a
wooden framework. Before being replaced by the present aviary, the latter
had been used for seven releases and had seen over 60 macaws take to the
skies before a bad storm brought some of the surrounding trees crashing
down on top of it and damaging it beyond repair. Fortunately, there were
no birds housed in it at the time.
The expensive new aviary has been designed in such a way that it can
be dismantled relatively easily and moved to a new site. This will enable
it to be used for the release of another group of Scarlet Macaws at a site
in the north-west of Costa Rica. This is again a region which no longer
supports a wild population, but thanks to a large reforestation project and the
cooperation of the farming community in the surrounding area it has become
possible to reintroduce some more of these stunning birds back into the wild
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.802084" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337067" page_num="111" year="" vol="">
ANDREWS - RELEASING MACAWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999521" page_id="56337067"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
111
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9955925" page_id="56337067"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
The author being filmed by Canamedia for a Canadian production on macaw
conservation.
The aviary prior to having part of the roof thatched with palm leaves and the sides
snake-proofed.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999108" page_id="56337068"  page_num="112" year="" vol="">
112
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.967308" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337068" page_num="112" year="" vol="">
ANDREWS - RELEASING MACAWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999141121951219" page_id="56337068"  page_num="112" year="" vol="">
where they belong. To anyone who doubts whether the effort is worth it, I
would ask, what is the alternative? The reforestation of large areas of land
is, of course, the long-term answer, but the simple maths show that the wild
population will increase only if more than two young hatched by each pair
survive and they too reproduce, less than this and we are only delaying the
end of yet another species.
Each group of macaws remains there for approximately two months prior
to release until they are weaned onto the fruits and nuts of the surrounding
area, a procedure which follows a standard soft release protocol and ensures
that the birds are ready for life in the wild. The largest proportion of their
diet consists of Guavas Psidium guayava and Beach Almonds Terminalia
cotappa , both of which are abundant within a 10km (approx. 6 mile) radius of
the release site, with the almond trees forming a coastal corridor northwards
and thereby assisting the dispersal of the birds from the release site and
providing them with a natural fly route.
It is the ongoing dispersal of this reintroduced population which interests
me now and which I am recording, as the 2011 release was the final release
in this region for, barring mishaps, the population has now reached a self-
sustaining level. The monitoring will continue, using visual identification to
better understand and map the movement patterns of the birds. The use of
radio telemetry has been deemed to be too invasive and beyond the finances
of the project. At the time of writing (April 2012) adult macaws can be seen
flying with their newly-fledged young and overhead I can hear the deafening
screeches which announce a flypast by groups of juvenile macaws behaving
badly and reminding me of football hooligans.
It is to be hoped that the number of trees suitable as nest sites can be
maintained because the felling of such trees in this region would again send
this species into decline. My own research shows that the Scarlet Macaw is
not easily seduced into using a nest box, unlike some other species which
use them to good effect.
Last year saw the first release of captive-bred Great Green (Buffon's)
Macaws, a species with a courtship display unlike any other macaw, in
which the male gives an incredibly loud shriek of a call, clasps the perch
with both feet and performs a figure-of-eight motion. Although the breeding
and rearing of these birds was undertaken by the same team responsible for
breeding the Scarlet Macaws, the release took place on the Caribbean side of
southern Costa Rica, again in an area from which the species was extirated in
the 1950s. It is in the north-eastern comer of Costa Rica, tucked up against
the border with Nicaragua, that a large stable wild population still exists.
As with the Scarlet Macaw, the availability of suitable nest trees will be
a key part of the long-term success of the reintroduction programme, with
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.802081" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337069" page_num="113" year="" vol="">
ANDREWS - RELEASING MACAWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999554" page_id="56337069"  page_num="113" year="" vol="">
113
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.925796611111111" page_id="56337069"  page_num="113" year="" vol="">
an immediate threat being the continued logging of Dipteryx panamensis, a
species of tree which is critical both for providing food and suitable nesting
cavities. Without the enforcement of already existing laws the effort put
into this and other breeding projects will have been in vain.
Only time will tell if the ever increasing pressure which ecotourism puts
on the environment can itself be monitored to ensure that as little harm as
possible is done to these regions in which work to restore and conserve the
fauna and flora is needed and is being undertaken at present. Sadly, as is
often the case, the majority of hotels, restaurants and other businesses which
cater for the tourist industry are owned by foreigners and it is difficult for
the local population where I live to get their heads around the idea that via
the conservation of what they have, they will benefit from ecotourism.
Bryan s previous articles for the magazine were about breeding the
Elegant Crested Tinamou Eudromia e. elegans and the UKfirst breeding of
the White-headed Mousebird Colius leucocephalus (Vol. 112, No. 3, pp. lll-
ll 5 &amp; 116-118 respectively (2006)). If you would like to know more about
the macaw releases in Costa Rica, Bryan can be contacted at the following
e-mail address: lfreelapa@gmail.com
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.833292" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56337069" page_num="113" year="" vol="">
IMPORTANT NOTICE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993479866666667" page_id="56337069"  page_num="113" year="" vol="">
Will members please note that their subscription for 2013 will become
due on January 1st. Please also note that the Avicultural Society account is
now at Barclays Bank. As the NatWest account has been closed, all future
standing orders, subscriptions and other payments should be made to Barclays
Bank, Bumham-on-Crouch Branch. Please quote: Account No. 13296954,
Sort Code 20 54 30. Please ensure that you include your name as the account
reference otherwise we cannot match payments. In case of difficulty please
contact the Hon. Secretary and Treasurer whose details can be found on the
inside front cover of the magazine.
Those who prefer to pay their subscription in US dollars can again send
a check or money order, US$40.00 for receiving the magazine by regular
mail or US$50.00 by air mail, to The Avicultural Society, c/o Jane Cooper,
12650 Hearst Road, Willits, California 95490-9231, USA. All checks and
money orders should be payable to The Avicultural Society.
All members can now, if they wish, pay their subscription by Paypal.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999711" page_id="56337070"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
114
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.974687" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337070" page_num="114" year="" vol="">
NATIVE PASSERINES IN NORTH AMERICAN ZOOS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.939634833333333" page_id="56337070"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
by Justin C. Hickman
I have compiled the following list of North American passerines housed
in North American institutions. It is organised by family and was compiled
using the International Species Information System (ISIS) - Species holding
database.
The four largest North American passerine collections are those at
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.886078787878788" page_id="56337070"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
Cove Forest at River Journey, Tennessee Aquarium; the North American
Migratory Songbird Aviary, Columbus Zoo, Ohio; the Laurentian Maple
Forest, Biodome de Montreal, Quebec, Canada; North Carolina Zoo, North
Carolina.
Passerines
Tyrant Flycatchers (Family Tyrannidae)
Eastern Phoebe Sayornis phoebe
Tennessee Aquarium Queens Zoo
Scissor-tailed Flycatcher Tyrannus forficatus
Oklahoma City Zoo Tulsa Zoo and Living Museum
Western Kingbird Tyrannus verticalis
Abilene Zoological Gardens
Eastern Kingbird Tyrannus tyrannus
Toledo Zoo Turtle Back Zoo
Great Crested Flycatcher Myiarchus crinitus
Tennessee Aquarium Oklahoma City Zoo
Shrikes (Family Laniidae)
Loggerhead Shrike Lanius ludovicianus
Bronx Zoo Toronto Zoo
Smithsonian Conservation Biology Institute
Vireos (Family Vireonidae)
Red-eyed Vireo Vireo olivaceus
North Carolina Zoo Tennessee Aquarium
Crows, Jays and Magpies (Family Corvidae)
Blue Jay Cyanocitta cristata
Audubon Aquarium of the Americas Oklahoma City Zoo
North Carolina Zoo Point Defiance Zoo &amp; Aquarium
Birmingham Zoo Living Desert State Park
Virginia Aquarium &amp; Marine Science Center Abilene Zoological Gardens
Dallas Zoo Assiniboine Park Zoo
Steller's Jay Cyanocitta stelleri
Arizona-Sonora Desert Museum Oregon Zoo
Moonridge Animal Park Assiniboine Park Zoo
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.745881" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337071" page_num="115" year="" vol="">
HICKMAN - NORTH AMERICAN PASSERINES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.961456" page_id="56337071"  page_num="115" year="" vol="">
115
</page>
<figure confidence="0.979144519480519" page_id="56337071"  page_num="115" year="" vol="">
Pinyon Jay Gymnorhinus cyanocephalus
Phoenix Zoo
Green Jay Cyanocorax yncas
Abilene Zoological Gardens
Houston Zoo
Audubon Zoo
Zoo Miami
Yellow-billed Magpie Pica nuttalli
Coyote Point Museum
Sacramento Zoo
Los Angeles Zoo Chahinkapa Zoo
Black-billed Magpie Pica hudsonia
Binghamton Zoo at Ross Park Bronx Zoo
Bronx Children's Zoo
ZooAmerica
Cleveland Metroparks Zoo
Utah's Hogle Zoo
Kansas City Zoo
San Diego Zoo
SD-WAP
Woodland Park Zoo
Toronto Zoo
Fish Crow Corvus ossifragus
Capron Park Zoo
Bronx Children's Zoo
Bronx Zoo
Central Florida Zoological Park
Brookgreen Gardens
American Crow Corvus brachyrhynchos
Akron Zoological Park Nashville Zoo
North Carolina Zoo
Audubon Zoo
Moonridge Animal Park
Binghamton Zoo
Chattanooga Zoo
Brevard Zoo
Boonshoft Museum of Discovery
Palm Beach Zoo at Dreher Park
Erie Zoological Gardens
ZooAmerica
Houston Zoo
Hutchinson Zoo
John Ball Park
Knoxville Zoo
Henry Vilas Zoo
Sunset Zoo
Orange County Zoo
Bergen County Zoological Park
National Aviary
Project Wildlife
Children's Zoo at Celebration Square
San Francisco Zoological Gardens
Happy Hollow Zoo
Riverside Discovery Center
Silver Spring Park
St Louis Zoo
Tracy Aviary
Tulsa Zoo and Living Museum
Virginia Aquarium &amp; Marine Science Center
Virginia Living Museum
Valley Zoo
Turtle Back Zoo
Magnetic Hill Zoo NY State Zoo
Chihuahuan Raven Corvus cryptoleucus
Abilene Zoological Gardens Pueblo Zoo
Arizona-Sonora Desert Museum
Albuquerque Biological Park
Raven Corvus corax
Greater Vancouver Zoo
Potter Park Zoological Gardens
America's Teaching Park
Buttonwood Park Zoo
Connecticut's Beardsley Zoo
Maryland Zoo
Bowmanville Zoological Park
Knoxville Zoo
NZP-WASH
</figure>
<page confidence="0.997851" page_id="56337072"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
116
</page>
<figure confidence="0.49125801754386" page_id="56337072"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
HICKMAN - NORTH AMERICAN PASSERINES
Caldwell Zoo
Living Desert State Park
Chehaw Wild Animal Park
Chicago Zoological Society
Cheyenne Mountain Zoological Park
Coyote Point Museum
Sequoia Park Zoo
Fort Worth Zoo
Zoo America
Utah's Hogle Zoo
Houston Zoo
Indianapolis Zoo
The Living Desert Zoo
Philadelphia Zoo
Phoenix Zoo
Project Wildlife
Roger William Park Zoo
Santa Barbara Zoological Gardens
Point Defiance Zoo and Aquarium
Florida Aquarium
Turtle Back Zoo
NY State Zoo
Natural History Museum of Adirondacks
Willow Park Zoo
Larks (Family Alaudidae)
Homed Lark (Shore Lark) Eremophila alpestris
North Carolina Zoo
Swallows (Family Hirundinidae)
Cliff Swallow Petrochelidon pyrrhonota
Project Wildlife
Titmice (Family Paridae)
Tufted Titmouse Baeolophus bicolor
Tennessee Aquarium South Carolina Zoo
Columbus Zoo and Aquarium Virginia Aquarium &amp; Marine Science Center
Carolina Chickadee Poecile carolinensis
Tennessee Aquarium Columbus Zoo and Aquarium
Verdin (Family Remizidae)
Verdin Auriparus flaviceps
Arizona-Sonora Desert Museum
Nuthatches (Family Sittidae)
White-breasted Nuthatch Sitta carolinensis
Tennessee Aquarium Minnesota Zoological Garden
Wrens (Family Troglodytes)
House Wren Troglodytes aedon
Tennessee Aquarium
Carolina Wren Thryothorus ludovicianus
Virginia Aquarium &amp; Marine Science Center
Cactus Wren Campylorhynchus brunneicapillus
Arizona-Sonora Desert Museum
Thrushes (Family Turdidae)
Eastern Bluebird Sialia sialis
Tennessee Aquarium Minnesota Zoological Garden
Columbus Zoo and Aquarium South Carolina Aquarium
Cosley Zoo St Louis Zoo
Houston Zoo Toronto Zoo
Hutchinson Zoo
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.764157" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337073" page_num="117" year="" vol="">
HICKMAN - NORTH AMERICAN PASSERINES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.993212" page_id="56337073"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
117
</page>
<table confidence="0.970302" page_id="56337073"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
Western Bluebird Sialia mexicana
Tracy Aviary
Mountain Bluebird Sialia currucoides
Denver Zoo
Wood Thrush Hylocichla mustelina
Tennessee Aquarium
Swainson's Thrush Catharus ustulatus
Tennessee Aquarium Columbus Zoo and Aquarium
Hermit Thrush Catharus guttatus
Arizona-Sonora Desert Museum North Carolina Zoo
Biodome de Montreal Tennessee Aquarium
Cosley Zoo
American Robin Turdus migratorius
Abilene Zoological Gardens Knoxville Zoo
Columbus Zoo and Aquarium NY Bronx
Cosley Zoo National Aviary
Coyote Point Museum South Carolina Aquarium
Dallas Zoo Florida Aquarium
Queens Zoo Toledo Zoo
Fort Worth Zoo
Mockingbirds, Thrashers (Family Mimidae)
Grey Catbird Dumetella carolinensis
Biodome de Montreal Tennessee Aquarium
South Carolina Aquarium Columbus Zoo and Aquarium
Florida Aquarium Boonshoft Museum of Discovery
Virginia Aquarium &amp; Museum Center Queens Zoo
Knoxville Zoo Virginia Living Museum
Northern Mockingbird Mimus polyglottos
El Paso Zoo
Fort Worth Zoo
Oklahoma City Zoological Park
The Living Desert
Tracy Aviary
Brown Thrasher Toxostoma rufum
Tennessee Aquarium
Oklahoma Living Museum
Virginia Living Museum
Curve-billed Thrasher Toxostoma curvirostre
Arizona-Sonora Desert Museum
Chicago Zoological Society
Living Desert State Park
The Living Desert
California Thrasher Toxostoma redivivum
</table>
<figure confidence="0.693756444444444" page_id="56337073"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
Coyote Point Museum
Waxwings (Family Bombycillidae)
Cedar Waxwing Bombycilla cedrorum
Biodome de Montreal
Tennessee Aquarium
Columbus Zoo and Aquarium
Knoxville Zoo
Minnesota Zoological Park
Philadelphia Zoo
</figure>
<page confidence="0.990005" page_id="56337074"  page_num="118" year="" vol="">
118
</page>
<figure confidence="0.971442833333333" page_id="56337074"  page_num="118" year="" vol="">
HICKMAN - NORTH AMERICAN PASSERINES
Coyote Point Museum
Sequoia Park Zoo
Fort Worth Zoo
Tulsa Zoo and Living Museum
Assiniboine Zoo
Bronx Children Zoo
New World Warblers (Family Parulidae)
Tennessee Warbler Vermivora peregrina
Columbus Zoo and Aquarium
Chestnut-sided Warbler Dendroica pensylvanica
Biodome de Montreal
Black-throated Blue Warbler Dendroica caerulescens
Biodome de Montreal Tennessee Aquarium
Yellow-ramped Warbler Dendroica coronata
North Carolina Zoo Columbus Zoo and Aquarium
Biodome de Monteal Virginia Aquarium &amp; Marine Science Center
Tennessee Aquarium
Magnolia Warbler Dendroica magnolia
Tennessee Aquarium
Palm Warbler Dendroica palmarum
Columbus Zoo and Aquarium
Yellow Warbler Dendroica petechia
Tracy Aviary
Pine Warbler Dendroica pinus
Tennessee Aquarium
Wilson's Warbler Wilsonia pusilla
Columbus Zoo and Aquarium
Ovenbird Seiurus aurocapillus
Tennessee Aquarium Columbus Zoo and Aquarium
Common Yellowthroat Geothlypis trichas
Biodome de Montreal South Carolina Aquarium
Tennessee Aquarium
Yellow-breasted Chat Icteria virens
Tennessee Aquarium
American Redstart Setophaga ruticilla
Biodome de Montreal
Tanagers (Family Thraupidae)
Summer Tanager Piranga rubra
North Carolina Zoo
Tulsa Zoo and Living Museum
Scarlet Tanager Piranga olivacea
Tennessee Aquarium
National Aquarium
Western Tanager Piranga ludoviciana
Arizona-Sonora Desert Museum
Coyote Point Museum
Reid Park Zoo
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.767102" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337075" page_num="119" year="" vol="">
HICKMAN - NORTH AMERICAN PASSERINES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997816" page_id="56337075"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
119
</page>
<table confidence="0.926388733333333" page_id="56337075"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
Towhees, Sparrows and Juncos (Family Emberizidae)
Abert's Towhee Pipilo aberti
North Carolina Zoo
Eastern Towhee Pipilo erythrophthalmus
Knoxville Zoo
South Carolina Aquarium
Tennessee Aquarium
Columbus Zoo and Aquarium
Brown Towhee Pipilo fuscus
Omaha's Henry Doorly Zoo
Chipping Sparrow Spizella passerina
Tennessee Aquarium
Fox Sparrow Passerella iliaca
Columbus Zoo and Aquarium
Song Sparrow Melospiza melodia
Tennessee Aquarium Queens Zoo
Columbus Zoo and Aquarium Minnesota Zoological Park
Harris' Sparrow Zonotrichia querula
Columbus Zoo and Aquarium
White-crowned Sparrow Zonotrichia leucophrys
Abilene Zoological Park Coyote Point Museum
White-throated Sparrow Zonotrichia albicollis
Biodome de Montreal Columbus Zoo and Aquarium
Tulsa Zoo and Living Museum Queens Zoo
Slate-colored Junco Junco hyemalis
Tennessee Aquarium Turtle Back Zoo
Columbus Zoo and Aquarium Queens Zoo
Virginia Aquarium &amp; Marine Science Center
Cardinals, Grosbeaks and Buntings (Family Cardinalidae)
Northern Cardinal Cardinalis cardinalis
Audubon Aquarium of the Americas Utah's Hogle Zoo
North Carolina Zoo Houston Zoo
Central Park Tennessee Aquarium
South Carolina Aquarium Chicago Zoological Society
Toledo Zoo Columbus Zoo and Aquarium
Virginia Aquarium &amp; Marine Science Center Cosley Zoo
Buttonwood Park Zoo Queens Zoo
Abilene Zoological Gardens Oklahoma City Zoo
Pyrrhuloxia Cardinalis sinuatus
Arizona-Sonora Desert Museum Living Desert State Park
North Carolina Zoo
Black-headed Grosbeak Pheucticus melanocephalus
Arizona-Sonora Desert Museum Tracy Aviary
Sequoia Park Zoo
The Living Desert
</table>
<page confidence="0.931404" page_id="56337076"  page_num="120" year="" vol="">
120
</page>
<table confidence="0.94628306060606" page_id="56337076"  page_num="120" year="" vol="">
HICKMAN - NORTH AMERICAN PASSERINES
Rose-breasted Grosbeak Pheucticus ludovicianus
Akron Zoological Park Minnesota Zoological Park
Biodome de Montreal Montgomery Zoo
Tennessee Aquarium Assiniboine Park Zoo
Columbus Zoo and Aquarium Tulsa Zoo and Living Museum
Knoxville Zoo
Indigo Bunting Passerina cyanea
Tennessee Aquarium Columbus Zoo and Aquarium
Painted Bunting Passerina ciris
Fort Worth Zoo The Living Desert
New World Blackbirds, Grackles and Orioles, etc. (Family Icteridae)
Eastern Meadowlark Sturnella magna
Columbus Zoo and Aquarium
Western Meadowlark Sturnella neglecta
Denver Zoo
Red-winged Blackbird Agelaius phoeniceus
Columbus Zoo and Aquarium Tracy Aviary
Florida Aquarium
Common Grackle Quiscalus quiscula
Akron Zoological Park Queens Zoo
Central Park National Aviary
Boat-tailed Grackle Quiscalus major
Palm Beach Zoo
Great-tailed Grackle Quiscalus mexicanus
Arizona-Sonora Desert Museum The Living Desert
Brewer's Blackbird Euphagus cyanocephalus
Tracy Aviary
Brown-headed Cowbird Molothrus ater
Columbus Zoo and Aquarium
Hooded Oriole Icterus cucullatus
Omaha's Henry Doorly Zoological Gardens
Northern Oriole Icterus galbula
</table>
<figure confidence="0.6344146" page_id="56337076"  page_num="120" year="" vol="">
Biodome de Montreal
Birmingham Zoo
Cosley Zoo
Fort Worth Zoo
Orchard Oriole Icterus spurius
Tennessee Aquarium
Scott's Oriole Icterus parisorum
Omaha's Henry Doorly Zoological Gardens
Spot-breasted Oriole Icterus pectoralis
MetroZoo
Minnesota Zoological Park
Florida Aquarium
Toledo Zoo
Assiniboine Park Zoo
National Aviary
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.758555" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337077" page_num="121" year="" vol="">
HICKMAN - NORTH AMERICAN PASSERINES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.982547" page_id="56337077"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
121
</page>
<table confidence="0.888716153846154" page_id="56337077"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
Finches (Family Fringillidae)
Purple Finch Carpodacus purpureus
National Aviary
Cassin's Finch Carpodacus cassinii
Tracy Aviary
Pine Grosbeak Pinicola enucleator
Calgary Zoo
Pine Siskin Carduelis pinus
Biodome de Montreal
Lesser Goldfinch Carduelis psaltria
North Carolina Zoo Tracy Aviary
American Goldfinch Carduelis tristis
Biodome de Montreal Columbus Zoo and Aquarium
Calgary Zoo Toledo Zoo
Tennessee Aquarium Virginia Aquarium &amp; Marine Science Center
House Finch Carpodacus mexicanus
North Carolina Zoo
Coyote Point Museum
Fort Worth Zoo
Utah's Hogle Zoo
The Living Desert
Evening Grosbeak Coccothraustes vespertinus
Columbus Zoo and Aquarium El Paso Zoo
References
International Species Information System (ISIS). Species holding [Database]. Retrieved 2011
from:http://www.isis.org/Pages/findanimals.aspx
</table>
<reference confidence="0.8202025">
J. Cody Hickman, North American Bird Keeper, Silver-beaked Tanager
Program Leader, Snowy Owl Program Leader, Tulsa Zoo and Living
Museum, 5701 E. 36th Street North, Tulsa, OK 74115, USA. Website:www.
tulsazoo. org/E-mail:jhickman@tulsazoo. org
</reference>
<figure confidence="0.7676465" page_id="56337077"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
Phoenix Zoo
Project WILDs
Toledo Zoo
Turtle Back Zoo
</figure>
<page confidence="0.999269" page_id="56337078"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
122
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.995926333333333" page_id="56337078"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
The following reminiscences were published originally in Foreign Birds
in 2007 - 2009. Bernard hadjust passed his fiftieth consecutive year in active
aviculture and, in that time had met and, in many cases, become longstanding
friends with many of the luminaries and great characters of the period and
in these reminiscences recalls some of the events and individuals that left
lasting impressions on him.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9794845" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337078" page_num="122" year="" vol="">
HAVING BEEN AN AVICULTURIST
FOR FIFTY YEARS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.924790333333334" page_id="56337078"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
Part 1
by Bernard Sayers
My parents were always somewhat puzzled, not to say distraught, by my
deep interest in natural history because no other member of the family had
the slightest interest in it. Indeed my father seemed to provoke a violent
response from the meekest of creatures and I frequently warned him against
becoming a lion tamer because I doubted he would survive to his first coffee
break. My mother had an antipathy to anything with fur or feathers and
could touch neither and my sister regarded all animals as being smelly and
noisy. It was therefore fortunate indeed that a local butcher and his wife,
Cliff and Win Palmer, took me under their wings. This delightful couple
had no children of their own and became like second parents to me. Even
better Cliff owned a car, which was something of a rarity in those days and
enabled us to visit collections of interest.
When I met Cliff and Win they bred exhibition budgerigars and also
bred and trained German Shepherd dogs. Cliff never lost interest in his
budgerigars, but under my influence we started to keep and breed pheasants.
Cliff converted some of his dog runs into pheasant pens and built another
row of pens on the opposite side of his large garden. I, in turn, worked
during the school holidays and at weekends to earn enough money to build
as many pens as my parents would (under protest) allow me to have in the
garden of our home in Chelmsford.
The range of species available had been sadly depleted during the Second
World War and up until that time very little new stock had been imported.
Our first acquisition, like that of so many pheasant breeders, was a pair of
Golden Pheasants Chrysolophus pictus. The pair was bought from local
farmer, Alf Ashby, who became a good friend. Alf farmed at Smallands
Hall, which although only a few miles (kilometres) from Chelmsford, was
surprisingly isolated. Indeed from Alf's farm hardly any other houses were
visible. This enabled Alf to keep and breed many species at liberty. He had
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.389594" page_id="56337079"  page_num="123" year="" vol="">
SAYERS - 50 YEARS AN AVICULTURIST
</construct>
<page confidence="0.999318" page_id="56337079"  page_num="123" year="" vol="">
123
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998441512195122" page_id="56337079"  page_num="123" year="" vol="">
free-flying Ravens Corvus corax , African Grey Parrots Psittacus erithacus ,
peafowl Pavo sp. and a homing flock of Quaker (Monk) Parakeets Myiopsitta
monachus which returned to their aviary each evening, after spending the
day foraging around Alf's stack yard and orchard. Alf was though a real
countryman and his main interest was in keeping British and European
species. He had a huge aviary and several smaller aviaries stocked with
some wonderful finches and softbills. There were also a few other aviaries
for owls, kestrels and crows.
The Golden Pheasants had been parent-reared in the very big aviary and
were just moulting into adult plumage. Alf caught and boxed a female and
then caught a male which he stood holding whilst he had a long conversation
with us. Pheasants always shed feathers easily and even more so during
the moult. As he talked Alf kept stroking the cock pheasant and each time
he did so another tuft of feathers became detached. As the conversation
proceeded I became increasingly convinced that rather than introducing a
bird of great beauty into our aviary we would release an oven-ready wreck
in need of a woolly jacket.
When the cock pheasant completed the moult and was in full colour it
was obvious that it was not a pure-bred bird and no doubt had some Lady
Amherst's Pheasant C. amherstiae blood in its ancestry. Indeed, until new
pure-bred birds were imported from China relatively recently all of the
Golden and Lady Amherst's Pheasants in the UK were, to some extent,
hybrid stock. Anyhow, because the pheasants bought from Alf were brother
and sister and showed such obvious signs of hybridisation they were soon
replaced with an unrelated pair which at least looked authentic.
In the ensuing years Alf was a generous friend who provided bags of
wild seed for our growing collection, hollow logs as nests for my parrots
and also introduced us to keeping British finches. Even more importantly
Alf started me on 45 years of keeping and breeding owls. Alf's relatives ran
Blackwater Timbers which cropped and processed local timber. One day a
tree felling gang cut down an Elm Ulmus sp. not realising that it contained
the nest of a pair of Tawny Owls Strix aluco. As the tree began to topple an
adult flew out of the nest and when it hit to the ground two chicks were found
in the hollow. They were both alive, but were obviously injured. One died
that night, but the other chick survived in spite of a damaged wing which
left it with limited ability to fly for the rest of its life. I had persuaded my
father to help me rescue the two owl chicks and the survivor, which was
named Hibou, was my first owl. In those days well before surgical and DNA
sexing it was thought to be a male and was paired with a larger bird which
was believed to be a female.
They did indeed prove to be a true pair and went on to be the most
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999215" page_id="56337080"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
124
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.344057" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337080" page_num="124" year="" vol="">
SAYERS - 50 YEARS AN AVICULTURIST
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997420268292683" page_id="56337080"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
successful pair of birds I have ever looked after of any species. Tawny
Owls normally lay two or three eggs in a clutch, but Hibou's mate always
laid four eggs and every egg was fertile and every chick - a total of 56 in
14 years - was reared. No other bird in my collection has ever come close
to equalling this record.
Alf was an accomplished raconteur who had a fleeting acquaintance with
scientific and technical terms and, without doubt, became the Stanley Unwin
(famous for speaking gobbledegook) of the Cage Bird Society speaking
circuit. He would begin with his personal observations which were fine,
but then getting into his stride he would launch into the world of exotic
species and science, whereupon accuracy and fact became early casualties.
I heard botanic and horticultural terms and diseases attributed to birds and
vice versa, countries of origin were continents awry and birds' relationships
shamelessly reclassified. It was all good humoured and entertaining though
and Alf never failed to hold his audiences spellbound.
Leaving a meeting with some friends who were expressing their
admiration for Alf's great knowledge, I asked them it they understood any
of it and they had to admit that it was way over their heads and, so it was,
because much of it was absolute moonshine. Alf Ashby was a generous
friend for many years and, without doubt, a great character, but I did not
take his discourses too seriously and I do not think he intended I should. I
was privileged to have known him.
When Cliff and I began keeping pheasants a regular advertiser in Cage
Birds (later to become Cage &amp; Aviary Birds) was Roger Willett. After
phoning and arranging to visit him we headed in Cliff's Ford Anglia car
for Ipswich where Roger lived. Roger was an elderly gentleman who was
semi-retired. He had been a Suffolk farmer and then built up a chain of
grocery stores. Named the Worthmore Stores the chain was a kind of early
forerunner to Tesco Express and sought to provide customers with excellent
value for their money. Roger and his wife worked hard and, had done well
enough, but would have become seriously wealthy if they had not been by
nature such a generous couple.
After retiring from farming and retailing, Roger and his wife bought
Whitton Lodge on the outshirts of Ipswich. It was a big old building with
numerous outbuildings and several acres (hectares) of wooded grounds. In
semi-retirement Roger took a keen interest in genealogy and kept and bred
pedigree poultry, gamebirds and waterfowl. However, his interest gained
a new dimension when several very large breeders including the legendary
Oliver Squires (more about whom later) retained Roger to buy and sell most
of their stock. This came about because Roger was the fairest and most
honest man one could ever find and everyone involved with him had total
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.389574" page_id="56337081"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
SAYERS - 50 YEARS AN AVICULTURIST
</construct>
<page confidence="0.999072" page_id="56337081"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
125
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999665365853659" page_id="56337081"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
respect and trust in him.
Early acquisitions from Roger were a pair of Blue Eared-Pheasants
Crossoptilon auritum and a pair of Reeves's Pheasants Syrmaticus reevesii.
The Blue Eared-Pheasant was the only one of the Crossoptilon spp. then
available. It was, of course, long before Jersey Zoo received its White
Eared-Pheasants C. crossoptilon from which a great many young were bred.
Although a few Brown Eared-Pheasants C. mantchuricum were available
all were descended from a single pair imported about a century before and
thus hopelessly inbred and infertile. New stock has now been imported from
China which has improved the situation.
The Blue Eared-Pheasants settled very well and were great favourites
of mine because unlike many pheasants, which can be nervous and volatile
in aviaries, they are naturally tame and placid. The pair bred very well and
we reared many youngsters, but alas the pair was very noisy which left our
neighbours less than impressed. Therefore, after a couple of years I had to
transfer the pair to Cliff's garden as his neighbours were farther away.
The Reeves's Pheasants were bought as youngsters and as they matured
the cock grew into a magnificent specimen. He was huge and beautifully
marked and had a 5ft (approx. 1.5m) long tail which was silver in colour
with black lateral bars. He was not noisy, but by golly he was aggressive
and was accordingly named Satan. It quickly became apparent that a single
hen stood no chance with him and would soon have been killed, so a further
four hens were quickly acquired. This worked wonderfully because if he
chased a hen with vicious intent she was quickly lost in the crowd and no
real harm was done.
Satan was certainly a red-blooded male and the five hens produced a great
many eggs and most of those we incubated were fertile. However, if we had
set all of the eggs we would have been knee-deep in Reeves's Pheasants,
so we ate the majority of them. Satan hated me and gave me a rough time.
When he saw I was about to enter the aviary he would jump onto the highest
perch in the hope that he could drop onto my back and rake me with his
spurs. Usually I was ready for him, but occasionally he won what for me
was a very painful encounter. On one occasion, I had successfully warded
him off and as I was backing out of the aviary door he saw his opportunity
and flew at me. I ducked and he sailed over my head and was loose in the
garden. He walked around somewhat bewildered for a time and I quietly
shepherded him to where two blocks of aviaries formed a right angle in the
hope that, once he was in the comer, I could grab him. I cornered him, but
as I went to grab him he burst vertically into the air and kept rising until
he was just a dot in the heavens. I thought I had lost him for ever, but in
the forlorn hope he might turn up I phoned the police and the local RSPCA
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998871" page_id="56337082"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
126
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.345029" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337082" page_num="126" year="" vol="">
SAYERS - 50 YEARS AN AVICULTURIST
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998696780487805" page_id="56337082"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
inspector. Miraculously, a couple of days later the inspector phoned to tell
me that a gentleman living not too far away had managed to entice, what he
called a "pretty chicken" into his garage and wondered if it might be Satan.
I lost no time in getting there and, sure enough, there was Satan shut in the
man's garage - but with his tail neatly cut off about 12in (30cm) from his
body. Apparently, his captor had gone into his garden where Satan was
tucked away under a privet hedge with only his magnificent 5ft (approx.
1.5m) long tail protruding across the lawn. Seeing the lateral black bars
the man convinced himself that it was an Adder Vipera berus - although it
would have been the mightiest Adder ever recorded - and fetched his spade
and cropped the 'snake' in half. He must have felt extremely foolish but
redeemed himself by laying a trail of bread across the lawn to the back door
of his garage where he finally trapped Satan.
In the early years following the opening of Jersey Zoo, Roger Willett
supplied the zoo with waterfowl, etc. and disposed of the zoo's surplus
stock. At the time the zoo was breeding Red-billed Francolins Francolinus
adspersus and sent some young to Roger. In addition, Roger had received
some Erckel's Francolins F. erckelii from another source. I found them very
attractive and asked if I could buy a pair of each of them. Roger liked them
too and had decided to keep them, but said that if he managed to breed them
he would remember me. He subsequently bred these francolins and, true
to his word, remembered my interest and offered me a pair of each. These
two species remain the only francolins I have kept or bred. Both could be
prolific breeders and very long-lived, I can remember a pair of Erckel's in
the collection of my friend Gary Robbins which seemed to live for ever and
continued to breed when they were distinctly elderly.
I have always been fond of shelducks and sheldgeese - the Andean
Chloephaga melanoptera , Magellan C. picta and Ashy-headed C.
poliocephala , etc. They are all beautifully marked, invariably look
immaculate and whereas some waterfowl are inclined to be timid and
retiring, shelducks and sheldgeese always look self-assured. A lot of
waterfowl keepers do not like them because they can prove aggressive in
mixed collections. This is quite true although the species do vary in this
respect. The Ashy-headed and Ruddy-headed C. rubidiceps are not too bad
whilst the real bruiser is the large and powerful Cereopsis or Cape Barren
Goose Cereopsis novaehollandiae. A gander of the latter species with an
incubating female or goslings to defend will make a fair attempt to virtually
kill anything, including his keeper, if given half a chance.
On one of my visits to Roger he had a nice batch of young Ruddy
Shelducks Tadorna ferruginea which I fell in love with and agreed to buy
a pair for #10 (approx. US$15). The pair settled in very well at liberty in
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.389526" page_id="56337083"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
SAYERS - 50 YEARS AN AVICULTURIST
</construct>
<page confidence="0.998764" page_id="56337083"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
127
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998186170731707" page_id="56337083"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
our garden and spent most of their time grazing on the lawn. Although
shelducks and sheldgeese do swim and my birds have access to a pool they
seem to spend most of their time on the lawn. My pair had the usual ration
of pellets and mixed com, but soon leamt to stand outside the kitchen door
braying until they were given some titbits such as cubes of brown bread,
cmmbled digestive biscuits or even cooked vegetables. It took my pair of
shelducks three years to reach maturity and they were very little trouble
in that time. They did very little damage in the garden and although they
made rather a mess on the lawn in dry weather, a few minutes with a rake
and hose soon rectified this. Moreover, they were not particularly noisy
and with their orange/brown 'suede' plumage looked magnificent on the
lawn in the sun. In their third year it was obvious that they wanted to breed.
They restlessly searched the garden (for a nest site I assumed) and the drake
became rather aggressive and charged at anyone who entered the garden,
but always veered off before he made contact. I placed a grandfather clock
nest box I had constmcted for my macaws on its side under a huge Fatsia
and stuffed half a bale of hay into it. Reasoning that shelducks are burrow
nesters I thought it would suffice and so it did. In a few hours the shelducks
were defending it vigorously. Soon the duck's ventral area became distended
and it was obvious she was laying. Ducks, of course, do not commence
incubation until the last egg has been laid, so it was a couple of weeks or so
before she disappeared. Even during incubation she spent surprisingly long
periods on the lawn with the drake. During one of these absences I opened
the door of the nest box to check inside and found a lovely down-lined nest
containing nine eggs. The down lining had a sort of flap, which had been
pulled over the eggs and this kept them perfectly warm during the duck's
off duty periods. Using a rolled up magazine and the sun I candled one of
the eggs and was fairly sure it was fertile.
The duck continued to incubate the eggs until one evening I returned
home from work to discover that nine ducklings had hatched. Shelduck
ducklings are adorable little creatures and I was thrilled with the family group.
As the ducklings grew bigger, however, the garden quickly turned into a
muddy mess and to say my parents were disenchanted puts it mildly.
I made a perfectly good job of pinioning the ducklings. However, the
other wing gradually drooped lower and lower, I sought advice from Bill
Bolton a very experienced local breeder of waterfowl who had the answer
immediately. I had fed the ducklings too rich a diet, which caused the
primaries to grow quicker than the muscles had developed to support them.
Obviously I needed to change the diet immediately and put a plaster of paris
bandage around the drooped wings to keep them in the correct position.
Thanks to Bill's help and advice all nine ducklings - six ducks and three
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997549" page_id="56337084"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
128
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.316717" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337084" page_num="128" year="" vol="">
SAYERS - 50 YEARS AN AVICULTURIST
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996361170731707" page_id="56337084"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
drakes - grew into lovely birds with no sign of wing defects. Roger Willett
seemed almost as pleased as me by the success and offered to buy all nine
youngsters for #4 (approx. US$6) each, I would have been satisfied with
less and told Roger so, bet he said the females would sell quickly and he
was pleased to be able to help me with my collection. Few dealers would
have been so generous and, to be fair, few could have afforded to. As the
following breeding season approached my parents applied increased pressure
on me to dispose of the pair of Ruddy Shelducks because they could not bear
the thought of the garden being turned into such a mess again. With great
reluctance, I returned the pair to Roger and came away with a pair each of
Laysan Teal Anas laysanensis , Carolina Aix sponsa and Mandarin Ducks
A. galericulata. They graced the garden for many years and being much
smaller never caused any problems even when they had young.
Roger often said that although birds fascinated him it was the personalities
who kept them which really interested him. He would gossip for hours
about the many individuals he had met through his activities, but he was
never bitchy or condescending about anyone even those who had treated him
badly. Roger's conversation was always good natured and he had a lovely
gentle sense of humour. I miss breaking my trips to Norfolk and Suffolk
to call at Roger's for a cup of tea and a chat now that he is no longer with
us. Incidentally, towards the end of Roger's time as a dealer, a schoolboy
was often there at weekends helping care for the birds. That schoolboy was
Trevor Lay who went on to become one of the biggest waterfowl breeders
and dealers in this country and I will write more about him later.
During my early membership of the Avicultural Society it used to have a
dining club (the British Aviculturists 5 Club) which met at the Windsor Hotel
at Lancaster Gate. It was the tradition that overseas members of the society
who found themselves in London at the appropriate time would attend these
dinners and it was at one of these evenings that I met the Australian Joe
Forshaw. It must have been in the late 1960s or even the early 1970s and
he had brought with him a mock up of part of a book he was working on
which included a specimen plate of the Hyacinth Macaw Anodorhynchus
hyacinthinus painted by William Cooper. This would eventually become the
monograph Parrots of the World. I had always been interested in books on
natural history and already had a modest library. In the library at London
Zoo I had seen some of the wonderful ornithological monographs with lovely
hand coloured plates, but although these were offered for sale occasionally by
dealers and at auctions, they were far too expensive for my pocket. However,
Parrots of the World was the next best thing, with its well researched text
and lovely plates, which were of course printed, rather than hand coloured.
The projected price of #35 (approx. US$50 at the current exchange rate)
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.389575" page_id="56337085"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
SAYERS - 50 YEARS AN AVICULTURIST
</construct>
<page confidence="0.999146" page_id="56337085"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
129
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.996440097560976" page_id="56337085"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
was a lot of money at the time, but was just about affordable. I was hooked
and this started a lifelong passion for collecting books on natural history.
My library now has in excess of 8,500 volumes and dominates every room
in the house with bookcases from floor to ceiling. It has even prompted
three extensions to the house. The other interest stimulated by Joe Forshaw,
although he did so unwittingly, is collecting the failed eggs of captive birds
and assembling them into a reference resource.
When Parrots of the World , was published I was quick to buy a copy
and read it avidly. The text brought together all the information available,
but for species after species I noticed that the egg remained undescribed.
How could this be I thought when many of these species had been bred in
captivity, some on numerous occasions. Then the realisation dawned that
eggs laid by captive birds were rarely described and if they failed to hatch
they were usually thrown into the bin. Clearly aviculture as a source of
reference material should be tapped, but how should this be done? At the
time I sat on the council of the Avicultural Society on which a fellow council
member was Dr Colin Harrison, who was a senior member of staff in the
Department of Ornithology at the British Museum (Natural History) with
special responsibility for the Oological (eggs) Department. I explained to
Colin what a rich source of reference material aviculture was and suggested
that the museum made use of it. Colin thought it was a good idea, but
explained that the museum only had a small number of staff and he doubted
it would have time to collect and blow eggs from UK zoos, bird gardens and
private collections. Also, many of the eggs would be addled or contain well
developed chicks and therefore he did not think that blowing them would be
a popular job at the museum. Upon reflection, I thought if the museum was
unable to tap this resource other museums would foresee similar difficulties
so, on the basis one should never suggest to others what one is unprepared
to do oneself, only one option remained -1 would start my own collection.
That was in 1972 since when thanks to the generous support received from
a huge number of collections my egg collection now extends to more than
60,000 eggs representing over 2,000 species and subspecies.
Initially progress was quite slow, but once friends and contacts realised I
was serious and really would drive long distances to collect putrid, stinking
eggs, the response was magnificent. At the peak of my collecting activity I
was collecting and blowing 5,000 eggs a year and taking into account that
the main breeding season spans only three or four months the demands on
my time and stamina were enormous. Some nights I did not go to bed but
worked through until 6.00am blowing eggs and then had a shower, shaved
and changed, before setting off for work. Although the effort and costs
involved in collecting the eggs has been considerable I have enjoyed it all
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.991976" page_id="56337086"  page_num="130" year="" vol="">
130
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.309798" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337086" page_num="130" year="" vol="">
SAYERS - 50 YEARS AN AVICULTURIST
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990005073170732" page_id="56337086"  page_num="130" year="" vol="">
immensely.
My collection is now quite important and I am very proud of it, especially
as not a single viable egg was destroyed in creating it. Indeed I can honestly
say that I have never taken a wild bird's egg not even when I was a boy. It
has always been my view that a blown eggshell is a poor exchange for a
bird which would otherwise have hatched. However, if the equation is that
the egg having failed to hatch would have been thrown in the bin, then I
think it is important to preserve it. I think I began this project in the nick
of time, because with the ban on the importation of wild birds into the
EU (European Union) now in place, the range of species laying eggs in
UK collections has reduced dramatically. Many species have laid in UK
aviaries occasionally, but not sufficiently regularly to establish permanent
self-sustaining-populations. This is particularly true of many species of
softbills and the more demanding seedeaters.
John Spedan Lewis (who was a Vice President of the Avicultural Society
from 1938-1962) inherited the John Lewis store chain from his father and
made all the staff partners in the business and gave them a share of the profits.
A leading aviculturist in the period between the two World Wars, John Spedan
Lewis established wonderful collections at Cookham and Wargrave by the
Thames in Berkshire. The birds in these collections ranged from macaws to
birds-of-paradise and over 100 owls. According to contemporary accounts
his owl collection at Wargrave was almost certainly the largest of its kind in
the world at the time. Unfortunately for me this collection was in being before
my time and I never had the pleasure of seeing it. Later John Spedan Lewis
moved to Leckford Abbas in the Test Valley, near Stockbridge in Hampshire
and built up a further collection of pheasants, waterfowl, cranes and owls,
etc., about which I will have more to say later. He had an impressive record
of keeping and breeding owls and I believe those which nested in his aviaries
included the Indian Bam Owl Tyto alba stertens , a subspecies of the Collared
Scops Owl Otus bakkamoena semitorques or what Clements (2007) lists as
the Japanese Scops Owl O. semitorques (which was then called the Half-
collared Scops Owl and, although it was said to "have nested", I can find
nothing to indicate that any youngsters were reared), the White-faced Owl
Philopsis leucotis or P. granti (split into two species now but formerly, of
course, well-known as the White-faced Scops Owl O. leucotis ), European
Eagle-Owl Bubo bubo , Greyish Eagle-Owl B. cinerascens (previously called
the Abyssinian Eagle-Owl and regarded as a subspecies of the Spotted Eagle-
Owl B. africanus ), Great Homed Owl B. virginianus , Burrowing Owl Athene
cunicularia nanodes and Spectacled Owl Pulsatrix perspicillata.
A rather formidible lady, Miss Ethel Chawner (who edited the Avicultural
Magazine for part of 1935 and from 1936-1938), kept a private collection
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.389596" page_id="56337087"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
SAYERS - 50 YEARS AN AVICULTURIST
</construct>
<page confidence="0.999111" page_id="56337087"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
131
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997334463414634" page_id="56337087"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
of owls at her home at Lyndhurst in the New Forest in the early part of
the twentieth century. She clearly knew what she was doing because she
successfully bred such species as the Andean Pygmy Owl Glaucidium
jardinii , known then as Jardine's Pygmy Owl, and the White-faced (Scops)
Owl, both for the first time in the UK, in 1915 and 1923 respectively. In 1927,
John Spedan Lewis engaged Miss Chawner to take charge of his collections
at Cookharn and Wargrave and, when he moved to Leckford, Miss Chawner
was mainly responsible for the formation of the Leckford collection. She
remained in charge until her retirement in 1939.
Although owls are easily managed birds in captivity, being long-lived,
ready breeders, hardy and easy to feed, such impressive results were by
no means the norm at the time. Many collections, including some of the
prominent zoos, fared poorly with their owls - photographs taken at the time
show birds in very poor conditions.
Initially, this puzzled me because stockmanship in the nineteenth and
early twentieth centuries was often excellent and many species of birds
which are a great deal more demanding than owls did very well when kept
in aviaries. However, having read accounts written at the time and talked
to those who were involved in aviculture during the early twentieth century
I believe I now understand the reasons why.
Firstly, some keepers reasoned that as owls are nocturnal they should be
kept in dark aviaries often facing north and/or in the dense shade of trees.
This was and remains totally wrong. Certainly owls need a shady comer
and a roosting/nesting box into which they can retire at will. However, owls
also love to sunbathe and on sunny days I often see my birds on the ground
with their wings outstretched as they soak up the sunshine. The second
mistaken belief was that owls did not need water because they obtained
enough moisture in the form of blood from their food. It is tme that owls
can survive without water, but they should never be denied access to it.
Owls certainly drink water, particularly during hot weather. Also, most owls
are regular and enthusiastic bathers and this helps keep their plumage in
good order. The third aspect of this inadequate husbandry was a poor diet.
Some owls particularly those kept by wealthy landowners were fed by the
gamekeepers on rabbits, rats, mice and sparrows, etc. caught on the estate.
This certainly applied at Wargrave and the results were fine. However,
other keepers advocated a diet of chicken heads and butchers' scraps and
whilst this kept the owls alive they usually failed to prosper and breed on
such an inadequate diet. The final problem was air pollution. Owls were
often badly affected by winter smogs. The fog, laden with smoke, badly
stained their plumage and, particularly if they were kept without access to
water, they were unable to bathe and wash it off. I believe these to be the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998236" page_id="56337088"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
132
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.342168" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337088" page_num="132" year="" vol="">
SAYERS - 50 YEARS AN AVICULTURIST
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998789292682927" page_id="56337088"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
reasons why some collections failed to do as well as they might have done
with their owls around a century ago.
Fortunately I had many opportunities to visit the Leckford collection,
which although impressive, was past its heyday by the time I did so. At
the time Cliff and I were assembling our pheasant collection much of the
Leckford stock was being sold off. According to Delacour the collection
was at its peak in 1939 when war was declared. Although the collection was
kept going throughout the war, the resultant problems of shortages of labour,
foodstuffs and the unavailablity of new stock caused a considerable decrease
in the size of the collection. Our first visit was memorable for several reasons,
not least because it was before the construction of motorways and the journey
took forever. The route took us around the infamous North Circular Road
in London and through every town and village between here and Leckford.
Having left home at some ungodly hour, we did not reach Leckford until
late lunchtime. Once there though what a revelation Leckford was. There
was the wonderful old historic house surrounded by lovely gardens full of
rare plants. Huge, grass floored aviaries contained remnants of what had
obviously been a vast collection of avian treasures. There were still many
rare species of pheasants, parakeets and pigeons I had never seen before and
could not identify. With some disappointment we realised that none of the
pheasants were suitable for our collection. Either they needed much bigger
aviaries than we could offer, were not hardy and needed a warm shelter,
were odd birds which we stood little chance of finding mates for or were old
and probably past breeding age. However, the arduous trip was not wasted
because Cliff and I were mightily impressed with what we saw and came
away with a young pair of Wonga Pigeons Leucosarcia melanoleuca.
I have not yet mentioned the vast collection of waterfowl at Leckford.
Long after the rest of the bird collection had been disbanded the waterfowl
were retained as a commercial breeding operation by the John Lewis
Partnership. The extensive waterfowl enclosures were situated away from
the Leckford Abbas mansion on the other side of the road. They spread
along the banks of the River Test in an idyllic setting beyond which were
lightly wooden slopes. I am no angler but I am told that the Test is one of
the finest trout rivers in the south of England and the crystal clear water is
full of fish fry and invertebrates. It was this water which was diverted so
that it flowed briskly through the breeding and rearing enclosures. I have
seen many waterfowl collections, some of them highly successful, where the
lasting memories were of copious mud and water which looked like brown
Windsor soup, but smelt much less appetizing. Leckford was as far removed
from this as one could possibly imagine. During every one of my visits the
grass was always luxuriant and clean and the water always appeared clean
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.389618" page_id="56337089"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
SAYERS - 50 YEARS AN AVICULTURIST
</construct>
<page confidence="0.999631" page_id="56337089"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
133
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.996275219512195" page_id="56337089"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
enough to drink.
The husbandry at Leckford was also excellent and I was intrigued by
the great attention to detail. For instance, all of the perimeter fences of the
enclosures had a skirting of small mesh wire-netting and fixed to the top of
it was a rolled metal overhang. This was, of course, to preclude the entry
of rats Rattus spp., Stoats Mustela erminea and Weasels M. nivalis. As one
would expect in such an excellent collection, Leckford's breeding results
were outstanding. Leckford was the first collection in the UK to breed
Eyton's or the Plumed Whistling Duck Dendrocygna eytoni , Wandering
Whistling DuckZ). arcuata, Australian Radjah Shelduck T. radjah rufitergum ,
Abyssinian Blue-winged Goose Cyanochen cyanoptera , Andean Crested
Duck Lophonetta specularioides alticola , Philippine Duck A. luzonica ,
Puna Teal A. puna and Southern Pochard Netta erythrophthalma brunnea.
Although not the first collection to do so, it also bred Hartlaub's Duck
Pteronetta hartlaubii, the male of which gets a somewhat swollen base to its
bill during the breeding season, as well as breeding a large number of Ringed
Teal Callonetta leucophrys which, at the time, was regarded as tricky.
Large numbers of young waterfowl were bred each year at Leckford
and when I saw them they invariably appeared to be of superb quality.
However, when these birds were bought by other waterfowl breeders they
did not always perform as well as their new owners would have liked and
dark rumours began to circulate that Leckford had, in some way, managed
to sterilize its young stock in order to protect its markets. This was, of
course, complete rubbish. The reason for this disparity in breeding success
was much more obvious. It was simply that the new owners' waterfowl
enclosures offered much poorer conditions than those at Leckford. If you
were moved from abundant clean grass and gin clear, invertebrate enriched
water, to mud and fetid brown Windsor soup-like water would not your tail
become a bit less bushy and your eyes less bright?
In all I met four successive managers of Leckford, although I knew only
the last manager well. At the time of my first visit it was managed by Mr
and Mrs Milligan and I can remember them telling us about the stock they
used to have at Leckford and seem to remember them mentioning cranes
and Emus Dromaius novaehollandiae. When this couple retired Terry Jones
took over and was succeeded by Fred Rees or it may have been Fred Reece?
The last manager was Tony Samways and he very kindly allowed me to
have some of the unsuccessful eggs for my collection. Looking through my
cabinet at the tickets giving the origins of the eggs I am often transported
down memory lane.
The second part of Bernard s reminiscences of his 50 years in aviculture
will be published in the next issue of the magazine.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999557" page_id="56337090"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
134
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9948885" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337090" page_num="134" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
GRASSFINCHES IN AUSTRALIA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9977165" page_id="56337090"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
Grassfinches in Australia by Joseph M. Forshaw and Mark Shephard,
illustrated by Anthony Pridham and published by CSIRO Publishing, August
2012, is described as the only up-to-date, fully illustrated monograph on
all Australian species of grassfinches. It is said to be a book which will
appeal to ornithologists, wildlife art book collectors and aviculturists, which
summarises our present knowledge of each species and gives readers an
appreciation of the birds in their natural habitats and in aviculture.
It is certainly an impressive book and will not look out of place alongside
Joseph Forshaw's earlier works on parrots and birds of paradise. It has
fewer species to cover, of course, and a different but equally outstanding
artist with a markedly different style and covers keeping Australian finches
in aviaries so fully that it could easily be classified as an avicultural title.
It is a book every Australian finch enthusiast will aspire to own, though
UK/European enthusiasts should be warned that the avicultural coverage
very much concentrates on keeping and breeding these birds in aviaries in
Australia and many will undoubtably be put off by the price, which I am
told will be #175.00 in the UK. 1
Joseph Forshaw begins his introduction by explaining the taxonomic
arrangement used in the book, before going on to deal with the distribution
and preferred habitats of the various species, their movements, social
behaviour, vocalisations, feeding, courtship and nesting, the development of
the young and differences in the mouth or palate markings of the nestlings.
In recent years there has been a spectacular upsurge in mining activities in
Australia and under the heading - Conservation - he concludes by warning
that these pose a serious threat to species such as the Black-throated Finch,
which has disappeared from more than 60% of its range. Habitat loss or
degradation has had a severe impact on bird populations in Australia and
even the ubiquitous Zebra Finch has disappeared from many coastal and
subcoastal districts of eastern Australia.
Mark Shephard follows with an historical overview of Australian finches
in aviculture in Australia and writes about the current status of these birds in
Australian aviaries, backed up by facts and figures and the use of tables and
graphs. He then tackles transport, housing and other aspects of keeping and
breeding these species in Australian aviaries. A table lists common ailments,
their causes, symptoms, diagnosis, treatment and prevention.
The species accounts (22 of them) begin with the Painted Finch,
followed by the Beautiful and Red-eared Firetails and the Diamond Firetail
or Diamond Sparrow and the various other species familiar to most of us
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909715" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337091" page_num="135" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998995" page_id="56337091"  page_num="135" year="" vol="">
135
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9977758" page_id="56337091"  page_num="135" year="" vol="">
and arriving eventually at the Blue-faced Parrotfinch and Gouldian - these
are followed by the Chestnut-breasted Mannikin, Yellow-ramped Mannikin,
Nutmeg Finch or Spicebird (Nutmeg Mannikin is the preferred name in the
book), the Pale-headed and Black-headed species, the Java Sparrow and,
finally, the Pictorella Mannikin or Finch. The surprise inclusion of the Java
Sparrow is because it occurs (as an introduced species) on Christmas Island
(an Australian Territory in the Indian Ocean), while the Nutmeg Finch or
Spicebird population of eastern Australia owes its origin to escaped and/or
released cage birds. The author declares himself uncertain about the inclusion
of the Black-headed Mannikin in any formal listing of Australian birds, as
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999399" page_id="56337092"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
136
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.971807" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337092" page_num="136" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995932814814815" page_id="56337092"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
no feral population has become established and has similar misgivings about
the inclusion of the Pale-headed Mannikin.
The colour plates are always a highlight of such a book - and these are
outstanding. Tony Pridham is an admirer of the work of Raymond Harris-
Ching and I can see a strong resemblance between his work and that of
Raymond Harris-Ching. Grassfinches in Australia is lavishly illustrated,
with a full-page plate of each species and often one, two, three or more
other paintings of the same species. The main plate usually shows an adult
male and female and in some cases the juvenile or immature, the different
subspecies where these occur and the different colour morphs in the case
of the Gouldian Finch. The paintings also give a good idea of the different
habitats of the various species.
Each species account concludes with up to one-and-a-half pages or
more of aviary notes. Mark Shephard begins with a history of the species
in aviculture, principally in Australia, but with some mention of Europe
and occasionally the USA or elsewhere. He usually notes when the species
was first imported into Europe - often into the UK or Germany - and when
it was first bred and refers to its current status. He deals with its status in
Australian aviculture under a separate heading, relying on official stock
returns and other fact based data. The housing, feeding and breeding of
each species are dealt with from a purely Australian point of view, though
a lot of the information could equally apply here in Europe although, of
course, the Australian climate enables Australians to keep and breed their
birds in outdoor aviaries, whereas in Europe breeders usually keep their
birds in cages indoors.
The final section covers mutations, colour variations and hybrids.
Grassfinches in Australia by Joseph M. Forshaw and Mark Shephard,
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.323553">
illustrated by Anthony Pridham and with line drawings and text figures by
Frank Knight. ISBN 9780643096349. Hardback, 336 pages, published by
CSIRO Publishing, PO Box 1139, Collingwood, Victoria 3066, Australia.
Website: http://www.publish.csiro.aU/E-mail:publishing.sales@csiro.au It
is distributed in the UK/Europe by Eurospan and in the USA and Canada
by Stylus Publishing. Websites: http://www.eurospanbookstore.com &amp;
www.styluspub.com/E-mail:info@eurospangroup.com &amp; StylusMail@
PressWarehouse.com, respectively. Price AS 185.00.
Malcolm Ellis
1 Since writing the above review, I have learned from Graeme Hyde,
</footnote>
<reference confidence="0.9251815">
former long-time Editor of Australian Aviculture , that Grassfinches in
Australia is available in the UK at the discounted price of #148, post free, if
ordered online at: http://www.eurospanbookstore/grassfinches-in-australia.
html
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.943953" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337093" page_num="137" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<keyword confidence="0.383375">
137.
</keyword>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993196" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56337093" page_num="137" year="" vol="">
PHEASANT PIGEONS AND FLAMINGOS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993295965517241" page_id="56337093"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
The International Zoo Yearbook Volume 46, 2012, which takes as its
special subject for this year the New World primates, has in its later section
on the developing zoo world, two articles about birds likely to be of interest to
aviculturists. The first of these deals with the White-naped Pheasant Pigeon
and covers housing, diet, breeding and general information accumulated
during the 22 years this species had been kept at Barcelona Zoo.
Five pheasant pigeons 2.2.1 confiscated by the Spanish authorities
arri ved at the zoo in 1988. The first chick hatched in 1992, since when an
amazing total of 65 chicks had been hatched. At the time of writing (the
manuscript was submitted in August 2010 and revised a year later) Barcelona
Zoo had 17.6 birds. Several of those hatched at the zoo had been sent to
other European institutions, including Zoo Krefeld and Weltvogelpark
Walsrode in Germany, Bristol Zoo Gardens and Chester Zoo here in the UK,
Zoobotaeico Jerez in Spain, Copenhagen Zoo in Denmark, Jardim de Liboa
in Portugal and Vogelpark Avifauna in Alphen in the Netherlands. These
have contributed greatly to the European population which at the time the
article was written comprised 26.12.4 birds in nine zoos, plus 3.2 in zoos
in the USA. A European Studbook managed by Weltvogelpark Walsrode
was established in 2001.
The second article describes a study the aim of which was to try to find
a quick and cost-effective way of predicting the gender of adult Chilean
Flamingos using biometric measurements. Three measurements - tarsus
length, flat wing length and body mass - were taken from a group of 68
Chilean Flamingos of known sex at Dublin Zoo. Only the maximum tarsus
length provided a useful guide to predicting their gender and was sufficient
to predict the sex of over 94% of the adult birds. All those with a tarsus
length of 26cm (1 OVfln) or more were male and all those with a tarsus length
of 25.5cm (lOin) or less were female.
Volume 48, due to be published in 2014, will take as its special subject
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.4770075">
- Avian Challenges.
The International Zoo Yearbook Vi olume 46 is published on behalf of The
Zoological Society of London (ZSL) by Wiley Blackwell, 9600 Garsington
Road, Oxford OX4 2DQ, UK. I find the pricing structure with the different
rates of tax, etc., difficult (or should this challeging?) to work out, therefore,
may I suggest that for the appropriate price and ordering information you
try the website: www.wileycustomerhelp.com/ask
Malcolm Ellis
</reference>
<page confidence="0.99881" page_id="56337094"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
138
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.987512" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337094" page_num="138" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
THE KEN SMITH STORY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994664282051282" page_id="56337094"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
Mention the name Ken Smith to any like-minded person under 50 and you
are likely to be met with a blank stare (as I was when I mentioned his name
to two younger members during the society's visit to Chester Zoo), yet in
the late 1950s and 1960s his name often cropped up in News &amp; Views and
when Russell Tofts was writing his biography of Ken Smith and enquired
about articles Ken had written for the magazine, I was able to come up with
an article on storks, another on the bird collection at Paignton Zoo, one on
the birds at Jersey Zoo and an obituary to Herbert Whitley (the founder of
Paignton Zoo).
After Ken Smith's widow, Trudy, and their daugthers, Russell Tofts must
be Ken Smith's biggest fan. He believes Ken never got the recognition he
deserved during his lifetime and wants to put this right and prevent his name
becoming completely forgotten. Animals in the Blood: The Ken Smith Story ,
described as "A Biography of Gerald Durrell's Right-Hand Man" is likely
to go a long way towards achieving this.
In 1949, Ken Smith was Durrell's partner on an animal collecting
expedition to what was then the British Cameroons (the subject of The Bafut
Beagles) and the following year to what was then British Guiana (the subject
of Three Singles to Adventure), mounted his own expedition to Sierra Leone
and, in 1952, became Superintendent of Paignton Zoo and six years later left
to set up Jersey Zoo while Gerald and Jacquie Durrell were off on an animal
collecting trip to Argentina. On their return they were perturbed to discover
that he had hastily built (and it showed) a conventional old-fashioned zoo.
You will have to read the book and decide for yourself whether Durrell
left behind a masterplan which Ken Smith failed to follow or whether he
did the best he could with the limited amount of money available and the
short time he had - the zoo (now the Durrell Wildlife Conservation Trust)
opened to the public on March 26th 1959 (while the Durrells were still in
South America).
Ken Smith had a three-year contract and continued to run the zoo while
Gerald Durrell more-or-less remained hidden away behind the scenes, no
doubt writing his books. Ken turned down the chance to manage Dudley
Zoo, when Donald Risdon left to open the Tropical Bird Garden at Rode,
in order to continue running Jersey Zoo. He ran it while the Durrells were
away for seven months filming and even continued to run it for a while after
he bought Exmouth Zoo. The relationship between the two men had though
well and truly broken down and in 1963 he left Jersey and never saw Durrell
again and was more-or-less airbrushed out of the story. He eventually had
four small zoos in south-west England, one of which, the present Shaldon
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909708" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337095" page_num="139" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999113" page_id="56337095"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
139
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.991219733333333" page_id="56337095"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
Wildlife Trust, still exists.
He was bom in Deddington in Oxfordshire, and Russell Tofts writes at
great length (perhaps at too greater length) about his schooldays, one of his
earliest jobs at Oxford Zoo (a long forgotten zoo which lasted less than six
years), his wartime service in the RAF and then working at Whipsnade Zoo
1946-1947, where he first met Gerald Durrell.
This is primarily a book for the zoo buff. It has a wonderful collection
of more than 80 old black-and-white photographs, many of them featuring
Ken Smith either during his collecting days or his zoo days. My favourite,
though it has no great relevance to the story, is the photo of the Regent Pet
Stores, universally known as "Palmers", in Parkway, Camden Town, in the
1950s, for I was bom and grew up nearby and cycled past it twice a day
when I worked in the Bird House at London Zoo.
Animals in the Blood: The Ken Smith Story by Russell Tofts. ISBN 978-
095315-884-3. Hardback, 232 pages, more than 80 photographs. Published
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.7705696" page_id="56337095"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
by The Bartlett Society, 6 Queen Street, Dawlish, Devon EX7 9HB, UK.
Website: http://www.zoohistory.co.uk Price #16.99, plus #3.99 p&amp;p.
Malcolm Ellis
*
*
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.765425" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56337095" page_num="139" year="" vol="">
PREPARING TO CELEBRATE ANNIVERSARY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.951854916666667" page_id="56337095"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
A special celebration will take place on December 17th 2012 to mark the
40th Anniversary of Loro Parque, Tenerife. What has become the largest
collection of parrots in the world, began with only 150 parrots and has grown
step by step until today Loro Parque is home to a large and diverse collection
of more than 500 species of birds and other animals. It still specialises
in parrots, of course, and these will be at the heart of the celebration, but
penguins (last year it bred two Southern Rockhopper Penguins Eudyptes
moseleyi and several Gentoo Pygoscelis papua ) and other birds (a Victoria
Crowned Pigeon Goura victoria hatched in November 2011) have been
added to the collection, as well as Killer Whales or Orcas Orcinus orca ,
white Bengal Tigers Panthera t. tigris. Western Lowland Gorillas Gorilla
g. gorilla and many other attractions.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995352" page_id="56337096"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
140
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9812785" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337096" page_num="140" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
NEWS FROM LORO PARQUE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995384105263158" page_id="56337096"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
Last year the Patagonian Conures Cyanoliseus patagonus were moved
to other enclosures. Three subspecies - the nominate form or Lesser C. p.
patagonus, Andean C. p. andinus and Greater C. p. bloxami - can now be
seen living side by side and it is easier to appreciate the differences in size
and coloration. The Greater began to breed for the first time while on public
exhibition and, in June, was raising a youngster. A new aviary for South
American conures, housing species such as the Blue-crowned Aratinga
acuticaudata and Sun Conure A solstitialis, was opened recently. It enables
visitors to see large flocks of various species and observe how the different
species interact with each other.
This year for the first time three young Purple-bellied Parrots Triclaria
malachitacea were being reared by their parents without human assistance.
A young Gang-gang Cockatoo Callocephalum fimbriatum had become a
special favourite amongst staff at the baby station and a pair of Green-winged
Macaws Ara chloropterus was fostering two young Hyacinth Macaws
Anodorhynchus hyacinthinus .
In July, one of the fundacion's older pairs of Hispanolan Amazons
Amazona ventralis which had bred successfully in the past, but had not been
successful since 2008, was rearing two chicks. Loro Parque Fundacion
is one of the few European zoo collections holding this species and if a
self-sustaining breeding population is to be established the help of private
breeders will be required.
A pair of Desmarest's Fig Parrots Psittaculirostris desmarestii was also
rearing young. It is important that the parents are not disturbed following
the hatching of the chicks, otherwise the chicks may be abandoned, killed
or even eaten. About four weeks are allowed to elapse before the nest box
is checked. Also gratifying is the fact that several pairs of Collared Lories
Phigys solitarius are now breeding regularly and rearing their own young.
They are breeding so successfully that some of these birds could be made
available to other collections interested in breeding this species from the
larger Fijian islands.
A very special breeding success was the hatching of three Philippine or
Red-vented Cockatoo chicks Cacatua haematuropygia. A newly formed
pair laid for the first time and all three eggs, which were incubated by the
parents, hatched and the chicks were being well cared for by their parents.
In the past the chicks had always been hand-reared.
Last year the first Blue-cheeked Amazon chick A dufresniana was raised.
This year two further chicks were being reared.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700243" genericHeader="method" page_id="56337097" page_num="141" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995971" page_id="56337097"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
141
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9988" genericHeader="method" page_id="56337097" page_num="141" year="" vol="">
RAYMOND'S BIRDS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.932206294117647" page_id="56337097"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
The male Purple-throated Fraitcrow Querulapurpurata which previously
belonged to our late President, Raymond Sawyer, has gone on breeding loan
to Wuppertal Zoo in Germany, which is believed to be the first collection
in the world to have succeeded in breeding this South American cotinga in
captivity.
Chris Brack
Young Purple-throated Fruitcrow hatched at Wuppertal Zoo. The black plumage still
shows remnants of the chick's buff-coloured down and It is this which gives the chick
its speckled appearance.
1 believe that several of Raymond's waders, such as the Redshanks Tringa
totanus , Lapwings Vanellus vanellus. Masked Lapwings V miles , Long-toed
Lapwings V crassirostris , Ringed Plovers Charadrius hiaticula and Little
Ringed Plovers C. dubius but not the Oystercatchers Haematopus ostralegus,
have gone to Exmoor Zoo, north Devon and the pair of Red-crested Turacos
Tauraco erythrolophus to Tropiquaria, in Somerset. I understand that
Chestnut Lodge has been sold, but I do not know who has bought it or what
their plans are for the house and garden - or the aviaries.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.608077" page_id="56337097"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.961745" genericHeader="method" page_id="56337097" page_num="141" year="" vol="">
CHESTER'S LATEST PROJECT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9487005" page_id="56337097"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
Chester Zoo's hugely ambitious #30 million (approx. US$45 million)
islands development, plans to bring "the Philippines, Papua New Guinea,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998576" page_id="56337098"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
142
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.891209" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337098" page_num="142" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.968403071428572" page_id="56337098"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
Bali, Sumatra, Sumba and Sulawesi to the heart of Cheshire." It will
showcase the zoo's conservation work in the region and bring together
animals such as Anoa Bubalus depressicornis, Babirusa Babyrousa
babyrussa , the Bali Starling Leucopsar rothschildi , cassowary Casuarius
sp., Rhinoceros Hombill Buceros rhinoceros , Wrinkled Hombill Aceros
corrugatus, Sumatran Orangutan Bongo abellii, Sulawesi Macaque Macaca
nigra , Sumatran Tiger Panthera tigris sumatrae and the Visayan Warty Pig
Sus cebifrons.
Designed by architects from the dan pearlman group in Germany, the
project will home in on the different animals and the different vegetation and
architecture seen on the various islands and will take visitors on a journey
which will include educational exhibits, play areas, restaurants and village-
style food stands.
Work is expected to begin this autumn and the planned opening date is
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.727401272727273" page_id="56337098"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
Easter 2015.
* * *
LAST YEAR AT WUPPERTAL ZOO
Zoo Wuppertal 130. Jahresbericht 2011 (the zoo's Annual Report for last
year), lists among the most important new arrivals: 0.1 Hyachinth Macaw
Anodorhynchus hyacinthinus , 1.1 Black-billed Amazons Amazona agilis,
0.1 Spangled Cotinga Cotinga cayana , 1.1 Andean Cocks-of-the-Rock
Rupicola peruviana , 1.1 Golden-headed Manakins Pipra erythrocephala,
three Paradise Tanagers Tangara chilensis and 1.0 Fawn-breasted Bowerbird
Chlamydera cerviniventris .
Birds bred during 2011 included: one King Penguin Aptenodytes
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.997428866666667" page_id="56337098"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
patagonicus , six African (Black-footed or Jackass) Penguins Spheniscus
demersus , one Elegant Crested Tinamou Eudromia elegans , one Scarlet
Ibis Eudocimus ruber , one Cape Thick-knee Burhinus capensis, 37 Avocets
Recurvirostris avosetta , 1.1 Red-crowned Cranes Grus japonensis , 0.1
Bateleur Terathopius ecaudatus , 0.3 Victoria Crowned Pigeons Goura
victoria , two Beautiful Fruit Doves Ptilinoptus pulchellus , five Barn
Swallows Hirundo rustica , one Vermilion Flycatcher Pyrocephalus rubinus ,
two Brazilian Tanagers Ramphocelus bresilius , six Turquoise Tanagers T.
mexicana , 13 Gouldian Finches Erythrura gouldiae and nine Bali Starlings
Leucopsar rothschildi.
Chris Brack told me that the zoo has an Andean Flamingo Phoenicopterus
andinus which was imported in 1971 by the dealer JABRIA. This means,
of course, that it is at least 41 years of age. It has outlived the other five
Andean Flamingos and six James's Flamingos P. jamesi which arrived at
the same time.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700239" genericHeader="method" page_id="56337099" page_num="143" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998357" page_id="56337099"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
143
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56337099" page_num="143" year="" vol="">
DESPITE THE WEATHER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9469125" page_id="56337099"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
Despite the exceptionally wet late spring and summer Paradise Park,
at Hayle, here in Cornwall, enjoyed a successful breeding season with
more chicks reared than the previous year. A pair of Galahs or Roseate
Cockatoos Eolophus roseicapilla produced three chicks, which as usual
were reared by their parents. The park, which is home to the World Parrot
Trust (WPT), has a colony of 10 of these cockatoos in its Australian aviary.
Keas Nestor notabilis, Blue-throated Macaws Ara glaucogularis , Citron-
crested Cockatoos Cacatua sulphurea citrinocristata , White -bellied Caiques
Pionites leucogaster , Plum-headed Parakeets Psittacula cyanocephala and
Black-cheeked Lovebirds Agapornis nigrigensis all had a good breeding
season. Six species of lorikeets successfully reared young, including two
pairs of Goldie's Lorikeets Psitteuteles goldei . Golden Conures Guaruba
guarouba and Mountain Parakeets Psilopsiagon aurifrons were incubating
eggs in August. Avocets Recurvirostra avosetta sat through the heavy
rain and when their chicks hatched led them to shelter. The flamingos
Phoenicopterus ruber got no further than building nests.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.521678" page_id="56337099"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.696074" genericHeader="method" page_id="56337099" page_num="143" year="" vol="">
SEEKING A REPLACEMENT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8969194" page_id="56337099"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
Since publication of the article on breeding the Blue-crowned Motmot
Momotus momota in France (Vol.118, No,2, pp.63-76 (2012)), Parc
Zoologique de Montpellier has lost its male Blue-crowned Motmot and
is seeking a replacement. If you k now where a replacement male may be
obtained, please contact Patrick Chattier. E-rna.il: patrick, chattier,aves@
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.7121028" page_id="56337099"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
gmail.com
*
*
A LITTLE DISAPPOINTING
Bernard Sayers describes the 2012 breeding season as having been a little
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.8407058">
disappointing. Bernard succeeded in breeding: four Burrowing Owls Athene
cunicularia , four Indian Scops Owls Otus bakkamoena , two White-faced
Owls Ptilopsis leucotis, three Boobook Owls Ninox boobook , two Tropical
Screech Owls Megascops choliba, one Chaco Owl Strix chacoensis, two
Striated Caracaras Phalcoboenus australis, one Sulawesi Ground Dove
Gallicolumba tristigmata , two Triangular-spotted or Speckled Pigeons
Columba guinea, one Red-collared Lorikeet Trichoglossus ( haematodus)
rubritorquis, two Swainson's T, k moluccanus , several wild-type grey Java
Sparrows Padda oryzivoro and several Black-cheeked Lovebirds Agapornis
nigrigenis.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999594" page_id="56337100"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
144
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9759415" genericHeader="method" page_id="56337100" page_num="144" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
THE AGE OF PARROTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999343" page_id="56337100"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
The Times , p.24, Saturday, September 15th 2012, reported the death of
an African Grey Parrot Psittacus erithacus, belonging to a Mrs Morgan, of
Exeter. The parrot was said to have been 55 years old (having been bought
as a chick by Mrs Morgan in Tanzania in 1957) and was, according to the
report, "believed to be one of the oldest domestic parrots in the world."
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.985873" genericHeader="method" page_id="56337100" page_num="144" year="" vol="">
NEWLY APPOINTED CURATOR
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.919455666666667" page_id="56337100"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
Simon Matthews is leaving Waddesdon Manor Aviary to take up the
position of Curator of Birds at A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation (AWWP) in
Qatar, owned by Sheikh Saoud Bin Mohamed Bin Ali A1 Thani. A1 Wabra
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.4498095" page_id="56337100"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
Wildlife Preservation is home to most of the captive population of Spix's
Macaw Cyanopsitta spixii and aims to re-establish this species back in its
natural habitat in Brazil, where it owns the 2,000 hectares (approx. 5,000
acres) Concordia Farm - the last recorded wild Spix's Macaw having been
seen near Melancia Creek - which flows through the property.
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.63428" genericHeader="method" page_id="56337100" page_num="144" year="" vol="">
BISHOPS BREEDING IN CORWALL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9946965" page_id="56337100"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
A few weeks ago, former Hon. Secretary and Treasurer Paul Boulden,
commented on the fact that, somewhat mysteriously, a number of Napoleon
Weavers Euplectes afer have become available lately. Now comes news
that this once common seed-eater, now more correctly known as the Yellow-
crowned Bishop, has bred successfully in the new African Wetlands Aviary,
opened earlier this year at Newquay Zoo. Several nests were built and chicks
hatched. The birds appear to belong to the nominate subspecies, the breeding
male of which has a broad yellow band across the breast. The new aviary
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.593063833333333" page_id="56337100"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
also houses Superb Starlings Lamprotornis superbus , Blacksmith Plovers
Vanellus armatus and Yellow-mantled Widowbirds E. macroura.
* * *
2013 SPRING SOCIAL MEETING
The society is planning to hold the 2013 Spring Social Meeting at
Paignton Zoo Environmental Park on Saturday, April 27th, with visits to
</table>
<reference confidence="0.94085725">
Newquay Zoo and Paradise Park at Hayle the following day, Sunday, April
28th. Further details of the arrangements, which are being made by Mike
Curzon (E-mail:mcurzonmbe@hotmail.co.uk/Tel:01373 824077), will be
announced once they are finalised.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999074" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337101" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTINUING MASCARENES PROGRAMME
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99764285" page_id="56337101"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Chester Zoo's 2011 Zoo Review reports that there are (or were at the end
of 2011) approximately 160 pairs of Mauritius Fody Foudia rubra. There is
a remnant wild population on the island of Mauritius and a second population
of translocated birds on the lie aux Aigrettes. An attempt to create a third
population, this time on Round Island, made a promising start but then the
birds began to be predated by Keel-scaled Boas Casarea dussumieri , leaving
just one remaining survivor. A further release of a small number of birds
took place in late 2011.
Breeding activity by the Mauritius Olive White-eyes Zosterops
chloronothos on the lies aux Aigrettes was delayed by two months due to
the worst drought for 40 years. Despite this, however, six chicks fledged
successfully. On Mauritius, a record number of nests resulted in 10 chicks
fledging and these provided a much needed boost to the population. Rat
control is thought to have had a significant impact on the breeding success
and is to be continued this year.
As part of the ongoing keeper exchange programme, two bird keepers
from Chester Zoo joined the passerine field survey team and assisted with the
monitoring of the Mauritius Fody and Mauritius Olive White-eye populations
in the Black River Gorges National Park. It is hoped to eventually map the
distribution and territories of these two endemic species.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9875075" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56337101" page_num="" year="" vol="">
OBITUARY
JEFFERY BOSWALL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8504501" page_id="56337101"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Jeffery Boswall died aged 81 on August 15th 2012. Jeffery, who was
with the BBC Natural History Unit at Bristol for 29 years and later worked
for the RSPB (Royal Society for the Protection of Birds), wrote a number
of articles for the magazine in the late 1970s and 1980s. Checking through
these, I came up with a surprisingly long list, including articles on tool-use
by birds and related behaviour (Vol.83, No.2, pp. 88-97, No.3, pp.146-
159, No.4, pp.220-228 (1977), Vol.84, No.3, pp.162-166 (1978) &amp; Vol.89,
No.2, pp.94-108 (1983)), birds of Chengdu Zoo (Vol.92, No.l, pp.47-50
(1986)), some birds at three Chinese zoos (Vol.95, No.l, pp.31-36 (1989))
and a bird show in Moscow, arranged at the Zoological Museum during the
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.904333">
18th International Ornithological Congress in August 1982 (Vol.89, No.l,
pp.47-49 (1983)). An obituary was published in The Times , p.81, Saturday,
August 25 th 2012.
</reference>
<table confidence="0.968125333333333" page_id="56337102"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Rearing couas at Weltvogelpark Walsrode in Germany
by Anne Hoppmann.97
Mixed fortunes for society's adopted hombills.103
The Southern Screamer Chauna torquata
at Paignton Zoo Environmental Park
by Jo Gregson.105
Releasing macaws in Costa Rica
by Bryan Andrews.108
Native passerines in North American Zoos
by Justin C. Hickman.114
Having been an aviculturist for fifty years: Part 1
by Bernard Sayers.122
Book Reviews
Grassfinches in Australia.134
International Zoo Yearbook, Volume 46.137
Animals in the Blood: The Ken Smith Story.138
News &amp; Views.140
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
</table>
</algorithms>
