<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.4725076" page_id="56259688"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
*li
gL WICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 115
No. 1
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259689" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.984815548387097" page_id="56259689"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2009 as for 2008: British
Isles #18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please).
The subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the
Society later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of
the AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, ARCADIA, THE MOUNTS, TOTNES, DEVON TQ9 7QJ,
UK.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TNI 3 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail: Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have not
been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of a
particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history. Articles
should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the scientific
names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given. References
cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line drawings,
black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular point in
the article will be used where possible and should be clearly captioned. If
authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when submitting the
article and write their name on the back of each photograph. Tables and
graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be aware of
the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of the page
which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997594" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259689" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982475333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<table confidence="0.1735715" page_id="56259690"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
VoL 115 - No. 1 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2009
The Avicultural Society
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.984777333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259690" page_num="" year="" vol="">
FOR THE STUDY OF BRITISH AND FOREIGN BIRDS
IN THE WILD AND CAPTIVITY
OFFICERS AND COUNCIL
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.894754" page_id="56259690"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
As from March 28th 2009
President
R. C. J. Sawyer
Vice Presidents
F. Barnicoat (South Africa)
S, Bruslund Jensen (Germany)
M. Curzon MBE (UK)
Dr W. Grummt (Germany)
C J. S. Marler (UK)
Dr H. Quinque (France)
R L. Restall (Venezuela)
Dr R. Wilkinson (UK)
Honorary Editor
M. Ellis
Honorary Secretary - Treasurer
R B oulden
Members of Council
</table>
<figure confidence="0.746352125" page_id="56259690"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
R. S. Abrey
P. Convy
J. A. Ellis
Mrs L. Gardner
R. B. Girling
N. R. Hewston
G. Masson
S. Pyper
V. P. Sargent
P. G. Schofield
P. Stocks
J. G. Thu f low
B. Tremlett
J, Trollope
Ms R. Wiseman
Chairman C J.S. Marler
</figure>
<page confidence="0.883308" page_id="56259691"  page_num="2" year="" vol="">
2
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8697185" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259691" page_num="2" year="" vol="">
THE COMPARATIVE BEHAVIOUR
OF HAND-REARED SPECTACLED THRUSHES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.975487405405405" page_id="56259691"  page_num="2" year="" vol="">
Turd us nudigensis
by Robin Restall
At the end of June 2008, the gardener brought me two nestling thrashes
that had fallen from their nest in a tree he had bumped something against.
One nestling was naked and its eyes were closed, the other had short quills
which were just breaking at the ends and its eyes were half-open. The
smaller nestling failed to survive but the second nestling was successfully
hand-reared. A week after it had been released a worker at the museum here
in Caracas, Venezuela, brought me two older young of the same species.
These notes describe the differences in the way the first nestling and the
second two birds behaved as they grew to independence.
The birds were Spectacled Thrashes (the species formerly named the
Bare-eyed Thrash) Turdus nudigensis. It is our common garden thrash in
Caracas and may be seen on lawns throughout the day searching for food,
exactly like a European Blackbird T. merula or a North American Robin T.
migratorius , and is about the same size as these two. Its alarm call is very
like that of a European Blackbird and the song of the territorial male is like
that of a young Blackbird that has not yet learned its full vocabularly. It
differs significantly, however, in also making a penetrating "mewing" sound
like that of the North American Catbird Dumetella carolinensis. Nestlings,
or much more likely, first-day fledglings, are raised all over the city every
year. People here are as incapable of leaving a baby bird on the ground
- where it would be fed by its parents - as they are in Europe and North
America. My neighbour hand-reared one last year and proudly released it
when he thought it was ready - only to watch it fly across the garden and
land on the lawn, where a cat dashed out from the shrubs, grabbed the bird
and was off in a flash!
The first two nestlings were apparently a couple of days apart in age.
The smaller nestling, that was naked and whose eyes were still closed, had
a broken leg; furthermore, it was bleeding from the bill and vent and its
faeces were black and very smelly. It died the same night. The surviving
bird begged readily and was one of the easiest birds to feed that I have ever
reared. I fed it on Kaytee Exact, a proprietary brand of rearing food for baby
birds, which is made and sold in the USA. It is claimed to be a complete
formula suitable for all kinds of birds. Various kinds of parrots are shown
on the label and, I guess, they are the prime market it is aimed at. I have
used the formula many times in the past and found it to be as good as the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.864477" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259692" page_num="3" year="" vol="">
RESTALL * SPECTACLED THRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.909614" page_id="56259692"  page_num="3" year="" vol="">
3
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999326170731707" page_id="56259692"  page_num="3" year="" vol="">
manufacturer claims. I made it into a somewhat loose pulpy consistency by
adding water to the dry mix and fed it to the baby thrash using the tip of the
handle of a teaspoon. All orphans and birds requiring isolation are kept in my
bathroom (having a separate bathroom from one's spouse is extraordinarily
convenient, especially when rearing baby birds and other creatures). The
bird seemed to recognise me when I entered the bathroom and would greet
me with a "I'm hungry" call and would watch me as I prepared the food,
and would instantly start begging as 1 approached it. At first it was kept in
an open false nest with a half-cover, then the cover was left off and later an
open shoebox lined with newspaper was used. Once the nestling reached the
standing and moving around the box stage it would, regardless of whether or
not it was hungry, squat lower and start wing-fluttering as 1 approached.
At about fledging time, it was moved into a roomy cage and placed on
the outside windowsill opposite my drawing board and computer, where I
sat and worked and the bird could see me come and go. It also watched my
wife come and go and anybody else who was around, and either ignored them
or watched them calmly. In contrast, I could tell by its change of posture,
agitation and/or alertness that it clearly recognised me. It would call me
with the "I'm here" location call, that presumably keeps parents aware of
where their fledgling chicks are. The call would change to a more insistent
"Feed me," if I had been away for a while, and then as I opened the cage
door, it would switch to the familiar urgent begging noise.
I experimented with its diet and tried to modify it by adding a little
crumbled yolk of hard-boiled egg, grated carrot, grated hard cheese, etc. As
a young man I learned a great deal from Frank Meaden about hand-rearing
birds and weaning them onto dry mixes, etc., and am always interested to
see how birds respond to different types of food. In this case the bird's
droppings always discouraged me from persisting with any variation to the
diet. The commercial formula always resulted in clean, neat, black and
white droppings, perfectly encased in transparent sacs. Any variation in
the diet resulted in imperfect sacs or green in the droppings. At the time I
was exchanging notes with lan Hinze in the UK, who had recently reared a
Blackbird. He had fed his bird with dog food. So, I experimented and tried
dog biscuits and those for cats. I soaked them long enough to soften them
and, at first, offered them on a spoon handle and then with my fingers. The
bird was very picky, refusing the buffy-coloured ones for both dogs and cats
and instead preferring the green ones and then the red ones.
The bird alternated between sitting quietly watching life in the garden,
and exploring its cage, often pulling up the comers of the newspaper on the
floor and pecking at whatever took its attention. One day I gave it a pot
containing some mealworms. These it watched with hawk-like fascination
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.917265" page_id="56259693"  page_num="4" year="" vol="">
4
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.956447" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259693" page_num="4" year="" vol="">
RESTALL * SPECTACLED THRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999796243902439" page_id="56259693"  page_num="4" year="" vol="">
for quite some time. Then, after a while, it picked up one and stood there
perfectly still - holding the mealworm in its bill. It hopped back down to the
dish and took another and returned to the perch with it, then more rapidly
hopped back down again and took a third mealworm. I could not contain
myself (so much for the detached scientist) and told the bird to get on and
eat them before they wriggled out of its bill and escaped. It took a fourth
mealworm and then expertly swallowed all four in two gulps, without losing
any. I soon began to feed it the pupae and beetles as well, which were all
eaten. Its order of preference was: first mealworms, second the pupae and
third the beetles.
One afternoon, another young thrush which was virtually identical
to mine, except for fewer spots on the breast (and was therefore a few
months older), flew to the cage and then into the room. I caught it and
after examining it, wondered what the reaction might be were I to put it in
the cage with my bird. I momentarily had dreams of keeping them with
the view to attempting to breed them later this year. It went into the cage
calmly and quietly, whereupon my bird attacked it furiously, refusing to let
go of the wing it was biting viciously. I therefore caught the newcomer and
immediately released it.
About three weeks after fledging my bird began singing. It was an
extended, sweet, gurgling subsong, typical of many birds and reminded
me of that of various young Jays Garrulus glandarius and Carrion Crows
Corvus corone I had reared while living in Spain. I have a Chinese bird
bath for thrashes. It is a modest-sized cage with a metal tray about 3cm
(l%in) deep, so in effect the whole cage is a bird bath. With the tray filled
with water, it is attached to the bird's cage with the doors open so that the
bird can pass from its cage into the bird bath. The Chinese train their birds
to bathe by closing the door once the bird is in the bath cage, and then take
the opportunity to clean its cage.
My bird happily went into the bath cage and would sit there looking
around, but would then hop back into its cage and would sometimes go back
and forth, but never once bathed. Six weeks after it arrived, the bird was
released in an ideal habitat, a small cove on the coast. The next day I saw it
there foraging by a stream that ran out of the wood and towards the beach.
The second two young were thought to have dropped, jumped or fallen
from their nest in a garden, though my guess is that they had already
fledged. My friend heard a tremendous commotion in the garden and went
to investigate. The young thrushes were being barked at by two guard dogs
which were in turn being dive-bombed by the young thrushes' parents, who
were intent on protecting their offspring. The young thrashes found their
way into my care, because it was believed they would not have survived the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.774295" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259694" page_num="5" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SPECTACLED THRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.868749" page_id="56259694"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
5
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99962968292683" page_id="56259694"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
attention of the dogs, or the cats in the next garden, were they to have been
put over the wall into the next-door garden. They were the most vociferous
and frightening young birds I have ever handled, keeping up a "yacking"
thrush alarm call and rocketing off in any direction at the slightest noise or
movement. The rescue scene must have been like bedlam. It had probably
been unnecessary to rescue the birds. This thrash is very common and
circumstances like these must be everyday occurrences all over the city
suburbs. I suspect that had they been left alone, their constant barracking,
combined with the attacks of the parents, would have deterred the dogs,
and the youngsters would soon have found a safe location to sit and wait
to be fed.
This time I fed the two young using a kind of syringe - a hand-feeder used
by Japanese birdkeepers to rear baby Java Sparrows Padda oryzivora. It is
not used like a normal syringe, but is loaded bit by bit by pushing food into
the end that goes into the bird's mouth. I used this gadget because the birds
would not stay still and would not gape. I had to force feed them for the first
day, but by the middle of the second day, they recognised the syringe in my
hand and readily gaped. Once their crops were full, they would sit quietly in
the shoebox, but as soon as the food had been digested a little, although not
enough for the birds to gape for more, they became as flighty and as noisy
as before. They could fly quite well and would fly around the bathroom
exploring. One would go off and a few minutes later the other would follow.
They could reach the basin and a couple of days later could make it up onto
the shower curtain rail. I used a small, mesh-covered carrying cage as their
&apos;home,' and they immediately took to this. They would go off and explore,
then stand quietly together behind the WC bowl for 10 minutes or so, before
one would fly up to the carrying cage, go in through the opening and settle
down inside. The other would soon fly up to join it and there they would
wait, sitting side by side, until I arrived to feed them. I continued to use the
syringe, which they accepted readily. One would often fly to me and land
on my head, back or shoulder, and the other would follow and invariably
land at my feet, and then jump up onto a foot.
A week or so after their arrival, I placed the two in the same cage the
previous thrash had been so happy in, and again placed it on the outside
windowsill. They immediately settled down in the cage and like the first
thrash, sat happily watching the world go by. One of the two would sit and
sing the same extended, rambling, gurgling subsong, that the first bird had
sang. For the first few days they continued to beg for food when I came by,
but then after the first feed began to refuse any further food. They ceased to
recognise me from afar and ignored me until I was close by. Although both
birds continued to beg for food, within a day or two they began to refuse to
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.96708" page_id="56259695"  page_num="6" year="" vol="">
6
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.933667" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259695" page_num="6" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SPECTACLED THRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.954483526315789" page_id="56259695"  page_num="6" year="" vol="">
take it from the syringe. I therefore switched to using the tip of the teaspoon
handle and they greedily took the food from this every time. I offered them
small, cat biscuits, which I had soaked long enough to soften them. One
would be taken from my fingers and greedily consumed, but when I offered
a second, they would turn their heads away. Soon they would only snatch
food from the side of the teaspoon handle and refused to take it directly.
Judging by the length of their tails, they were at the stage at which the first
bird continued to happily feed from the front of the spoon. I offered them
mealworms and these were looked at, but not with the same fascination the
first bird had shown. From then onwards I made the food more crumbly
and placed it on a saucer and put the soaked cat biscuits in a small bowl.
From then onwards they happily fed themselves and did not beg for food
again. I again offered them mealworms. One of the two took one and sat
on the perch almost motionless holding the mealworm in its bill. The other
bird immediately began a high-intensity wing fluttering, pleading, pathetic
sounding begging - with its bill open. Its sibling ignored it, bit the mealworm
a couple of times and then swallowed it. During the following few days,
they continued to feed from the bowls, but ignored the mealworms. One
bird sat in the water bowl, attempting to bathe, and completely emptied the
bowl in the process. They completely ignored the bath cage. They did not
even enter it to explore it.
They were later transferred to a large flight cage in my birdroom/
laboratory, where they became wild and independent almost immediately.
They used the large bird bath hung on the cage door, ate the regular softbill
mix and assorted soaked dog and cat biscuits, and quickly polished off a bowl
of mealworms. It was only then that they began tearing up the newspaper
on the cage floor, exploring or searching for insects. I was happy to release
them soon afterwards in an orchard in the country.
Rearing two young birds together clearly worked much better, as they
interacted with each other and their leaming/exploring was obviously greater.
What surprised me, however, was the way they 'trained me' to feed them, by
progressively refusing and accepting food. Without having given it much
thought before, I suppose I assumed that the parents did the weaning, but
clearly the youngsters seemed to have their own in-built programming.
Avicultural Society Vice President Robin Restall painted the illustrations
for and is one of the authors of Birds of Northern South America (reviewed
in the Avicultural Magazine Vol.113, No.2, pp. 89-90 (2007)). Robin resides
in Caracas, Venezuela. E-mail: robinrestall@gmail.com
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.986346" page_id="56259696"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
7
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.647860666666667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259696" page_num="7" year="" vol="">
HAND-REARING WHITE-BROWED COUCALS
Centropus superciliosus
by Louise Peat
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998231694444445" page_id="56259696"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
The Cuculiformes is a fascinating order that has two distinct families:
Musophagidae (turacos) and Cuculidae (cuckoos). The subfamily
Centropinae contains almost 30 species of coucals of which the White-
browed species is the only representative in captivity in Europe according
to the ISIS database (2008).
The White-browed Coucal occurs on Socotra Island and in south-west
Arabia and has a wide distribution in Africa, from eastern Sudan, Ethiopia
and Somalia, southwards through Uganda, Kenya and Tanzania, to Angola,
Zambia, Malawi, Namibia, Botswana, Zimbabwe, Mozambique and South
Africa. Clements (2007) listed four subspecies: C. 5. superciliosus, C. s.
sokotrae, C. s. loandae and C. 5. burchelli (fasciipygialis), however, other
recent authors (e.g. Sinclair &amp; Ryan, 2003; Hockey, Dean &amp; Ryan, 2005) treat
the latter as a full species, which they call Burchell's Coucal C. burchelli.
The White-browed Coucal inhabits rank vegetation, thickets, bush
and wooded grassland, often near water. It feeds mostly on grasshoppers,
crickets, locusts and beetles, along with lizards, frogs, mice and young birds
and eggs.
It is monogamous. The nest is a large and untidy domed structure with
a side entrance. It is built of dry grasses and twigs and is usually lined with
leaves. It is usually built in reeds, a bush or tree, especially one with tangles
of creepers or thick foliage. Three to five white eggs are laid, which are
incubated mainly by the male for a period of 14-15 days. If disturbed the
chicks emit a foul-smelling black cloacae liquid (del Hoyo et al. 1997). They
fledge at 18-20 days, at which point they are barely able to fly and mostly
creep about waiting for their parents to feed them.
Here at the Cotswold Wildlife Park in Oxfordshire we first began working
with the White-browed Coucal in 2004, following the arrival of six birds from
Parc Paradisio, Belgium. Three went to Exmoor Zoo to set up a breeding
pair there, with an unrelated pair and a female offspring being retained
here. Our birds are housed in an aviary with two further representatives of
the order Cuculiformes, the Guira Cuckoo Guira guira and the Roadrunner
Geococcyx californianus. The three species cohabit peaceably and rarely
interact with each other.
In 2005 we successfully hand-reared a White-browed Coucal, following
which the parents went on to rear a further three young. Since then the
parents have successfully reared a further nine young.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.508283" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259697" page_num="8" year="" vol="">
PEAT - WHITE-BROWED COUCAL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987758512820513" page_id="56259697"  page_num="8" year="" vol="">
Early on in 2008 the breeding pair hatched several clutches of eggs,
but only one chick survived. Due to the long list of collections that have
expressed an interest in obtaining this species and the age of the breeding
pair, we decided to intervene and maximise the number of young raised in
2008. Three clutches (a total of 16 eggs) were taken for artificial incubation.
Fourteen of the eggs hatched.
Using information gained when we hand-reared the chick in 2005, e-mail
information on coua rearing at Walsrode and the article in the Avicultural
Magazine about the hand-rearing of this species at Exmoor Zoo (Gibson,
2007), I put together a hand-rearing protocol. Using further information
gained during 2008, this has been tweaked here and there, resulting in the
following revised protocol which is, I believe, comprehensive and easy to
use.
Hand-rearing protocol
Hatch weight 6.7g-7.9g
Brooder temperature 35*C (95*F)
The chicks are kept hydrated by having distilled water from a syringe
carefully dribbled onto their beaks. This is done every few hours during the
first 24 hours. The water is generally lapped up by the chicks. They tend
not to defecate during the first 24 hours. The chicks, which are blind and
covered in white hair, are kept in small baskets with tissue substrate. They
are generally alert and responsive to noise stimulation and touch. When
touched they gape. Their movements are jerky.
Age 1 day
Average intake per feed 0.5g Average growth rate 6.49%
During the early days the chicks are fed pinkie mice with the milk sac
and all sharp bones removed, and waxworms with the head removed. Each
item is placed in luke warm distilled water for a few seconds immediately
prior to being dropped in the chick's mouth. One feed per day is dusted
with Nutrobal (multivitamin powder). Chicks are fed only when they
gape and never receive more than 10% of their morning body weight per
feed (generally they receive far less). The amount of food is decreased or
increased according to their daily weight gain which is carefully monitored.
They receive six to seven feeds between 7.00am-10.00pm, being fed initially
every two hours to two and a half hours.
Their hydration levels are monitored closely, with their faeces being a
good indication. They should normally be enclosed in a faecal sac. If they
are not, it may indicate that there is a problem. Raising the level of humidity
in the brooder will encourage defecation.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.177696" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259698" page_num="9" year="" vol="">
PEAT - WHITE-BROWED COUCAL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.96372" page_id="56259698"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
9
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.979752684210526" page_id="56259698"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
Age 2 days
Average intake per feed Q.8g Average growth rate 22.9%
Chicks should defecate after every other feed. If this does not occur, handling
can induce defecation or stimulating the cloaca with a warm, damp cloth
can be effective.
Age 3 days
Average intake per feed lg Average growth rate 24.32%
Age 4 days
Average intake per feed 1.5g Average growth rate 29.87%
Slits of eyes should be apparent now.
Age 5 days
Brooder temperature reduced to 34*C (93.2*F)
Feeds reduced to every three hours
Average intake per feed 1.8g Average growth rate 27.79%
Pin-feathers begin to protrude on edges of wings and those of the tail begin
to appear.
Age 6 days
Average intake per feed 2g Average growth rate 27.39%
From this point they tend to defecate after every feed.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.989877" page_id="56259698"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
Age 7 days
Average intake per feed 2g-2.5g Average growth rate 20.54%
Pin-feathers appear along sides of torso.
Age 8 days
Average intake per feed 2.5g-3g Average growth rate 20.5%
Age 9 days
Average intake per feed 3g Average growth rate 17.31%
Age 10 days
Brooder temperature reduced to 32*C (89.6*F)
Average intake per feed up to 3.5g Average growth rate 13.85%
Crickets with their legs, wings and head removed introduced into the diet.
Age 11 days
Average intake per feed 4g Average growth rate 11.02%
By now the body should be covered with pin-feathers.
Age 12 days
Average growth rate 12.25%
Age 13 days
Brooder temperature reduced to 30*C (86*F)
Average growth rate 10.42%
</table>
<page confidence="0.991032" page_id="56259699"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
10
</page>
<table confidence="0.750521" page_id="56259699"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
PEAT - WHITE-BROWED COUCAL
Age 14 days
Average growth rate 8.27%
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.8424115" page_id="56259699"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
The feathers should be emerging from their sheaths and the young should
be starting to explore their surroundings.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.4056285" page_id="56259699"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
David Edgington
An adult White-browed Coucal photographed in the wild in Africa.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.165717" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259700" page_num="11" year="" vol="">
PEAT - WHITE-BROWED COUCAL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.926252" page_id="56259700"  page_num="11" year="" vol="">
11
</page>
<figure confidence="0.61336025" page_id="56259700"  page_num="11" year="" vol="">
Louise Peat
Chick at about two to three days old.
Aged sixteen days.
Louise Peat
</figure>
<page confidence="0.9887" page_id="56259701"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
12
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.300901" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259701" page_num="12" year="" vol="">
PEAT - WHITE-BROWED COUCAL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.966982487179487" page_id="56259701"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
Age 15 days
Average intake per feed 5g Average growth rate 8.73%
Beginning to make adult-like sounds.
Age 16 days Average growth rate 8.05%
Brooder temperature reduced to 26*C (78.8*F)
Fully feathered.
Age 17 days Average growth rate 4.92%
Food intake drops and their weight levels off as they get ready to start to fly.
As their feet develop and their grip gets stronger they should be attempting
to perch.
Age 18 days Average growth rate 3.33%
Generally able to perch from this point onwards.
Age 19 days Average growth rate 3.33%
Attempt to fly.
Age 20 days Average growth rate 0.84%
Room temperature 20*C (68*F)
Two to three feeds a day along with all-day access to the adult diet as the
young are encouraged to feed themselves.
Notes on rearing
All of the chicks are kept in separate baskets to enable better individual
monitoring and reduce the risk of them injuring each other at feeding time.
From day 15 onwards, however, the chicks are placed together in a hospital
cage. At this stage minimal aggression is observed (generally pre-feeding
excitement only) and the chicks generally spend time in close proximity
to each other. It is important though to always take care to place together
birds that are of a similar age, otherwise the younger birds will tend to get
trampled on by the older ones.
Initially, the chicks were weighed several times a day, but each time they
were handled they became stressed and stopped feeding, therefore, they are
weighed once a day only in the morning 10 minutes before the first feed. As
the chicks grow older though, it is advisable to give them a genera! physical
check each afternoon, which entails handling them for a second time each
day. They develop rapidly and differences can be seen from feed to feed,
with pin-feathers growing rapidly throughout the day. It is also important
to check the development of the legs and toes. From day three the chicks
should be pushing themselves up with their legs in order to reach the food
and, if they are not doing this, it could indicate that there is a problem.
The chicks resort to a delightful olfactory defence mechanism when they
are stressed - they produce smelly, runny, brown liquid faeces, after which
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.177503" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259702" page_num="13" year="" vol="">
PEAT - WHITE-BROWED COUCAL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999279" page_id="56259702"  page_num="13" year="" vol="">
13
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999403384615385" page_id="56259702"  page_num="13" year="" vol="">
they are very subdued for a few minutes. The first time this happens it can be
quite concerning. The first time it happened to me, I was certainly fooled into
thinking that I had a very sick bird on my hands. One particularly nervous
chick was an habitual offender. The slightest change in routine would upset
it - even hearing a different voice in the room whilst it was being fed, would
result in an odorous event!
If a chick is sluggish and unresponsive, it should be checked for bloating.
This occurred quite early on with the chick which had the lowest hatch weight.
It appeared very uncomfortable, was extremely bloated and quickly became
unresponsive. Because we were worried that it might have an infection, we
placed it on a four day course of 2.5% oral Baytril (one small drop on its
food each day), which was followed by a five day course of probiotic. The
chick responded slowly to treatment and eventually began feeding without
assistance. Strangely, this chick lacked any black markings on its tongue
(which the others had) and, in hindsight, I cannot help but wonder if this
chick would have survived had it been in the care of its parents. Having
made a full recovery following the treatment, it grew into a healthy looking
character and thrived alongside its siblings.
Chicks should remain keen and eager to feed. Their appetites vary
throughout the various developmental stages. They have the largest appetites
when the feathers begin to emerge from their sheaths. As a general rule,
once the birds weigh between 90g-100g (at 18=20 days), they become much
more interested in their surroundings and are ready to fledge.
Summary of 2008 breeding results
In total three clutches of eggs were taken. From the first clutch, six
chicks hatched, two of which did not pass normal faecal sacs. These two
chicks died in quick succession and without warning, one after passing a
large quantity of faeces overnight. Both had been active and alert up until
the point of death. The decision was taken to euthanase a third chick from
the clutch. This chick hatched with an overshot lower mandible and as the
bird grew, the left side of its body developed at a slower rate than the right
side. Furthermore, from the day it hatched its left leg bone between the foot
and ankle did not grow and its left eye began to bulge in the eye socket. I
have never come across this before and would be interested to hear from
anyone who may have an explanation for this condition.
Over the course of the year a total of 11 chicks were successfully reared,
each one had a different character and varied needs. From mid-July until
the end of October, my life revolved around these needy characters and at
the end of the breeding season I found myself feeling a little lost.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.9961" page_id="56259703"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
14
</page>
<table confidence="0.92656625" page_id="56259703"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
PEAT - WHITE-BROWED COUCAL
Louise Peat
Fledged young coucal aged just over 20 days.
Growth rate of White-browed Coucal chicks
</table>
<figure confidence="0.260182333333333" page_id="56259704"  page_num="15" year="" vol="">
PEAT - WHITE-BROWED COUCAL
15
Louise Peat
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.951628" page_id="56259704"  page_num="15" year="" vol="">
Unlike the others, this chick lacked any black markings on its tongue. It was the chick
with the lowest hatch weight and had some feeding and health problems. However it
responded slowly to treatment and eventually began feeding without assistance.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995271" page_id="56259705"  page_num="16" year="" vol="">
16
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.831061" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259705" page_num="16" year="" vol="">
PEAT - WHITE-BROWED COUCAL
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.732606933333333">
Clements, J. F. 2007. The Clements Checklist of the Birds of the World Sixth Edition.
Christopher Helm, London and Cornell University Press, USA.
del Hoyo, J., Elliott, A. and Sargatal, J. (eds.). 1997. Handbook of the Birds of the World Y oh
4. Sandgrouse to Cuckoos. Lynx Edicionc, Barcelona, Spain.
Gibson, D. 2007. Hand-rearing a White-browed Coucal at Exmoor Zoo. Avicultural Magazine
113,4:166-169.
Hockey, P. A. R., Dean, W. R. J. and Ryan, P. G. 2005. Roberts - Birds of Southern Africa Vllth
Edition. The Trustees of the John Voelcker Bird Book Fund, Cape Town, South Africa.
ISIS. 2008. International Species Information System. Website: http:www.isis.org (accessed
September 2008).
Sinclair, I. and Ryan, P. 2003. Birds of Africa south of the Sahara. Struik, Cape Town, South
Africa.
Louise Peat is Registrar at the Cotswold Wildlife Park, Burford, Oxon.
0X18 4JW, UK. E-mail:records@cotswoldwildlifepark.co.uk/Website:
www. cotswoldwildlifepark. co. uk
</reference>
<equation confidence="0.6967555" page_id="56259705"  page_num="16" year="" vol="">
*
* *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.666892" genericHeader="introduction" page_id="56259705" page_num="16" year="" vol="">
CHESTER ZOO NEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.815736636363636" page_id="56259705"  page_num="16" year="" vol="">
In recent months Chester Zoo has acquired several new birds, including
White-bellied Go-away Birds Corythaixoides leucogaster and Hamerkops
Scopus umbretta. They will be among the many African species housed in
the new Tsavo Bird Safari Walk-through Aviary that is due to be opened
later this years.
Other new arrivals include Rufous-bellied Niltavas Niltava sundara,
Collared Grosbeaks Mycerobas affinis and Black-and-white Laughing-
thrushes Garrulax bicolor , for which zoo staff are to hold the studbook.
Chester Zoo continues to provide funding for wardens, the translocation
of birds and education programmes for the Katala Foundation's Philippine
Cockatoo Conservation Programme (PCCP), which is also supported
by Loro Parque Foundation (LPF), CEPA (Conservation des Especes et
des Populations Animales (including ZooParc de Beauval)) and ZGAP
(Zoological Society for the Conservation of Species and Populations). From
a low of some 22-25 birds, the PCCP has through its efforts during its first
10 years, overseen a rise in the number of Philippine Cockatoos Cacatua
haematuropyia on Rasa Island to, in 2008, an estimated 205 birds. Last
year wardens monitored 32 nests, six of which were new, and 49 fledglings
were ringed (banded).
Chester Zoo is also continuing to provide funding for work with the
Visayan Writhe-billed or Rufous-headed Hornbill Aceros waldeni on the
island of Panay.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.989458" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259706" page_num="17" year="" vol="">
THE UNUSUAL NESTING BEHAVIOUR OF A PAIR OF
WHITE-BROWED COUCALS Centropus supercitiosus
AT EXMOOR ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997778" page_id="56259706"  page_num="17" year="" vol="">
17
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.974903388888889" page_id="56259706"  page_num="17" year="" vol="">
by Derek Gibson
Readers of the magazine may recall that in the Avicultural Magazine
Vol.112, Mo.2, pp.49-52 (2006) &amp; Vol.113, No.4, pp.166 -169 (2007), I
described various aspects of the husbandry of this species here at Exmoor
Zoo. In the following notes I concentrate on various aspects of the White-
browed Coucal's nesting behaviour here at Exmoor. The zoo now houses
two adult pairs, one on display and the other off display. The latter pair are
the subject of this account.
Both birds were obtained from private collections, the female on
November 13th 2005 when she was about four years of age and the male on
February 24th 2008. He was hatched on June 1st 2007. On March 1st 2008,
after a period of quarantine, both birds were placed in an aviary measuring
8ft long x 6ft wide x 8ft high (approx. 2.4m long x 1.8m wide x 2.4m high),
with three-quarters of the roof covered to give protection from the more
inclement north Devon weather, but with no heating provided. There are
no plants growing in the aviary, but it is densely perched with branches of
willow Salix sp., Beech Fagus sylvatica and Ash Fraxinus excelsior . The
male was placed in the aviary first and was joined by the female two days
later. She had in the past been a rather bullish bird and had not tolerated
any other bird in her aviary.
An Sin x 8in x 6in high (approx. 20.5cm x 20.5cm x 15.5cm high) nest
basket is positioned 1ft (30.5cm) below the roof of the aviary. There is also
a standard design parrot nest box measuring 6in x 6in x 1ft high (15.5cm x
15.5cm x 30.5cm high), with a lin (2.5cm) deep covering of wood chips on
the bottom and with a 2 !Z i:o (6.5cm) diameter entrance hole. At the beginning
of August it was noticed that the female was spending time inside the nest
box, normally in the morning when the aviary was being serviced by the
keeper. She was occasionally joined inside the box by the male.
In the wild this species is recorded as making a large, bulky and untidy
domed nest, with a side entrance. It is built of twigs and grass, sometimes of
grass alone, with the inside, which lacks a distinctive cup, lined with leaves
(Payne et al. 2005). With our second pair here at Exmoor (the subject of
this account) the open nest basket was, so far as we know, never inspected
and certainly no nesting material was ever placed in it. Nor was any nesting
material taken into the nest box, though there was plenty of material available
on the floor of the aviary, should the pair wished to have used it.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996306" page_id="56259707"  page_num="18" year="" vol="">
18
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.580861" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259707" page_num="18" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-BROWED COUCAL
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.73491">
Derek Gibson
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996060076923077" page_id="56259707"  page_num="18" year="" vol="">
Aviary housing pair of White-browed Coucals.
On August 2nd 2008, the female was once again inside the nest box and,
this time, appeared for only a minute or two before making her way back
inside the box. As with a great many species, the White-browed Coucal
does not seem to tolerate human inspection of its nest site. We were keen,
however, to know what was going on inside the box, so, the decision was
taken that when an opportunity occurred, a brief inspection of the inside of
the box would take place. When this happened, much to our surprise, three
white eggs were found in the box. Over the following 10 days the female
was seen outside the nest box on only a few occasions and, at no time, was
the male seen to enter the nest box. On August 17th, when the nest box was
inspected again, the three eggs were still there, but as they had gone over the
incubation period, all three were removed and candled and, unfortunately,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.491691" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259708" page_num="19" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-BROWED COUCAL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995898" page_id="56259708"  page_num="19" year="" vol="">
19
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.798361">
Derek Gibson
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9973806" page_id="56259708"  page_num="19" year="" vol="">
Parrot nest box in top right-hand corner of aviary.
all found to be clear. It was the first time this female had laid and, given the
young age of the male, we looked forward to the pair, hopefully, reproducing
in 2009. However, a second clutch of eggs was laid in the nest box. These
were incubated but like those of the first clutch proved to be clear.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.533645">
Reference
</subsectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.9556762">
Payne, R., Sorenson, M. and Klitz, K. 2006. The Cuckoos. Oxford University Press, Oxford
and New York.
Derek Gibson is Head Keeper at Exmoor Zoo, South Stowford, Bratton
Fleming, Nr Barnstaple, North Devon, UK. Website:www. exmoorzoo.co.uk/
E-mail:exmoorzoo@btconnect. com &amp; derek. r.gibson@htinternet. com
</reference>
<page confidence="0.986606" page_id="56259709"  page_num="20" year="" vol="">
20
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.959875" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259709" page_num="20" year="" vol="">
THE SOCIETY'S VISIT TO BERLIN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.984469736842106" page_id="56259709"  page_num="20" year="" vol="">
by Nigel Hewston
Twenty-six members of the Avicultural Society and their guests travelled
to Berlin on September 26th 2008 and enjoyed an extremely interesting
and enjoyable weekend visiting the city's two great zoos. The weekend
was greatly enhanced by the very generous hospitality with which we were
greeted at both zoos. Our host and guide for the weekend was Dr Wolfgang
Grummt, former Director of Tier park Berlin, who kindly arranged for us to
meet and be guided by Assistant Curator, Birds, Dr Martin Kaiser at Tierpark
Berlin and, at Zoo Berlin, by Curator Heiner Klos, who is responsible for the
carnivores, nocturnal animals, primates, bears, seals and penguins.
We arrived on Friday from various UK airports and used Berlin's
excellent public transport system to make our way by train and tram to our
base at the Abacus Tierpark Hotel, just opposite Tierpark Berlin in the east
of the city, where despite the late arrival of the bulk of the party, we were
met with a warm welcome and a welcome hot meal. Thus fortified and
refreshed with a pilsner or two, we were ready for sleep, in preparation for
a full day at Tierpark Berlin on Saturday.
The size of the zoo surprised those (most) of us who had not visited it
before. One of the largest in Europe, it is set in a wooded park with many
large enclosures for hoofstock and other mammals. There are breeding herds
of both African Elephant Loxodonta africana and Asian Elephants Elephas
maximus, which have as the centrepiece of their indoor quarters a large tank
housing an active group of Caribbean Manatees Trichechus m. manatus.
The bird collection is large and varied. Pelicans are a feature, with large
numbers of several species. Pelicans breed regularly at Tierpark Berlin,
usually indoors in the winter quarters (as seems to generally be the case with
these birds in northern Europe). They are free to roam about the tierpark
and make a striking, if incongruous, display among the formal flowerbeds.
Waterfowl are well represented, with Flying Steamer Ducks Tachyeres
patachonicus and breeding Chinese Mergansers Mergus squamatus standing
out as new species for me. Large domed aviaries also house gulls, shorebirds,
ibises and other wetland and marine birds. I particularly enjoyed seeing the
breeding colony of Little Pied Cormorants Phalacrocorax melanoleucus .
Tropical species are housed in the Alfred Brehm Cat House in individual
aviaries and a large 1,1 OOsq m (approx. 12,000sq ft) walk-through enclosure.
Groups represented and, mostly breeding, in the smaller aviaries include
hornbilis, barbets, bulbuls, babblers and roadrunners. In the walk-through
are ovenbirds Furnarius sp. with their mud nests built onto the framework
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.712199" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259710" page_num="21" year="" vol="">
HEWSTON - SOCIETY'S VISIT TO BERLIN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997719" page_id="56259710"  page_num="21" year="" vol="">
21
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997251780487805" page_id="56259710"  page_num="21" year="" vol="">
of the enclosure, barbets, turacos, African Jaqanas Actophilornis africana
- incubating at the time of our visit - Freckled Duck Stictonetta naevosa and
other waterfowl. Also, African starlings and a number of pigeon species.
The birds share their habitat with fruit bats.
Birds of prey are something of a speciality, with a varied collection of
owls and several species of eagles, including the massive S teller's Sea Eagle
Haliaeetuspelagicus and Harpy Eagle Harpia harpyja. Vultures are housed
in a huge aviary which is large enough to allow the smaller species to soar
when weather conditions are suitable and has a cliff face at the back.
We enjoyed a very good lunch at the restaurant (which also houses the
aquarium) at the kind invitation of Dr Bernhard Blaszkiewitz who, after
having been Director of Tierpark Berlin since the 1990s, has more recently
become the first Director of both the city's zoos, which are now managed
as one collection.
After lunch we continued our tour, one of the highlights of which for me
was the pheasantry, which houses not only a nice collection of pheasants,
but alongside them a range of laughingthrushes and liocichlas, a number of
which are breeding there. Tierpark Berlin is one of the few European zoos
to regularly breed the threatened Omei Shan Liocichla Liocichla omeiensis.
We were shown a male which was still breeding successfully at 20 years
of age.
Neotropical birds are housed in a section of the walk-through crocodile
house which houses tortoises and terrapins. There we found a range of
tanagers, breeding Red-headed Marshbirds Amblyramphus holosericeus
and Sunbittems Eurypyga helias feeding a chick. Hummingbirds have also
bred in this house in the past.
Cranes are well represented and it was a treat to see Siberian Cranes
Grus leucogeranus calling and displaying. They breed regularly there, but
artificial insemination has proved necessary to obtain fertile eggs. In the
off-show aviaries we saw young birds, including young cranes, storks and
Goliath Heron Ardea goliath , as well as many waterfowl and other species,
along with extra breeding pairs of softbills and other birds to supplement
those on display to visitors.
Despite spending the whole day at the zoo, I doubt whether any of us saw
all of it. I certainly did not. Dr and Frau Grammt joined us for dinner and
the next morning Dr Grummt led us across the city to Zoo Berlin. This is
one of the oldest zoos in Europe, with many historic buildings alongside state
of the art modem exhibits. Heiner, who is the son of former Director Prof.
Dr Heinz-George Klos, was just the person to provide us with an historical
perspective, as well as an insight into the latest developments.
Among these is the hippopotamus house, where we were privileged to
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.990001" page_id="56259711"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
22
</page>
<table confidence="0.9000372" page_id="56259711"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
HEWSTON - SOCIETY'S VISIT TO BERLIN
(c) Joe Blossom
Black-necked Crane Grus nigricollis at Tierpark Berlin.
(c) Joe Blossom
Oriental White Stork Ciconia boyciana also at Tierpark Berlin.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.702068" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259712" page_num="23" year="" vol="">
HEWSTON - SOCIETY'S VISIT TO BERLIN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.982278" page_id="56259712"  page_num="23" year="" vol="">
23
</page>
<table confidence="0.756765666666667" page_id="56259712"  page_num="23" year="" vol="">
J
Steller's Sea Eagle at Tierpark Berlin,
(c) Joe Blossom
</table>
<page confidence="0.993136" page_id="56259713"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
24
</page>
<table confidence="0.867079" page_id="56259713"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
HEWSTON - SOCIETY'S VISIT TO BERLIN
(c)Joe Blossom
Both zoos h ave I) it I n 1 31 i m ii Pelicans Pelicuttus cvispus .
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.712178" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259714" page_num="25" year="" vol="">
HEWSTON - SOCIETY'S VISIT TO BERLIN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99532" page_id="56259714"  page_num="25" year="" vol="">
25
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.996388463414634" page_id="56259714"  page_num="25" year="" vol="">
be taken for a look behind the scenes. The house houses both the large and
pygmy hippos, Hippopotamus amphibius and Hexaprotodon liberiensis
and African waterfowl, including Hartlaub's Duck Pteronetta hartlaubi.
Although we were all obviously interested in the bird collection, like the
tierpark the zoo is packed with other delights. Those in our party who know
about these matters found the small cats and the way they are exhibited very
special and, the nocturnal house, was excellent, with very active Aardvarks
Orycteropus afer the highlight (or twilight?) for me. The aquarium is a
large, apparently historic building with three floors (it was rebuilt after
the Second World War, during which much of the zoo was destroyed and
the collection reduced from 4,000 to just 91 specimens). The life-size
dinosaur at its entrance was engulfed by wild Red Squirrels Sciurus vulgaris
playing on its tail. Inside the aquarium, the ground floor is given over to an
extensive series of geographical tropical marine exhibits, in which the coral
is as impressive as the fish. Other exhibits include some very large sharks,
rays and morays. Reptiles are housed on the first floor and amphibians and
invertebrates on the second floor.
The bird facilities include a number of large aviaries housing waterfowl,
storks, ibises, vultures and birds of prey and there are enclosures for cranes
and pelicans. There is also a refrigerated penguin exhibit and a large comer
of the zoo is given over to more traditional houses and aviaries housing
a wide range of birds. The pheasantry is a long house containing much
more than pheasants - we also saw Kagu Rhynochetos jubatus, a Trumpet
Manucode Manucodia keraudrenii, which obligingly called and displayed,
Channel-billed Cuckoos Scythrops novaehollandiae (the world's largest
parasitic cuckoo), waders, weaver colonies, White-backed Australian
Magpies Gymnorhina tibicen hypoleuca , curassows, Pied Egrets Egretta
plicata and many more unusual species. This building also houses North
Island Brown Kiwis Apteryx australis mantelli which, unsurprisingly at
midday, we were not lucky enough to see. Zoo Berlin is one of the few
institutions outside New Zealand which regularly breeds kiwis. At the end
of this range of aviaries is a wader and seabird exhibit with a wave machine.
Next to this aviary are the zoo's Andean Flamingos Phoenicoparrus andinus
and James's P jamesi. Although their relatively small enclosure with its
small number of flamingos is not necessarily the sort of set up one would
recommend for breeding flamingos, the zoo has been repeatedly successful
with these two difficult species, both of which were feeding healthy chicks
at the time of our visit.
The unimposing entrance to the nearby tropical bird house, made the
further surprises and delights we found inside all the more impressive.
The house has a large number of aviaries housing single species or small
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.993457" page_id="56259715"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
26
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.921957" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259715" page_num="26" year="" vol="">
HEWSTON - SOCIETY'S VISIT TO BERLIN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996781769230769" page_id="56259715"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
communities. Most are linked to outdoor flights and there are also smaller
indoor enclosures for more delicate softbills, some practical cages for African
and Australian finches, as well as a large central aviary. The path leads on into
a south-east Asian walk-through, which houses Lesser Malayan Chevrotain
or Mouse Deer Tragulus javanicus, as well as a wide range of softbills,
pigeons and other birds. There is then a smaller African walk-through with
a linked outdoor aviary. There is also a series of indoor/outdoor hombill
aviaries. Another door leads directly into the parrot house, which again has
a large number of indoor and indoor/outdoor enclosures in which, despite
a very obvious mouse problem, the large and varied collection looked very
well and happy.
On the Monday morning we were free to revisit the zoos or explore the
city, before meeting up at the airport and comparing notes. We had expected
large and interesting zoos, but the size and variety of the bird collections
at both zoos had taken many of us by surprise. The city must be unique in
that history has presented it with not one but two world-class zoos. I must
mention again the warm hospitality we received, which added so much to
our enjoyment of the weekend. Special thanks must go to Dr Grummt, who
spent two whole days and evenings with us (I hope I have his energy when
I am in my eighties!). We were given admission and guidebooks to both
zoos, lunch at the tierpark, were guided by senior staff, and really could not
have been looked after better.
Thanks are also due to Mike Curzon and Christopher Marler for arranging
another superb weekend. This was my third Avicultural Society European
weekend. On each trip I have enjoyed great company, and am very much
looking forward to our next trip.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.313019666666667" page_id="56259715"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
* * *
THE AGE OF THE SUPERZOO
Chester Zoo recently unveiled a #225 million (approx. US$320 million)
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.944075111111111" page_id="56259715"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
expansion plan, which it was reported "could usher in the age of the
superzoo." An enormous biodome, which will cost #90 million (approx.
US$128 million) to construct, will house animals of the African rainforest,
including a wide variety of birds, along with Gorillas Gorilla gorilla.
Chimpanzees Pan troglodytes , Okapi Okapia johnsoni, amphibians, reptiles,
fishes and invertebrates. The zoo which has 1.3 million visitors a year, more
than any other zoo in the UK, will seek planning permission for the first
phase later this year and is hopeful that the project will be completed by
2018. For further information visit:www.chesterzoo.org
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.993931" page_id="56259716"  page_num="27" year="" vol="">
27
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.698651" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259716" page_num="27" year="" vol="">
THE PARENT-REARING OF HOODED PITTA CHICKS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.26803" page_id="56259716"  page_num="27" year="" vol="">
Pitta sordida mulleri IN A MIXED SPECIES
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.758043" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259716" page_num="27" year="" vol="">
WALK-THROUGH EXHIBIT AT ZSL LONDON ZOO
by Nicholas Ackroyd
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99062703030303" page_id="56259716"  page_num="27" year="" vol="">
In 2008 two Hooded Pitta chicks Pitta sordida mulleri were successfully
parent-reared in the recently refurbished Blackburn Pavilion tropical bird
house at ZSL London Zoo. A key factor in the success was the species-
specific feeding system. This provided an almost unlimited supply of
earthworms and other rearing food to the parent birds even when the keeping
staff were not present. The pair successfully incubated the eggs and reared
the chicks to independence despite being on show to the public in the newly
planted mixed species exhibit.
In the wild
The Hooded Pitta is widely distributed from northern India, across and
down through south-east Asia. According to Erritzoe &amp; Erritzoe (1998) it
found in India, Bangladesh, Myanmar (Burma), Thailand, Laos, Kampuchea,
Vietnam, China, the Nicobar Islands to Sumatra, Borneo, Java, Sulawesi,
New Guinea, the Bismarck and Sulu Archipelagos and the Philippines. They
listed 13 subspecies, while Clements (2007) listed 12, with P s. mulleri
occurring in extreme southern Thailand, the northern Malay Peninsula,
Greater Sunda Islands and west Sulu Island.
They are generally encountered in forested and woodland habitats,
including overgrown plantations, orchards and scrub, up to an altitude of
about 2,000m (6,500ft).
This pitta measures approximately 16cm-19cm (6 1 /4in-7 1 /2in) in length. It
is a predominantly green bird with a black head and beak (some subspecies,
though not P s. mulleri , have a dark/chocolate brown crown). The upper
wing-coverts, lower rump and upper tail-coverts are azure blue and it has a
white wing patch that is visible when it flies and displays. Its upper belly
and tail are black, the latter broadly or narrowly tipped with blue or wholly
black (Erritzoe &amp; Erritzoe, 1998), and its lower belly and under tail-coverts
are bright red.
In the wild the Hooded Pitta's diet includes invertebrates, such as ants,
beetles, earthworms, snails, etc., and invertebrate larvae. It may also feed
on fallen fruits and berries, which it finds on the ground.
When nesting in the wild, both adults build the ball-shaped nest of
loosely woven bamboo leaves, roots and grass, which is then lined with
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997438" page_id="56259717"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
28
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.901105" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259717" page_num="28" year="" vol="">
ACKROYD - HOODED PITTA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970106333333333" page_id="56259717"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
softer material. The nest is constructed on the ground in thick cover. There
may be a flattened pathway in front of the nest.
Housing at ZSL London Zoo
The breeding pair of DNA sexed Hooded Pittas arrived at the zoo in
2006. Both birds were captive-bred at Burgers' Zoo in the Netherlands. The
male hatched there on August 17th 2005 and the female on July 8th 2006.
Both were parent-reared.
The pair bred at ZSL London Zoo in the recently refurbished Blackburn
Pavilion tropical bird house, in a mixed species large walk-through exhibit.
The enclosure is approximately 50m long x 20m wide x 7m high (roughly
164ft long x 65ft wide x 22ft high). It houses more than 50 birds of over 20
different species. The Blackburn Pavilion is heavily planted and has overhead
sprinklers, which provide misting and daily rain showers. A large central
pool and waterfall provide drinking and bathing water for the birds.
Feeding
In such a large mixed species exhibit it is difficult to quantify exactly
what each species eats. Food dishes, which include in them the ZSL fish
mix and egg mix, chopped fruit and pulses, are distributed throughout the
enclosure and the pittas had access to all of these foods. In addition, they
would readily take livefood during the scatter feeds, which are given three
or four times a day.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.909927333333333" page_id="56259717"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
Diary of events
August 27th
August 30th
September 1st
September 14th
September 15th
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.995253266666667" page_id="56259717"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
The pair was seen mating and nest building.
Both birds were seen sitting in the nest. In order to avoid
disturbance the nest was not checked.
Four eggs were seen in the nest.
The parents were observed carrying food to the nest, so
it was assumed that chicks had hatched.
Two chicks and one unhatched egg were seen in the
nest.
Species-specific feeding system and target feeding
Due to competition from other species in the enclosure, keepers felt that
the adult pittas would not find enough livefood to sustain their developing
chicks. To resolve this problem, approximately one week prior to the
chicks hatching, a livefood feeding system and a target feeding programme
were established in the enclosure. Buckets approximately 25cm (lOin) in
diameter and 25cm (lOin) deep were sunk into the ground at points where
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.758832" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259718" page_num="29" year="" vol="">
ACKROYD - HOODED PITTA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998046" page_id="56259718"  page_num="29" year="" vol="">
29
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997204263157895" page_id="56259718"  page_num="29" year="" vol="">
the pittas were often seen foraging. The lips of the buckets were level with
the substrate and a small amount of substrate (less than 1 cm (or l Am) deep)
was placed in the bottom of the buckets. In the week leading up to the date
of hatching, the pittas were fed a large number of live dendrobaena worms
in the buckets, as well as being target fed chopped pinkie mice and other
livefbod in and around the buckets. This encouraged the pittas to identify
the buckets as sources of food.
Although they were initially hesitant about jumping down into the
buckets, within days they were using them regularly. Other species would
not enter the buckets, although Montserrat Orioles Icterus oberi and Crested
Wood Partridges Rollulus rouloul would occasionally follow the pittas to
the buckets and steal the food that the pittas carried out. If this happened,
the pittas would immediately jump back down into the bucket to get more
food. The buckets could be loaded with worms in the evening to supply
livefood throughout the night and early morning. During the day keepers
could, in addition, target feed the two adults with livefood.
This system of livefood feeders and target feeding ensured the adult
pittas had a ready supply of livefood both when keeping staff were present
and, more importantly, when they were not.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.71051">
Rearing
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99974175" page_id="56259718"  page_num="29" year="" vol="">
The parents were first observed carrying food to the nest site on
September 14th 2008, so this is assumed to have been the day the chicks
hatched. Due to unsuccessful previous breeding attempts, no attempt was
made to check the number of chicks in the nest. However, the following day
(day one), two chicks were seen at the mouth of the nest, when the parents
left the nest to forage.
On these two days the parents were not often seen feeding the chicks,
but by day three the male was doing nearly all the feeding. He would jump
down into one of the livefood buckets, catch a worm, which he would hop out
with and then spend an extended period of time breaking up the worm into
small pieces. During the initial stages earthworms were the preferred food
fed to the chicks. The earthworms were not gut-loaded and this appeared to
have little effect of the development of the chicks. Gut-loaded mealworms
were offered four to five times per day. Both adults would also readily
take crickets and pinkie mice when these were target fed to them. Keepers
believe that the varied livefood diet aided the chicks' digestion and helped
prevent gut impaction. The consistency and frequency of the faecal sacs
produced by the chicks throughout the rearing, were good indications that
they had no digestive problems.
During this time, bouts of feeding were followed by extended periods
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.301956166666667" page_id="56259719"  page_num="30" year="" vol="">
30 ACKROYD - HOODED PITTA
Paul Atkin
Both parents in the nest on September 15th, approximately one day after the chicks
hatched. It is unclear whether one or both parents are brooding them.
Paul Atkin
Chick aged approximately seven days old. The second chick is hidden behind it.
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.758062" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259720" page_num="31" year="" vol="">
ACKROYD - HOODED PITTA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998862" page_id="56259720"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
31
</page>
<figure confidence="0.6613398" page_id="56259720"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
Paul Atkin
Male carrying food back to the chicks in the nest, approximately four days after they
hatched.
Paul Atkin
Young pitta approximately 16 days old. It had fledged the previous day.
</figure>
<page confidence="0.998587" page_id="56259721"  page_num="32" year="" vol="">
32
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.931171" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259721" page_num="32" year="" vol="">
ACKROYD - HOODED PITTA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.978366256410256" page_id="56259721"  page_num="32" year="" vol="">
when the chicks were brooded, often with both parents in the nest. The female
began foraging day three after the chicks hatched, but was not observed
feeding the chicks until the afternoon of day four. During these early days,
when out of the nest, the female spent much of her time foraging for food
for herself, bathing, preening and gathering nest material.
Closer to the fledging date, both parents were seen regularly feeding the
chicks larger meals, although at a lower frequency than during the first seven
days. Earthworms remained the livefood of choice. The parents varied the
chicks' diet with mealworms and crickets when they were target fed these
items. Faecal sacs were produced regularly and were removed from the
nest by the parents, who concealed them in the grating of the drain at the
exit of the enclosure.
Fledging
The time of hatching to fledging for the Hooded Pitta is 16 days, which
gave us an estimated fledging date of September 29th. On September 27th,
an estimated 13 days after the chicks had hatched, they were seen moving
in the nest. They fledged at approximately 8.30am on the following day
(September 28th).
A member of staff (out of uniform) remained in the aviary for much of
the day. They noted the position of the young pittas and feeding carried out
by the parents, both of which fed the young frequently. The male was heard
calling during the afternoon and showed far more aggression towards other
species in the exhibit. He was observed making aggressive flights at the
Sunbittems Eurypyga helias , Montserrat Orioles and Blue-bellied Rollers
Coracias cyanogaster. The female pitta was not as aggressive and spent the
majority of her time feeding the young.
The parents continued to use the feeding buckets, which were topped up
three times a day and in which ample food was left overnight.
Independence
The young were first seen taking livefood themselves on September
30th, 16 days after they had hatched. However, they were not seen using
the food dishes in the aviary. The young pittas became very interested in the
keeping staff whenever they entered the aviary with buckets. They would
come to the keepers during livefood feeds and try to take food from the hand,
although this was discouraged.
The adult pair began nest building again on September 29th, the day
after the chicks fledged. The female had laid four eggs by October 11th,
when she was found dead in the enclosure. The eggs were removed from
the nest and artificially incubated. Three chicks hatched successfully, but
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.758733" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259722" page_num="33" year="" vol="">
ACKROYD - HOODED PITTA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999212" page_id="56259722"  page_num="33" year="" vol="">
33
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.983736473684211" page_id="56259722"  page_num="33" year="" vol="">
did not survive past the third day of hand-rearing.
The earlier young were DNA sexed, ringed (banded) and wormed on
October 2nd 2008. About December 10th the adult male became aggressive
and began chasing the youngsters. One spent more time around him and
was consequently chased more often. To save the youngster from the male's
aggression, it was moved to a holding enclosure, but quickly lost condition
and died.
The second youngster (like the first a female) was later moved to another
holding enclosure with an unrelated male and is currently (March 2009)
doing well
Conclusions
Keeping staff believe that the bucket livefood feeders were very important
to the success of the parent-rearing process. The constant supply of livefood
allowed the parents to feed the young at liberty throughout the day. Although
quick to find and eat food, the pittas would otherwise have been unable to
compete with many of the other species in the mixed exhibit. We believe
this method of livefood feeding tailored to the pitta's method of foraging,
allowed the parents to get enough livefood to successfully rear their young.
The method of targeted livefood feeding could, we believe, be applied to
other species kept in mixed exhibits. By finding ways of supplying specific
species with extra livefood when they are rearing young, it should be possible
to increase the number of young successfully reared by their parents in
mixed exhibits.
Minimal disturbance of nesting birds is, of course, advisable although not
always possible, particularly in collections open to the public. However, the
breeding pair of pittas seemed comfortable with keepers and members of the
public around. Monitoring of the nest to record developments is a useful tool
and keepers should use their judgement regarding how much disturbance the
birds will safely tolerate. Determining accurate hatching dates in a mixed
exhibit enables the livefood systems to be brought into play and the birds
to become accustomed to them before the chicks hatch.
With more collections keeping species in mixed exhibits, it is important
to increase breeding success in this style of enclosure. The Hooded Pitta has
been upgraded recently to a European Studbook (ESB) monitored species.
It is possible that the number of young successfully reared to independence
could be increased by the targeted feeding of livefood and other rearing foods
to breeding pairs. This would help achieve the studbook aim of creating a
stable, self-sustaining, European captive population.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994317" page_id="56259723"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
34
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.590722" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259723" page_num="34" year="" vol="">
ACKROYD - HOODED PITTA
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.156975">
Paul Atkin
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.526646" page_id="56259723"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
Pitta approaching one of the feeding buckets.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.830889" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56259723" page_num="34" year="" vol="">
Acknowlegements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.957826333333333" page_id="56259723"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
Thanks to Curator John Ellis, Mick Tiley, Adrian Walls, Paul Atkin and
all other staff and volunteers on the ZSL London Zoo bird section for their
assistance with the rearing and documentation of this breeding.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.948862" genericHeader="references" page_id="56259723" page_num="34" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.7626845">
Clements, J. F. 2007. The Clements Checklist of the Birds of the World Sixth Edition. Christopher
Helm, London and Cornell University Press, USA.
Erritzoe, J. and Erritzoe, H. B. 1998. Pittas of the World A Monograph of the Pitta Family. The
Lutterworth Press, Cambridge, UK.
Nicholas Ackroyd BSc GradDip TchLn (secondary), Qualified Keeper,
Birds, Zoological Society of London, Regent's Park, London NWl 4RY, UK.
</reference>
<bodyText confidence="0.884005285714286" page_id="56259723"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
Website :www. londonzoo. co. uk
Following the author s decision to return to New Zealand, any enquiries
about the breeding should be addressed to Adrian Walls or Paul Atkin. E-
mail:adrian.walls@zsl.org orpaul.atkin@zsl.org
The above breeding account (ora similar version of it) will be published
in Ratel, the journal of the Association of British and Irish Wild Animal
Keepers (ABWAK). Website:www.abwak.org
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996782" page_id="56259724"  page_num="35" year="" vol="">
35
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.677802" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259724" page_num="35" year="" vol="">
FURTHER NEWS OF THE BLUE-THROATED MACAW
by David Waugh
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.976567542857143" page_id="56259724"  page_num="35" year="" vol="">
Loro Parque Fundacion (LPF) has since 1995 supported the Armonia
organisation's plans for the recovery of the Critically Endangered Blue-
throated Macaw Ara glaucogularis , particularly the need to stop the illegal
trafficking of this species and to reduce the loss and deterioration of its
habitat. As part of the Armoma/LPF conservation programme, an extensive
search was made of vast areas of savannah in an attempt to locate more
birds. This resulted in a new flock of 70 being discovered on a ranch, which
helped raise the total known population to an estimated 350 birds (see News
&amp; Views Vol. 113, No.4, p. 186 (2007)).
Armonia has now succeeded in purchasing the ranch on which this
concentration of Blue-throated Macaws live. The 4,254 hectares (approx.
11,000 acres) ranch is in Yacuma Province to the north-west of the city of
Trinidad, capital of Beni, in north-east Bolivia. It is a typical example of
Blue-throated Macaw habitat, with seasonably inundated savannah and
higher ground free from water, which forms islands of palms and other trees.
The purchase of the ranch was made possible thanks to donations from the
American Bird Conservancy and World Land Trust. It is the first protected
area specifically for the Blue-throated Macaw and the programme can now
begin to take measures to protect the habitat, which were not previously
possible. Habitat restoration studies will be undertaken and experiments with
artificial nest designs, along with planning for the long-term sustainability
of the programme through ecotourism.
During the 2007-2008 breeding season, 57 nest boxes were put up, 51
in the southern area and six in the north, some of which were sponsored
by The Bird Endowment. Only Blue-and-yellow Macaws A. ararauna
investigated the boxes in the northern area, but four of those in the south
were occupied by Blue-throated Macaws, while 24 of the nest boxes were
occupied by Blue-and-yellow Macaws and other animal species (see Table
1). Two of the Blue-throated Macaw nests were successful, one produced
one chick and the other three, all of which fledged in March.
January-mid-May the principal markets in Cochabamba and Santa Cruz
were monitored for parrots. A total of 5,714 of 19 different species were
recorded. Thankfully, no Blue-throated Macaws were seen, though there
were three Red-fronted Macaws A. rubrogenys , a Bolivian endemic and
threatened species.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.992544" page_id="56259725"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
36
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.6145245">
WAUGH - BLUE-THROATED MACAW
Table 1. Occupancy of nest boxes 2007-2008 breeding season.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.9625445" page_id="56259725"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
Species
No. occupied
Blue-and-yellow Macaw Ara ararauna
24
White-eyed Parakeet Aratinga leucophthalmus
6
Wasp Polistes spp.
5
Blue-throated Macaw Ara glaucogularis
4
Honey Bee Apis mellifera
4
Black-bellied Whistling Duck Dendrocygna autumnalis 3
Cattle Tyrant Machetornis rixosus
1
Muscovy Duck Cairina moschata
1
Total
</figure>
<page confidence="0.969555" page_id="56259725"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
48
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.758919466666667" page_id="56259725"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
Eleven boxes were unoccupied.
Of all the parrots recorded, 86% were of five species: the Yellow-
chevroned (or Canary-winged) Parakeet Brotogeris chiriri 26%, Blue-
fronted Amazon Amazona aestiva 22%, Green-cheeked Parakeet Pyrrhura
molinae 17%, Monk (or Quaker) Parakeet Myiopsitta monachus 11% and
Blue-winged Parrotlet Forpus xanthopterygius 10%.
Another important advance was the signing of a formal agreement
between LPF/ Armonia, Zoo Fauna Sudamericana (the zoological park of
the Municipality of Santa Cruz) and Noel Kempff Mercado Natural History
Museum (also in Santa Cruz and affiliated to the Autonomous University
Gabriel Moreno). The agreement formalises the initiation of a managed
cooperative breeding programme in Bolivia, as part of the international
conservation effort for the Blue-throated Macaw, with LPF as International
Studbook Keeper and supporting the programme with expertise and
funding.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.656829" page_id="56259725"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
* *
*
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.842113" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259725" page_num="36" year="" vol="">
WORTHY WINNERS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9183595" page_id="56259725"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
At the recent Council Meeting held at Colchester Zoo, Peter Karsten's
account of breeding the European Robin Erithacus rubecula (Vol. 114,
No. 3, pp. 101-117 (2008)) was judged the best/most informative article in
the magazine last year and a worthy winner of the D. H. S. Risdon Award.
The Dulcie Cooke Award went to Simon Espley for his photos of the Fawn-
breasted Waxbill Estrilda paludicola (Vol. 114, No.4, pp. 161-167 (2008)).
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998223" page_id="56259726"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
37
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.882347" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259726" page_num="37" year="" vol="">
FURTHER NOTES ON AN AFRICAN BUNTING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.925244972972973" page_id="56259726"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
by Neville Brickell
Cabanis's Bunting Emberiza cabanisi
Description
Length 1 5cm 17cm (6in-6 3 /4in). The adult male is shown in the
photograph on the following page. Unlike other similar looking African
buntings, this species lacks a white stripe below the eye. Sinclair &amp; Ryan
(2003) and Hockey, Dean &amp; Ryan (2005) recognised three subspecies. These
differ from each other mainly in the shades of streaking and striping on the
head, back and mantle, and in size. The former list the northern nominate
subspecies E. c. cabanisi and two southern subspecies E. c. orientalis and
E. c. cognominata, the latter two formerly and, alternatively still sometimes,
known as the Three-streaked Bunting. Clements (2007) recognised only E. c.
cabanisi and E. c. orientalis. Emberiza c. cabanisi is larger and is darker on
the head and also on the upperparts, the latter being grey with black streaking.
Its chin and throat are white. Emberiza c. orientalis has an inconspicuous
narrow white or whitish stripe down the centre of its crown, which usually
broadens at the back of the neck, and has the feathers of the mantle and back
chestnut, with sooty-brown centres, grey edges and bluish-grey bases. Only
the chin is white. Emberiza c. cognominata has a narrow pale greyish stripe
down the centre of the crown, greyer upperparts than E. c. orientalis and is
larger (Hockey, Dean &amp; Ryan, 2005). There is a slight seasonal variation
as the fresh plumage becomes worn and fades.
The female is a paler/duller version of the male. Her head and face
markings are dark brown (rather than black), her eye stripe has a huffish tinge
and is less conspicuous, her throat is tinged huffish and her wing bars are
less striking; the centre of her breast may be washed orangish-brown, with
the rest of the underparts yellow. The juvenile is in turn a duller, browner
version of the female. Its upperparts are pale tawny-brown with blackish
streaking and its eye-stripe is also pale tawny-brown; its breast is pale dull
yellow with, according to some descriptions, dark brown streaking on the
chest and often also on the flanks.
Voice
Song, delivered from a prominent perch, a piercing, sweetly modulated
and variable "wee, chidderchidder , chidder, we," "her, ip, ip, ip...her, hee,"
"sweet-sweet-sweet-sweet ," "peetu-peetu-peetu" or a rapid "twi-twi-twi-twi."
Call a soft, clear, whistled " turee " (Hockey, Dean &amp; Ryan, 2005). Stevenson
&amp; Fanshawe (2002) described the song of E. c. cabanisi as a fairly rapidly
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998376" page_id="56259727"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
38
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.879827" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259727" page_num="38" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - CABANIS'S BUNTING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8137931" page_id="56259727"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
delivered "swi chi chi chi chi chi ," while that of E. c. orientalis is a much
sweeter "swi sisi swee swee swee swee" Both are described as loud and
far-carrying.
Distribution
Emheriza c. cabanisi occurs from Sierra Leone and Guinea on the
west coast, eastwards across Africa to southern Sudan, the north-east of
the Democratic Republic of Congo and north-west Uganda. Emberiza
c. orientalis occurs from the south-east of the Democratic Republic of
Congo and Tanzania to Zambia, Malawi, northern Mozambique and eastern
Zimbabwe. Emberiza c. cognominata occurs in southern Gabon, the Congo,
Angola, the south-west of the Democratic Republic of Congo, western
Zambia and north-western Zimbabwe.
Habitat
Miombo ( Brachystegia ) woodland with little or no undergrowth in
southern Africa, at the forest edge and bushed and wooded grassland from
300m-2,000m (approx.985ft-6,550ft) in East Africa and wooded, savannah
in West Africa.
Behaviour
Forages on paths, at roadsides and on patches of open ground, particularly
those on poorly drained soil. It is usually solitary or in pairs, or may form
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.585711" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259728" page_num="39" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - CABANIS'S BUNTING
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998459" page_id="56259728"  page_num="39" year="" vol="">
39
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.924879128205128" page_id="56259728"  page_num="39" year="" vol="">
small flocks with other small birds, feeding on the ground, in the non-
breeding season.
Food
Eats seed and grain, including millet and rice, and insects including
beetles and grasshoppers, the remains of which were among the stomach
contents of specimens collected in Nigeria. A captive pair belonging to Ken
Arnold, formerly of Zimbabwe, then residing in KwaZulu-Natal, was fed a
finch seed mixture and mealworms, along with livefood recorded in the wild,
including the Common Green Mantis Sphodromantis gastrica and crickets,
from which the legs were removed by the parents before they were fed to
the nestlings between day seven and day II, after which seed was offered.
Chickweed, thistle and dandelion leaves were also offered, plus a softfood
with the addition of hard-boiled egg. The birds were also provided with
finely crushed cuttlefish bone.
Our Feeding Record Cards show that this species has a liking for three
indigenous grasses, namely: Natal Red-top Melinis repens , Guinea Grass
Panicum maximum and Natal Panic P. natalense, as well as livefood collected
from the wild, along with mealworms, when it is breeding.
Breeding
Nigeria and Cameroon, June-September; Central African Republic,
February-May; Democratic Republic of Congo and Zambia, March; Angola,
September-January; Malawi, October-November; Zimbabwe, September-
March (30 out of 44 records October-November).
Nest construction is undertaken by the female alone, with the male in
constant attendance, including following her on nesting material collecting
trips. The nest is usually lm-2m (approx. 3ft 3in-6ft 6in) above the ground
but can be up to 5m (approx. 16ft) above the ground. It is usually built in a
multiple-twigged fork of a small tree or bush and screened by leafy foliage. In
Zimbabwe a Mufuti Brachystegia boehmii , Munondo Julbernadia globiflora
or Camels-foot Piliostigma thonningii is frequently chosen. A pair built in a
bunch of plantains in full view of Bate's house in southern Cameroon. He
found the birds so shy that they were seldom seen, so it came as a surprise to
him that they chose such an exposed site. Bannerman (1953) also mentioned
a nest in an exposed situation in a yam vine in southern Nigeria.
Bannerman (1953) described the nest as "shallow and loosely made" but
Hockey, Dean &amp; Ryan (2005) described it as a "deep, almost thrush-like
cup" made of roots, twigs, grass and weed stems (often with flowers and
leaves attached) and dry and skeletonised leaves. It is lined with soft, fine
grass and rootlets. The outside of the nest measures up to about 110mm in
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.989636" page_id="56259729"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
40
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.880935" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259729" page_num="40" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - CABANIS'S BUNTING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997512090909091" page_id="56259729"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
diameter, with the cup about 50mm in diameter and 30mm deep. The nest
is about 60mm-80mm high.
One to three eggs may be laid, but the usual clutch consists of two eggs,
which measure on average about 20.2mm x 14.6mm. They are white or
pale greenish blue, with large and irregular fine twirling lines, short wavy
pencillings, hair lines and blotches coloured brown and grey, often in a
ring around the thick end. The incubation period is 12-14 days. A nestling
period of 14-16 days has been recorded in captivity. On vacating the nest
the fledglings are fed by the male for a further eight to 10 days. An attempt
to consume dry seed was observed after 12 days of having left the nest.
Cabanis's Bunting is parasited by Klaas's Cuckoo Chrysococcyx klaas.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.862159" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56259729" page_num="40" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8261395" page_id="56259729"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
Thanks to aviculturist Ken Arnold for his contribution to the above
information.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.363695">
Bibliography
</subsubsectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.977771823529412">
Bannerman, D. A. 1953. The Birds of West and Equatorial Africa Vol.2. Oliver &amp; Boyd,
Edinburgh and London, UK.
Brickell, N. and Konigkramer, T. (eds). 1997. African Birds in Field &amp; Aviary. Avicultural
Research Unit, RSA.
Byers, C., Olsson, U. and Curson, J. 1995. Buntings and Sparrows - A Guide to the Buntings
and North American Sparrows. Russell Friedman Books, South Africa.
Clements, J. F. 2007. The Clements Checklist to the Birds of the World Sixth Edition. Helm,
London and Cornell University Press, USA.
Hockey, P. A. R., Dean, W. R. J. and Ryan, P. G. (eds). 2005. Roberts - Birds of Southern
Africa Vllth Edition. The Trustees of The John Voelcker Bird Book Fund, Cape Town, South
Africa.
Sinclair, I. and Ryan, P. 2003. Birds of Africa south of the Sahara. Struik Publishers, Cape
Town, South Africa.
Stevenson, T. and Fanshawe, J. 2002. Field Guide to the Birds of East Africa. T &amp; AD
Poyser, London.
Tarboton, W. 2001. A guide to the Nests &amp; Eggs of Southern African Birds. Struik Publishers,
Cape Town, South Africa.
</reference>
<equation confidence="0.342962" page_id="56259729"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.814247" genericHeader="references" page_id="56259729" page_num="40" year="" vol="">
BLACK-AND-WHITE LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.871962" page_id="56259729"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
Dave Coles remembers the Black-and-white Laughingthrushes Garrulax
bicolor, then called Sumatran Jay Thrushes or Sumatran Laughingthrushes G.
leucolophus bicolor, living in one of Raymond Sawyer's aviaries at Cobham,
Surrey (see Vol.114, No.3, p.132 (2008)). The pair was, Dave wrote, there
when he left in 1987. So far as he is aware, the pair never bred and came,
he believes, from Rex Merritt.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998654" page_id="56259730"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
41
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.880158" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259730" page_num="41" year="" vol="">
THE CHALLENGE OF KEEPING KINGFISHERS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.981357736842105" page_id="56259730"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
by Gary Bralsford
Over the past 25 years, I have kept many foreign birds. Softbills have
been my first love, my favourites being the kingfishers, rollers and bee-eaters.
Of these, the kingfishers are to me the real beauties and have presented the
greatest challenge to my birdkeeping skills.
I bought my first kingfisher, a Grey-headed Halcyon leucocephala , from
a dealer in Doncaster named Terry Merrick, who sadly is no longer in the
hobby. Its staple diet was mealworms, crickets and locusts. At the time,
in the early 1980s, I also had a pond with a thriving goldfish population
and the fry were eagerly consumed by the kingfisher. My bird was a male
(which in my experience has a more prominant grey head) and as I could
not get a female to pair it with, after about 18 months I sold it to someone
who already had three Grey-headed Kingfishers.
This species has a wide range in Africa and is also found on the Red Sea
coast of the southern Arabian Peninsula. It inhabits woodland and bush,
usually near water. Some populations are migratory, breeding in one part
of Africa and spending the non-breeding season elsewhere in Africa. The
Grey-headed Kingfisher feeds on a wide variety of prey, including insects
(mainly grasshoppers, locusts and crickets), lizards, small mammals such
as mice and more rarely takes frogs and small fish.
I then went on to keep the slightly larger Blue-breasted Kingfisher H.
malimbica. It is a fantastic bird to keep, being both a colourful and an
energetic aviary inhabitant. It is found from the Senegambia region of West
Africa, south to Cameroon, Angola and Zambia, and eastwards to southern
Sudan, western and southern Uganda and right up in the north-west comer
of Tanzania. It is primarily a forest kingfisher, that keeps in deep shade
below the canopy, but may also be found in dense riverine woodland and in
mangroves. Like the Grey-headed species, it feeds mainly on insects, but
may also catch frogs, crabs and prawns but not fish. It is said often to nest
in an arboreal termite nest, 10m (30ft) or more above the ground, or in a hole
in a tree. Up to four, round, smooth, glossy white eggs are laid.
I bought my first Blue-breasted Kingfisher from Mark Peckett of Preston
and later bought two more from Pegasus Birds. I found that Blue-breasted
Kingfishers were prone to arrive from quarantine with damaged beaks, which
was the case with one of the latter, that had a chip out of its upper mandible.
All three were quite nervous and whenever I entered their flight would crash
against the wire mesh. I therefore put up mini-corrugated sheeting on the
inside of the flight to prevent them crashing against the wire and to protect
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998042" page_id="56259731"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
42
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.926404" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259731" page_num="42" year="" vol="">
BRALSFORD - KINGFISHERS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998386853658537" page_id="56259731"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
their beaks.
For about a year, the three would eat only whitebait and sardines, which
was a problem in the summer when my wife objected to the smell of the
fish, whenever we opened the back door. I had to wean them off fish by
slowly introducing minced (ground) beef into their diet. All three got on well
together and displayed with their wings outstretched. They were provided
with nest logs 2ft (approx. 0.6m) high, with a 4in (10cm) diameter hole
2in (5cm) from the top. However, although I saw plenty of displaying and
bill wiping, the three birds which were unsexed (although I suspect males
have a more colourful blue breast), made no attempt to nest during the three
years I had them.
After years of being without the Blue-breasted Kingfisher, I purchased a
pair from Mark Peckett at the end of 2007. I had the two birds DNA sexed
and to my surprise and delight, they proved to be a true pair. The pair had
been housed in a treble-sized breeding cage for some considerable time.
Both birds were in reasonable condition but would, I thought, look better
after having moulted. I placed the pair in a 9ft x 4ft x 6ft high (approx. 2.7m
x 1.2m x 1.8m high) flight in my birdroom shed.
I provided the pair with a varied diet consisting of minced (ground) beef,
strips of beef and pinkie mice, along with morio worms, Pachnoda (fruit
beetle) grubs, locusts and black crickets. I provided a small earthenware
dish of water for bathing. After a few months, the pair looked good, but
with room for improvement. I therefore replaced the small earthware dish
with a large, plastic, cat litter tray of water for bathing. I also began using
The Birdcare Company product Feather Up, which I put on their minced
(ground) beef and strips of meat. Over a period of four months or so their
plumage improved and they eventually underwent a complete moult, after
which they began to look really good. The moult of this species is the longest
I have ever witnessed by any of the birds I have kept.
It is a fantastic sight to see them dive some 3ft (0.9m) or so from the perch
into the water with quite a splash, then return to the perch to preen. They
often regurgitate pellets and drop them into the water. In my experience,
they do not feed everyday. The food may remain untouched one day and
then be eaten eagerly the following day.
They have now started to call, usually at night or in the early morning.
Their song is a loud whistled series of rising and then falling notes, which
usually finishes on the same tone as the opening note. They also have a loud
alarm call, but neither is loud enough to upset the neighbours. They have
access to a large nest box, which they have started to roost in. I am hoping
that the pair will breed this year. However, it would be reassuring to have
one or two spare birds as back-up.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.677543" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259732" page_num="43" year="" vol="">
BRALSFORD - KINGFISHERS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99959" page_id="56259732"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.985368829268292" page_id="56259732"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
I am in contact with Bengt Larsson in Sweden, who has several males
and a female. If possible, I would like to obtain one of his spare males,
which he has offered me as part of an exchange deal.
I was told that Barcelona Zoo in Spain has this species on show, but never
saw any when I visited there recently. Quite large numbers were imported
a few years ago. I know that Borgstein in the Netherlands often had this
species on his list. Nowadays, however, there are not many Blue-breasted
Kingfishers about.
The White-collared (or Collared) Kingfisher H. ( Todiramphus ) chloris
is another species I kept in the past and have again now. I first kept this
species in the early 1980s. I bought a pair from Dave Campbell at the
National Exhibition of Cage &amp; Aviary Birds. I housed the pair in a 6ft x
6ft x 6ft (approx. 1.8m x 1.8m x 1.8m) flight, but unfortunately after just a
few weeks I lost the male. As the chance of getting another male was slim,
I sold the female to a dealer.
It was many years before I again got the opportunity to keep this species.
In late 2006,1 learned that the White-collared Kingfisher was being bred at
Chester Zoo and one or two were being allowed to go to private breeders. A
friend of mine, Safter Ikbal, obtained a young true pair from the zoo in part
exchange for some turacos. I told him that if ever he wanted to sell them,
I would love to have them. The chance came in August 2008, when Safter
called me and said that if I still wanted them, they were mine. We arranged
a part exchange deal and I returned home with them and set about getting
them into peak condition.
I put Feather Up on their food. They took about six weeks to complete
their full moult, which was a lot quicker than the Blue-breasted Kingfishers
took to complete their moult. I keep the pair in an 8ft x 4ft x 6ft (approx.
2.4m x 1.2m x 1.8m) flight. Both birds have settled in well, but are not as
steady as the Blue-breasted Kingfishers. They remain quite flighty whenever
I enter their flight. I have put up a nest box which the two birds regularly go
into. At the time of writing (December 2008), the male is feeding the female,
which is exciting to see. He is a deeper blue on the head and upperparts
than the female, who is more greenish.
This species cannot, I learned, be trusted with other birds, even those
considerably larger than itself. On a recent tour of the bird collection at
Chester Zoo, I was told that they had lost pheasants and other birds with
head injuries, and wondered who was the culprit. A careful watch was
kept and a White-collared Kingfisher was seen diving from a perch "like
an exocet missile" and killing a dove in one swoop. After this they were
removed and housed on their own. It was then that they went on to breed.
I was told that so long as they are in tiptop condition, they will breed at
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997799" page_id="56259733"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
44
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.882693" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259733" page_num="44" year="" vol="">
BRALSFORD - KINGFISHERS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997045634146342" page_id="56259733"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
anytime of the year.
The White-collared Kingfisher has an enormous range, stretching from
the coast of Eritrea in north-east Africa, across to India, south China, Australia
and the south-west Pacific. Clements (2007) lists 49 subspecies, most of
which are confined to islands. This kingfisher is associated mainly with tidal
habitats, from mangroves and mudflats to sandy beaches and coral reefs and
may be seen around fishing villages. In some areas though, such as on the
Indonesian island of Sumatra, it may move far inland into open woodland
and cultivation. Its food in the wild can vary from crustaceans caught on
the sand or mud, to insects, worms, frogs, lizards and even small snakes.
The White-collared Kingfisher excavates its own nest hole in a tree trunk,
ant or termite nest.
A few years ago a friend of mine and fellow Avicultural Society member
Richard Green, obtained a pair of Woodland Kingfishers H. senegalensis
from Mark Peckett. When he got them back to Doncaster, he put them in
his tropical house, in which he has a fantastic set up, but within a few hours
disaster struck, when one of the pair drowned while bathing in the waterfall
and rock pool. Their plumage had become dry and the unfortunate bird's
feathers became waterlogged.
Richard managed to get a replacement and when the two birds were DNA
sexed, they proved to be a true pair. A new enclosure was built measuring
12ftx 12ft x 7ft high (approx. 3.9m x 3.9m x 2.1m high), into which the pair
was released. It has a stream and a pump, so that there is constant running
water. The pair love this and use the stream to bathe in.
An array of nest boxes have been put up, some with holes in them and
some with slots. They are fixed at an angle of forty-five degrees, to replicate
the broken bough of a tree. Nothing happened for the first couple of years,
but this changed in 2008. The pair looked immaculate and all of a sudden
became very vocal and began displaying. There was a lot of wing flicking
and bill wiping going on. In August the female was sitting in a nest box
about 4ft (approx. 1.2m) above the ground. On inspection she was found
to be sitting on three white eggs, one of which hatched after an incubation
period of 16 days. Richard fed the young kingfisher on mealworms, morio
worms, lance fish and crickets. It lived for 14 days. By then it was quite
large, with pin-feathers covering its body and a lot of other feathers already
in place. Richard blamed himself for the loss, because he felt he had failed to
provide enough livefood. Kingfishers have quite a large gape and, I suspect,
the young are capable of swallowing larger livefood from about five days
old or so. Hopefully, Richard will be successful this year with his Woodland
Kingfishers, a species first bred in the UK at Winged World in 1971.
This kingfisher inhabits woodland and savannah throughout much of
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.677739" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259734" page_num="45" year="" vol="">
BRALSFORD - KINGFISHERS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997553" page_id="56259734"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
45
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999074258064516" page_id="56259734"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
Africa, from the Senegambia region of West Africa across to Ethiopia and
southwards all the way down into South Africa. Like other Halcyon spp., it
eats mainly insects, but has also been recorded taking small fish, small birds
such as the Bronze Mannikin Lonchura cucullata and quelea and barbet
chicks (Hockey et al. 2005). Some populations, like those of the Grey-headed
species, are intra-Africa migrants, that breed in one part of Africa and then
spend the non-breeding season elsewhere. Both migrate at night.
The African Pygmy Kingfisher Ispidina ( Ceyx ) picta is another species
I have been lucky enough to keep. I bought a pair from an import station in
Lincolnshire. I housed the pair in a 6ft (approx. 1.8m) long block of cages.
The pair lived on mealworms, small crickets and locusts, waxworms, casters
and small earthworms. The pair refused to eat mince or any other meat and
would take nothing but livefood. Both were very active and a joy to keep,
but the weekly cost of the livefood made them expensive to feed.
Many years ago, the Bird Box at Wakefield Garden Centre, which was
run by a man named Bill and his wife Sue, kept a pair in a small, covered
outside flight. Bill provided the pair with an artificial bank and began to feed
the pair on tadpoles at various stages of development. Shortly afterwards the
pair began to excavate a nest chamber in the bank. Unfortunately, however,
the chamber kept collapsing and after a couple of months trying to breed
them, Bill eventually sold them.
I have been told that an aviculturist in the Netherlands has perfected the
breeding of this species. He is said to have bred five young in 2007 and I
am still trying to find out how he did with his Pygmy Kingfishers 2008.
The African Pygmy Kingfisher, which measures little more than 11cm
(AViin) in length and has a similar distribution to the Woodland species,
inhabits mostly woodland and savannah, often far from water, and feeds
mainly on insects. Some populations are migratory. They are thought to
migrate mostly at night and many (mostly juvenile birds) perish as a result of
colliding with buildings in urban areas. The same is true of many migrating
Grey-headed and Woodland Kingfishers (Hockey et al. 2005).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9849" genericHeader="references" page_id="56259734" page_num="45" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.966270571428571">
Clements, J. F. 2007. The Clements Checklist of the Birds of the World Sixth Edition.
Christopher Helm, London and Cornell University Press, USA.
Hockey, P. A. R., Dean, W. R. J. and Ryan, P. G. 2005. Roberts - Birds of Southern Africa Vllth
Edition. The Trustees of the John Voelcker Bird Book Fund, Cape Town, South Africa.
Gary Bralsford is a UK member who lives in south Yorkshire. He was
the first person in the UK to breed the Chestnut-backed Thrush Zoothera
dohertyi.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.997053" page_id="56259735"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
46
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.989411" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259735" page_num="46" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEW
THE WISDOM OF BIRDS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999062216216216" page_id="56259735"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
Prof. Tim Birkhead has written a history of ornithology that is a pleasure
to read. On receiving this large (433 page) volume I wondered how I would
find time to read it. Like a good novel though, once I started reading it I
could not put it down. It is rare to enjoy a book to the extent that you rush
back home from a day's birding in order to read more. I first met Tim over
30 years ago at a job interview, at which he was the successful applicant and
went on to begin his distinguished career at Sheffield University. With our
shared interests in birds and behaviour, especially the sexual behaviour of
birds, it was perhaps not unsurprising that we later collaborated on writing an
academic paper on the copulation of the Greater Vasa Parrot, which resulted
from my observations of captive birds at Chester Zoo.
The Wisdom of Birds An Illustrated History of Ornithology evolved
from a concept Tim developed several years ago, which aimed to document
the central role of bird keeping to the science of ornithology. In the first
chapter Tim discusses the early growth of ornithology and makes a strong
case for the approach taken by John Ray in The Wisdom of God Manifested
in the Works of Creation published in 1691. Ray questioned how birds are
designed to be equipped to fit their place in nature. This was considered by
Ray to indicate design by God. It was his way of thinking about what we
now call adaptations, that set the stage for Darwin and others to follow and
produce the theory of evolution by natural selection.
The following chapter is on birds' eggs and outlines the development
of our knowledge of fertilisation, sperm storage and embryology. Eggs of
domestic chickens and pigeons provided most of this body of knowledge.
In describing how hen birds paired to vasectomised males may continue to
produce fertile eggs, this chapter helps set the scene for a later chapter on
promiscuity and infidelity in birds.
The importance of bird keeping to the development of ornithology is not
a subject that has been fully documented or appreciated - doubtless because
keeping birds in captivity is considered, at best, irrelevant by many modem
field ornithologists and birdwatchers. This book includes in its history of
ornithology the important role played by the observations of bird trappers
and bird keepers. The close observation of birds and the incentive to breed
them in captivity to produce birds that are more attractive to bird fanciers
in looks, behaviour and/or song, have helped unravel many aspects of bird
biology.
The chapter on instinct and intelligence covers the ground breaking
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.866878" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259736" page_num="47" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEW
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998507" page_id="56259736"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
47
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998846756097561" page_id="56259736"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
work of Konrad Lorenz, Niko Tinbergen, Bill Thorpe and others in the
development of behaviour in individual birds. Much of this research and
more recent work has and continues to be conducted on captive birds. Our
knowledge of the complex learning ability of parrots, for example, results
from the recent research by Irene Pepperberg on Alex, her pet African Grey
Parrot.
Over 400 years ago bird trappers in Italy discovered that keeping birds in
the dark affected their annual cycles and, as a result, they could be induced
to sing at times they would have normally been silent. In the 1920s this
same 'trick' was used by a bird breeder in Germany to induce Nightingales to
sing at the same time that his canaries had chicks in the nest, with the result
that the latter learned the Nightingale's song. Thus a strain of canaries that
sang like Nightingales was produced. Nowadays, of course, we have sound
recordings that make such 'tricks' unnecessary. Such observations formed
the basis of later scientific investigations and experiments that have led to
our present understanding of the role of light in controlling avian breeding
cycles. Similarly the observations by European bird keepers of seasonal
restlessness, or Zugunruhe as it is called in Germany, by captive migratory
birds, set the scene for work by modem scientists on the physiology of
migration. Much of this recent research in both the USA and Europe, has
been and could only have been conducted on captive birds.
Chapters follow on the history of our understanding of territoriality
in birds and of bird song. Most of the work on the function of territorial
behaviour, as would be expected, is field based, though some of the earlier
observations of territorial behaviour linked with song were made by bird
catchers, who had direct practical experience of wild birds. The chapter on
bird song begins with an account of the work on captive Bullfinches by a hero
of mine, the German bird keeper and ornithologist Jurgen Nicolai. My own
PhD work was on Bullfinches and these remain a personal favourite of mine.
Again most of our knowledge of the development of bird song of individual
birds has come from experiments with captive birds, with the work of Bill
Thorpe and of Peter Marler on Chaffinches, being of especial significance.
I am disappointed that no mention is made of Klaus Immelmann who
integrated field and aviary studies. Immelmann's books on Australian
parakeets and finches, which I bought as a teenager, opened new paths of
interest for me.
Sex has a chapter of its own which is devoted mainly to our knowledge
of how the sex of an individual bird is determined. In aviculture we often
hear of birds that have changed sex or have had experience of this with some
of our own birds. Again many cited observations of this are of captive birds.
Most often it is a female that later takes on the appearance of a male and the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997963" page_id="56259737"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
48
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.952192" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259737" page_num="48" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEW
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.96536571875" page_id="56259737"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
physiological basis of this is explained.
Infidelity is the subject of the penultimate chapter. Many, if not most
birds, are promiscuous and indulge in extra-pair copulations - although
the Bullfinch appears to break that pattern and practises true monogamy.
Male Bullfinches possess comparatively small testes, little in the way of a
cloacal protuberance and, compared to other birds, produce very few sperm.
From this it is deduced that evolution has not selected for big testes in male
Bullfinches, because the females choose not to 'play away.'
Too much sex is bad for you - or so it would appear from the final
chapter. Birds that reproduce quickly and often and have large broods also
have short life spans. We learn that human eunuchs live on average 10-12
years longer than other men. Perhaps abstinence from sex does make the
heart grow stronger!
This chapter goes on to explain the refutation of theories of group
selection in the regulation of animal numbers and the importance of natural
selection on individuals through lifetime reproductive success. Tim Birkhead
finishes by returning to infidelity and questioning the evolutionary advantages
that accrue to females that pair with only one male yet continue to seek
copulations with other males. Perhaps the exceptions may prove the rule
and further studies of Bullfinches take us towards the answer.
Prof. Birkhead clearly enjoys his birds and his science and, a combination
of clear thinking, good writing, scholarship and an extensive knowledge
of ornithological literature, coupled with his own field and bird keeping
experience, make his book a really good read. It is illustrated with and
enhanced by many beautiful colour reproductions, mostly from old works,
coupled with some fascinating anecdotes. I really enjoyed this book and can
recommend it to those with an inclination to learn more about the biology
of birds.
As much about birds as it is about the history of ornithology, The Wisdom
of Birds An Illustrated History of Ornithology (ISBN 978 0 7475 9256 3) by
Tim Birkhead, is a 433-page hardback with many colour illustrations. It is
published by Bloomsbury, London, New York and Berlin. Price #25.00.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.8233465" page_id="56259737"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
Roger Wilkinson
* * *
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.619155" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259737" page_num="48" year="" vol="">
EDITOR'S FINAL ISSUE
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.8886304">
Following publication of the February 2009 issue of Australian Aviculture ,
journal of The Avicultural Society of Australia Inc. (Website: www.birds.org.
au), Graeme Hyde retired after having edited and produced 395 consecutive
issues over a period of 33 years. Graeme joined The Avicultural Society of
Australia Inc. in 1954 at 19 years of age.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.902851" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259738" page_num="" year="" vol="">
A REMARKABLE ACHIEVEMENT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8523082" page_id="56259738"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Having begun in 1999 with just one pair of Pekin Robins Leiothrix lutea,
Peter Karsten in Canada now has eight pairs and by the end of the 2008
breeding season had bred to independence 114 young, which is a remarkable
achievement. Peter's book Pekin Robins and Small Softbills was reviewed
in Vol.113, No.4, pp. 182-183 (2007). It is published by Hancock House
Publishers, Surrey, B.C., Canada, and is distributed by them. Price Canada
$49.95 (subject to verification with the publisher at time of order). In case
of difficulty contact: Lorraine Christian, Sales Promotion, Hancock House
Publishers Ltd. Tel:800-938-1114/Fax:800-938-2262 (in North America
only)/Website:www.hancockhouse.com Alternatively, you can contact
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.317285" page_id="56259738"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Peter - Website:www.pekinrobin.ca /E-mail:silvpine@island.net - who will
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.560621" page_id="56259738"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
forward enquries and is happy to answer questions on keeping and breeding
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.7154505" page_id="56259738"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Pekin Robins.
*
* *
DAVID SNOW
David Snow died on February 4th 2009, aged 84, less than a year after
the death of his friend and former colleague Derek Goodwin, whose obituary
was published in Vol.114, No.l, pp.45-47 (2008).
David Snow's book The Cotingas , published in 1982, will be familiar
to many aviculturists interested in this group of birds. He served from
1957-1961 as Resident Naturalist for the New York Zoological Society at
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.902909692307692" page_id="56259738"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
its tropical field station run by William Beebe on the island of Trinidad, then
from 1963-1964 was Director of the Charles Darwin Research Station on the
Galapagos Islands. In 1964, David Snow returned to the UK, his wife Barbara
having travelled ahead for the birth of their second son. He was appointed
Director of Research at the British Trust for Ornithology (BTO) that year and
held the post until 1968, when he became Senior Principal Scientific Officer
in the birdroom of The Natural History Museum at Tring. He retired from
the museum in 1984. He edited Ibis for a number of years and was Editor
of the Concise Edition of The Birds of the Western Palearctic.
He was elected President of the British Ornithologists' Union in 1982
and awarded its Godman-Salvin Medal for outstanding contributions to
ornithology. The American Ornithologists' Union had preceded this with
its Brewster Medal in 1972.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.910816" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259739" page_num="" year="" vol="">
SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION LIBRARIES
</sectionHeader>
<figure confidence="0.966771153846154" page_id="56259739"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
3 9088 01463 4703
CONTENTS
The Avicultural Society.1
The comparative behaviour of hand-reared Spectacled Thrushes
Turdus nudigensis
by Robin Restall.2
Hand-rearing White-browed Coucals Centropus superciliosus
by Louise Peat.7
The unusual nesting behaviour of a pair of White-browed Coucals
Centropus superciliosus at Exmoor Zoo
by Derek Gibson.17
The society's visit to Berlin
by Nigel Hewston.20
The parent-rearing of Hooded Pitta chicks Pitta sordida mulleri in
a mixed species walk-through exhibit at ZSL London Zoo
by Nicholas Ackroyd.27
Further news of the Blue-throated Macaw
by David Waugh.35
Further notes on an African bunting
by Neville Brickell.37
The challenge of keeping kingfishers
by Gary Bralsford.41
Book Review
The Wisdom of Birds.46
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</figure>
</algorithms>
