<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.965476666666667" page_id="56254360"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
G)L
AVICULTURAL
m MAGAZINE
VOLUME 117
No. 2
2011
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990762" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254361" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.96126375" page_id="56254361"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2011: British Isles #21.00:
Overseas #24.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the
Society later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of
the AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.701188333333333" page_id="56254361"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, SHERATON LODGE, STATION ROAD, SOUTHMINSTER,
ESSEX CM0 7EW, UK.
</construct>
<bodyText confidence="0.91745" page_id="56254361"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Barclays Bank, Southminster Branch. Please quote
Account No. 13296954, Sort Code 20 54 30, and ensure you send your
name as the account reference, or else we cannot match payments. In case
of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and Treasurer at the address
above, or e-mail: otusscops@talktalk.net
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have not
been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of a
particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history. Articles
should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the scientific
names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given. References
cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line drawings,
black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular point in
the article will be used where possible and should be clearly captioned. If
authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when submitting the
article and write their name on the back of each photograph. Tables and
graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be aware of
the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of the page
which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997594" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56254361" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982475333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.79309" genericHeader="method" page_id="56254362" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.280854" page_id="56254362"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 117 - No. 2 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2011
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.666869" genericHeader="method" page_id="56254362" page_num="" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE ORIENTAL GREENFINCH
Carduelis sinica
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9813304" page_id="56254362"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Gary Bralsford
I have over the years kept and bred three species of Asian greenfinches,
the Oriental Greenfinch Carduelis sinica , Black-headed Greenfinch C.
ambigua and Vietnamese Greenfinch C monguilloti , all three of which can
be bred in a cage or aviary.
I had the most success with the Oriental Greenfinch, also known as the
Chinese, Grey-headed or Grey-capped Greenfinch, which I bred in a cage.
This species looks very like the British or European Greenfinch C. chloris,
but is slightly smaller and has a slate grey head. The male's head, however,
turns almost black when he is in breeding condition, but the female's plumage
remains more or less the same all year round. The male also has a more
prominent and longer yellow wing-bar than the female.
The Oriental Greenfinch is found in north-east Asia, where it breeds as
far north as Kamchatka and Sakhalin in the Russian Far East. The northern
population though is migratory and moves south following the breeding
season. The Oriental Greenfinch is a resident species principally in China,
Korea and Japan, where it inhabits wooded areas, city parks and gardens.
Its song is a melodious trilling "kirr-kirr korr-korr djeeeen" and its call a
metallic, harsh "cheeeh."
I always split up my pairs in the autumn, because after a few months
apart, they are keener to breed when spring comes around. I put the male and
female in a double or treble-sized breeding cage, separated from each other
by a wooden divider or slide. Then in early March, when the male begins to
sing, I open the divider or slide just enough to enable them to poke their heads
through and see each other. When the male comes into breeding condition,
he will attempt to feed the female. When she has been seen accepting food
from him, I place a basket with a nest pan in it on a bracket mounted on the
cage front. She will then usually begin to carry around in her beak the few
bits of nesting material I have provided. When this happens, I let the male
in with her and carefully watch their behaviour. If no fighting occurs I leave
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.984859" page_id="56254363"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
50
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.73584" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254363" page_num="50" year="" vol="">
BRALSFORB - ORIENTAL GREENFINCH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995178724137931" page_id="56254363"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
them together and see what happens.
Nest building usually occurs in April or early May. The nest is usually
built by both the male and female, but with the female lining the nest and
putting the finishing touches to it. Egg-laying occurs within five days of
the nest being completed. The usual clutch consists of three or four eggs
but there may, occasionally, be up to five eggs. These are light blue in
colour with brown markings mostly at the large end. The female sits for
12-14 days and all of the eggs hatch within 36 hours. The chicks fledge
after about 14 days.
I provide the parents with soaked seed, using a British and a Greenfinch
seed mix, and also provide them with plenty of seeding grasses and Dandelion
Taraxacum officinale heads. None of my Oriental Greenfinches have shown
any interest in eggfood I have placed in the dishes for them. On the advice
of a friend I give them comfrey Symphytum sp. as a greenfood before they
begin nesting.
Before the eggs are laid I also put a sulphur drag in the drinking water
to prevent problems with birds 'going light. 5 If this is given to the parents
early enough, I find that this can usually be avoided. A couple of seasons
ago, however, I lost seven out of nine young when they were 35 days old
and also lost five young Desert Finches Rhodospiza obsoleta with the same
condition at the same time.
It is a distressing problem. The youngsters gorge themselves on seed but
fail to put on weight and their beaks become caked with seed husks. If you
catch them up, you find that they are very thin and this is particularly evident
when you feel their breast bone. Once this happens there is little chance of
saving them and they usually die within a day or two. I have been told that
this is not quite such a problem if they are bred in an outside aviary.
Gary Bralsford is a UK member who lives in Yorkshire . E-mail: gary.
bralsford@hotmail. co. uk
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.6350015" page_id="56254363"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
* *
*
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.815629" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56254363" page_num="50" year="" vol="">
AUTUMN SOCIAL MEETING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.427188333333333" page_id="56254363"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
Members are reminded that this year&amp;apos;s Autumn Social Meeting is
being held on Saturday, September 24th, at Paultons Park, Gwer, Romsey,
Hampshire SOS 1 6AL
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.985988" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254364" page_num="51" year="" vol="">
VISUALLY SEXING THE HAWK-HEADED PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<keyword confidence="0.29863">
Deroptyus accipitrinus
</keyword>
<page confidence="0.989377" page_id="56254364"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
51
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.236553">
by Paolo Bertagnolio
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990134619047619" page_id="56254364"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
Most authors, including Hilty &amp; Brown (1986), Arndt (1996), Collar in
del Hoyo et al. (1997), Robiller (1997), Juniper &amp; Parr (1998), Clements &amp;
Shany (2001), Rodriguez-Mahecha &amp; Hemandez-Camacho (2002), Hilty
(2003) and Forshaw (2006), consider Deroptyus accipitrinus a sexually
monomorphic species. An exception is Sick (1993), who stated that the
female is larger, but provided no measurements.
Juniper &amp; Parr (1998) gave the following description: "...centre of breast
and belly claret-red with blue tips, creating blue-and-red scaling effect
sometimes with some green, especially on upper breast..." I considered the
green margin to the feathers of the upper breast of the male of the pair of the
nominate subspecies at the Centro per lo Studio e la Conservazione degli
Psittaciformi (CSCP) in Rome merely a somatic variation. In May 2008,
however, whilst looking at two proven pairs in the aviaries of an Italian
breeder, I noticed that the males had a green fringe to the feathers of the
upper breast, which the females lacked.
I have now examined no fewer than 36 proven adult pairs of the northern
nominate subspecies D. a. accipitrinus and can definitively confirm that the
presence or absence of the green margin to the feathers of the upper breast
represent a true and, easily interpreted, secondary sexual character. I found
the same difference between the male and female of two proven pairs of the
southern subspecies D. a. fascifrons I had the opportunity to examine.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.82637" genericHeader="references" page_id="56254364" page_num="51" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.761456166666667" page_id="56254364"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
Amdt, T. 1996. Lexicon of Parrots. Vol.4. Amdt Verlag, Bretton.
Clements, J. F. and Shany, N. 2001. A Field Guide to the Birds of Peru. Ibis Publishing
Company, Temecula, California.
Collar, N. J. 1997. Family Psittacidae. In: del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A. and Sargatal, J. (eds.). Handbook
of the Birds of the World. Volume 4 - Sandgrouse to Cuckoos. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona.
Forshaw, J. M. 2006. Parrots of the World - An Identification Guide. Princeton University
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.977877272727273">
Press, Princeton, New Jersey, USA.
Hilty, S. L. 2003. Birds of Venezuela. Christopher Helm, London.
Hilty, S. L. and Brown, W. L. 1986. Birds of Colombia. Princeton Univeristy Press, Princeton,
New Jersey, USA.
Juniper, T. and Parr, M. 1998. Parrots - A Guide to Parrots of the World. Pica Press, East
Sussex.
Robiller, F. 1997. Handuch der Vogelpfledge. Papageien, Band 3. Eugen Ulmer, Stuttgart.
Rodriguez-Mahecha, J. V. and Hernandez-Camacho, J. I. 2002. Loros de Colombia.
Conservation Intemacional Colombia.
Sick, H. 1993. Birds of Brazil. A Natural History. Princeton University Press, Princeton, New
Jersey, USA.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.995758" page_id="56254365"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
52
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9930355" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254365" page_num="52" year="" vol="">
ON SOME UK BIRD BREEDINGS
BY MEMBERS OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY IN 2009
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.980415108108108" page_id="56254365"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
by Reuben B. Girling
Introduction
I present here an insight into a small fraction of UK bird breeding
statistics. It is based on the species and numbers of birds voluntarily recorded
as bred in the UK in 2009 by some members of the Avicultural Society.
Specifically, the potentially eye-opening view drawn from twenty breeding
records covers a total of 916 birds bred from 155 species.
As a general point, the collated information is a survey. Extrapolation
of the collated data rests on the robustness of the original information. For
example, a particularly divergent breeding number, such as a sky high figure
present on one of a handful of reports that each are of single digit value,
will have a marked effect on typical values. For such reasoning, the range
of overall variation within some typically average values is sometimes
shown.
Data source
The breeding results are taken from returned Foreign Bird Federation
(FBF) Breeding Census forms for 2009 which were issued originally with
the Avicultural Magazine towards the end of that year.
The forms carried a request by the then FBF Registrar (at that time me,
and now fellow Council Member Philip Schofield) for completed returns
to be made by March 31 st 2010. In the event, the first duly completed form
was returned on December 4th 2009 and the final form was returned on
February 25th 2010.
Labelled - Birds UK-bred in 2009 by a member of the Avicultural Society
- the forms were printed on green paper for administration purposes. There
was a space for the contact details of the breeder, then there were three
columns, the first for the species scientific name (if known), the second for
the species common name and the third and final column for reporting the
number of each species bred. The forms had space for 10 species - which
is far more than some owners possess - never mind breed. If more than 10
species were bred, the additional species could be submitted by responding
breeders by photocopy or annotation.
Interestingly, as is the case with articles in the Avicultural Magazine
where both scientific and vernacular names are used, some 90% of the
returned forms included both the scientific and common names of the species.
One breeding record was received as a list within an e-mail, which
after I had extracted and printed it was mis-placed but recovered later.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.733523" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254366" page_num="53" year="" vol="">
GIRLING - UK BIRD BREEDINGS 2009
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997932" page_id="56254366"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
53
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.8919755" page_id="56254366"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
Distribution of species
The distribution of species on reports is listed in Table 1.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.860545">
Table 1. Distribution of species (n=155) on reports (n=20).
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.990673125" page_id="56254366"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
Number of species 130 18 4 2 1
No. of times reported 1 2 3 4 5
This shows the very small proportion of species that were most frequently
reported. It can be calculated that 95% of species (148 of 155) were bred
by a single or at most, two, individual breeders. Continuing at this extreme,
approaching 85% of the species bred were raised by single breeders.
Number of young raised
The distribution of the number of young raised from individual species
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.6836855" page_id="56254366"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
(Table 2) records that for each of ca. 28% (43) of all species bred (155) only
one young was raised.
</construct>
<tableCaption confidence="0.91239">
Table 2. Distribution of 916 young raised from 155 species bred.
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.623146" page_id="56254366"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
Birds bred per species 1 2345 6 7 89 11-20 22-46
No. of species 43 13 18 20 15 6 5 5 4 20 6
Species most often reported
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.8072775" page_id="56254366"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
As expected, some of the species that are commonly held in UK
aviculture were cited in several reports (Table 3).
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.985574">
Table 3. Top three species most often reported.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.958452181818182" page_id="56254366"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
Species
No. of reports
No. bred
Superb Starling Lamprotornis superbus
5
23
Diamond Dove Geopelia cuneata
4
16
Java Sparrow Padda oryzivora
4
</figure>
<page confidence="0.996234" page_id="56254366"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
29
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.988833" page_id="56254366"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
The five reports of the Superb Starling constitute 25% of all reports. The
top three species most often bred (ca. 2% of all 155 species bred) together
yielded a total of ca. 7.5% (68) of all (916) young raised.
Species bred in greatest number
As expected, some of the species that are commonly bred in large
numbers in UK aviculture were reported (Table 4).
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.987319">
Table 4. Top three species bred in greatest number.
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.45312425" page_id="56254366"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
Species No. of reports No. bred
Mandarin Duck Aix galericulata 2 46
Barbary Dove Streptopelia roseogrisea dom. 1 39
Java Sparrow Padda oryzivora 4 29
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.814755" page_id="56254366"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
The top three species bred in greatest number (ca. 2% of all 155 species
bred) together yielded ca. 12.5% (114) of all (916) young raised.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996357" page_id="56254367"  page_num="54" year="" vol="">
54
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.929536" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254367" page_num="54" year="" vol="">
GIRLING - UK BIRD BREEDINGS 2009
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997042285714286" page_id="56254367"  page_num="54" year="" vol="">
Species reported as bred
Save for some of what in earlier times were classed in exhibition circles
as "Common Seedeaters," the majority of the 155 species recorded (Table
5) are largely unseen at cage bird shows. Indeed, the reported species bred
are mostly those present in public and private collections and that are part
of conservation programmes rather than birds held by private individuals
for exhibiting and related purposes.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.68261">
Table 5. Species reported as bred in 2009.
</tableCaption>
<equation confidence="0.9492695" page_id="56254367"  page_num="54" year="" vol="">
R = number of reports; B = number bred
R B Species
</equation>
<footnote confidence="0.972306">
2 13 African Grey Parrot Psittacus erithacus
1 1 African Olive Pigeon Columba arquatrix
1 3 African Pygmy-Goose Nettapus auritus
1 1 Amethyst Starling Cinnyricinclus leucogaster
1 3 Azure-winged Magpie Cyanopica cyanus
1 5 Baikal Teal Anas formosa
1 39 Barbary Dove Streptopelia roseogrisea dom.
1 2 Barbary Partridge Alectoris bar bar a
1 1 Bare-eyed Pigeon Patagioenas corensis
1 2 Bare-faced Ground Dove Metriopelia ceciliae
1 4 Barnacle Goose Branta leucopsis
1 5 Bengalese Lonchura striata dom.
1 15 Black Francolin Francolinus francolinus
1 20 Black-crested Guineafowl Guttera pucherani edouardi
1 4 Black-headed Greenfinch Carduelis ambigua
1 1 Blacksmith Plover Vanellus armatus
1 1 Black-winged Lory Eos cyanogenia
1 2 Blue Eared-Pheasant Crossoptilon auritum
14 Blue Ground Dove Claravis pretiosa
1 4 Blue-capped Waxbill Uraeginthus cyanocephalus
1 5 Blue-headed Macaw Primolius couloni
1 7 Boobook Owl Ninox boobook
1 6 Bornean Crested Fireback Lophura ignita
1 12 Bourke's Parrot Neopsephotus bourkii
1 1 Brown Eared-Pheasant Crossoptilon mantchuricum
1 5 Burrowing Owl Athene cunicularia
1 12 Carolina/Wood Duck A ixsponsa
1 1 Chaco Owl Strix chacoensis
1 3 Cheer Pheasant Catreus wallichii
3 13 Chestnut-backed Thrush Zoothera dohertyi
3 20 Chinese Bamboo Partridge Bambusicola thoracicus
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.902557" page_id="56254368"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
11
7
</page>
<figure confidence="0.9044774" page_id="56254368"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
1
3
3
2
16
5
13
5
1
3
18
1
8
19
17
1
1
1
5
5
13
1
4
4
1
5
1
2
7
7
1
3
29
20
1
6
4
9
1
GIRLING - UK BIRD BREEDINGS 2009
</figure>
<page confidence="0.389921" page_id="56254368"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
55
</page>
<table confidence="0.958531390243903" page_id="56254368"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
Chinese Painted Quail Coturnix chinensis
Common Bronzewing Phaps chalcoptera
Common Mynah Acridotheres tristis
Coroneted Fruit Dove Ptilinopus coronulatus
Crested Wood Partridge Rollulus rouloul
Demoiselle Crane Anthropoides virgo
Diamond Dove Geopelia cuneata
Edwards's Pheasant Lophura edwardsi
Elliot's Pheasant Syrmaticus ellioti
Emerald Dove Chalcophaps indica
Eurasian Hoopoe Upupa epops
Eyton's/Plumed Whistling Duck Dendrocygna eytonii
Falcated Teal Anas falcata
Fischer's Turaco Tauracofischeri
Giant Wood Rail Aramides ypecaha
Golden Pheasant Chrysolophus pictus
Gouldian Finch Erythrura gouldiae
Great Curassow Crax rubra
Greater Blue-eared Starling Lamprotornis chalybaeus
Greater Necklaced Laughingthrush Garrulax p. pectoralis
Green Pheasant Phasianus v. versicolor
Grey Junglefowl Gallus sonneratii
Grey Peacock-Pheasant Polyplectron bicalcaratum
Guira Cuckoo Guira guira
Hahn's Macaw Diopsittaca n. nobilis
Heck's Grassfinch Poephila acuticauda hecki
Hill Mynah Gracula religiosa
Himalayan Monal Lophophorus impejanus
Hispaniolan Amazon Amazona ventralis
Hooded Merganser Lophodytes cucullatus
Hottentot Teal Anas hottentota
Hume's Pheasant Syrmaticus humiae
Hyacinth Macaw Anodorhynchus hyacinthinus
Indian Scops Owl Otus bakkamoena
Java Sparrow Padda oryzivora
Javan/Lesser Whistling Duck Dendrocygna javanica
Koklass Pheasant Pucrasia macrolopha
Lady Amherst's Pheasant Chrysolophus amherstiae
Laughing Dove Streptopelia senegalensis
Laughing Kookaburra Dacelo novaeguineae
Leadbeater's Cockatoo Cacatua l leadbeateri
</table>
<page confidence="0.545579" page_id="56254369"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
9
</page>
<figure confidence="0.953050925" page_id="56254369"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
5
1
2
2
2
8
46
4
6
7
4
8
4
3
5
1
5
4
3
4
4
1
1
3
9
16
6
3
18
3
1
11
5
2
4
1
4
1
5
3
</figure>
<page confidence="0.945668" page_id="56254369"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
7
</page>
<table confidence="0.992531372093023" page_id="56254369"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
GIRLING - UK BIRD BREEDINGS 2009
Lemon Dove Aplopelia larvata
Lesser Kiskadee Pitangus lictor
Lilac-breasted Roller Coracias caudatus
Lilac-crowned Amazon Amazona finschi
Lineated Kalij Pheasant Lophura leucomelanos lineata
Livingstone's Turaco Tauraco livingstonii
Luzon Bleeding-heart Gallicolumba luzonica
Mandarin Duck Aix galericulata
Mikado Pheasant Syrmaticus mikado
Mindanao Bleeding-heart Gallicolumba criniger bartletti
Mountain Bamboo Partridge Bambusicola jytchii
Nepal Kalij Pheasant Lophura leucomelanos
Orange-headed Thrush Zoothera citrina
Orange-winged Amazon Amazona amazonica
Oriental Greenfinch Carduelis sinica
Pacific Brent Goose Branta bernicula nigricans
Pacific Scaup Aythya marila mariloides
Pagoda Starling Sturnus pagodarum
Peaceful Dove Geopelia placida
Pekin Robin Leiothrix lutea
Plum-headed Parakeet Psittacula cyanocephala
Purple Glossy Starling Lamprotornis purpureus
Purple Grenadier Uraeginthus ianthinogaster
Purple Swamphen Porphyrio porphyrio poliocephalus
Purple-crested Turaco Tauraco porphyreolophus
Red-and-Yellow Barbet Trachyphonus erythrocephalus
Red Avadavat Amandava amandava
Red Turtle Dove Streptopelia tranquebarica
Red-billed Firefmch Lagonosticta senegala
Red-billed Starling Sturnus sericeus
Red-breasted Goose Branta ruficollis
Red-crested Cardinal Paroaria coronata
Red-crested Finch Coryphospingus cucullatus
Red-crested Turaco Tauraco erythrolophus
Red-fronted Barbet Tricholaema diademata
Red-fronted Kakariki Cyanoramphus novaezelandiae
Red-legged Seriema Cariama cristata
Red-tailed Amazon Amazona brasiliensis
Red-tailed Laughingthrush Garrulax m. milnei
Red-whiskered Bulbul Pycnonotus jocosus
Red-winged Starling Onychognathus morio
Ringed Teal Callonetta leucophrys
</table>
<figure confidence="0.940720976190476" page_id="56254370"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
2
1
5
1
6
1
4
4
1
4
2
3
13
1
1
1
3
23
5
1
8
1
1
6
4
1
1
3
1
3
9
1
22
3
1
2
1
1
8
2
27
GIRLING - UK BIRD BREEDINGS 2009
</figure>
<page confidence="0.914908" page_id="56254370"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
57
</page>
<table confidence="0.983406756097561" page_id="56254370"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
Rufous-vented Chachalaca Ortalis ruficauda
San Bias Jay Cyanocorax sanhlasiana
Satyr Tragopan Tragopan satyra
Scarlet-faced Liocichla Liocichla ripponi
Silver Pheasant Lophura nycthemera
Silver Teal Anas versicolor
Smew Mergellus albellus
Snowy-crowned Robin-Chat Cossypha niveicapilla
Socorro Dove Zenaida graysoni
Southern Lapwing Vanellus chilensis
Southern White-faced Owl Ptilopsis grand
Spangled Cotinga Codnga cayana
Speckled Pigeon Columba guinea
Spicebird Lonchura punctulata
Sulawesi Ground Dove Gallicolumba trisdgmata
Sulawesi Ground Dove Gallicolumba trisdgmata bimaculata
Sun Conure Aradnga solsddalis
Superb Starling Lamprotornis superbus
Tambourine Dove Turtur tympanistria
Tawny Frogmouth Podargus strigoides
Tropical Mockingbird Mimus gilvus
Tropical Screech Owl Megascops choliba
Turkey Vulture Cathartes aura
Vinaceous Dove Streptopelia vinacea
Violet Turaco Musophaga violacea
Von der Decken's Hombill Tockus deckeni
Vulturine Guineafowl Acryllium vulturinum
Western Grey Plantain-eater Crinifer piscator
White Stork Ciconia ciconia
White Woodpecker Melanerpes candidus
White-cheeked Turaco Tauraco leucods
White-naped Crane Grus vipio
White-shouldered Starling Sturnus sinensis
White-throated Magpie-Jay Calocitta f. formosa
Wompoo Fruit Dove Pdlinopus magnificus
Yellow-crowned Amazon Amazona ochrocephala
(Double) Yellow-headed Amazon Amazona oratrix oratrix
Yellow-lored Amazon Amazona xantholora
Yellow-necked Francolin Francolinus leucoscepus
Yellow-shouldered Amazon Amazona barbadensis
Zebra Finch Taeniopygia guttata ( castanodsl )
</table>
<page confidence="0.996259" page_id="56254371"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
58
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.930736" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254371" page_num="58" year="" vol="">
GIRLING - UK BIRD BREEDINGS 2009
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9195955" page_id="56254371"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
The focus on non-exhibition species largely holds to the magazine text,
social events and visits by members of the Avicultural Society (thanks to
noble volunteers the society has a presence at some primary exhibition/sales
events).
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.9646695" page_id="56254371"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
Numerical summary
Number of birds bred = 916.
Number of species bred =155.
Number of breeding reports = 20.
Breedings per report 916/20 = 46 (range 3-196).
Species per report 155/20 = 8 (range 1-34).
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.947618083333333" page_id="56254371"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
Highest breeding, one species = 46 Mandarin Duck A. galericulata.
Highest breeding, one breeder = 196 (21% of all birds bred).
Most species bred by a single breeder = 34 (ca. 3.5% of all species bred).
Top recorded species = Superb Starling L. superbus (on 25% of reports).
Clearly, the collated UK breeding records presented here are but a small-
scale survey of avicultural achievement within the UK membership of the
society. The overall record of breeding achievement in this small-scale
survey is incomplete. Greater participation by UK members would produce
a clearer picture. More's the pity when an aviculturist, be they a beginner
or well versed in the subject, is seeking unrelated birds and especially so of
UK-bred stock. However, this is addressed in part by the Special Interest
Groups.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.869551" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56254371" page_num="58" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9849354" page_id="56254371"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
Thanks to the Foreign Bird Federation (FBF) for much of my
apprenticeship with UK bird breeding statistics - leading to articles in,
for example, Cage &amp; Aviary Birds (published in 2009 by IPC Media, but
published now by the Kelsey Publishing Group), Foreign Birds (Foreign
Bird League) and Tyto (International Owl Society).
Special words of congratulations and thanks go to those UK members
of the Avicultural Society who volunteered details of their breeding results
for 2009 to the FBF when I was Breeding Registrar.
Reuben B. Girling is a Council Member of the Avicultural Society and
lives with his wife, Pam, in Cornwall. E-mail: rgirling@btinternet.com
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996714" page_id="56254372"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
59
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.978606" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254372" page_num="59" year="" vol="">
THE DALLAS WORLD AQUARIUM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996666473684211" page_id="56254372"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
by Pierre de Chabannes
To European zoo and animal lovers the USA is a dream destination
with many renowned zoological institutions and comprehensive animal
collections. My introduction to North American zoos and only previous
visit to the New World had been in 2007 when I spent a winter's day at the
famous Toronto Zoo in Canada. In spite of being there during a snowstorm,
I was really impressed by the overall quality of the zoo and the number of
species rarely seen in captivity.
Since then I had been excitedly looking forward to making my first visit
to a US zoo. The opportunity eventually came in February 2010, when my
friends Josef and Natalie Lindholm invited me to spend two weeks with them
in Texas. Josef is Senior Aviculturist at Dallas World Aquarium which is, of
course, one of the institutions I most wanted to visit. I was though totally
unprepared for the extraordinary animal collection I discovered there.
To those of us living in Europe, Dallas World Aquarium has remained
something of a mystery. The first time I heard about it, it sounded like a
fairly standard aquarium with, apparently, not only fish but also some birds.
However, the truth did not even come close to this.
Dallas World Aquarium was, as the name suggests, originally an aquarium
showcasing mostly tropical sea fish and an impressive collection of corals
and invertebrates in beautifully designed tanks. The only birds were a small
group of African Black-footed Penguins Spheniscus demersus housed beside
the main building.
The story began with an old warehouse in downtown Dallas which was
purchased by Daryl Richardson and transformed according to his tastes and
design into the Dallas World Aquarium. It took a year to construct and was
eventually opened to the public in 1992. As its popularity increased, Daryl
Richardson decided to expand his collection and add some more birds, as well
as adding mammals, reptiles and amphibians. In order to build the exhibits
he visualised, he bought two more nearby warehouses in 1996 and 2000.
In 1995, eight species of toucans purchased from Jerry Jennings's
Emerald Forest Bird Gardens in California arrived at the aquarium. Since
then the bird collection has never stopped growing. Daryl Richardson's
passion and knowledge of Central and South American wildlife has led to
Dallas World Aquarium working closely with indigenous associations such
as PROFAUNA and FUNPZA in Venezuela and IBAMA in Brazil, not
only in the creation of captive breeding programmes for species which had
previously hardly ever been seen in captivity, but also in providing funding
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.991143" page_id="56254373"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
60
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.933922" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254373" page_num="60" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - DALLAS WORLD AQUARIUM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990343829268293" page_id="56254373"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
and logistical support for field work and the construction of rehabilitation
centres in Mexico, Costa Rica, Venezuela and other countries.
Today, Dallas World Aquarium has one of the most interesting collections
in North America. Its bird collection is especially exciting, including as it
does many members of the Ramphastidae family, cotingas and hummingbirds.
Many world first breedings have been recorded, thanks to the excellent work
of Daryl Richardson and his dedicated team of biologists and keepers.
I was fortunate enough to spend a full week at the aquarium and to visit
every part of it, including the behind the scenes breeding facilities. With
the help of Daryl Richardson and Josef Lindholm, I was able to observe
and photograph almost all of the species kept in this most impressive
collection.
Even before reaching the entrance, we had observed a number of
interesting species exhibited in small to medimum-sized aviaries which form
part of the first thematic zone, the - Wilds of Borneo. I was surprised to see a
pair of Jambu Fruit Doves Ptilinopus jambu , recently arrived from a private
aviculturist in Florida. I had previously seen this species during my 2009
visit to Penang Bird Park in Malaysia but, due to a memory card failure, my
photos had been lost. This fruit dove remains quite common in the USA and
is exhibited by at least 22 US institutions, whereas it has virtually disappeared
from European zoological gardens. Other birds displayed in this zone include
a pair of Rhinoceros Hombills Buceros rhinoceros , a breeding pair of Great
Argus Argusianus a. argus and a breeding pair of Victoria Crowned Pigeons
Goura victoria , which live with a US captive-bred pair of Palm Cockatoos
Probosciger aterrimus (subspecies unknown). A breeding pair of Matschie's
Tree Kangaroos Dendrolagus matschiei is also displayed.
Next, there is big, recently built aviary, which houses African birds
including a Saddle-billed Stork Ephippiorhynchus senegalensis, a flock of
Red-billed Ducks Anas erythrorhyncha imported from Tanzania and the
Eastern Yellow-billed Hombill Tockus flavirostris , plus several species of
turacos, including the beautiful Great Blue Turaco Corythaeola cristata
and Fischer's Turaco Tauraco fischeri. Behind the scenes there were
two more species, Ross's Musophaga rossae and the White-crested T.
leucolophus. A breeding group of eight Little Blue Penguins Eudyptula
minor novaehollandiae , a species rarely kept in captivity and one which
has now almost disappeared from European collections, is visible from the
main entrance hall and from the courtyard where the African Black-footed
Penguins are kept. Three young were hatched in 2010, two of which are
still alive today.
Our route next took us through a stairway leading to the first major
attraction of the complex, the incredible - Orinoco exhibit - the first of
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.818425" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254374" page_num="61" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - DALLAS WORLD AQUARIUM
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998166" page_id="56254374"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
61
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.97106925" page_id="56254374"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
two gigantic tropical halls to be opened to the public in 1997. The first
birds I spotted was a young US-bred pair of Blue-throated Macaws Ara
glaucogularis in a small aviary, one of several aviaries in which the birds
are displayed behind glass. These macaws will eventually be set up as a
breeding pair. Another nearby exhibit called - Jungle Jewels - consists of a
very nicely landscaped aviary, housing behind glass more than 10 different
species, ranging from tanagers to manakins, doves and barbets, too delicate
to risk with larger and potentially aggressive birds in the large, open exhibits.
The two largest species in this aviary are the Rufous-breasted Quail-Dove
Geotrygon chiriquensis and the Little Tinamou Cryturellus soui , both living
in breeding groups. These two rarely seen species are kept in fewer than five
zoos around the world. The rarest species of bird in this aviary is the unusual
Prong-billed Barbet Semnornis frantzii. A pair was imported from Panama
in 2007 but, unfortunately, the female died after laying eggs. However,
a further importation is planned and it is still hoped to breed this species.
Tanagers are well represented in this aviary and amongst those we saw were
a pair of Swallow Tanagers Tersinia viridis , examples of one of the yellow-
ramped subspecies of the Paradise Tanager Tangara chilensis paradisea , a
Black-faced Dacnis Dacnis lineata - a species once relatively common in
captivity but now impossible to find anymore in other public collections - and
a small group of Blue-naped Chlorophonia Chlorophonia cyanea , another
species absent now from other public collections. As many Central and South
American countries stop bird exports, many species such as the tanagers are
becoming rarer in public collections, especially in Europe. Dallas World
Aquarium is still fortunate enough to exhibit several species of manakins.
It has the Red-capped Manakin Pipra mentalis , Golden-headed Manakin R
erythyrocephala , the Golden-collared Manakin Manacus vitellinus which has
bred twice behind the scenes, Lance-tailed Manakin Chiroxiphia lanceolata
and Blue-crowned Manakin Lepidothrix cornata.
The entrance to the Orinoco tropical hall features a huge aviary on the
left-hand side. This houses a Giant Anteater Myrmecophaga tridactyla ,
along with a breeding group of Red Howler Monkeys Alouatta car ay a, a
pair of Toco Toucans Ramphastos toco , Swainson's Toucans R. (ambiguus)
swainsonii and Keel-billed Toucans R. sulfuratus , a pair of Northern
Helmeted or Helmeted Curassows Pauxi pauxi which bred for the first
time in 2010 and is unrelated to other US specimens, and a breeding group
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.8562304">
of Yellow-crowned Night Herons Nyctanassa v. violacea which came
from a bird rehabilitation centre on the outskirts of Dallas. There is also a
Montezuma Oropendola Psarocolius montezumae , a group of Grey-necked
Wood Rails Aramides cajanea - a species replaced in European zoos by the
Giant Wood Rail A. ypecaha - a Groove-billed Toucanet Aulacorhynchus
</reference>
<page confidence="0.941535" page_id="56254375"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
62
</page>
<figure confidence="0.5825736" page_id="56254375"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - DALLAS WORLD AQUARIUM
Pierre de Chabannes
Male Andean Cock-of-the-Rock.
Pierre de Chabannes
Andean Cock-of-the-Rock chick.
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.890635666666667" page_id="56254375"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
s. sulcatus , a species which cannot be seen in captivity anywhere else (one
is on display and others are housed behind the scenes) - and the northern
subspecies of the Collared Ara?ari P. t. torquatus.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.803633" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254376" page_num="63" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - DALLAS WORLD AQUARIUM
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.97596" page_id="56254376"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
63
</page>
<table confidence="0.665905" page_id="56254376"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
Pierre de Chabannes
Male Guianan Cock-of-the-Rock.
Pierre de Chabannes
The displaying male crouches on a patch of ground known as his court.
Flying free in this amazing tropical hall are five different species of
</table>
<reference confidence="0.301796">
Icteridae, the Green Oropendola P, viridis. Crested Oropendola R decumanus ,
some Yellow-ramped Caciques Cacicus cela and a number of Red-ramped
Caciques C. haemorrhous , a species which breeds regularly, and the Scarlet-
</reference>
<page confidence="0.997651" page_id="56254377"  page_num="64" year="" vol="">
64
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.940635" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254377" page_num="64" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - DALLAS WORLD AQUARIUM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995225268292683" page_id="56254377"  page_num="64" year="" vol="">
headed Marshbird Amblyramphus holosericeus. The beautiful Curl-crested
Jay Cyanocorax cristellus , a species rarely seen in captivity, also inhabits
the dense vegetation growing in the hall. There are also three members of
the toucan family, hatched at Dallas World Aquarium, which often come
close to visitors. By far the most numerous of these is the Pale-mandibled
Araqari P. erythropygius , a species which has bred at Dallas World Aquarium
since 2002. This araqari is now fairly common in North American zoos,
thanks largely to the work of Daryl Richardson and his team and others,
but is to be seen in only two public collections in Europe. The other two
species are the Crimson-rumped Toucanet A. haematopygus - also found in
Europe but in fewer than five zoos - and the striking looking Venezuelan
Ivory-billed Araqari P. azara flavirostris , bred at the aquarium for the first
time in 2005.
There are two enormous aviaries on the far side of the hall. Although
the public can get a glimpse into these two exhibits from the walkway, they
were purposely built in a quiet area in which the occupants can breed largely
undisturbed. This has been achieved to great success with the breeding
group of Andean Cocks-of-the-Rock Rupicola p. peruviana. Two females
lay eggs regularly and, since the first breeding in 2007, 38 chicks have been
hatched and 24 are still alive today. There is also a flock of Capuchinbirds
Perissocephalus tricolor , a species which has been bred in captivity only at
San Diego Zoo in the early 1990s (see Avicultural Magazine Vol. 100, No. 1,
pp.3-7 and photos of chick aged 22 days and aged 28 days). This species
is currently kept in fewer than five zoos around the world, including in one
European collection. A pair of Wattled Guans Aburria aburri, a breeding
pair of Pale-mandibled Araqaris, a group of Green Araqaris P. viridis , a
Blue-crowned Motmot Momotus momota lessonii, several Screaming
Pihas Lipaugus vociferans, two further members of the Icteridae family, the
Common Hangnest or Troupial Icterus icterus and the rarely seen Moriche
Oriole I. chrysocephalus , and three Red-crested Cardinals Paroaria coronata
are among the other inhabitants of these aviaries. There are also a pair of
Nocturnal Curassows Nothocrax urumutum , a Puerto Rican Woodpecker
Melanerpes portoricensis, a nice flock of Pompadour Cotingas Xipholena
punicea and several species of tanagers, including the familiar Blue-grey
species Thraupis episcopus and two rare species, the Yellow-rumped
Ramphocelus (flammigerus) icteronotus and the Scarlet-rumped Tanager
R. passerinii.
Following the path, we walked passed the tamarin island and the pair
of Brazilian Giant Otters Pteronura brasiliensis to a small aviary designed
to house young toucans and aratparis which are tame enough to be fed by
visitors with fruit provided from a stand nearby. We then passed some more
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.81841" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254378" page_num="65" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - DALLAS WORLD AQUARIUM
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998231" page_id="56254378"  page_num="65" year="" vol="">
65
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.994648219512195" page_id="56254378"  page_num="65" year="" vol="">
mammal exhibits, including a pair of Three-toed Sloths Bradypus variegatus,
currently the only examples of this species outside of tropical America. We
then came to a tall aviary housing a number of birds including a second
pair of Wattled Guans, two male Plate-billed Mountain Toucans Andigena
laminirostris - a breeding pair is housed behind the scenes - a Red-breasted
Toucan R. discolor us, a species which has now almost vanished from
zoological collections - and an Emerald Toucanets. p. prasinus.
The main path takes visitors into each comer of this tropical hall and we
saw several small terrariums designed for poison-dart frogs, a large pool
occupied by a breeding pair of Endangered Orinoco Crocodiles Crocodylus
intermedins , an exhibit displaying a group of Vampire Bats Desmodus
rotundus housed behind glass and several other small exhibits with freshwater
fish, turtles and other reptiles. Amongst these exhibits there are two more
aviaries with the birds displayed behind glass. The first of these is occupied
by a pair of (Double) Yellow-headed Amazons Amazona o. oratrix which
has laid eggs and partly reared chicks, the second is a mixed-species exhibit
housing a pair of Chestnut-eared Aragaris P. castanotis, living with Golden
Lion Tamarins Leontopithecus rosalia and Anacondas Eunectes murinus.
Dallas World Aquarium is the only collection currently displaying the
Chestnut-eared Aragari, a species it bred for the first time in 1990.
There are three more aviaries in the tropical hall each displaying
the birds behind glass. The first houses a pair of Hawk-headed Parrots
Deroptyus a. accipitrinus, the second a pair of Red-crowned Woodpeckers
M. rubricapillus and the third is usually occupied by young Many-banded
Aragaris P pluricinctus , young Saffron Toucanets Baillonus baillonii , or
other young aragaris or toucanets. The largest of two other exhibits houses
an Ariel Toucan R. vitellinus ariel , a Channel-billed Toucan R. v. vitellinus
and a pair of Bare-faced Curassows C.fasciolata. The smaller of the two is
home to two Giant Tinamous Tinamus major castaneiceps which share the
exhibit with Night Monkeys or Douroucoulis Aotus trivirgatus and sloths
Bradypodidae.
Two orphaned Antillean Manatees Trichechus m. manatus brought
back from Venezuela live in a huge 200,000 gallons (approx. 166,000 UK
gallons/750,000 litres) pool in which there is a viewing window through
which they can be watched swimming underwater. The pool and its surrounds
is also home to a flock of White-faced Whisling Ducks Dendrocygna viduata,
some Brazilian Ducks Amazonetta brasiliensis , a pair of Orinoco Geese
Neochen jubata and some Black-necked Swans Cygnus melanocoryphus .
Stairs lead down to some amazing seawater fish exhibits, which showcase
many species which are not often seen in public aquariums in Europe. There
are Leafy Seadragons Phycodurus eques from Australia, beautiful Philippines
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.831904" page_id="56254379"  page_num="66" year="" vol="">
66
</page>
<table confidence="0.6548322" page_id="56254379"  page_num="66" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - DALLAS WORLD AQUARIUM
Male Black-cheeked Woodpecker.
Pierre de Chabannes
One of two female Guianan Crested Eagles, a species not found in captivity
outside of America.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.800847" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254380" page_num="67" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - DALLAS WORLD AQUARIUM
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.972174" page_id="56254380"  page_num="67" year="" vol="">
67
</page>
<table confidence="0.836325" page_id="56254380"  page_num="67" year="" vol="">
Pierre de Chabannes
The male Scarlet-thighed Dacnis's red thighs are concealed from view by the branch.
Pierre de Chabannes
Female Sparkling Violet-ear on nest.
</table>
<page confidence="0.998238" page_id="56254381"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
68
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.928775" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254381" page_num="68" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - DALLAS WORLD AQUARIUM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987143926829268" page_id="56254381"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
Clownfish Amphiprion thiellei and Spectacled Angelfish Chaetodontoplus
conspicillatus also from Australia. Dallas World Aquarium has one of the
most interesting collection of clownfishes in the world, with many rare
and unusual species, and the largest group of Leafy Seadragons outside of
Australia.
Walking through the book shop takes visitors outside, where a small
group of African Black-footed Penguins live in a nicely landscaped enclosure
with a pool. An aviary nearby houses White-crested Turacos and hyraxes
Procaviidae. Then there are some reptile and amphibian displays which
focus on Madagascan and East African species, with a pair of African Green
Pigeons Treron calva in a temporary exhibit.
We then entered a sort of cave exhibit called the Sacred Cenote, which
consists mostly of terrariums, but also includes a grassy enclosure in
which Elegant Crested Tinamous Eudromia elegans and a breeding pair
of Burrowing Owls Athene cunicularia hypugaea are kept with Desert
Cottontails Sylvilagus audubonii. A pair of Eastern Screech Owls Megascops
asio live in small aviary above a ciclid tank. Passing through the impressive
shark tunnel and past some more reptile exhibits, we come to another cave
exhibit, this one showcasing a pair of Barred Owls Strix varia helveola in
front of a small enclosure in which bats are kept.
The second and last huge hall has a totally different type of vegetation
and landscaping, modelled on the dry tropical forests of Mexico and South
America. This monster exhibit, appropriately named - Mundo Maya - houses
an impressive collection of birds, ranging from jananas and flamingos to
hummingbirds and tanagers. There are also enclosures housing larger
mammals, including a Jaguar Panthera onca and an Ocelot Fells pardalis,
as well as a group of Orange-ramped Agoutis Dasyprocta leporina. The
latter live with a breeding pair of Ocellated Turkeys Meleagris ocellata and
a breeding pair of Spectacled Owls Pulsatrix perspicillata .
On the upper storeys of Mundo Maya are aviaries built to accommodate
three species of raptors and a pair of Scarlet Macaws Ara m. macao . Two of
the three species of birds of prey, the Black Hawk-Eagles Spizaetus tyrannus
and Ornate Hawk-Eagles S. ornatus , are breeding. The third species, the
Guianan Crested Eagle Morphnus guianensis, a bird not found in captivity
anywhere outside of America, is represented by two females. Following
my visit the Black Hawk-Eagles were replaced by a young Harpy Eagle
Harpia harpyja.
Dallas World Aquarium has two female Jabiras Jabiru mycteria and is
now the only public collection in North America displaying this Central and
South American stork. Just below the feeding area for the hummingbirds,
which is accessible only to the keepers, is a large aviary beneath an artificial
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.818382" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254382" page_num="69" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - DALLAS WORLD AQUARIUM
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998055" page_id="56254382"  page_num="69" year="" vol="">
69
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997111975609756" page_id="56254382"  page_num="69" year="" vol="">
rocky outcrop. Living in this aviary is a mixed group of Black-tailed
Trogon melanurus and White-tailed Trogons T. viridis , along with some
Blue-crowned Motmots and Ruddy Quail-Doves G. montana. The Jabirus
are easy to observe as their aviary is close to the main path, but seeing the
raptors and trogons is more difficult as their aviaries are high in the hall and
can be seen only from a distance.
Between the shark tank and the Jaguar exhibit there is a small pool with
an island in the centre on which a small colony of Caribbean Flamingos
Phoenicopterus ruber has been installed. This is amongst the most popular
exhibits in this huge hall. There are also Wattled Ja^anas Jacana jacana ,
with a few of the birds roaming free and it was wonderful to see them flying
and showing-off their bright yellow flight feathers, which would otherwise
have remained hidden.
The Cotingidae family is well represented in Mundo Maya. Firstly there
is the Spangled Cotinga Cotinga cayana, the beauiful male with his amazing
turquoise and purple plumage, proving a favourite with visitors. Less brightly
coloured, but no less interesting are the Bare-necked Fruitcrow Gymnoderus
foetidus and, the Purple-throated Fruitcrow Querula purpurata , which has
only ever been bred at Wuppertal Zoo in Germany. Both of these species,
which are extremely rare in captivity, can also be seen at Veldhoven Parrot
Park in the Netherlands. Other occupants of Mundo Maya include a Yellow-
green Grosbeak Caryothraustes canadensis , a Golden-bellied Grosbeak
Pheucticus chrysogaster , a group of Rufous-breasted Quail-Doves and a
pair of Golden-collared Manakins. The manakins can rarely be seen but
the "clicking" sound made by the male during his courtship display could
be heard throughout the exhibit several times a day.
Many of the smaller birds are difficult to observe in this gigantic hall,
there are some exceptions though such as the conspicuous Red-legged
Honeycreeper Cyanerpes cyaneus, the Purple Honeycreeper C. caeruleus - a
species which bred in the hall some years ago - and the Green Honeycreeper
Chlorophanes spiza. Less easy to see is the Crimson-backed Tanager R.
dimidiatus , which can occasionally be seen near the feeding area. There is
also an interesting collection of euphonias, including a group of Antillean
Euphonias Euphonia musica - a species which can be seen only at Dallas
World Aquarium and San Antonio Zoo - some Yellow-throated Euphonias E.
hirundinacea , a few Violaceous Euphonias E. violacea and a Thick-billed
Euphonia laniirostris. Other tanagers include the Burnish-huff 7.' cayana
which is extremely shy, some more Paradise Tanagers T. c. paradisea , a
Blue-necked Tanager T. cyanicollis , a group of Speckled Tanagers T. guttata
eusticta , two Silver-throated Tanagers T. icterocephala - a species seen in
Europe only at Basel Zoo - a nice group of Opal-ramped Tanagers T. velia
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.942392" page_id="56254383"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
70
</page>
<table confidence="0.288674333333333" page_id="56254383"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANMES - DALLAS WORLD AQUARIUM
Pierre de Chahannes
Venezuelan Ivory-billed Ara^ari.
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.996288357142857" page_id="56254383"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
and a Western Spindalis Spindalis zena. There are also some Silver-beaked
Tanagers R. carbo , a group of beautiful Scarlet-thighed Dacnis Dacnis
venusta and probably one or two other species that I failed to spot despite
the countless hours I spent in this gigantic hall.
Mundo Maya is also home to one of the largest collections of
hummingbirds in captivity today. Many were imported for the opening
of this massive exhibit in 2004. Of course, not all of them have survived,
but at least a dozen species have established themselves and some breed
regularly, the most prolific of these being the Sparkling Violet-ear Colibri
coruscans which can be seen in various parts of the hall. Thanks to Daryl
Richardson and his team, I was able to go to the top of the hall where the
feeding area is, so that I could photograph the birds and was able to see
the beautiful female Long-tailed Sylph Aglaiocercus kingi - a species seen
nowhere else in captivity today - and a bird which almost never comes down
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.779266" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254384" page_num="71" year="" vol="">
DE CHABAMNES - DALLAS WORLD AQUARIUM
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.937185" page_id="56254384"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
71
</page>
<figure confidence="0.722406" page_id="56254384"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
Pierre de Chabannes
The unusual coloured Saffron Toucanet
Pierre de Chabannes
Blue-banded Toucanet
</figure>
<page confidence="0.996814" page_id="56254385"  page_num="72" year="" vol="">
72
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.945481" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254385" page_num="72" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - DALLAS WORLD AQUARIUM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998203804878049" page_id="56254385"  page_num="72" year="" vol="">
to the public area.
It was mostly a matter of waiting patiently to see some of the other birds.
A few hours spent walking slowly around the hall enabled me to obtain good
views of many of these gems such as the Amazilia Hummingbird Amazilia
amazilia - a species bred at Wuppertal Zoo and kept now in a number of
other European collections - the rare Antillean Mango Anthracothorax
dominicus which usually remains hidden high in the trees, two female
Ruby-throated Hummingbirds Archilochus colubris, a Puerto Rican Emerald
Hummingbird Chlorostilbon maugeus , some unidentified specimens which
may have been Green Violet-ears C. thalassinus and a beautiful Broad-billed
Hummingbird Cynanthus latirostris. The beautiful Green-throated Carib
Eulampis holosericeus was probably one of two or more elusive species I
failed to see.
I was extremely lucky to also be able to spend time behind the scenes in
the incredible breeding station for tropical American species, where most
of the breeding successes, including all of the world first captive breedings,
have occurred. More than 70 well-planted medium-sized to larger aviaries
house an enormous collection of toucans, cotingas and many other species,
most of which are very rare in captivity or are not to be found in any other
public collection.
Members of the toucan family are by far the most numerous birds in
the breeding station. There are many Toco, Keel-billed, Ariel and Red-
breasted Toucans, a pair of Cuvier's Toucans R. (tucanus) cuvieri and a pair
of the extremely rare Citron-throated Toucans R. ( vitellinus ) citreolaemus.
There are also many ara 9 aris, including the Green and the rare humboldti
subspecies of the Lettered Ara^ari P inscriptus, more Ivory-billed, Chestnut-
eared, Many-banded and Pale-mandibled Ara^aris, as well as Curl-crested
Ara^aris R beauharnaesii and the rare Fiery-breasted R frantzii. There is
a Blue-throated Toucanet A caeruleogularis, some more Crimson-ramped
Toucanets, a Groove-billed Toucanet and a pair of Blue-banded Toucanets A.
coeruleicinctis - a species not kept anywhere else - as well as many Guianan
Toucanets Selenidera culik , a pair of Spot-billed Toucanets S. maculirostris ,
a few Plate-billed Mountain Toucans and a breeding pair of Saffron Toucanets
with the pair's offspring.
Larger birds are also kept in these aviaries for breeding purposes. I was
very lucky to see a pair of the Critically Endangered Blue-billed Curassow C.
alberti , a pair of rare Southern Helmeted or Homed Curassows R unicornis
- a species kept in only one other public collection, in this case in the UK - a
pair of Homed Guans Oreophasis derby anus, another rarity, and a pair of
Yellow-knobbed Curassows C. daubentoni. Also hidden away behind the
scenes are a pair of Shoebills Balaeniceps rex and several raptors, including
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.818342" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254386" page_num="73" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - DALLAS WORLD AQUARIUM
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998371" page_id="56254386"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
73
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.990722678571429" page_id="56254386"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
young Ornate and Black Hawk-Eagles raised at the aquarium and the only
Black-and-white Hawk-Eagle Spizastur melanoleucus ever known to have
been kept in captivity.
There are also many smaller birds, including Columbidae, hummingbirds,
cotingas and passerines. There are, for example, several specimens and,
in some cases even breeding groups, of each of the species of manakins I
mentioned earlier, as well as more Golden Tanagers and some more Speckled
Tanagers. There is also a pair of the rare and impressive Giant Hummingbird
Patagona gigas which arrived in 2009, several Ruddy Ground Doves
Columbina talpacoti , a breeding group of Crested Bobwhite Colinus cristatus ,
a pair of the rarely seen Scaled Pigeon Patagioenas speciosa , a pair of the
equally rare Spot-crowned Barbet Capita maculicomnatus , a few Sunbittems
Eurypyga helias major and several more Little Tinamous. There is also a
Purple-breasted Cotinga C. cotinga , an old female Long-wattled Umbrellabird
Cephalopterus penduliger and a pair of Ornate Umbrellabirds C. ornatus,
a Three-wattled Bellbird Procnias tricarunculata , a pair of Black-cheeked
Woodpeckers and a pair of the rare and unusual-looking Pesquet's Parrot
Psittrichas fulgidus . Of course, this account would not be complete without
the three species which impressed me most, both by their rarity and their
beauty. The first of these is the aforementioned Andean Cock-of-the-Rock,
with all the young raised there kept together in a very large aviary, along with
many toucans and a pair of Blue-banded Toucanets. Another highlight was
seeing the two pairs of Resplendent Quetzals Pharomachrus m. mocinna which
arrived in 2010, this wonderful species having been absent from zoological
collections for more than 30 years. Finally, the most beautiful of all according
to Daryl Richardson, and I strongly agree with him - the amazing group of
Guianan Cocks-of-the-Rock R. rupicola which live in a huge aviary in which
they bred for the first time in 2008 - a world first captive breeding.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.869783" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56254386" page_num="73" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999702363636364" page_id="56254386"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
I wish to express my gratitude to Daryl Richardson for welcoming me
to his extraordinary collection and allowed me to visit every single aviary
and all areas of what is an incredible achievement.
His passion is definitely contagious and it was an absolute privilege
to spend time with him talking about his amazing bird collection and
forthcoming projects. I also wish to say an enormous "Thank you" to
the team of keepers, biologists and curators, who helped with identifying
species and took me around the areas behind the scenes. The time spent
with them was invaluable and without their help my visit would not have
been anywhere near as successful.
Finally, I wish to thank Josef Lindholm and his wife Natalie for
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.9981" page_id="56254387"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
74
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.943826" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254387" page_num="74" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - DALLAS WORLD AQUARIUM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998925846153846" page_id="56254387"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
welcoming me and for inciting me to discover Texas and its amazing-
extravaganza animal parks, I also wish to thank them for their help and
the additional information they provided during the writing of the above
account of my visit.
Pierre de Chabannes lives at Le Chesnay in France. E-mail;
pedroyayadrums@yahoo. com
The number of Andean Cock-of-the-Rock chicks hatched at Dallas World
Aquarium and the number of birds still living today, given in the above
account (P.64), are the latest figures (May 27 th 2011) and include a chick
hatched on May 18th and another hatched on May 20th 2011. I also learned
from Josef Lindholm that in January 2011 an Andean Cock-of-the-Rock
chick, sired by a 2007-hatched Dallas World Aquarium male, was hatched
and reared by its parents at San Diego Zoo. - Ed.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.811246" page_id="56254387"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.678594" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56254387" page_num="74" year="" vol="">
REPRODUCING ANNUALLY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990895090909091" page_id="56254387"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
Weltvogelpark Walsrode obtained a group of Black-cheeked Lovebirds
Agapornis nigrigenis from Frankfurt Zoo in 2005. These birds thrived and
this once common lovebird has bred there annually ever since. The 35-
strong group produced 24 young in 2010. They do well in a group of 10-50
birds with an even sex ratio, write Simon Bruslund and Martin Gaede, but
attention must be paid to ensuring that they have enough space and a sufficient
number of nest boxes, as well as a plentiful supply of nesting material This
is in order to avoid quarrels which can be very stressful, especially for the
young in the nests and recently fledged birds. At Walsrode they have found
that they mix well with other birds such as the smaller starlings and larger
weavers, so long as they all have plenty of nesting material.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.6931438" page_id="56254387"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
* * *
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY AT STAFFORD
The Avicultural Society will be present at the Parrot Society Show at
Staffordshire County Showground on Sunday, October 9th. We look forward
to meeting members at our usual place on the balcony of the main hall
</figure>
<page confidence="0.996156" page_id="56254388"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
75
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.987101" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254388" page_num="75" year="" vol="">
NOTES ON TINAMOUS CURRENTLY FOUND IN
AVICULTURE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.893536368421053" page_id="56254388"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
by Simon Bruslund, Wolfgang Magnus and Geer Scheres
Tinamous are poorly known in aviculture, probably as a result of their
less than glamorous plumage. This is a pity as they are very inquisitive and
rewarding aviary birds, as well as interesting research subjects.
Joao Marco Rosa
Female Solitary Tinamou at nest.
Natural history
The tinamous belong to the superorder Palaeognathae, a group of
birds which are different to all other living birds. In addition to the order
Tinamiformes, the tinamous, it includes the ratites, the most familiar of
which are the ostriches, rheas, emus, cassowaries and kiwis. These are the
remaining survivors of a once larger group of birds which share several
anatomical features, most notably with regard to the structure of the jaw and
foot. Recent DNA studies suggest that the closest relatives of the tinamous
are the extinct moas of New Zealand and that the tinamous are distantly
related to the living kiwis and not, as might be expected, the rheas with which
they share much of South America. It has been proposed that the common
ancestor of all the large ostrich-like birds, the ratites, is likely to have been
very similar in appearance to the modem day tinamous.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.986811" page_id="56254389"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
76
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.878227" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254389" page_num="76" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND ET AL - TINAMOUS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999492024390244" page_id="56254389"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
These are a very successful group of 46 species living in Central and
South America, where they occupy almost all types of habitat ranging from
mountain desert to lowland rainforest. Why, you may ask, do they exist only
in Central and South America? Fossil remains indicate that tinamous were
once distributed throughout the Southern Hemisphere. Fossils of primitive
looking tinamou-like birds with full wings have been found in the European
and North American regions, suggesting that tinamous and ratites may have
developed in the north and then dispersed south throughout Gondwanaland
(one of the two ancient supercontinents, comprising chiefly what is now
Africa, South America, Australia, Antarctica and the Indian subcontinent).
This also supports the theory that the individual groups - the ostriches,
rheas, emus, cassowaries, kiwis, moas and elephant birds - each evolved
their terrestrial lifestyle and large size independently, most likely from a
common, small tinamou-like ground-living, but flying, ancestor.
All tinamous share a similar basic blueprint: they are bulky, roundish
birds, with a small head and comparatively large eyes. That they have
adapted to life on the ground is obvious, as is the fact that they share many
characteristics with other groups of ground-living birds such as quail,
buttonquail and rails. Tinamous have only a rudimentary hind toe, or lack
a hind toe, which makes it difficult for them to perch on branches. They
mostly run for cover rather than take flight and it is only when they are
under great pressure or in imminent danger that they take to the wing. Their
flight is not particularly elegant but is very powerful and rocket-like. For
species which live in dense cover this ability helps them escape through the
foliage. In captivity this behaviour can result in birds colliding with aviary
roofs and other obstacles.
Tinamous are not fussy eaters and will feed on almost anything from
insects to roots and leaves. Most species feed principally on small seeds,
particularly grass seeds, but those living in forested environments include
a large percentage of berries and fruit in their diet. Water is important for
tinamous which seem to drink at least once a day in the wild. They also seem
to enjoy bathing which they often do in the safety of a small group, leading
to it also becoming a social event. Similarly, sunbathing and dustbathing
also seem to extend for as long as possible.
The size of the territory occupied by tinamous is highly variable and
ranges in size from 0.1 hectare (approx. 0.25 acre) of cloud forest occupied by
an individual Highland Tinamou Nothocercus bonapartei to the 30 hectares
(approx. 74 acres) of lowland rainforest home range documented for female
Solitary Tinamous Tinamus solitarius. It almost seems that as a group the
tinamous are experimenting with different social structures, with different
species having different mating structures and hierarchies. A few species
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.66887" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254390" page_num="77" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND ET AL - TINAMOUS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996861" page_id="56254390"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
77
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.993436615384615" page_id="56254390"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
live in monogamous pairs which aggressively chase away other birds, at least
for part of the year. Others live in large groups with a seemingly equally
high number of males and females living and breeding together with little
or no aggression - so-called polygynandry. Many species form polygynous
harems where the male attracts several females in his area until he has a
nestful of eggs and begins incubation. After which the females generally
leave the area and mate with another male. There is also a polyandrous
version in which a female will mate with different males between eggs. In
general female tinamous are larger and more colourful than males and it
is always the male who incubates the eggs and remains with the precocial
chicks until they become independent. In some clutches he may have more
than 30 young in his care.
The complex social structures are poorly understood. Females will
often compete with other females and males will compete with each other
for good nesting sites and the attention of the females. This seems to be
a social adaptation to high predator pressure and the need for an effective
reproduction rate.
Sexing tinamous
Tinamous have a similar number of chromosomes to ratites and like
them do not carry any differentiated sex chromosomes and, in this respect,
differ from most other birds. This is why early attempts to sex tinamous
using the standard DNA sex test proved so difficult and - not all companies
have mastered it yet. Fortunately, with a little practise tinamous can be
sexed by a simple examination of the cloaca. Mature males have a fairly
obvious penis.
The eggs
The females of some species of tinamou can lay more than 200 eggs a year
and have one of the highest rates of reproduction of any higher vertebrate.
Amongst birds it is surpassed only by some of the selectively bred modem
breeds of domestic poultry.
Tinamous lay tmly stunning looking eggs, the colour of which varies
from species to species and ranges from chocolate brown to emerald green
and turquoise blue. All have a smooth and seemingly glazed surface. Why
the eggs are so brightly coloured remains a mystery. Colourful eggs would
be expected to attract predators and it is known that incubating males cover
the nest and eggs with grass or leaves when they leave the nest, even for a
short period. Schwartz and Lentino (1984) suggested that the coloration
of the eggs must have something to do with the male's affinity to the nest
and help him relocate the covered eggs. Our observations of tinamou
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996488" page_id="56254391"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
78
</page>
<table confidence="0.962151857142857" page_id="56254391"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND ET AL - TINAMOUS
Henning Wegner/CBCC
Day old Solitary Tinamou chicks hatched at Cracid Breeding and Conservation Centre
in Belgium.
Henning Wegner/CBCC
Incubator at Cracid Breeding and Conservation Centre containing mainly Solitary
Tinamou eggs.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.668151" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254392" page_num="79" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND ET AL - TINAMOUS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996984" page_id="56254392"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
79
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.98090475" page_id="56254392"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
Elegant Crested Tinamou returning to its clutch of eggs.
Due to its southerly distribution the Elegant Crested Tinamou is well prepared for poor
weather, but it is not advisable to expose it to long periods of freezing temperatures or
rain without a suitable shelter.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.903379" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254393" page_num="80" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND ET AL - TINAMOUS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999611921052632" page_id="56254393"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
behaviour would seem to support this as males have a strong bond with the
nest. However, one of us (S.B.) also suggests that the very conspicuous
looking eggs are more likely to result from female competition. Perhaps
males often tend clutches which are larger than they can manage to cover
and therefore have to prioritize which eggs to incubate and possibly prefer
the most colourful eggs. As a result, the most conspicuous looking eggs
are preferred and thus through natural selection particularly colourful eggs
have become the norm. This is, however, only an hypothesis and remains
to be proven by experiments.
Tinamous in zoos
According to the results of a recent survey by the Ratite Taxon Advisory
Group, the responsible subgroup of the European Association of Zoos and
Aquaria (EAZA), very few tinamous are maintained in European zoos. The
survey revealed that only seven species are kept and at least three of these
are kept in such low numbers that it is unlikely viable captive-breeding
populations can be established. Concerns have also been expressed about
the risks of inbreeding in the future, as most of these species originate from
very small founder populations (see Table 1).
There also seem to be some still undetermined issues concerning
unintentional hybrids between the Small-billed Tinamou Crypturellus
parvirostris and the Tataupa Tinamou C. tataupa. These hybrids are
widespread in zoos and it is uncertain when and where these two very similar
looking species first became mixed-up and, it is likely, that a number of such
hybrids still remain to be identified. We know that amongst these hybrids
there is a high degree of infertility and a low hatch rate with almost 100%
embryonic mortality. At Weltvogelpark Walsrode only a single chick from
this hybrid line is known to have hatched. It survived only a few hours and
its internal organs exhibited physical disorders and it was highly anaemic.
These observations suggest that the hybrids are not capable of reproduction
or at least have impaired powers of reproduction and therefore, fortunately,
are unlikely to become established in aviculture.
In general, ever fewer birds are being kept in zoos, where they often
lose out to competition from standard zoo animals such as big cats, primates
and large herbivores. Furthermore, tinamous are also competing for space
in zoos with other ground-dwelling birds such as Galliformes and waders,
which are themselves becoming restricted to a decreasing number of zoos
which remain keen to focus on them and are willing to invest time, space
and money on displaying them and attempting to breed them.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.668337" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254394" page_num="81" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND ET AL - TINAMOUS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996688" page_id="56254394"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
81
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.997063">
Table 1. Tinamous maintained in European zoos according to the EAZA
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.6394745" page_id="56254394"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
Ratite Taxon Advisory Group Regional Collection Plan for Palaeognaths
2010 . _
Species No. of birds No. of
_____ in EAZA zoos institutions
Solitary Tinamou Tinamus solitarius 510 2
Little Tinamou Crypturellus soui 1 1
Dark-legged Tinamou Crypturellus obsoletus 230 1
Small-billed Tinamou Crypturellus parvirostris 7 3
Tataupa Tinamou Crypturellus tataupa 31 7
Red-winged Tinamou Rhynchotus rufescens 8 2
Elegant Crested Tinamou Eudromia elegans 154 _ 12
Tinamous at Weltvogelpark Walsrode
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.973601423076923" page_id="56254394"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
Weltvogelpark Walsrode has a long established practise of keeping little
known species and developing the required know-how to optimize their
husbandry. Tinamous are a good example of this, as they are a little known
family of birds, making them particularly interesting to that cherished group
of our visitors who have a special interest in birds. They also give us the
opportunity to tell the story of these interesting birds to others and the more
generally interested visitors, who quickly learn the there is plenty to discover
about these birds.
Hand-rearing the Elegant Crested Tinamou
The Elegant Crested Tinamou Eudromia elegans has been kept at
Weltvogelpark Walsrode for the past decade and all of the individuals
currently living here were hatched and raised here. This species has a
relatively short lifespan though and the birds which bred here originally
are no longer alive, but their descendents live on and continue to breed at
Weltvogelpark Walsrode. Although some species such as the large Solitary
Tinamou are known to live in captivity for up to 15 years, this is not true of
most other species, including the Elegant Crested Tinamou. The average
lifespan of a healthy Elegant Crested Tinamou seems to be closer to four
to six years. The population at Weltvogelpark Walsrode and indeed the
entire population currently maintained in European aviculture seem to have
originated from just a single importation of a few birds. We have found this
species to be a very prolific breeding bird here at Weltvogelpark Walsrode and
have now bred it to at least the third generation. A dominant female may lay
200 or more eggs during a season. This species is generally kept in mixed
groups with a similar number of males and females. Such groups can vary
in size from four to six birds sharing an exhibit to large groups of up to 50
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99356" page_id="56254395"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
82
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7473165" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254395" page_num="82" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND ET AL - TINAMOUS
Henning Wegner/CBCC
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986003714285714" page_id="56254395"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
Dark-legged Tinamou.
birds housed off-exhibit during rearing. A strong hierarchy develops within
the group and dominant birds, particularly females, suppress other members
of the group which as a result become less active and produce fewer eggs.
Here at the Weltvogelpark most of the eggs are artificially incubated and the
chicks are hand-reared. We have found that Elegant Crested Tinamous are
poor parents, but are unsure whether this is due to breeding related issues,
with parental skills having been lost over generations of artificial incubation
and the subsequent hand-rearing of the chicks, or if it is related to the social
structures and restrictions of life in a group setting.
According to the literature we have consulted, the incubation period
should be 20-21 days, but we have found that eggs incubated at an average
temperature of approximately 37.5*C (99.5*F) sometimes hatch after only
19 days and the incubation period may occasionally extend to 21 days. The
beautiful emerald green eggs have a high hatch rate in an incubator and
are less sensitive to disturbance and small fluctuations in temperature and
humidity than those of most other birds.
The freshly hatched chicks are, like all young tinamous, covered in dense
down and are very active. They are removed from the incubator between
six to 24 hours after hatching and placed under a infrared heat lamp with a
temperature in the core area of 35*C-40*C (95*F-104*F). It usually takes
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.668782" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254396" page_num="83" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND ET AL - TINAMOUS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995787" page_id="56254396"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
83
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.503329" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56254396" page_num="83" year="" vol="">
Lyubomila Krivoshieva/Weltvogelpark
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999813772727273" page_id="56254396"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
A minor dispute between two female Small-billed x Tataupa Tinamou hybrids.
Tinamous frequently use their feet in such disputes.
very little effort to persuade the chicks to seek the warmth of the lamp. Food
and water are provided in shallow dishes and food is held in a pair of forceps
and shown to the chicks if they do not find it instinctively. In the past a
major problem threatening the survival of the chicks was the development
of a healthy bacterial culture. A large number of chicks developed severe
diarrhoea and we experienced various problems with their growth.
Examining the intestinal anatomy of the Elegant Crested Tinamou, the
sheer volume as well as numerous appendixes to the larger intestines suggest
that this species is highly dependent on microorganisms for its digestion.
Based on experience at the Bronx Zoo, we made a few attempts at collecting
faeces from adult birds and feeding it in small amounts to the young chicks.
However, the results were less than satisfactory and we had hygiene concerns
about bringing faeces into the nursery, especially as this occasionally seemed
to cause other problems and could result in the chicks smearing it into their
down. Currently we use a commercially available probiotic product called
Bene-Bac(R) which contains Lactobacillus spp. in powdered form which is
added to the diet throughout the main growth phase. The normal rearing
diet consists of chicken crumble (chick crumbs). A similar diet for turkeys
but without any additional medication would surely also be suitable. In
addition they are offered chopped greens of various types, depending on
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995875" page_id="56254397"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
84
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.878701" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254397" page_num="84" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND ET AL - TINAMOUS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.982914609756097" page_id="56254397"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
seasonal availability, and small seeds. Excessive protein in the rearing diet
often leads to growth problems and, in particular, often causes the wings to
twist outwards, so that the birds develop so-called 'angel wing,' which can
be corrected by taping the wings for a few days and slightly reducing the
amount of crumble in comparison to the other food.
We have found that chicks do well in a largish group and that slightly
different age groups can be kept together. The social development of young
tinamous seems to be of some importance. If individuals are kept on their
own they not only become rather tame but sometimes develop stereotypical
behaviour. We have not yet investigated whether these birds have social
problems later in life.
Even though normally kept in small groups of four to eight birds,
juveniles have been kept together successfully in large groups of up to 50
birds, even beyond the advent of sexual maturity which is reached at about
10 months of age.
Farming potential
Because of their high reproductive rate tinamous have considerable
potential to be bred and reared as a source of food. Wild populations cannot
cope with very high levels of hunting and there are several examples of
local populations of tinamous in various parts of Central and South America
being exterminated due to excessive hunting. Therefore, in cooperation
with government agencies in Latin American countries, the CBCC (Cracid
Breeding and Conservation Centre at Zutendaal, Belgium) is (among other
things) investigating the feasibility of introducing tinamou farming as a
source of food and income for local communities within tinamou ranges
and thereby discourage the need to hunt the wild populations. This is
a multidisciplinary research project which aims to look into long-term
reproduction and mortality rates, economic husbandry methods, including
safe enclosure design, endemic parasites and other health issues, as well as
genetic and behavioural stability. In order to conduct reliable research a large
pool of birds is required and the CBCC has set aside considerable resources
in order to build up a population of about 500 Near Threatened Solitary
Tinamous and about 200 Dark-legged Tinamous. This will be possible only
through targeted breeding and careful strategic planning. These two forest
species were chosen because they appear to be sensitive to excessive hunting
and are facing problems in many locations within their natural ranges. In
the future, however, similar research may well be extended to include other
species of tinamous.
Endangered tinamous
Some endangered populations of tinamous are not being monitored
continuously and could easily disappear unnoticed by science. The protection
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.668493" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254398" page_num="85" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND ET AL - TINAMOUS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995442" page_id="56254398"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
85
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9540175" page_id="56254398"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
of tinamous is particularly difficult due to the relatively short lifespan of many
species and their potentially high reproduction rates. These cause natural
fluctuations in the size of the populations which are not fully understood.
It could also mean that if breeding is interrupted, perhaps as the result
of a natural disaster such as a storm or flooding, the situation could very
quickly become critical for some populations. Species with very small or
localised distributions may not be able to recover without assistance once
their numbers have fallen below a certain threshold. The Weltvogelpark
Foundation seeks to secure the long-term protection of endangered tinamous
in Brazil and other Latin American countries through further research into
the distribution and population dynamics of little known species. It is also
our goal to support the protection and development of key areas, once these
have been identified.
Table 2. Official IUCN listings of threatened tinamous. Although very
valuable these listings do not take into account local populations and
subspecies which may be even more threatened by extinction. __
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.9467245" page_id="56254398"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
Species
IUCN status
Solitary Tinamou Tinamus solitarius
NT
Black Tinamou Tinamus osgoodi
VU
Pale-browed Tinamou Crypturellus transfasciatus
NT
Choco Tinamou Crypturellus kerriae
VU
Yellow-legged Tinamou Crypturellus noctivagus
NT
Taczanowski's Tinamou Nothoprocta taczanowskii
VU
Lesser Nothura Nothura minor
VU
Dwarf Tinamou Taoniscus nanus
VU
NT=Near Threatened; VU=Vulnerable
Release programmes in Brazil
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.9899245" page_id="56254398"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
At the facilities of CRAX Brasil several species of tinamous are bred for
release into the wild. A priority species is the Solitary Tinamou, which is
considered Near Threatened, but with the status of one of two subspecies,
the distinctive T. s. pernambucensis, more precarious. It has an isolated
distribution at the north-eastern end of the range of this species, in an area
which has suffered large scale deforestation. The surviving population has
been estimated to number fewer than 100 birds.
CRAX Brasil produces a large number of Solitary Tinamous each year
for reintroduction into the wild. In several areas of rainforest in eastern
Brazil from which this tinamou has disappeared, as well as newly-reforested
areas, the establishment of large ground-living birds is a key component
in the development of a healthy ecosystem. Not only do these birds act
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.993299" page_id="56254399"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
86
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.878858" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254399" page_num="86" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND ET AL - TINAMOUS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.952902222222222" page_id="56254399"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
as seed dispersers but they are also a source of food for large predators in
these areas. The presence of such birds in an ecosystem is one of the best
indicators when assessing its current condition. By releasing large number
of tinamous, authorities and NGOs in Brazil hope to boost the dwindling
population. It is also hoped that the released birds will help reduce poaching
and predator pressure on the population as a whole.
If you would like to help us save endangered tinamous and other species
around the world you can do so by sending a donation to the Weltvogelpark
Foundation. E-mail:Foundation@weltvogelpark.de
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.92462" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56254399" page_num="86" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9963105" page_id="56254399"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
We wish to thank the EAZA Ratite Taxon Advisory Group and the
Cracid Breeding and Conservation Center at Zutendaal, whose data and
indispensible knowledge were freely drawn upon during the preparation of
the above manuscript.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.396089285714286" page_id="56254399"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
Product mentioned in the text
Bene-Bac(R): PetAg, Inc., 255 Keyes Avenue, PO Box 396, Hampshire, IL 60140, USA. Available
in the UK from: Pet Ag, Kruus UK Ltd., Unit 17, Moor Lane Industrial Estate, Sherbum in
Elmet, N. Yorkshire LS25 6ES. Website:www.petag.com
Bibliography
Bruslund, S., Gregson, J., Lammers, J. 2010. Regional Collection Plan for Palaeognaths
Version I, EAZA Ratite TAG.
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.434177125" page_id="56254399"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
Davies, S. J. J. F. 2002. Ratites and Tinamous. Bird Families of the World. Oxford University
Press, Oxford, New York and Tokyo.
del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A. and Sargatal, J. (eds.) 1992. Handbook of the Birds of the World.
Volume 1 - Ostrich to Ducks. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona.
Harshman, J. et al. 2008. Phylogenomic evidence for multiple losses of flight in ratite birds.
Proceedings of the National Academy of Science of the United States of America 105.
Schwartz, P and Lentino, M. 1984. Relariones de los tinamidos Venezolanosdel grupo
Crypturellus noctivagus indicadas por su voz (Aves: Tinamidae), Serie Informes Cietificos
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.439613666666667" page_id="56254399"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
QGSIIA/IC/23.
* * *
AFTER 19 YEARS OF TRYING
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.964427" page_id="56254399"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
Meg and the late Frank Woolham's son, Andrew, a Team Leader on
the birdkeeping staff at Chester Zoo, is delighted to have at long last bred
the Philippine Cockatoo Cacatua haematuropygia after 19 years of trying.
Andrew said: "I might risk the wrath of my wife in saying this, but breeding
these birds after 19 years of trying is just as exciting as my wedding day
and the birth of my son."
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998073" page_id="56254400"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
87
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8588215" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254400" page_num="87" year="" vol="">
CONSERVING PARROTS AROUND THE WORLD
by Rene Wiist
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970483405405406" page_id="56254400"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
The Zoologische Gesellschaft fiir Arten-und Populationsschutz e.V.
(ZGAP) - the Zoological Society for the Conservation of Species and
Populations - promotes the conservation of highly endangered, but lesser
known animal species, which are not usually in the public spotlight, but are
no less worthy of protection. While urgent measures are necessary to protect
popular species such as the Mountain Gorilla Gorilla b. beringei, Giant
Panda Ailuropoda melanoleuca and Tiger Panther a tigris which already
receive much public attention, there are many other species threatened with
extinction which remain largely unnoticed. It was because of these that
ZGAP was founded in 1982 and provides scientific and financial support
for conservation projects around the world. Basic principles underlying this
support, include training nationals in conservation techniques, as well as
involving the local population in the measures being taken. This results, we
believe, in the efficient running and cost effective operation of the projects.
Our French ZGAP sister organisation Conservation des Especes et des
Populations Animates (CEPA) was set up in 1997. The Strunden-Papageien-
Stiftung (SPS) - the Strunden Parrot Foundation - which is managed within
ZGAP was set up in 1998, followed in 2001 by the Stiftung Artenschutz im
Zoobereich - the Species Conservation Foundation.
The Fonds fur bedrohte Papageien (FbP) - Funds for Endangered Parrots
- a working group which was set up in 1989 within ZGAP, is made up of
dedicated specialists involved on an honorary basis in the protection and
conservation of parrots. The fact that almost a quarter of all parrot species are
seriously endangered, with a quarter of these threatened with extinction, led
to the setting up of the working group. Measures taken in the parrots' native
habitats are the most effective way of providing long-term conservation.
ZGAP was the first organisation to highlight the plight of Spix's Macaw
Cyanopsitta spixii in the wild in Brazil.
The FbP largely takes its own decisions about which projects it will fund.
In the 20 years since it was set up it has awarded some [euro]500,000 (approx.
#440,000/US$700,000) to a wide variety of projects. The FbP is made up
of parrot experts dedicated to conserving parrots in the wild. It is formally
devolved into a decision making committee, as well as project guardians
elected from its members. It is the task of the FbP and its working group
members to examine and evaluate project applications, seek out proposals
for projects, conduct ongoing appraisals of the work and prepare for and
organise seminars. The current committee members are Thomas Arndt,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.512069" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254401" page_num="88" year="" vol="">
WUST - CONSERVING PARROTS
</sectionHeader>
<author confidence="0.685806">
Andreas Bigge, Dr Marcellus Biirkle, Detlev Franz, Hans-Jiirgen Kiinne, Dr
Rainer Niemann, Dr Matthias Reinschmidt, Marion Wiegel and Rene Wust
</author>
<bodyText confidence="0.999565416666667" page_id="56254401"  page_num="88" year="" vol="">
(spokesperson for the FbP). Each autumn since 1997 the FbP has organised
an annual one-day seminar for members and other interested parties. There
are presentations covering a wide range of parrot related topics, ranging from
parrot conservation in the wild and the activities of the hind, to European
captive breeding programmes and studbooks, breeding and keeping reports
on less endangered species, feeding and nutrition, veterinarian and biological
topics, reports from the field and the latest developments in taxonomy.
Each presentation is followed by an open discussion on the subject of the
presentation. The seminars regularly attract some 150 German-speaking
parrots keepers. The surplus after expenses is donated to conservation
projects. The seminars are usually held in conjunction with a parrot/bird
show or in cooperation with a bird park or zoo.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.617476">
Conservation
Projects
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999056782608696" page_id="56254401"  page_num="88" year="" vol="">
The main reasons why so many parrots are threatened or seriously
endangered are ongoing habitat destruction, often along with the illegal trade
in wild-caught parrots. Other causes include hunting and the persecution of
birds as crop pests, the introduction of non-native species into their habitats,
changes to the habitats by man and threats to breeding sites and trees used
for nesting, as well as pressure on their food supplies.
An especially important aspect of FbP support for projects to conserve
parrots, is working closely with other conservation organisations and
the human population of the regions concerned to ensure that through
cooperation and education, the measures taken for the conservation of the
species and their habitats are lasting. ZGAP bases its priorities closely on
the IUCN Red List.
Examples of the work of the FbP
As part of the plan to conserve the Santa Marta Conure Pyrrhura
viridicata in Colombia, the FbP supports a project run by the Colombian
foundation Alianza para Ecosistemas Criticos - the Alliance for Critical
Ecosytems. This promotes close cooperation with the Indians living in the
Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta. The endemic Santa Marta Conure acts as a
key species in educating the population on the uniqueness of the flora and
fauna of this mountain range. The project treats all participants as equal
partners in the observation activities in the Indian reserve and in establishing
distribution patterns, the identification of breeding areas and migration
corridors, as well as analysis of the situation regarding the population and the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.587593" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254402" page_num="89" year="" vol="">
WUST - CONSERVING PARROTS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.9972" page_id="56254402"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
89
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.969006111111111" page_id="56254402"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
causes of endangerment. Through optimising cheese production by small-
scale farmers in the conure's area of distribution and with the assistance of
a diary specialist from the FbP, an attempt will be made to set up a brand
of cheese products to safeguard the habitat structure of the conure over the
long-term. Further local products earmarked for development are honey
and coffee.
Another important FbP partner in Colombia is ProAves, an organisation
which has been very successful in the conservation of the Yellow-eared Parrot
Ognorhynchus icterotis . At present the research work on the Rusty-faced
Parrot Hapalopsittaca amazonina is also being supported by the FbP. We
also work with SELVA, as well as with Asociacion Armonia in Bolivia and
Aquasis in Brazil.
The situation concerning the Citron-crested Cockatoo Cacatua sulphurea
citrinocristata on the Indonesian island of Sumba is different to that of parrots
in South America. On Sumba the main problems are the loss of nesting
opportunities along with the capture and trade in the cockatoos on the black
market. In addition to the collection and evaluation of basic information
on its distribution, population density and the importance of various factors
threatening the population, the control and monitoring of the trade in this
cockatoo are among the project's main tasks. For the first time recently
poachers were successfully prosecuted. At the same time a strategy has been
developed to raise the awareness of the local population about the plight of
this cockatoo by, for example, visiting schools and showing an educational
film produced by the FbP. As many small schools do not have an electricity
supply, showing such a film is always a major event. Our local partner on
this project is Burung Indonesia.
Further examples of parrot projects being funded in the region, include
work with the White or Umbrella Cockatoo C. alba on Halmahera and with
the Red-vented Cockatoo C. haematuropygia in the Philippines where we
work with the Katala organisation.
To learn more about ZGAP you can visit the websites:www.zgap.de and
www.papageienfonds.de
CEPA and ZGAP, along with the Avicultural Society, Chester Zoo and the
International Turaco Society (ITS), are among a number of organisations
which have helped fund field work on Prince Ruspoli s Turaco Tauraco
ruspolii in southern Ethiopia.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.992967" page_id="56254403"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
90
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.994411" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254403" page_num="90" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
POEMS ABOUT PARROTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990340828571428" page_id="56254403"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
Babbling Birds is an anthology of poems about parrots - and claims to
be the first ever published on this theme. The compiler is David L. O'Neal,
a retired rare book dealer now enjoying a second career as a writer. In his
introduction, he mentions that poets often speak of the beauty of parrots,
their dominion over other household animals, parrots repeating gossip or
revealing infidelites and parrots who suffer from being caged. The poems
range from the ancient to the modem, from Ovid to Wordsworth, from the
long to the short. One of the briefest, by Po Chu-l, is:
The Red Cockatoo
Sent as a present from Amman
A red cockatoo
Coloured like a peach tree blossom
Speaking the speech of men
And they did to it what is always done
To the learned and eloquent:
They got a cage with stout bars
And shut it up inside
It is interesting that many of the poems (not modem) lament the loss of
the parrot's liberty or, in the parrot's voice, tell of its misery at being caged.
So moving and unexpected were these poems...indeed, The Parrot of Rumi
brought tears to my eyes. Others are more humorous such as the Ballard of
Billy M'Caw by T. S. Elliot. The parrot was the life and soul of the "Bull
and Bush." Finally, there is one from the compiler:
I have a bird that speaks like me,
Yet mixes words atrociously;
Sometimes it will in English speak:
Moving its tongue within its beak:
But my bird talks with a strange syntax
And often the wrong word unpacks.
That's why (it should be clear to see)
I've named my parrot, Parody
The book is illustrated by a number of coloured photographs of parrots
although I must confess some of these seem irrelevant or out of place. The
words are enough. A small criticism is that the title does not direct one to
parrots but made me think of babblers. Perhaps Parrot mimics in poetry
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.90979" genericHeader="method" page_id="56254404" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99634" page_id="56254404"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
91
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.913026375" page_id="56254404"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
would have been more appropriate.
Babbling Birds: An Anthology of Poems about Parrots, From Antiquity
to the Present. Compiled, with an eight-page introduction, by David L.
O'Neal. Comprising 101 poems by 89 poets. One hundred and fifty-eight
pages, 20 colour illustrations, one black and white illustration. Soft cover.
Price US$17.50. It can be ordered directly from Green Parrot Press by
e-mailing:davidloneal@yahaoo.com, or, to use PayPal go to the website:
http://davidloneal.us
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.650741" genericHeader="method" page_id="56254404" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
Rosemary Low
RESCUED FROM THE BRINK OF EXTINCTION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995499379310345" page_id="56254404"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
Mark Carwardine co-presenter of the 1989 and 2009 BBC TV series Last
Chance to See , opens his Foreword to Rescuedfrom the Brink of Extinction:
Kakapo with the words, "It's hard to believe that anyone would fly nearly
20,000 kilometres, halfway around the world, just to see a parrot". But he is
not referring to just any parrot, he is referring to the extraordinary Kakapo.
It is not hard for me to believe. I have done it twice. For 30 years or so I
have followed with particular interest the fortunes of what is arguably the
world's most unique bird.
The story of New Zealand's flighless, nocturnal parrot, has been a heart-
stopping one. Now Alison Ballance has put it all together, with a fascinating
collection of photographs. I defy anyone to look at a photo of a Kakapo and
not go "Aaah!" Did a more appealing creature ever exist?
The photographs, many of outstanding interest or beauty, came from the
people who, over the years have been most closely associated with saving
this iconic parrot - none more so than Don Merton who became a national
hero for his work saving the Kakapo and the New Zealand Black Robin
(when it was down to the last pair). Sadly, Don died on April 1 Oth - and the
book was his last Christmas present to me. I am privileged that it is a unique
copy, containing a few margin notes in his own handwriting.
Alison Ballance's book is divided into three parts. The first details the
unique biology of the Kakapo - and I do mean unique. I will not describe
here all the features that set it apart from all other birds on earth because
the author has made an excellent job of recounting them in a very readable
way.
Part 2 describes how the Kakapo was on the knife-edge of extinction and,
at one point, was believed to be effectively extinct as no more females were
known to exist. Just how the tide turned is a breathtaking story.
The third part of the book concerns its breeding in the wild as well as the
hand-rearing of the young and the enormous effort that went into this. In the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995869" page_id="56254405"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
92
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.971626" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254405" page_num="92" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.983362625" page_id="56254405"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
later stages of the story, nest-minders watched over every nest with the help,
during the past 15 years, of infrared cameras. Each chick was so precious
that every possible action was taken to ensure that every egg survived and
every chick was reared. Extreme difficulties had to be overcome.
It is an absorbing story which like the best mystery novel will keep you
turning the pages.
Rescuedfrom the Brink of Extinction: Kakapo by Alison Ballance. ISBN
978 1 877517 27 3. Hardback, 20cm x 25cm, 211 pages. Craig Potton
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.298657" page_id="56254405"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
Publishing, New Zealand.
Rosemary Low
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.61998" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56254405" page_num="92" year="" vol="">
EXTREMADURA, SPAIN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997536428571428" page_id="56254405"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
The Crossbill Guide to Extremadura, Spain , which is the subject of this
review is not a birdwatchers site guide. It is, however, an extremely well
produced guide that will greatly enhance a visitor's appreciation of the natural
history of this very rich and wild area of south-west Spain. Extremadura
borders Portugal and is a region the size of Switzerland which contains a
wealth of animals and plants in scenically beautiful habitats which range
from the steppes of Caceres in the south to the mountains of La Vera in
the north. Between these lies the magnificent Monfrague National Park, a
mountainous area surrounded by lower lying cork and holm oak landscapes
and steppes. No one, even with the prime objective of birdwatching in this
area, can fail to notice the flowers and butterflies or be bewitched by this
fantastic area and its historic towns of Trujillo and Caceres.
The guide is divided into several parts. The first covers - Landscape -
with an overview of the various habitats that define the natural history of the
area. This chapter includes an explanation of the ecology of the dehesas and
their dependence on a cycle of traditional land use, and also covers steppes,
rivers and reservoirs, mountains and Mediterranean evergreen forest. The
importance of people in this landscape is also covered as are the history of the
region and the influence of the Romans and Moors. This section concludes
with the challenges to this region posed by our changing world.
The second part covers the important flora and fauna. This and other
sections are liberally illustrated with colour photographs and maps and graphs
(virtually on every page). The section begins with flora and discusses and
illustrates the plants of the different areas and habitats of the region. These
include the holm and cork oaks so typical of this area and also includes many
of the local flowers. It concludes with a section on the orchids and lists
over 30 species of Extremadura. A short section on mammals is followed
by a larger section on birds that gives prominence to the avian specialities
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.90944" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254406" page_num="93" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994982" page_id="56254406"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
93
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.936059393939394" page_id="56254406"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
and other characteristic birds which are the Spanish Imperial Eagle, Black-
winged Kite, Griffon Vulture, Great and Little Bustards, Pin-tailed and
Black-bellied Sandgrouse, Black Stork, European Bee-eater, Woodchat
Shrike, Rock Bunting and Azure-winged Magpie. Sections on reptiles and
amphibians and insects, including butterflies and dragonflies, conclude this
part of the guide.
Headed the - Practical Part - the third part of the guide gives both
driving and walking routes that can be taken when exploring this region.
Seventeen routes are covered in detail. The first is for a full-day drive around
Monffague and indicates the important features, history and flora and fauna,
that may be seen at various points en route. Following on from this is a
similarly detailed walking route around the castle of Monfrague. Taking
six hours this may not be every visitor's cup of tea but there are also easier
routes taking one-and-half to two hours. Without having tried any of these
routes it is difficult to comment on how these would work out in practise,
but the maps and directions look reasonably clear, although I would always
recommend backing these up with a good road map and with more detailed
maps for the walks.
The final section gives tourist advice and observation tips and concludes
with species lists for the plants and animals of the region. There is no index
which means one cannot easily find information on any particular plant or
animal species or where to find it. For the birds, however, there is a short
section that provides a few lines on each species and indicates on which
routes these may be found. However, as mentioned at the onset, this is not
a bird site guide but a very useful companion guide for anyone visiting or
thinking of visiting Extremadura. I can recommend it and only wish that I
had owned this guide prior to my own visit nearly five years ago.
Extremadura, Spain. Crossbill Guides, second edition, (ISBN 978 90
5011 381 6) by Dirk Hilbers. Soft cover, 224 pages with numerous colour
photographs and illustrations, published by Crossbill Guides Foundation,
Arnhem, the Netherlands. Price #19.95/624.95.
For further information visit the website:www.crossbillguides.org/
e-mail: info@crossbillguides.org
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.360377">
Roger Wilkinson
</subsectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99822" page_id="56254407"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
94
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9797265" genericHeader="method" page_id="56254407" page_num="94" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
MAKING PROGRESS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998275181818182" page_id="56254407"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
Inspite of a slow start to the 2010 breeding season due to an extended
period of cold weather early in the year, 48 Corncrakes Crex crex bred at
Whipsnade as part of The Zoological Society of London (ZSL), Royal
Society for the Protection of Birds (RSPB) and Natural England Species
Recovery Programme (see Vol.l 13, No.l, pp. 13-21 (2007)), were released
last year on the Nene Washes in Cambridgeshire. Earlier in 2010,21 calling
males were located, of which 14 were bred at Whipsnade. Of the 14, one
male was released in 2007, one in 2008 and 12 in 2009. A female caught in
the summer was bred at Whipsnade and released in 2006. Two wild-bred
chicks captured with her may have been her young. Five unringed males
were probably hatched on the Nene Washes in 2009.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.839463" page_id="56254407"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.759782" genericHeader="method" page_id="56254407" page_num="94" year="" vol="">
IN FULL SWING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989262083333334" page_id="56254407"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
By April the breeding season was already in full swing at Loro Parque and
393 chicks had been ringed (banded). Each day more pairs were beginning
to breed and about 200 chicks were being cared for 24 hours a day at the
fundacion's Baby Station.
A notable success had been the breeding of a White-capped Parrot
Pionus seniloides. The birds arrived from a breeding station in Mexico in
2008 and it was the first time the pair had laid. The clutch of three eggs was
removed and placed with an experienced pair of Scaly-headed Parrots P.
maximilliani but only one of the eggs was fertile. The chick was well cared
for by its adoptive parents, whose own chicks were being hand-reared at
the Baby Station. The pair of White-capped Parrots was being allowed to
hatch its second clutch of eggs. A second pair had also began to lay, so the
fundacion has taken an important step forward in its attempt to establish a
self-sustaining breeding stock of this species. The closely related Speckle-
faced or Plum-headed Parrots P tumultuosus, with which the fundacion
had already had limited success, had also laid again and three chicks were
currently being hand-reared.
Pesquet's Parrot Psittrichas fulgidus breeds regularly at Loro Parque.
The first chick of 2011 was being reared in the Baby Station and the pair
was preparing to lay a second clutch. A second pair, consisting of a male
bred at Loro Parque in 2006 and an unrelated female, was busy excavating
a nesting cavity in a palm log.
The breeding pair of Spix's Macaws Cyanopsitta spixii laid an egg but
the chick failed to survive beyond about the twentieth day of incubation
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.699456" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254408" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.993658" page_id="56254408"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
95
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.990804178571429" page_id="56254408"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
and two of the other females, the first hatched in 2004 and the second in
2006, laid infertile eggs. However, the fact that the two have laid their first
eggs is regarded as an important step forward. Two eggs belonging to a
pair of Blue-headed Macaws Primolius couloni were placed with the 2006
female and her partner's fifth clutch of infertile eggs, both of which hatched
successfully and the inexperienced pair of Spix's Macaws was making a
good job of rearing the Blue-headed Macaw chicks. Zoological Director Dr
Matthias Reinschmidt wrote that it again shows that hand-reared birds can
make good parents, so long as they have been properly socialised.
By May nearly 600 chicks had been ringed (banded). Amongst those that
had done particularly well were the Brotogeris parakeets. For the first time
in several years, two pairs of Grey-cheeked Parakeets B. pyrrhoptera had
reared a total of nine young at the same time. The Cobalt-winged Parakeets
B. cyanoptera again produced chicks, as did (Gustav's) B. c. gustavi , the
Plain Parakeets B. tirica, Canary-winged or Yellow-chevroned Parakeets
B. chirini , White-winged Parakeets B. versicolurus and Golden-winged
Parakeets B. chrysopterus , as well as (the Tuipara) B. c. tuipara.
Last year Loro Parque Fuedaeion obtained from a Dutch breeder its first
two pairs of the Red-breasted or Moustached Parakeet subspecies Psittacula
alexandri dammermanni. This year one of the pairs nested and, in May,
four chicks were being reared. A male Purple-naped Lory Lorius domicellus
which arrived at Loro Parque 26 years ago, paired with a female at least 17
years old, produced a clutch of infertile eggs, followed by a second clutch
from which a chick hatched and was growing well. This species is now very
rare on the Indonesian island of Seram and there is the need to build up a
reserve population in captivity.
Several pairs of Peach-fronted Conures Aratinga aurea had between
them parent-reared a total of 17 young.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.226405285714286" page_id="56254408"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
* \0x2666
OFF TO AN EXCELLENT START
Early in May when I contacted Alison Hales at Paradise Park here in
Cornwall about an article on the hand-rearing there by Becky Waite of a
Great Blue Turaco Corythaeola cristata (an article which, hopefully, will
be published in No.3, 2011), Alison mentioned that a Chestnut-backed
Thrush Zoothera dohertyi had just fledged and Red-crested Turacos Tauraco
</table>
<reference confidence="0.9505478">
erythrolophus , Superb Starlings Lamprotornis superbus , Village Weavers
Pioceus cucullatus and Great .Argus Argusianus argus had eggs.
Pekin Robins Leiotkrix lutea, which had arrived from the Durrell Wildlife
Conservation Trust in Jersey only a few weeks earlier, had already begun
to lay. Keas Nestor notabilis had five chicks, Eclectus Eclectus rotatus had
</reference>
<page confidence="0.995485" page_id="56254409"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
96
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.924798" genericHeader="method" page_id="56254409" page_num="96" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997694142857143" page_id="56254409"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
one chick, Duyvenbode's Lories Chalcopsitta duivenbodei had their first
two chicks (which were still very young) and Blue-throated Macaws Ara
glaucogularis had three eggs.
At the time, Red-billed Choughs Pyrrhocoraxpyrrocorax had six chicks,
three of which were 13 days old and three in another nest which were just five
days old. A further nest of five eggs was due to hatch the following week.
In the wild, 15 chicks had hatched at four nest sites in west Cornwall.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.818757" page_id="56254409"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.829671" genericHeader="method" page_id="56254409" page_num="96" year="" vol="">
FIFTH OLDEST SURVIVING ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.942184538461538" page_id="56254409"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
An Illustrated History of Bristol Zoo Gardens by Tim Brown, Alan Ashby
and Christoph Schwitzer, published by the Independent Zoo Enthusiasts
Society to coincide with the 175th Anniversary of the founding of this famous
UK West Country zoo, is reviewed in International Zoo News Vol.58, No.2,
pp. 109-110, 2011 by Nicholas Gould, its recently retired Editor.
Even the most well-informed zoo aficionado might, he wrote, be hard-
pressed to name, in order, the world's five oldest surviving zoos. The five are
Schonbrunn (1753), the Jardin des Plantes (1793), London (1828), Dublin
(1830) and Bristol (1836).
An Illustrated History of Bristol Zoo Gardens , price #15.00 plus #3.00
p&amp;p, can be purchased online at: www.bristolzoo.org.uk/web-shop or by
sending a cheque payable to Bristol Zoo Enterprises to: Maggie Pearson,
Bristol Zoo, Clifton, Bristol BS8 3HA. For overseas enquiries e-mail:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.5445905" page_id="56254409"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
mpearson@bristolzoo.org.uk
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.469212" genericHeader="method" page_id="56254409" page_num="96" year="" vol="">
MORE ON MAJOR HORSBRUGH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.819717375" page_id="56254409"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
Following the two items on Major Horsbrugh in the previous issue
(News &amp; Views, Vol. 117, No. 1, pp.45-47 (2011)), Alison Harding, Assistant
Librarian, Ornithology &amp; Rothschild Libraries at the Natural History
Museum at Tring, contacted the magazine to say that a few years ago the
museum received from Patrick Horsbrugh, a descendent of Major Horsbrugh,
manuscripts, correspondence, watercolour paintings, photo albums and
sketches, etc., left by Major Horsbrugh. Details of these can be found on
the NHMLibrary Catalogue.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.407948" page_id="56254409"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.79973" genericHeader="method" page_id="56254409" page_num="96" year="" vol="">
BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.93891">
For details contact Peter Stocks, Hon. Secretary and Treasurer, The
Avicultural Society, Sheraton Lodge, Station Road, Southminster, Essex
CMO 7EW. E-mail:otusscops@talktalk.net/Tel:01621 772427.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.847028" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254410" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE POPULARITY OF PENGUINS
</sectionHeader>
<footnote confidence="0.359232">
Our President, Raymond Sawyer, was among the guests invited to the
unveillingofZSL London Zoo's new penguin pool. Thel,200sqm (approx.
12,900sq ft), 450,000 litres (approx. 99,000 UK gallons) pool is said to be
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.990446896551724" page_id="56254410"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
the largest penguin pool in England. The site is landscaped to mimic the
birds' natural habitats, with burrows leading to nest boxes, the ability to
watch the penguins swimming underwater and there is a hand-rearing unit.
The exhibit currently houses 65 Humboldt Spheniscus humboldti , African
(Jackass or Black-footed) S. demersus, Macaroni Eudyptes chrysolophus
and Rockhopper Penguins E. crestatus. The Zoological Society of London
hope it will eventually house a 200-strong breeding colony.
Anew penguin exhibit has also been opened at Birdworld near Famham,
Surrey. The 750sq m (approx. 8,300sq ft) walk-through attraction was
inspired by the penguin colony on Robben Island, the island on which
Nelson Mandela was imprisoned for 17 years and which is now a World
Heritage Site. As well as 30 African (Jackass or Black-footed) Penguins,
which are part of the European Breeding Programme for this species,
the exhibit has Little Egrets Egretta garzetta. Sacred Ibis Threskiornis
aethiopicus. Blacksmith Plovers Vanellus armatus , Curlew Numenius
arquata , Cape Thick-knees or Dikkops Burhinus capensis. Red-winged
Starlings Onychognathus morio and Wattled Starlings Creatophora cinerea,
all of which have been recorded on Robben Island. The exhibit will be
used to raise funds to support conservation research on African Penguins
in southern Africa, in partnership with the Animal Demography Unit of the
University of Cape Town.
So far this year 10 Humboldt Penguins have been bred at Chester Zoo.
Each pair lays two eggs which hatch after about 40 days. Both parents take
turns to incubate the eggs and both rear the young, which leave the nest after
about eight weeks. The new arrivals mean that the zoo now has a colony of
more than 50 Humboldt Penguins. The zoo funds conservation initiatives
in South America aimed at protecting the habitat of this species in Peru and
Chile, where it faces a number of threats, principally from the overfishing
of its food stocks by man and habitat loss.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.757781" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56254411" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.82523752631579" page_id="56254411"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Breeding the Oriental Greenfinch Carduelis sinica
by Gary Bralsford.49
Visually sexing the Hawk-headed Parrot Deroptyus accipitrinus
by Paolo Bertagnolio.51
On some UK bird breedings by members of the
Avicultural Society in 2009
by Reuben B. Girling .52
The Dallas World Aquarium
by Pierre de Chabannes...59
Notes on tinamous currently found in aviculture
by Simon Bruslund, Wolfgang Magnus and Geer Scheres.75
Conserving parrots around the world
by Rene Wtist.87
Book Reviews
Poems About Parrots.90
Rescued from the Brink of Extinction.91
Extremadura, Spain.92
News &amp; Views.94
Published by the Avicultural Society , England.
</table>
</algorithms>
