<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.884188333333333" page_id="56266237"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
B x Xv ICULTUR AL
MAGAZINE
2000
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990772" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266238" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991582857142857" page_id="56266238"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in freedom and captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2000 as for 1999: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.550846" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266238" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.75389475" page_id="56266238"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Subscription, changes of address, orders for back numbers etc. should be
sent to:
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, c /o BRISTOL ZOOLOGICAL GARDENS, CLIFTON,
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.7790924" page_id="56266238"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
BRISTOL BS8 3HA, ENGLAND.
Enquiries regarding membership should be sent to:
THE MEMBERSHIP SECRETARY, Stewart Pyper, 21, Primrose Hill,
Nunney, Frome, Somerset BA11 4NP.
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.99665325" page_id="56266238"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998437" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266238" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.9972025">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8206735" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266239" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.394096" page_id="56266239"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 106 - No. 2 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2000
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.975618" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266239" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ECUADORIAN BIRDS: NESTING RECORDS AND EGG
DESCRIPTIONS FROM A LOWLAND RAINFOREST
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990028724137931" page_id="56266239"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Ryan L. Hill and Harold F. Greeney
Despite its small size, Ecuador is a strikingly biologically diverse country.
It boasts at least 1,600 species of birds, most which are seriously threatened
by habitat destruction. As is often stated, tropical forests are being destroyed
at an ever increasing rate. In light of this fact, ecological data of all kinds
must be made available in the general literature so that conservation minded
individuals have access to it. Birds are particularly amenable to conservation
applications because of their relative ease of detection and popularity with
birdwatchers and nature enthusiasts. It is with these thoughts that we present
the following observations.
The nest records below were all observed in the vicinity of La Selva
Jungle Lodge in the Provincia Sucumbios near the town of Anyangu. The
lodge is located approximately 75 km (about 46 miles) downstream from
the town of Coca along the Rio Napo at an elevation of approximately 250m
(about 820ft). The habitat in this area, typical of upper Amazonia, is a
complex mix of terra firme, varzea (flooded forest) and meandering oxbow
lakes. Over 500 species of birds have been recorded from this site, which
give it one of the most diverse avifaunas in the world.
Zigzag Heron Zebrilus undulatus
Observed March 23rd and 24th, 1998. An adult and one chick were
located on a platform-type nest composed of spiny palm leaflets and petioles.
The nest was encountered because either the adult or chick was vocalizing,
and alerted us to its position. The call was different than that normally
heard from this species. The normal call is a two noted, throaty 'enng-nah'
that is slurred together (Moore, 1993 and pers. obs.). The call was higher
pitched than that normally heard. It consisted of a medium pitched 'ehmp'
repeated every second for two or three seconds followed by a pause before
it was heard again. Because of the high pitch we believe it to have been
made by the chick. Only the adult was visible from its perch on the nest,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.970383" page_id="56266240"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
50
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.972412175" page_id="56266240"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
HILL &amp; GREENEY - ECUADORIAN BIRDS
which was hidden among many 'chontilla' palms Bactris sp. These palms
are heavily armed with long sharp spines so the nest was well protected.
The nest was within 2m (approx. 6ft) of a narrow backwater channel
connecting an oxbow lake to the main river. At the time, the area was well
flooded so that the area under the nest was inundated with water
approximately lm (about 3ft) deep. The nest was 1.5m (about 5ft) above the
water.
While observers remained at a distance, the adult remained frozen in a
hunched-neck, cryptic posture. When we approached to take photographs
the adult stretched its neck with its beak pointed up in a defence posture. At
this time the chick became visible. It seems apparent that the adult was
hiding the chick because the chick was pure white and obvious once the
adult moved. The pair remained perfectly still and no more vocalizations
were heard.
On June 8th, 1998 an adult and immature were observed flying together
in varzea forest along the outlet to an oxbow lake. The pair flew in front of
us and landed in relatively plain sight less than lm (3ft 3in) above the water.
The immature then flew directly at the adult, came very near to striking it
and then returned to nearly the same perch. The adult moved a short distance
deeper into the forest, perched, and then retreated into the forest beyond our
view.
White-eared Jacamar Galbalcyrhynchus leucotis
Two adults were observed April 26th, 1998, emerging from and entering
a large termitary located approximately 8m (26ft) up in a dead tree. The
tree was located in a man-made clearing adjacent to the Napo River. The
surrounding area was mostly coffee plantation adjacent to large tracts of
primary forest. No food was observed being brought to the nest, and it is
unknown if there were young present at the time.
Black-tailed Tityra Tityra cayana
March, 1998, two adults were observed entering and exiting a hole in a
tree Cecropis sp. adjacent to an oxbow lake. The nest hole was approximately
9m (30ft) from the ground. The adults were observed in the late afternoon
and evening. The area had several similar trees with holes that appeared
suitable for nesting.
Black-fronted Nunbird Monasa nigifrons
A nest was discovered April, 1998, in the side of a gentle hill on the edge
of a large oxbow lake. The hole was over lm (3ft 3in) deep, and no
observations of the nest itself could be made. Adults regularly perched for
hours at a time in nearby foliage.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.235006" page_id="56266241"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
HILL &amp; GREENEY - ECUADORIAN BIRDS
</figure>
<page confidence="0.993034" page_id="56266241"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
51
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9921577" page_id="56266241"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
White-fronted Nunbird Monasa morphoeus
Two adults were observed April, 1998, excavating a hole in flat ground
within 1m (3ft 3in) of a well used trail in primary forest. The nest was soon
abandoned. It seems likely this was because of human traffic.
Ocellated Poor will Nyctiphrynus ocellatus
Observed on December 18th and 22nd, 1997, between 9.00am and
10.00am. The nest was found on the side of a steep ridge (with an approx.
35-40 degree slope) in primary forest. It was located within 4m (approx.
13ft vertically) of the top of the ridge of a north facing slope. The nest
consisted of a loose assemblage of dead leaves. The nest's downhill portion
had several leaves arranged into a raised edge to create a flattened area and
served to camouflage the adult from below.
The lateral portions of the nest also consisted of leaves arranged so that
overall it resembled a shallow dish. Under and around the eggs, the leaves
were flattened down, which made them distinguishable from the surrounding
non-nest leaves. However, without the clues of an adult or egg, the nest was
barely discemable from the surrounding leaf litter. There was a single egg
in the nest. This was pale tan with a slight hint of orange. The egg was
sparsely blotched with darker tan at its thickest part. The egg was estimated
to measure 32mm x 19mm.
The nest was less than 0.5m (2ft) from an infrequently used trail and
was discovered when the adult flew off the nest as we passed. Had the adult
remained motionless, it is doubtful it would have been detected due to its
incredible camouflage when sitting in the leaf litter. The adult flew
approximately 5m (about 16ft) away, landed the ground, and then moved to
a horizontal liana 3m (almost 10ft) farther away. During the second visit to
the nest, the adult stayed on the nest while we observed from only 3m (almost
10ft) away. Its eyes were open and it remained quiet and still. R. Hill
approached within 0.5m (not quite 2ft), and it did not move until an insect
net was brought closer still. It then flew off.
Black-spotted Bare-eye Phlegopsis nigromaculata
This nest, observed April 22nd and 23rd, 1998, was found in primary
forest near the river's floodplain, but in an area that rarely floods. The
surrounding area was flat and contained many palms and large kapok Ceiba
sp. and fig trees Ficus sp. The most numerous trees in the area, however,
were the Stilt-root Palm Iriartea deltoidea. The undergrowth was not overly
dense in this area, and allowed us to pass with relative ease. Nearby (within
100m (320ft)) was a moderately sized ravine.
The nest itself was found in the stump of a Stilt-root Palm approximately
lm (3ft 3in) from the ground. The stump had rotted such that its centre
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.988624" page_id="56266242"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
52
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.970469658536585" page_id="56266242"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
HILL &amp; GREENEY - ECUADORIAN BIRDS
formed a cup-like cavity. The nest consisted of a bowl-shaped mat of palm
leaflets and thin vines. There was a young fern growing out of the palm that
partially shaded the nest. The trunk had rotted away in such a fashion that it
left an opening on one side. The adult sat on the nest in a position to see
potential predators through this opening.
Two eggs were found in the nest. They were pale pink with dense,
wavy, mauve lines. One egg was removed and measured 26mm x 19mm.
When the nest was first encountered, we had approached from the side with
the opening and the adult detected us and fled. It landed 10m (just over
30ft) away and allowed for proper identification. As we moved to get a
closer look it fled again. The next day, when we approached from the opposite
side the adult stayed on the nest until an attempt to photograph it from less
than lm (3ft 3in) was made. It promptly fled when we were detected. In
both instances it flew rapidly and no vocalizations were heard.
White-winged Swallow Tachycineta albiventer
A nest was found in May, 1998 inside the bamboo hand railing of a
boardwalk that served as a dock. The nest was 5m (approx. 16ft) away from
shore out over the water on an oxbow lake. The nest was located in a piece
of bamboo that had a small hole in the end that was approximately 6cm -
7cm (approx. 2V4in-2 3 /4in) in diameter. It consisted of pieces of vegetation
such as grasses and possibly thin palm leaflets formed into a rough platform.
Another nest was observed in late September 1997. This nest was located
in the semi-hollowed out end of a fallen tree that was sticking out of an
oxbow lake. This nest was approximately 3m-4m (approx. 10ft-13ft) from
the bank. There were eggs in it at the time. The eggs were observed being
eaten by a Cuvier's Toucan Ramphastos cuvieri as the adult swallows dive
bombed it in obvious protest.
Black Vulture Coragyps atratus
Two young were discovered on June 27th, 1998 in a protected area that
was made by the buttressed roots of a Kapok tree Ceiba sp. Two large roots
growing out from the tree formed the sides, which were approximately 3m
(about 10ft) tall and a secondary root off of one of the large roots grew
between the two creating an enclosure. This enclosure seemed impenetrable
to all but the most agile of terrestrial predators. The lowest part of the
protected enclosure was 1.5m (almost 5ft) tall where the secondary root
contacted the other large root. The ground area contained by the roots was
perhaps 1.5m (almost 5ft) square.
The tree was located in terra firme primary forest. The adult was guarding
the nest from a nearby perch approximately 5m (approx. 16ft) off the ground
and made a rasping breathy, hiss-like warning call when we approached.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.232674" page_id="56266243"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
HILL &amp; GREENEY - ECUADORIAN BIRDS
</figure>
<page confidence="0.99798" page_id="56266243"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
53
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999290888888889" page_id="56266243"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
The young began hissing as well. The adult then swooped down over our
heads and perched 3m (about 10ft) above us. The adult hissed again and
then remained quiet. The young continued hissing when we looked down
upon them.
Habitat preservation is critical to the process of saving our planet's wild
areas. Yet correct choices cannot be made without knowledge of the ecology
and behaviour of the world's fauna. We hope this, and other natural history
papers, do not end up as nothing more that epitaphs, but instead serve as
valuable resources for generations of scientists to come.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.885927" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56266243" page_num="53" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99911875" page_id="56266243"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
We would like to thank the staff and administration of La Selva Jungle
Lodge for their hard work and continual support without which our field
work would remain tiresome and mundane. R. Hill would like to give special
thanks to Bernard and Darlene Hill for their continued support and interest
in his studies. H. Greeney would like to thank Robert and Katt Azar for
their encouragement and support of his interest in natural history. This work
is dedicated to the memory of Robert Yonally, whose passion for birds made
a difference.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.980655" genericHeader="references" page_id="56266243" page_num="53" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.9402168">
Moore, J. V. 1993. Sounds of La Selva: Ecuador. Astral Sounds
Recording. San Jose, California, USA.
Ryan /. Hill is with the University of Oregon, Eugene, Oregon 97403
and Harold F. Greeney is with the Department of Entomology, The University
of Arizona, Tucson, Arizona 85721, USA.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.996323" page_id="56266244"  page_num="54" year="" vol="">
54
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8065" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266244" page_num="54" year="" vol="">
WATCHING BALI STARLINGS AT JERSEY ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986208128205128" page_id="56266244"  page_num="54" year="" vol="">
by Trace Williams
The recent raid on the captive-breeding centre at Bali Barat National
Park (see News &amp; Views, Vol. 106, No. 1, p. 44), in which many of the adult
Bali Starling Leucopsar rothschildi breeding stock were stolen, has
highlighted the desperate situation that this species faces in the wild. Time
is running out for the national bird of Bali, making maintenance of the captive
population elsewhere even more important.
I began studying the Bali Starling at Jersey Zoo, headquarters of the
Durrell Wildlife Conservation Trust, at the start of the 1998 breeding season.
Successful breeding of this species had been varied across all holding
institutions, with no real solutions to why some years were better than others
or why some parent birds seemed unable to successfully rear their young.
Jersey Zoo decided to investigate their variability through the innovative
use of small cameras placed inside specially adapted nest-boxes, linked to
monitors and video cameras, enabling all activity to be observed. In that
year I was able to observe egg laying and incubation for 16 clutches from
six different pairs and to quantify details of both parent and chick behaviour
for seven broods.
The results of my investigation supported continuing improvements in
husbandry made by the Bird Department and, along with nutritional studies
being carried out, enabled positive changes to be made concerning variety
and nutritional content of the diet, timing and availability of food supplies
and encouragement of the chicks immune system through medicated food;
the bulk of their insect diet itself being maintained on a nutritionally balanced
diet. As with all changes in husbandry, immediate results were not expected,
however, in the following breeding season there was an encouraging slight
increase in the survival of parent reared chicks.
Close observation of the breeding ecology of Bali Starlings from hours
of video watching gave me insight into activity not usually seen. I was
intrigued by many aspects of their behaviour, especially concerning the
hatching process, and began study for a masters degree in spring 1999,
through the Durrell Institute of Conservation and Ecology, University of
Kent, at Canterbury. I decided it would be also interesting to study the
hatching process of another stumid, the Common Starling Sturnus vulgaris,
for comparison with another member of the Stumidae family.
In 1999, using the same methods and equipment, three pairs of Bali
Starlings were studied and I was able to record on video nine different
hatching events. One nest-box was made available to Common Starlings
which provided four hatching events. I investigated behaviour of both parent
</bodyText>
<address confidence="0.427078">
WILLIAMS - BALI STARLINGS
</address>
<page confidence="0.995682" page_id="56266245"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
55
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.987707875" page_id="56266245"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
birds for a fixed period prior to each egg hatching, calculating the actual
duration of hatching (visible externally only), and observing behaviour of
parents and chicks, one hour post-hatch.
Another interesting aspect of the investigation are the eggshells. With
help from the bird keeping staff, I collected eggshells from the Bali Starlings,
which most of the birds kindly deposited at the front of the aviary ready for
collection. Eggshell thickness is measured using a micrometer, the length
and breadth of both halves of the eggshell are also measured and using a
binocular microscope in the Veterinary Department, Jersey Zoo, I am looking
for signs of use of the chick's egg tooth. Although retreating soon after
hatching it is not known when the so-called 'hatching-muscle' Musculus
complexus or the egg-tooth of a Bali Starling chick disappears, so I am also
examining any very young chicks (&lt;6 days) that do not survive and
documenting the detection of either.
At the beginning of March 2000, a further two nest-boxes were erected
for Common Starlings, all of which have cameras linked to monitors and
video recorders. Only one nest-box was opened initially, in an effort to
stagger the hatching events from different pairs. The other two boxes will
be opened in sequence as soon as a good nest is completed in the first. The
Bali Starling breeding season begins at the end of April. It is anticipated
that five pairs will be selected for breeding this year, some being different
birds to last year enabling me to increase the sample size and data collected.
The exceptional plumage and vocabulary of the Bali Starling has,
unfortunately, been its downfall. While the political unrest continues in
Indonesia, the possibility of further reintroductions are minimal, as is the
likelihood of survival for the remaining few wild birds. The importance of
continued research to support best husbandry practices for this species in
the captive situation cannot therefore be underestimated. This project will I
hope give us more clues as to how we can help to conserve the Bali Starling
and in this way, hopefully, we can ensure that the Bali Starling does not
become another Dodo.
This project is currently being supported by: Jersey Zoo, John Ray Trust,
British Ornithologists' Union, the International Fund for Avian Research,
the Eric Hosking Charitable Trust, Bali Mynah Species Survival Plan, USA
and the Avicultural Society.
The Durrell Wildlife Conservation Trust operates species recovery
programmes for some of the world&apos;s most endangered animals at its Jersey
Zoo headquarters and through projects in-country. You can help save animals
from extinction by supporting the Durrell Wildlife Conservation Trust, Les
Augres Manor, Trinity, Jersey, Channel Islands JE3 5BP.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.986868" page_id="56266246"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
56
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.953473" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266246" page_num="56" year="" vol="">
THE UNIQUE FISHING TECHNIQUES AND NEST
BUILDING BEHAVIOUR OF CAPTIVE HAMMERKOPS
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.448427">
Scopus umbretta
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9195531875" page_id="56266246"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
by Greg Bockheim
The African aviary and its inhabitants
At Disney's Animal Kingdom (DAK) the pair of Hammerkops Scopus
umbretta is housed in a large free-flight aviary. The aviary covers an area
50m long x 20m wide x 19m high (approx. 164ft long x 65ft wide x 62ft
high) with a densely planted understory which includes mature trees that
create a nearly unbroken canopy overhead. A two-storey waterfall pours
into pools at two different levels intentionally flooding areas which become
'tidal zones'. A path meanders through the centre of the aviary allowing
guests (as we call visitors to DAK) a close encounter with over 140 individual
specimens of 28 avian species.
Aquatic birds in the aviary include African Ja#anas Actophilornis
africanus. Pygmy Geese Nettapus auritus , White-backed Ducks Thalassomis
leuconotus , Black Crakes Amauromis flavirostris and Hottentot Teal Sarcelle
hottentote. The more arboreal species that the Hammerkops may have
occasional or frequent contact with include Hadada Ibis Hagedashia
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.8350725" page_id="56266246"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
hagedash brevirostris, Superb Starlings Spreo superbus , Golden-breasted
Starlings Cosmopsarus regius, Olive Pigeons Columba arquatrix, African
Grey Parrots Psittacus erthacus, Ross's Touracos Musophaga rossae and
Long-tailed Magpie Shrikes Corvinella melanoleuca. Fish in the African
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.987524882352941" page_id="56266246"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
aviary pools include Tilapia Oreochromis variabilis, two species often
referred to as 'spiny eels' - Bichir Polypterus ornatipinnis and Zaire Eel
Afromastacembelusfrenatus, four mid-size ciclid species from Lake Malawi,
and the live-bearing Florida native species referred to as Mosquito Fish
Gambuisa sp. All of the fish species, except the 'spiny eels' reproduce and
provide a continuous supply of live fish in the aviary pools. The fish inhabit
all the pool zones from the very shallow water of the planters (2cm-12cm
( 3 /4in-4 3 Ain) in depth), preferred by the Gambuisa and ciclid fry, to the larger
pool areas (up to lm (3ft 3in) in depth). In these deeper pool areas we see
the fish species divide into well defined zones with the small Gambuisa
schooling at the surface, and the colourful ciclid species staying close to the
rocky bottom.
DAK's two Hammerkops, both captive reared, were acquired from two
separate zoological institutions in October 1997. In February 1998 they
were introduced to their new habitat following a quarantine period and then
an introductory protocol which involved placing the birds in a 'howdy' cage
on the second floor of the aviary habitat. When released the birds did not
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.51287" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266247" page_num="57" year="" vol="">
BOCKHEIM - HAMMERKOPS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997226" page_id="56266247"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
57
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.996768268292683" page_id="56266247"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
initially seem to favour any particular area of the aviary and seemed to enjoy
the upper canopy as well as the water features. Competition between the
bird species remains minimal, likely due to the large size of the aviary, dense
foliage, the diverse species, the bird's gradual introduction to the habitat
and individual species' populations. The arrangement and quantity of feeding
stations also seems to reduce aggressive interactions between species.
Fishing techniques
The Hammerkops have demonstrated some unusual fishing practises.
Some techniques observed at DAK have been reported in other avian
collections, or in the wild, but another technique has not been reported in
the professional literature reviewed. After the hammerkops had been in the
aviary for six months they were observed presumably searching for fish
using the species-typical means of searching for livefood in wet marshy
areas. This fishing style was best described by M. P. Kahl.
'Stirring with the feet is a common technique used by Hammerkops to
fish for prey. The foot is placed in the normal standing position; then it is
shuffled rapidly four to five times while being brought forward to a position
under the bill. The foot is then placed down in this forward position and the
process repeated with the other foot. Meanwhile the bird peers intently at
the water. Such movements are likely to drive concealed prey into sight.
Occasionally a bird was seen to open both wings partially for an instant
while foot-stirring. Presumably this 'wing-flashing' technique also served
to startle prey into action so that it could be more easily seen ' (Cowles,
1930).
Our birds also employ another form of fishing that has been observed to
occur among birds in the wild. On these occasions the birds fly slowly,
using deep wing beats, low over the water. The legs dangle, brushing the
surface, as the bird peers down into the water. When approaching potential
prey, the bird hovers momentarily, dips its beak into the water and grabs the
prey. Our Hammerkops are frequently successful using this technique. We
often observe our Hammerkops using the same technique, but without
hovering, and instead simply flying directly across the surface of the pool
dipping their beaks in and catching fish that they had presumably seen from
the shore or because the Gabusia schools are so concentrated at the surface
that the birds are often guaranteed to catch one without having seen it first.
The distance across the pools varies from 2m-7m (approx. 6ft 7in-22ft 7in)
and the birds have been seen covering these distances when fishing. On
occasions our birds also fly across the pools lightly dragging their toes across
the surface of the water while not appearing to be searching for fish. We
have surmised that the birds are attracting fish to the surface of the water so
that they might be captured the next time they fly over.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995639" page_id="56266248"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
58
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.866605" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266248" page_num="58" year="" vol="">
BOCKHEIM - HAMMERKOPS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998848926829268" page_id="56266248"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
Foot stirring appears to be our Hammerkops' most popular means of
pursuing livefood. Probing for it with their beaks is also popular but not
nearly as commonly seen. Like those Hammerkops observed in the wild
(Cowles, 1930), our birds also wash all of the prey caught in the water before
swallowing it. They do not, however, take insects caught on dry land to the
water to wash before eating them. After they have caught a medium to large
fish that is more difficult to swallow, the birds may take up to 25 minutes to
repeatedly attempt to swallow it, regurgitating it again even after only its
tail is sticking out of the beak. Our birds have also captured Tilapia, much
too large for them to swallow, and have deserted the carcass. The
Hammerkops have also been observed perched at the water's edge and then
running swiftly through shallow water (2cm-7cm ( 3 /4in-2 3 /4in) deep) to jab
at small Mosquito Fish or Tilapia fry hiding in the shelter of fallen leaves or
other such deadfall. They have also been observed to approach quickly and
freeze near a leaf or other particle that falls on the water and floats, in apparent
anticipation of a fish coming to feed off the fallen item or to seek shelter
beneath it.
An unusual fishing technique
It is in feeding the following diet that we have observed our Hammerkops
using an unusual fish 'baiting' or fish capturing method. Our Hammerkops
are fed a staple diet twice daily that is equal parts soaked Mazuri flamingo
complete and Milikin Meats 'carnivore meat'. The ingredients are kneaded
together and rolled into balls roughly 3cm (1 V4in) in diameter. Our birds
take these balls of food and fly to the water's edge with them. Upon arrival
at the water's edge, they most often drop the ball of food on the shore or at
the water's edge. They then shake it into pieces with their beak; this shaking
behaviour scatters pieces of the mixture into the water and this attracts fish.
The birds then repeatedly pick up a chunk of food, breaking smaller pieces
from it which float into deeper water. A feeding frenzy ensues with the fish
not only struggling to get the food particles which have landed in the water
but also almost throwing themselves onto the shore or into the shallow water
at the Hammerkops' feet. The Hammerkops then simply choose which size
fish seem most desirable and pick them up. On many occasions the birds
have pecked at and pulled from the water very large fish up to 20cm (8in)
long (nearly a third of their own length) and dropped them back into the
water. When 'baiting' and then choosing a fish, the birds most often select
small Tilapia and the smaller colourful ciclids.
Nest building
Our pair began to build in April 1998 when they were both 11 months of
age. During their early nest building attempts the birds brought tree branches,
twigs and leaf matter to three different locations in the aviary. Within the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.512837" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266249" page_num="59" year="" vol="">
BOCKHEIM - HAMMERKOPS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996815" page_id="56266249"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
59
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.996845195121951" page_id="56266249"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
first five days of what might be referred to as frenzied nest building the pair
settled on a light platform site 8m (just over 26ft) above the largest aviary
pool. During this first attempt the nest under construction was frequently
visited by the pair of Hadada Ibis which would alight on the mass of sticks
and scavenge for material for their own nest. During these visits the pair of
Hammerkops did not defend the nest but instead perched nearby. Later,
when nearing completion of this first nest, a pair of Superb Starlings scolded
and chased off the Hammerkops, took over the nest and eventually reared
young. The Hammerkops did not retaliate other than utter their high pitched
screams when being chased by the starlings. In June 1998 the pair of
Hammerkops began their second nesting attempt in the fork of a Tepu Tree
Tipuana tipu 3m (almost 10ft) above the path. In mid-July the pair had two
eggs (later found to be infertile). By the end of July one of the eggs was
found broken beneath the nest and the other had disappeared. No significant
disturbances were recorded at this nest site although snakes were frequently
captured in the aviary during this season. Through the early part of August
1998 the pair were frequently observed aggressively chasing each other and
fighting. The male often was the aggressor and appeared to be pushing the
female in the direction of the unsuccessful nest in the Tepu Tree. After a
couple of weeks the pair settled and chose to repair and continue nest
construction at the original site on the light platform but frequently visited
the nest in the Tepu Tree. A third nest site on another light platform, also 8m
(approx. 26ft) from the ground was also begun during this time. The pair
soon settled though on the most recent light platform and began dismantling
the nest in the Tepu Tree and bringing nest material to this platform. Within
four weeks the pair had completed this nest, having dismantled the old nest
in the tree, and abandoned the nest on the first platform. Being far out of
reach this new nest site was impossible for the keeper to check and on
February 18th, 1999 a fully developed chick could be seen peering out of
the nest. Within a week three chicks had left the nest. From the beginning
these newly fledged Hammerkops were accomplished fliers and manoeuvred
well when flying in the aviary. Within the week, however, it was discovered
that the two younger chicks were not thriving as well as the first chick.
Following examination by our veterinary staff it was determined that the
younger chicks had suffered nutritional deficiencies which were corrected
after six weeks of nutritional therapy and hospitalization.
Reproduction summary
The two birds which make up our founder pair of Hammerkops were
hatched at different zoological institutions on April 27th and 28th, 1997.
They were acquired by DAK when they were eight months of age. After a
quarantine period and four weeks of introduction to each other and their
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.988091" page_id="56266250"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
60
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.86372" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266250" page_num="60" year="" vol="">
BOCKHEIM - HAMMERKOPS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998838404761905" page_id="56266250"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
new habitat they began nest building at 11 months of age. This nest building
behaviour began after only six weeks of living in their new habitat. They
built four successive nests over a 14 *month period and laid their first clutch
of eggs, which were infertile, at 18 months of age. The pair hatched and
successfully reared young when they were 21 months old in the fourth nest
constructed. This fourth nesting attempt was also interfered with by the
Superb Starlings, which built their own nest in the side of the Hammerkop
nest on the opposite side of the nest entrance. (During this fourth nesting
attempt the flock of Superb Starlings comprised females only and it may be
that the aggressiveness of the starlings was reduced due to the absence of
males). The pair of Hammerkops actively participated in building up to
three nests at a time and dismantled a previous nest and used the detritus to
construct another nest.
Each of the four nests were built at different locations in the aviary at
heights varying from 3m 8rn (approx. 1 Oft 26ft) from the ground (8m
(approx. 26ft) is mid-canopy height in our aviary). Only one nest was built
directly over water, the others were all within 16m (approx. 52ft) of the
largest pool. Two nests were built on platforms (45cm (17 3 /dn) wide around
18cm (Tin) aviary pole supports) covering the lights in the aviary and the
other two were built in forks of medium-sized trees (24cm (9 : Mn) in
diameter). All the nests were in clear view of everyone and provided a
terrific experience for observers. More often than not guests (or visitors)
had to duck their heads when the Hammerkops made the endless trips to
and from the nest under construction. Nest construction was continuous
throughout the season and nest completion (when the nest roof was in place
and the integrity of the nest appeared to be such that eggs may be laid inside)
took from 21-40 days. Nest size and shape remained uniform and averaged
1.5m 2m (almost 5ft 6ft Tin) in width and height, with the narrow entrance
hole facing different directions at each site. Our Hammerkops were not
observed to aggressively disturb other aviary inhabitants but were themselves
the focus of other bird's aggression when they ventured too close to nests.
The most intense bouts of aggression from the Hammerkops were conspecific
but were not a cause for alarm. In order to control the number of chicks
hatched, the latest Hammerkop clutch has been replaced with wooden dummy
eggs which the birds have accepted and continue to incubate. On five
occasions the Hadada Ibis and Superb Starlings were observed removing
nesting material from the top and sides of the Hammerkop nests. These
intrusions did not cause either Hammerkop to defend their nests, for by
nature they seem passive.
An interesting observation was mentioned by the African nationals
working at DAK. These staff members, acting as guest informational hosts
in the aviary, warned us to stay clear of Hammerkop nests because of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.512786" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266251" page_num="61" year="" vol="">
BOCKHEIM - HAMMERKOPS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99817" page_id="56266251"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
61
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998737666666667" page_id="56266251"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
insects that inhabit them. The literature cited (Cowles, 1930) describes how
beetles, cockroaches, millipedes and other arthropods inhabit the nests,
attracted to them by the abundant food supply originating either directly or
indirectly from the filthy nesting habits of the Hammerkops. Upon
dismantling one of our Hammerkop nests we did not encounter an excess of
insects nor filthy conditions, both a possible result of the clean captive
conditions.
Since raising their chicks our pair of Hammerkops have gone on to build
another nest in a Tepu Tree. The breeding pair's remaining juvenile, five
months old at the time of writing, lives in the aviary with the parents and
has not been seen to aid or interfere with its parents' present attempts at
nesting. No aggression has been recorded between the adults and the juvenile,
whose sex remains unknown at this time.
Reviewing the reproductive data collected at DAK and having accurate
historical records of our original pair of Hammerkops has given us the
opportunity to determine the age at which captive Hammerkops may begin
to build their nests, lay eggs and successfully rear young, information not
available in the sources cited.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.856551" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56266251" page_num="61" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997862" page_id="56266251"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
This paper was made possible due to the diligent behavioural observations
recorded by the aviary team at Disney's Animal Kingdom.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.813521" genericHeader="references" page_id="56266251" page_num="61" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.856018444444445" page_id="56266251"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
Campbell, B. and Lack, E. 1985. A dictionary of birds. Buteo Books, South Dakota, USA.
Cowles, R.B. 1930. The Life History of Scopus Umbretta. Auk 47, 2:159-176.
del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A. and Sargatal, J. (eds). 1996. Handbook of the Birds of the World. Vol.3.
Hoatzin to Auks. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona, Spain.
Kahl, M.R 1967. Observations on the behaviour of the hammerkop Scopus umbretta in Uganda.
Ibis 109,1:25-32.
Greg Bockheim, who with Shannon Mezzell won the D.H.S. Risdon Award
for the account of breeding the Black Crake Amaurornis flavirostris at DAK
(Avicultural Magazine 105,1:12-21), is a member of the Bird Department
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.8488805">
team at Disney&apos;s Animal Kingdom, P.O. Box 10,000, Lake Buena Vista,
Florida 32830-1000, USA. Tel:407 938-6383/Fax:502-333-3966. Susan
Congdon and Bill Zima, who describe the breeding of the African Jagana
Actophilornis africanus at DAK (pp. 62-74), are members of the same team.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.997091" page_id="56266252"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
62
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998721" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266252" page_num="62" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE AFRICAN JAQANA Actophilornis africanus
AT DISNEY'S ANIMAL KINGDOM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.957590888888889" page_id="56266252"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
by Susan Congdon and Bill Zima
Introduction
The African Jaqana. Actophilornis africanus , with its striking blue frontal
shield and long toes which allow it to walk easily across lily-pads, is a
fascinating bird to display. It is also of great interest from the natural history
point of view on account of its unusual mating behaviour. One female may
mate with up to 10 different males in a season (Tarboton, 1995), identifying
this species as being polyandrous. Polyandry has been documented in fewer
than 50 avian taxa. The greatest challenge in keeping African Ja 9 anas is
breeding and rearing the young successfully. Few collections have had luck
hand raising ja^ana chicks and even fewer have had the parents raise them
successfully. At Disney's Animal Kingdom here in Florida we have raised
by hand four African Jaganas in our nursery.
Habitat and feeding
The African Jac^anas are among the inhabitants of the large free-flight
walk-through African aviary described earlier (P. 56) by Greg Bockheim.
There are 11 feeding stations throughout the aviary, six on the lower level
and five on the upper level. Two of the bowls contain carnivore diet mixed
with Mazuri flamingo pellets. The waterfowl bowl has Mazuri waterfowl
pellets, small bird breeder and lettuce mixed together. The mixed species
bowl has chopped mixed fruit, soaked Mazuri parrot breeder and small bird
breeder, lettuce, carrots, seeds and Quicko insectivore diet. The jaganas
have been seen eating at all the feeding stations. Insects are also dispersed
throughout the day to all the birds. There has been very little if any
interspecific aggression between the ja?anas and other birds.
Breeding
There are three wild caught African Ja 9 anas in the aviary. The male was
purchased from North Carolina Zoological Park and the two females came
from Disney's Discovery Island. The male was released in the aviary on
January 29th, 1998 after two months of quarantine and acclimation to the
aviary. The females were released together on February 6th, 1998.
The first sign of breeding was seen on September 15th, 1998, when the
male ja 9 ana began displaying to both females. He threw his head back two
or three times then stretched his neck out and began calling. Both females
seemed uninterested and the male ceased after a minute. Early September
has been recorded as the beginning of the breeding season for ja 9 anas in the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.467722" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266253" page_num="63" year="" vol="">
CONGDON &amp; ZIMA - AFRICAN JA#ANA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998419" page_id="56266253"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
63
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999536" page_id="56266253"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
wild (Postage, 1982). On September 29th, however, it was discovered that
the male had moulted his primaries and tail feathers. The breeding female
did not moult until October 15th, nearly four weeks after the male had begun
moulting. The non-breeding female did not moult at this time. With jaganas
in the wild, the non-breeding females moult first. This should have led to
the male to begin displaying to the other female (Tarboton, 1992). On
October 9th the male was seen displaying to an unidentified female. He
shuffled his feet and danced around her. It was not until October 27th though
that we witnessed the 'wing salute' to the breeding female. The male repeated
this several times throughout the day. The following day, the male and the
breeding female chased the non-breeding female away from the pond area.
By December 13th the non-breeding female was moulting.
On December 16th, 1998, the male and breeding female performed the
typical mating ritual ofjaganas. The female stretched out her neck with her
head held low while at the same time keeping her tail pointed upwards. The
male mounted her and attempted to copulate unsuccessfully for three seconds.
The male then crouched beneath the female and began lightly pressing his
head on her breast, cloaca and under her wings. The male then flew off
without attempting to copulate again. Later in the day the breeding female
called to the male and the ritual started again. This time they copulated for
18 seconds, with the male moving from the right side to the left side of the
female's tail. They continued the mating ritual for the following week,
copulating both successfully and at times unsuccessfully.
The first egg was discovered on December 23rd. We had not provided
any floating vegetation, and hoped they would lay their eggs on the island
under the cover of the rice grass and safe from predators. They, however,
chose to lay by the edge of the first catch pool for the waterfall. The nest
was poorly assembled. The female had gathered what little vegetation that
was in the immediate area and stomped it down. This was the same spot
where the pair copulated most frequently. In the wild the male and female
African Jagana copulate on a lily-pad or other floating vegetation on which
they plan to nest. It is said this is to test whether it is strong enough to
support the weight of the eggs and the chicks. If the nest sinks during mating,
they will choose a new nest site (Tarboton, 1992). The female laid an egg
each morning for the next three days. The typical clutch size in the wild is
three to five eggs, with four being most common (Tarboton, 1992). On the
morning of December 29th, there were only two eggs remaining in the nest.
The nest and water were checked for any sign of disturbance, but nothing
was found. The two eggs that remained were taken to the nursery to be
artificially incubated. Two dummy eggs made of wood were put in their
place in the nest. The following morning though both had disappeared without
trace. The two eggs in the nursery were candled after four days and found
to be infertile.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996517" page_id="56266254"  page_num="64" year="" vol="">
64
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.732728" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266254" page_num="64" year="" vol="">
CONGDON &amp; ZIMA - AFRICAN JA#ANA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999646714285714" page_id="56266254"  page_num="64" year="" vol="">
The last nest was so poorly constructed that each time the male left the
nest the eggs rolled away a short distance. More vegetation was placed in
the nest area and shaped so there would be a cup for the eggs to rest in. The
male and female both flew to the area and picked at the new vegetation for
about 12 minutes, before flying to the rice grass area. The jaganas started
showing signs of interest again on December 31 st, when the male flew to
the nest site and began calling. The female responded by flying from the
lower pond to the nest and stretching out her neck and keeping her head
low. They copulated for 13 seconds. The male then tapped his head on the
female's breast and flew off. The female stayed and patted down the
vegetation in the nest area. An egg was found in the nest two days later but
it quickly disappeared. Another was laid the following morning. It was
removed by the keepers and replaced with a dummy egg. This vanished
four hours later. The female called to the male about 3.00pm and the male
responded by circling her and lightly pressing his head against her underside.
No attempt was made to copulate. They repeated this behaviour three times
in 15 minutes. The next morning the female laid an egg in the rice grass
area. It was later found submerged in the water and removed by the keeper
and taken away in the hope that it could be artificially incubated.
The ja 9 anas spent the next week moving back and forth from the rice
grass to the side of the waterfall. They spent time copulating, fixing the nest
and going through the mating ritual. On January 13th, 1999 the female laid
another egg on the side of the waterfall. Once again, because of our fear of
losing another egg, we removed it and took it to be artificially incubated.
The following day she did not lay an egg on the nest as expected. Instead a
second nest site was discovered. This was on the upper story about 10ft
(approx. 3m) from the closest water source. The nest consisted of an old
palm frond and other leaves. It was another poorly constructed nest with no
visible structure or cover.
The decision was made to leave the egg and monitor the nest to see what
happened. We initially thought that the Black Crakes Amaurornis flavirostris
were predating the eggs. Tarboton (1992) assumed that predation was the
leading cause of the low hatching success rate of African Ja^anas' eggs even
though no eggs had been seen being predated. In the wild, male jaganas
chase Black Crakes from their territory but ignore White-backed Ducks
Thalassornis leuconotus (Postage, 1982). Both these species are housed in
the aviary with the ja 9 anas and similar behaviour has been observed. Anytime
Black Crakes approach the nest site, the ja 9 anas chase them away, whereas
the White-backed Ducks are tolerated.
As most of the eggs were vanishing at night an infra-red camera and a
time lapse video recorder were used to monitor the nest. This enabled us to
record the female laying the next two eggs of her clutch. In the wild it was
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.466463" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266255" page_num="65" year="" vol="">
CONGDON &amp; ZIMA - AFRICAN JA#ANA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.993454" page_id="56266255"  page_num="65" year="" vol="">
65
</page>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.322325">
Photo Susan Congdon
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999266368421053" page_id="56266255"  page_num="65" year="" vol="">
jacana chicks at three and five days old
noted that females laid their eggs between 6.07am and 7.55am (Tarboton,
1992). In the aviary at Disney's Animal Kingdom we found that our female
laid her eggs between 7.15am and 8.10am. When laying the female squatted
slightly and dropped the egg. She then spent five to 10 minutes arranging
the nest before she left and the male appeared. The male normally sat on the
nest for only one to two minutes before he would fly off.
The morning of January 18th, 1999 brought further frustration. One of
the eggs had been cracked open and the other two had been scattered. The
two good eggs were removed and taken to be incubated and replaced with
one of the infertile eggs. The male inspected the nest after about an hour.
He then smashed the infertile egg with his beak and flew off. The Black
Crakes began eating the contents of the egg. We immediately examined the
video tape to see what had happened. We found that the male hardly sat on
the nest during the night. He was typically on the nest for less than five
minutes before he would fly off and not return for some time. At
approximately 20 minutes past midnight a rat could be seen eating the egg.
The pair began mating again the next day at the upper nest site. This
continued for the next four days. On January 25th, 1999 the male called to
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.976575" page_id="56266256"  page_num="66" year="" vol="">
66
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.727654" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266256" page_num="66" year="" vol="">
CONGDON &amp; ZIMA - AFRICAN JA#ANA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999567333333333" page_id="56266256"  page_num="66" year="" vol="">
the female from the earlier nest site on the side of the waterfall. The following
day an egg was found on this lower nest site. This was interesting because
wild ja 9 anas are said to rarely re-use their nesting platforms (Tarboton, 1992).
The egg was removed and taken away to be incubated. The female laid
daily and ended with a clutch of three eggs. The male and female ja 9 anas
were seen copulating in the rice grass on the afternoon the third egg was
laid. They spent the next two weeks chasing the non-breeding female from
the pond area and towards the densely planted area.
On February 17th, 1999 the pair again showed signs of mating. The
female lowered her head and then the male did the same. They stayed for a
few moments and then the male flew off. This behaviour continued for a
few more days until on February 20th, the pair were seen copulating at the
original nest site next to the waterfall pool. On February 25th an egg was
laid at this earlier nest site. The female continued laying until the clutch
contained four eggs.
A review of the time lapse video showed the male was sitting tighter on
this clutch than on the earlier ones. With the male sitting tighter we were
optimistic he would deter other birds from predating the eggs. Then on the
night of March 2nd, at 10.30pm, an automatic sprinkler head popped up 2in
(5cm) from the nest, startling the male and causing the eggs to be scattered.
The male did not return until 7.00am the following morning. On March 4th
we went with the horticulture team to cap the sprinkler system so this would
not happen again. When we arrived at the nest site the male was not there,
but immediately came and watched while we worked. He did not vocalize
or show any aggression. However, he unfortunately never again returned to
this nest area. We had suspected this might happen, but a study in Africa
encouraged us to think differently. Of 99 nests checked, not a single male
abandoned the nest due to human disturbance (Tarboton, 1992); even after
the males were trapped, checked and weighed. In our case, one egg was
missing when the sprinkler was capped. The other three were left in the
nest in the hope that the male would return. At 5.45pm two Black Crakes
were caught on film eating two of the remaining three eggs. The fourth was
removed and taken to be incubated.
The male began moulting on March 15th, 1999 and the breeding pair
was seen copulating for the last time on April 13th. An egg was found the
morning of April 19th but vanished quickly. It was the female's nineteenth
and final egg of the season that had lasted from mid-December until mid-
April 1999.
Using time lapse and infra-red video, we have been able to evaluate
some of the challenges facing the ja 9 anas when attempting to successfully
incubate their eggs. Some we had anticipated, and some we had not. We
knew that rats and other predators were likely to be a problem. Similarly,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.467612" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266257" page_num="67" year="" vol="">
CONGDON &amp; ZIMA - AFRICAN JA#ANA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997952" page_id="56266257"  page_num="67" year="" vol="">
67
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997379829268293" page_id="56266257"  page_num="67" year="" vol="">
we feared the crakes might be a problem as they also breed in the pond area.
We had not, however, anticipated the sprinkler popping up and scaring the
male off the nest. Water lilies have now been planted in and around the rice
grass island in an attempt to encourage the ja 9 anas to use these during the
coming breeding season.
Hand rearing
The ja 9 ana eggs were incubated in the DAK nursery at 99.9*F (37.7* C)
and hatched after 22 and 23 days of incubation. The eggs hatched on January
18th, February 5th, 19th and 20th. Each weighed about 5g. Three other
eggs hatched but the chicks did not survive past the seventh day. One had
the umbilicus wrapped around its left leg and had to be assisted in hatching.
It showed some interest in food but died on the first day. Another had to be
euthanized due to a slipped tendon on the second day. The third died on the
seventh day possibly due to a yolk sac infection.
The chicks were raised primarily on a diet of small crickets, live brine
shrimps, minced newborn mice and finely crushed Mazuri gamebird starter.
Mealworms were added to the diet on the eighth day. Crickets and live
brine shrimps were the initial food preference of all four chicks. Later, the
preference changed to crickets and gamebird starter. The chicks were initially
fed crickets every hour, later switching to every two hours. The crickets fed
to the chicks were not dusted with vitamins or minerals but instead fed
Mazuri cricket food for 24-48 hours.
No attempt was made to isolate the chicks from the sight or sound of
humans. A puppet was used briefly (three to five days) for feeding all except
for the first chick. It was made from large forceps, gauze and medical tape.
Coloured pencils and markers were used to colour the puppet to look like an
adult. The puppet was introduced to the second chick a week after hatching.
The following two chicks were fed using the puppet from hatching and
were much more receptive to it. Although the chicks were attracted to the
puppet, it is too early to determine whether this impacted upon the chicks'
development.
They were housed in a brooder until the 15th-20th day at 98*F (36.7*C)
and this was then decreased as needed. They were later placed in 3ft x 3ft x
18in (91.5cm x 91.5cm x 46cm) and 4ft x 4ft x 30in (approx. 1.2m x 1.2m x
76cm) Plexiglas (perspex)-sided open brooders with radiant heat. Both had
towels and rubber matting for substrate. Artificial grass was placed in a
comer at first and then all around as they became acclimated. A feather
duster was placed in the comer of both brooders. Initially the chicks spent
a majority of their sleeping time under the dusters. A mirror was used with
the first chick after the 19th day, the second inconsistently after the second
day, and from hatching with the third and fourth chicks. The second chick
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.989651" page_id="56266258"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
68
</page>
<table confidence="0.8125252" page_id="56266258"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
CONGDON &amp; ZIMA - AFRICAN JA#ANA
Photo Susan Congdon
Ja^ana chicks at three and five days old being fed using puppet
Photo Susan Congdon
Ja^ana chick at 19 days old
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.338073" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266259" page_num="69" year="" vol="">
CONGDON &amp; ZIMA - AFRICAN JA#ANA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.679088" page_id="56266259"  page_num="69" year="" vol="">
69
</page>
<figure confidence="0.998264733333333" page_id="56266259"  page_num="69" year="" vol="">
Chick weights
Day
Chick 1
Chick 2
Chick 3
Chick 4
Chick 5
Chick 6
Chick 7
Tarsus measurements
Chick 1
-- Yen--
Chick 3
Chick 6
Chick 7
</figure>
<page confidence="0.968301" page_id="56266260"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
70
</page>
<equation confidence="0.180596" page_id="56266260"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
CONGDON &amp; ZIMA - AFRICAN JA#ANA
Photo Susan Congdon
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.617716" page_id="56266260"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
Measuring the tarsus of 30 day old chick
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.654089">
Photo Susan Congdon
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.963329" page_id="56266260"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
Measuring the bill of 30 day old chick
often stood in close proximity to the mirror. All chicks were initially housed
alone except for the fourth, which was placed with the third as soon as it
was dry. The first two chicks were introduced when the first chick was 30
days old and the second chick was 17 days old. A physical barrier was used
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.467554" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266261" page_num="71" year="" vol="">
CONGDON &amp; ZIMA - AFRICAN JA#ANA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997345" page_id="56266261"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
71
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999852418604651" page_id="56266261"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
initially as a precaution due to the larger size of the older chick. Though the
younger chick was much smaller, a second food source had to be added due
to displacement of the older, larger chick.
There were some minor health problems associated with the surviving
chicks. The second and fourth chicks had to have their toes taped to stop
them from turning outwards. This occurred on the 29th and 18th days
respectively. The taping corrected the problem within five days. The second
chick's Oright leg deviated at the ankle joint causing the bird to limp. This
chick was housed in a small brooder until the 15th day. After this chick was
moved to a larger enclosure and had more exercise the problem corrected
itself. Subsequently, the third and fourth chicks were moved to a larger
enclosure at an earlier age. Some cracks in the plantar surface of the foot
were easily healed by using A &amp; D ointment and allowing the chicks access
to more water.
The weight of each chick was taken daily. Graph 1 (p.69 top) shows the
daily weight of each of the seven chicks that hatched in the nursery. All
four surviving chicks were similar in weight until about the 25th day. At
this point the female began to increase in weight faster than the three males.
The weights of the chicks appeared to level off at about the 60th day. One
chick, now known to be the female, levelled off at 180g while the three
males levelled off at 110g-120g. It appears, therefore, that they may be able
to be sexed by weight, however, they were karyotyped to confirm this.
Calipers were used to measure the growth rate of each chick's tarsus,
beak/shield and toes. The toe measurement was obtained by measuring
from the tip of the third digit to the back of the surface pad, then adding this
to the length of the hallux. Neither toenail was included in the measurement.
Measurements were not taken of the first chick until the 22nd day because
being the first chick to hatch we wanted to assess the rearing difficulty first.
The third chick was measured from the fourth day until the seventh day
when the above mentioned leg problem occurred. Measurements resumed
on the 70th day but had levelled off by this time. The 70th day is included
on the graph for a male/female size comparison. Measurements of the other
two chicks were taken throughout their development.
Graph 2 (p.69 bottom) charts the tarsus measurements of the four
surviving chicks. There appeared to be no major differences in the rate of
tarsus growth between the males and the female. As shown on Graphs 3
and 4 (p/72) beak and foot growth did not differ between the female and
males either. As more chicks hatch in the nursery, this will become an
ongoing project, and a larger sample may reveal more differences between
male and female development.
The chicks were on view to guests (or visitors) for much of their
development, and due to their unusual appearance they were a huge hit. At
the time of writing, all four are cohabiting in a small aviary with a pool,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.914031" page_id="56266262"  page_num="72" year="" vol="">
72
</page>
<figure confidence="0.985489636363636" page_id="56266262"  page_num="72" year="" vol="">
CONGDON &amp; ZIMA - AFRICAN JA#ANA
Beak measurements
Chick 1
Chick 3
Chick 6
Chick 7
Chick foot measurements
Chick 1
Chick 3
Chick 6
Chick 7
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.467674" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266263" page_num="73" year="" vol="">
CONGDON &amp; ZIMA - AFRICAN JA#ANA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997964" page_id="56266263"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
73
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9916816" page_id="56266263"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
sand-box, plants and banana leaves. On the first day there was slight
aggression from the second chick, which because of its weight we suspected
was the only female, and this was confirmed later. This aggression has not
been seen much since. The chicks spend most of their time in the large
pool.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.933653" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56266263" page_num="73" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgments
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.670923625" page_id="56266263"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
This paper was only made possible due to the diligent efforts of the
Africa aviary team and the nursery staff at Disney's Animal Kingdom:
Shannon Mezzell, Lyn Heller, Jeff Ignaut, Greg Bockheim, Susan Stevens,
Lynne Silkman, Lynne Sutcliffe, Allison Keeley, Jody Daugherty, Greg
Bruehler and Trisha Olow. The Disney's Animal Kingdom's bird department
management team of Grenville Roles, Chelle Plasse and Scott Barton and
Nursery Manager Suzie Kasielke contributed beneficial insights.
Bibliography
</table>
<reference confidence="0.9388395">
Fry, C.H. 1983. Incubation, Brooding and a Structural Character of the African Jacana. Ostrich
54,3:175-176.
Hodgson, R. 1983. Rearing the African Jacana Actophilornis africana at the Wildfowl Trust,
Slimbridge, Glos. Avicultural Magazine 89, 2:67-68.
Postage, A. 1984. The Behaviour of Breeding African Jacanas. Bokmakierie 36, 1:12-14.
Tarboton, W.R. 1992. Aspects of the Breeding Biology of the African Jacana. Ostrich 63,
4:141-157.
Tarboton, W.R. 1995. Polyandry in the African Jacana:The Roles of Male Dominance and Rate
of Clutch Loss. Ostrich 66, 2-3:49-60.
Taylor, C. and Harper, D. 1988. The feeding ecology of the African lily trotter Actophilornis
africanus (Gmelin) at Lake Naivasha, Kenya. African Journal of Ecology 26, 4:329-335.
DR LUIS FELIPE BAPTISTA
Dr Luis Felipe Baptista died on June 12th while tending the garden of
his home at Sebastopol, California. He was 59. He last wrote in the magazine
in 1994 (Vol. 100, No. 4, ppl83-188) on Aviculture's Contribution to Science
and Conservation. An Obituary by Ian Hinze will appear in the next issue.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998063" page_id="56266264"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
74
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.718034" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266264" page_num="74" year="" vol="">
CHESTER ZOO BIRD REVIEW 1999
by Roger Wilkinson
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.94008552631579" page_id="56266264"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
The highlight of 1999 was the arrival of a pair of Red Birds of Paradise
Paradisea rubra received on loan from the New York Zoological Society,
the Bronx/Wildlife Conservation Park, New York. Two of the Chester Zoo
senior bird staff went to the Bronx where they spent time working with the
birds before returning to Chester accompanying the Red Birds of Paradise.
These birds which were bred at New York in 1998 are currently held in our
purpose built off-show bird of paradise breeding area and will be transferred
to the on-show breeding aviaries in the new 'Islands in Danger' exhibit
when it is ready.
Two White-eared Catbirds Ailuroedus buccoides bred at Stuttgart Zoo
have also recently been received at Chester and will also be gracing one of
the 'Islands in Danger' aviaries. Another aviary is planned to hold New
Guinea Blue-crowned Pigeons Goura cristata , Duyvenbode's Lories
Chalcopsitta duivenbodei and Stella's Lorikeets Charmosyna papou. This
exhibit will also house a pair of St. Lucia Amazon Parrots Amazona
versicolor , to be received on loan from Jersey Zoo, and includes a spectacular
enclosure for Komodo Dragons Varanus komodensis.
Another important species received into the collection in 1999 was the
Vietnamese Pheasant Lophura hatinhensis. A pair of these endangered
pheasants were received on loan from the World Pheasant Association, the
male having been bred at Antwerp Zoo and the female at the Old House
Bird Gardens, nr. Reading, England.
Mountain Peacock Pheasants Polyplectron inopinatum were especially
productive in 1999. After a barren year in 1998 when no eggs were laid,
this year the female laid nine eggs. Despite our best efforts to screen the
area where she made her scrape with planting, she chose not to incubate any
of these eggs and we were obliged to remove them for artificial incubation.
Six chicks were hatched of which four were reared successfully. Other
pheasants bred in 1999 included Malay Crested Fireback L. erythrophthalma
erythrophthalma, Satyr Tragopan Tragopan satyra and Golden Pheasants
Chrysolophus picta. One Blyth's Tragopan T. blythii was hatched from five
fertile eggs but it died shortly after hatching. This repeated the problems we
have had previously with embryo and chick viability in these pheasants and
may perhaps in part be explained by inbreeding depression in this stock.
However, we would be pleased to hear from anybody who has had experience
in improving egg viability through nutritional or incubation management.
Four Common Peafowl Pavo cristatus were reared and although two Green
Peafowl P muticus were hatched neither was reared. Five Roulroul Partridges
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.443424" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266265" page_num="75" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - CHESTER ZOO BIRD REVIEW 1999
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996568" page_id="56266265"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
75
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.992301380952381" page_id="56266265"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
Rollulus roulroul were reared including four that were parent-reared. Two
Red-legged Partridges Alectoris rufa were reared from eggs laid in 'Europe
on the Edge'. Chinese Painted Quail Excalfactoria chinensis hatched but
failed to rear two chicks in the 'Finch Flight'.
As in 1998 we followed the EEP (European Endangered Species Breeding
Programme) Humboldt Penguin Sphenicus humboldti coordinator's request
and bred only from genetically under-represented birds. Four penguin chicks
were hatched of which two were reared successfully. Waldrapp Ibis
Geronticus eremita successfully reared eight chicks. There are now over
700 Waldrapps in zoos and bird gardens in Europe and this is another species
which we now have to actively manage to control breeding in our collections.
How different this situation is to that only 10 years ago when we were hand-
rearing Waldrapp to maintain our breeding colony. In contrast to the now
productive Waldrapps, the Little Egrets Egretta garzetta sharing their
enclosure failed to rear any of the chicks they hatched. The European
Spoonbills Platalea leucorodia, also in 'Europe on the Edge', laid for the
first time. The eggs were left with the parents but although the eggs were
fertile they failed to hatch. Also for the first time at Chester two pairs of
Dalmatian Pelicans P elec anus crispus built nests. One of the female pelicans
laid and incubated an egg but as with the spoonbills this fertile egg failed to
hatch.
Caribbean Flamingos Phoenicopterus ruber ruber bred particularly well
in 1999 with a total of eight birds reared. Chilean Flamingos P. chilensis
laid later in the year and unusually in 1999 with only two chicks reared
were less successful than their Caribbean cousins. From 1990 to the end of
1999 the Chilean Flamingo flock increased in size through breeding from
28 to 48 birds and the Caribbean flock from 40 to 59 birds. Careful egg
management is practised by the flamingo keeping staff. Eggs are removed
as they are laid and replaced with dummy wooden eggs. Because of the loss
of eggs and dummies by being knocked off the nest by other flamingos,
each wooden egg has a thick nail hammered into it so it can be spiked into
the nest. Despite the parents being unable to turn these dummies they are
accepted by them and maintain the birds' incubation behaviour until their
own egg is returned before internal pip. This also permits many other
management options. For example, if their own egg proves to be infertile
the dummy may be removed thereby encouraging the pair to relay or the
fertile egg from another pair may be fostered to them.
The flamingo nests are mapped and regular observations made of
incubating birds so that parentage of all eggs on nests can be recorded. Eggs
are numbered and marked with a pencil. Careful egg and nest records ensure
the parentage of eggs and chicks can be recorded. Shortly after hatching
each chick is pinioned and a web tag attached to the web of skin between
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.979646" page_id="56266266"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
76
</page>
<table confidence="0.9291346" page_id="56266266"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - CHESTER ZOO BIRD REVIEW 1999
Photo Roger Wilkinson
Male Superb Fruit Dove
Photo Roger Wilkinson
Superb Fruit Dove fledgling
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.988076833333333" page_id="56266266"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
the toes. These web tags are numbered so that later in the year when the
young flamingos are caught up for ringing (we use Darvic leg bands above
the 'knee') the ring details can be recorded for each youngster along with
parentage and individual history. Only occasionally are eggs discovered on
the ground between nests for which the parentage cannot be determined.
Waterfowl bred included two Black-necked Swans C. melanocoryphus,
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.61165325">
two Cuban Whistling Ducks Dendrocygna arborea, a Ross's Snow Goose
Anser rossii, 13 Marbled Teal Marmaronetta angustirostris, eight Northern
Shovelers Anas clypeata, three Ferruginous Ducks Aythya nyroca, eight
Carolina Wood Ducks Ah c sponsa, three Mandarin Ducks A. galericulata
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.438148" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266267" page_num="77" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - CHESTER ZOO BIRD REVIEW 1999
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.982377" page_id="56266267"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
77
</page>
<author confidence="0.48816">
Photo Roger Wilkinson
</author>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.514558">
Wrinkled Hornbill
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.87397948" page_id="56266267"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
and three Smew Mergus albellus. However, 1999 was a very disappointing
year for crane breeding with chicks hatched but not reared from Red-crowned
Cranes Grus japonensis and West African Crowned Cranes Balearica
pavonina pavonina.
A Superb Fruit Dove Ptilinopus superbus , a Jambu Fruit Dove P. jambu
and three Golden Heart Pigeons Gallicolumba rufigula were successfully
parent reared. The latter are particular favourites of mine and it was a pleasure
to breed from them. A Pink Pigeon Nesoenas mayeri was foster reared by
Java Doves Streptopelia risoria dom. One Mindanao Bleeding Heart Pigeon
G. criniger was hatched but this was not reared and a Nicobar Pigeon
Caloenas nicobarica which was hand-reared died before it became
independent. Crested Bronzewing Pigeons Ocyphaps lophotes and Common
Bronzewing Pigeons Phaps chalcoptera also hatched chicks and Speckled
Pigeons Columba guinea, Rock Doves C. livia and Diamond Doves Geopelia
cuneata were reared. A Tawny Frogmouth Podargus strigoides was reared
as were two Spectacled Owls Pulsatrix perspicillata, three Snowy Owls
Nyctea scandiaca and a Bam Owl Tyto alba. Because of reduced demand
for Snowy Owls we had planned not to breed this species in 1999. Once
eggs were laid these were removed and replaced by dummies. However the
female laid further eggs adding to the dummy clutch and these went
undetected and hatched.
Highlights in the Parrot Section included the successful parent rearing
of three Mount Apo Lorikeets Trichoglossus johnstoniae, a Yellow-backed
Chattering Lory Lorius garrulus flavopalliatus and a Duyvenbode's Lory
Chalcopsitta duivenbodei. The Greater Vasas Coracopsis vasa laid four
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997226" page_id="56266268"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
78
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.572007" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266268" page_num="78" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - CHESTER ZOO BIRD REVIEW 1999
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998588697674418" page_id="56266268"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
eggs but because of lack of interest in this species from other zoo collections
we removed and discarded two of the four eggs. The remaining two eggs
hatched under the parents and both chicks were reared. Because they are
already well represented with many youngsters in the managed EEP/ESB
populations we decided not to breed the Green-cheeked Amazons Amazona
viridigenalis , Red-fronted Macaws Ara rubrogenys and Blue-eyed Cockatoos
Cacatua opthalmica in 1999. Sadly the Red-fronted Macaws were lost late
in the year following the use of levamisole as a worming agent. I would
strongly caution against the use of this anthelminthic by injection in this
species. A Red-tailed Amazon A. brasiliensis was hatched but failed to
survive and later in the year we were saddened by the death of the breeding
female. A new female bred in 1998 at the Tropical Bird Gardens, Rode, was
located and this has joined the widowed male at Chester as part of the
managed EEP breeding programme. Other parrots bred included three Cuban
Amazons A. leucocephala, one Thick-billed Parrot Rhynchopsitta
pachyrhyncha, three Slender-billed Conures Enicognathus leptorhynchus
and a Golden-capped Conure Aratinga auricapilla.
Chester Zoo had its first success breeding Wrinkled Hombills Aceros
corrugatus in 1995 when a brood of four chicks was successfully parent-
reared. Both parents were confiscated birds received on loan from HM
Customs &amp; Excise in December 1986. They first attempted to breed in
1990 and in 1991, 1992 and 1993 hatched but did not rear chicks. The
success of 1995 was followed by a further successful breeding in 1996 but
on that occasion only one chick was reared. Wrinkled Hornbills are
threatened in the wild and since 1997 have been the subject of an EEP. All
five Wrinkled Hombills were lent to other EEP participants; one female to
Aalborg, Denmark, two females to the Tropical Bird Gardens, Rode, UK,
one female to Upie, France and a male to Paignton, Devon, UK.
In 1997 the Wrinkled Hombill pair again attempted to breed but lost
both youngsters, one of which survived to over nine weeks old. The pair
then made a second nesting attempt but the female emerged from her last
attempt in very poor physical condition and died shortly afterwards from
what the post mortem indicated to be chronic liver disease. Evidence of
haemochromatosis (iron storage disease) was looked for but not found and
the aetiology of the liver disease remains unknown. In December 1998 we
were pleased to receive an adult female on loan from Antwerp Zoo. The
female was quarantined before being introduced to our male. Our male was
extremely attentive trying to feed her immediately but she wanted only to
hide from him and initially appeared very unrelaxed in his company. After
several unsuccessful attempts at introducing these birds the female was again
introduced to the male on February 8th 1999, and only 10 days later was
seen being fed by the male at which time she began mudding-up the nest-
box entrance. She remained in the nest-box from February 1999 and emerged
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.443399" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266269" page_num="79" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - CHESTER ZOO BIRD REVIEW 1999
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997589" page_id="56266269"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
79
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.976600428571429" page_id="56266269"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
110 days later with two strong chicks, a third equally healthy chick fledging
three days later. As with a number of other Asiatic hombills both sexes of
juveniles resemble the male on fledging. With almost twice as many females
as males in the EEP population we hoped that our previous imbalance of
sexes would be reversed but they proved to be two females and one male.
The male has since been transferred to the Tropical Bird Gardens, Rode,
where it is now paired to a female that was bred at Paultons Park, Ower,
Romsey. The two 1999-bred female Wrinkled Hombills have been sent to
Heidelberg Zoo where a group of this species is being assembled to facilitate
natural partner choice in the expectation that this may increase the number
of pairs breeding successfully.
Lilac-breasted Rollers Coracius caudata successfully reared three chicks
in their aviary in the Tropical Realm but the pair of Green Wood Hoopoes
Phoeniculus purpureus made no breeding attempts following the transfer of
their previous year's offspring to Paradise Park, Hayle. Perhaps as co-
operative breeders in the wild the wood hoopoes would have been more
inclined to breed had the family group remained intact. The Laughing
Kookaburras Dacelo novaeguineae reared a single chick and the Blue-winged
Kookaburras D. leachii made their first breeding attempt after six years in
the collection. The female Blue-winged Kookaburra laid a clutch of two
eggs but these proved infertile. Three Violaceous Turacos Musophaga
violaceous , four Schalow's Touracos Tauraco schalowi, a Red-crested
Touraco T. erythrolophus and four White-cheeked Touracos T. leucotis were
bred.
New arrivals were a pair of Magpie Robins Copsychus saularis and two
Pope Cardinals Paroaria dominicana bred at London Zoo. These were
initially housed in the free flight area of the Tropical Realm but the Magpie
Robins proved to be such accomplished escape artists that they are now
confined to barracks in one of the aviaries in this building. Birds bred in the
Tropical Realm in 1999 included Emerald Starling Lamprotomis iris, Scissor-
billed Starling Scissirostrum duhium , White-rumped Shama C. malabaricus ,
Red-billed Leiothrix Leiothrix lutea and Silver-beaked Tanager
Rhamphocelus carbo. Two Bali Starlings Leucopsar rothschildi were hand-
reared. Yellow-throated Laughing Thrushes Garrulax galbanus and Red-
winged Laughing Thrushes G. formosus hatched chicks in the free flight
area of the Tropical Realm but these were left with the parents and none
were reared successfully. Food competition and disturbance in this mixed
species area may have contributed to these nest failures and some chicks
may be taken for hand-rearing in the future.
A total of nearly 200 birds, of 62 species, was reared in 1999.
Dr. Roger Wilkinson is now General Curator: Higher Vertebrates and
Research Co-ordinator at Chester Zoo, Upton, Chester CH2 1LH, England.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.974892" page_id="56266270"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
80
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.928033" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266270" page_num="80" year="" vol="">
WAXBILLS AND THEIR ALLIES:
THE LAVENDER WAXBILL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.909513428571428" page_id="56266270"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
by Ian Hinze
Genus Estrilda - the typical, swee and lavender waxbills
All the species that are thought of as typical or 'true' waxbills are included
in this genus, which is a remarkably homogeneous group. It includes the
Common, Black-rumped and Orange-cheeked Waxbills Estrilda astrild, E.
troglodytes &amp; E. melpoda , which have been imported into Europe for
centuries and those sealing wax-like red bills gave rise to their English name.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.635561">
Lavender Waxbill
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994022857142857" page_id="56266270"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
Most possess finely barred plumage and are endowed with tremendous
agility, being able to feed by clinging to growing grasses, hold their food
under one foot and manipulate nesting material. Their nests tend to be fairly
large structures with a tubular entrance and, usually, a cock-nest on top or
alongside. The swee and lavender waxbills diverge slightly from the norm
in some respects and the latter are believed to be a link between the typical
waxbills and the firefinches Lagonosticta spp.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.444255333333333" page_id="56266270"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
Lavender Waxbill Estrilda caerulescens
Other names; Lavender Finch, Red-tailed Waxbill, Red-tailed Lavender
Waxbill
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.436041" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266271" page_num="81" year="" vol="">
HINZE - LAVENDER WAXBILL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994198" page_id="56266271"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
81
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.37974">
Description
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994125047619048" page_id="56266271"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
Length 10cm (4in). The sexes are alike. The lower back, rump, upper
and under tail-coverts and the central tail feathers are a deep, rich crimson.
There is a short and narrow black eye-line from the gape which tapers to a
point just beyond the dark brown eye. The cheeks, throat and upper breast
are whitish grey. The centre of the belly and lower flanks are sooty grey to
almost black. There are small white spots on the lower flanks. The rest of
the plumage is a most attractive light bluish grey. The tip of the bill is
blackish, as is usually the culmen and lower part of the lower mandible. The
base of the bill, especially at the centre, is bluish grey to dark reddish. The
legs and feet are blackish brown, black or very dark olive. The juvenile's
rump to the base of its tail is a slightly paler, duller crimson and the black
lores are not so well defined. There is also an absence of spots on the lower
flanks.
Field guide
It is a tiny, active bluish grey bird with black lores, and a crimson lower
back, rump and tail.
Distribution
Tropical western Africa in Senegal, Gambia and Guinea-Bissau east
through southern Mali, southern Burkino Faso, northern Ghana, northern
Nigeria, extreme northern Cameroon, north-west Central African Republic
and south-west Chad.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.401522">
Status
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.896463769230769" page_id="56266271"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
Common or locally common.
Introduced distribution
Introduced to the Hawaiian Islands (Hawaii and Oahu) around 1965
(Lever, 1987) and apparently established, but numbers declined by 1980
and it is now considered unlikely to survive (Clement et al. 1993).
Berger reported that this species has been on Oahu since 1965, after
having been deliberately or accidently released. Birds were recorded in the
Kapiolani Park - Diamond Head area from 1966 to 1976, although no
breedings were recorded. In late 1976 or early 1977 it was estimated that
only 30-50 birds made up the entire population. In 1978, Ashman &amp; Pyle
found the bird established on the island of Hawaii, in a small area near the
Puu Waawaa Ranch, and also indicated that it is established on Oahu (all
reports in Long, 1981).
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.988924" page_id="56266272"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
82
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.4234335" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266272" page_num="82" year="" vol="">
HINZE - LAVENDER WAXBILL
Voice
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993040131578947" page_id="56266272"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
The close contact call is a short, shrill, high-pitched 'squee' or 'tsee',
which is lengthened and intensified to ' tseeay ' (Immelmann et al. in Goodwin,
1982), or 'a shrill, explosive squeep' (Harrison in Goodwin, 1982). The
distance or high intensity contact call of the female is a two or three-syllabled
'tseeeht-tseeeht-tseeef , which the male answers with his song phrase - a
two-syllabled ' seeyou ' (Harrison in Goodwin, 1982), the first note high-
pitched and short, the second longer, lower pitched and more melodious.
This seems to be confirmed by Claflin (1994), who bred from 12 out of
approximately 15 pairs, and reports the male emitting a two-note call, first
up and then down, with the female making two or three short calls, each one
sounding the same, and Dodwell (1993), who, while finding the 'distinctive
two-note call' of the male to be one hundred percent reliable, is quick to
stress that birds which do not use this two-note call are not always females;
some males refused to call if they were within sight or sound of other,
presumably dominant, males. Goodwin (1982) gave the nest call as a soft
&apos;tseeteek tseeteek teek teek\
Habitat, feeding and general habits
It is found in semi-arid country with bushes and/or trees and some open
areas, rocky places with mimosa and other shrubs, areas of short grass with
scattered or adjacent bushes or trees, the grass verges of roads and sometimes
gardens and cultivated areas that provide comparable conditions (Goodwin,
1982; Serle et al. 1977). It feeds on the ground but is also more arboreal
than other species (Barlow et al. 1997). It is usually spotted in pairs or
small groups, sometimes with other waxbills and weavers, and with larger
aggregations not uncommon. It is often tame and confiding and has a low,
direct and fairly fast flight compared with other waxbills (Clement et al.
1993; Serle et al. 1977).
Records in the field (Brickell, 1995 pers. com.) revealed seeds, mainly
grasses but also small plant seeds (species unknown) being taken. Some
insects and ripe fruit are also consumed.
Courtship display
The male holds a piece of nesting material in his bill by one end, makes
a triangular head and angles his tail, then bobs up and down like other Estrilda
species. The female responds by giving a greeting or nodding display, i.e.
partly turns towards the male with triangular head, angled tail and the rump
and flank feathers erected, but showing a smooth-looking surface. Both
birds may then perform bowing or nodding movements, heads turning slightly
inwards, sometimes with one bird having its head up while the other's is
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.436475" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266273" page_num="83" year="" vol="">
HINZE - LAVENDER WAXBILL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998785" page_id="56266273"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
83
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9842196" page_id="56266273"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
down and vice-versa. The male usually starts to sing and the female replies
with her contact call. The female then solicits the male with quivering tail.
She may also take the initiative and perform the display with the nesting
symbol herself.
The greeting or nodding display is performed frequently and intensely
by courting or recently paired birds, but only by established pairs if they
have been separated for a short period and then meet up again or if a strange
individual is close by. It therefore appears to be given when the bird's
aggression is aroused but it is inhibited from attacking by sexual attraction.
As Goodwin (1982) pointed out, if two strangers are put together the display
may be interspersed with aggression and fleeing even if the birds are of the
opposite sex. Should they be two males or two females, then it could be
superseded by violent fighting in which the loser may well be seriously hurt
if it cannot escape or be removed in time.
Nesting
Nest building takes place in the second part of the rainy season (Koepff,
1984). The nest itself is an untidy dome-shaped construction of seeding
grassheads. Five nests examined were approximately 20cm (8in) in diameter
and each had an entrance tunnel on one side, about 5 cm (2in) long and
3.5cm (almost lVrin) in diameter, which pointed downwards; three were
sited in the forks of citrus trees and two in exotic shrubs. A clutch of eggs
averages 4-6. Barlow et al. (1997) state it has been recorded breeding in the
Gambia in the mid rainy season, from August to September.
Captive observations
A frequently available species and arguably the most beautiful. A truly
healthy specimen is constantly on the move and extremely captivating.
Freshly imported birds require plenty of warmth, around 77*F (25*C) for
the first few weeks (Koepff, 1984). Although first bred in the UK in 1900,
by Miss R. Alderson (Coles, 1987), for a long time afterwards breedings
were extremely rare in captivity. Now a growing number of aviculturists
have been successful, particularly when pairs have been housed on their
own. Groups of birds kept together outside the breeding season are renowned
for feather plucking and during the breeding season have produced fatalities
due to fighting.
Dodwell (1993) found it was three years before his birds reared young,
and then only after finding compatible pairs that produced fertile eggs. Still,
not all his pairs reared young and a considerable number of clear eggs
continued to be laid. However, of those young that hatched, losses were
negligible. The majority of his birds favoured building their nests in holes
in small hay-bales, although some utilised wicker baskets and others
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995484" page_id="56266274"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
84
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.792038" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266274" page_num="84" year="" vol="">
HINZE - LAVENDER WAXBILL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999156260869565" page_id="56266274"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
constructed their own. Claflin (1994) covered the tops of the, presumably
all-wire, breeding cages with hay and pine branches and the sides with burlap,
afterwhich the cages were misted twice each day to bring the birds into
breeding condition. Thurlow \s (1985) birds built their nests in shrubbery.
Most favoured nesting materials appear to be grass stems and coconut
fibres, with the latter and a few feathers used as a lining. One of Thur low's
(1985) pairs constructed a rather untidy structure with a well concealed
entrance underneath a grassy overhang. The overhang became a small
platform on which the birds placed small pieces of cuttlefish bone and soil.
For the first week after hatching Dodwell (1993) found the nestlings
appeared to be fed almost entirely on livefood. After this period soaked
seed and softfood were taken, with the livefood becoming somewhat reduced.
In addition to the livefood de-frosted frozen bloodworm, an insectivorous
mixture and seeding grasses were also provided. Young birds called quite
loudly when either parent entered the nest. Fledglings spent the first day on
the ground, but normally found a sheltered place in which to roost thereafter.
None of the birds appeared to return to the nests although Koepff (1984)
mentioned that this species roosts in unused nests, including those of other
species. The incubation period is 11-12 days, with the fledging period some
16-20 days after hatching. The parents continue to feed the young for about
14 days after fledging. During the nesting period it is wise not to inspect the
nest as this has resulted in young being abandoned. Thurlow (1985) found
his adult birds enjoyed taking the juice and flesh from slices of ripe pear.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.950705" genericHeader="references" page_id="56266274" page_num="84" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.993688428571428">
Barlow, C. Wacher, T. &amp; Disley, T. 1997. A Field Guide to Birds of The Gambia and Senegal.
Pica Press, Nr. Robertsbridge, East Sussex.
Claflin, L. 1994. Breeding Lavender Waxbills. The NFSS Bulletin 11,6:38-39.
Clement, P., Harris, A. &amp; Davis, J. 1993. Finches and sparrows. Christopher Helm/A. &amp; C.
Black, London.
Coles, D. 1986. First Breeding Records for Birds Reared to Independence under Controlled
Conditions in the UK (with 1995 update). Coles, Berkshire.
Dodwell, J. 1993. The Lavender Waxbill. The Estrildian 2,1:22-24.
Goodwin, D. 1982. Estrildid finches of the world. British Museum (Natural History), London.
Gore, M. E. J. 1990. Birds of The Gambia (2nd revised edition). British Ornithologists' Union,
London.
Jobling, J. A. 1991. A Dictionary of Scientific Bird Names. Oxford University Press, Oxford.
Koepff, C. 1984. The New Finch Handbook. Barron's, New York.
Lever, C. 1987. Naturalized birds of the world. Longmans, London.
Long, J. L. 1981. Introduced birds of the world. Agricultural Produce Board of Western Australia.
Serle, W., Morel, G.J. &amp; Hartwig, W. 1977. A Field Guide to the Birds of West Africa. Collins,
London.
Thurlow, G. 1985. Breeding Lavender Finches. Newsletter of the FBBA Issue 85/4:31-33.
Ian Hinze's main interest is waxbills , and the above comes from a book
he has written on the subject, for which he is hoping to find a publisher. Ian
(E-mail:Calian@tesco.net) lives in Manchester, England.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.995452" page_id="56266275"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
85
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9607" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266275" page_num="85" year="" vol="">
THE NEW PENGUIN DEVELOPMENT AT WHIPSNADE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991308717948718" page_id="56266275"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
by Nick Lindsay
During the winter of 1998-1999 W hipsnade Wild Animal Park completely
redeveloped its penguin enclosure following a successful fund-raising
campaign run by the keeping staff. In some ways the decision to redevelop
the area was a bold one as, although showing the ravages of time, this area
continued to produce breeding successes for all three species - Humboldt
Penguin Spheniscus humboldti , Rockhopper Penguin Eudyptes chrysocome
and King Penguin Aptenodytes patagonica . It was recognised by the keepers
however, that each species has different requirements and the area was really
too small to provide sufficient opportunities for the three. The aim of the
redevelopment, therefore, was to provide a larger area of water and for this
to be of a greater depth (3m (approx. 10ft)) than previously available, to
provide a more challenging land space and to provide a better setting overall
for the birds and visitors. Because of the increasing problem of malaria in
the UK and to keep costs down it was decided to redevelop the existing area
which has as good a natural air conditioning system as one could ask for in
southern England (for those who don't know, it is situated high on the
Dunstable Downs).
The original pool has been maintained with a second pool built adjacent
to this but at a different level The shape of this was very much determined
by the existing landscape and the planning authorities. This extension
allowed the provision of a greater land area in a more exposed site with the
aim of encouraging the penguins to cover more ground and gradients.
Between the two pools a rock mound has been developed with water flowing
down this into each pool. Pumps circulate the water through sand filters
and UV filters before it flows down the waterfalls within which shingle
traps have been incorporated to act as a natural (and additional) filtration
system. Each pool has an independent system so a pump or filtration failure
will affect only one pool and not the other. The land area has been landscaped
using wonderful Welsh slate and granite along with sand, shingle and cobbles.
The area, both Inside and around the outside, has been planted with dwarf
conifers, pampas grass and other tussock grass varieties which amazingly
survived the attention of the penguins during the first year.
Although the penguins were returned to the new area in time for the
1999 breeding season only a few Humboldt Penguins bred. The activity of
all species has Increased tremendously and the Rockhoppers, in particular,
have made use of even the biggest rocks, often each individual claiming a
rock for &apos;itself on which to rest during the day. The King Penguins walk
around the whole area and are quite happy to walk up the waterfalls rather
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.9931" page_id="56266276"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
86
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.823242" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266276" page_num="86" year="" vol="">
LINDSAY - WHIPSNADE ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.951632470588235" page_id="56266276"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
than taking an easier route. All the species use the deeper pools. The sand
areas, and in particular the slate slabs, are very much appreciated by the
penguins and in the summer misters are used in some of these areas to cool
the penguins. The quality of the water has remained good although algal
growth has occurred on the sides of the pools. This year a vacuum cleaning
system is being used to remove this and the pumps are producing a stronger
current in the pools, as well as circulating the water. Fibreglass nest-boxes
have been developed for the Humboldt Penguins. These can be removed
and cleaned at the end of each season.
A completely new information system has been introduced with both
static boards and interactive information disks on all penguin species. The
public viewing areas have been greatly enhanced and although there is no
underwater viewing visitors can see the penguins swimming in both pools.
The setting is probably one of the most spectacular any penguin exhibit can
offer and visitors spend a considerable amount of time in this comer of the
park.
Nick Lindsay is Curator at Whipsnade Wild Animal Park, Dunstable,
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.471572" page_id="56266276"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
Bedfordshire LU6 2LF, England. Tel: 01582 872171/Fax: 01582 872649.
* * *
PLANET PENGUIN
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.982720076923077" page_id="56266276"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
The largest penguin exhibit in the world, Planet Penguin, was opened
last November at Loro Parque, Tenerife, Canary Islands. The spectacular
main exhibit houses 65 King Penguins Aptenodytes patagonicus, 46
Rockhopper Penguins Eudyptes chrysocome, 40 Gentoo Penguins Pygoscelis
papua and two Kelp Gulls Larus dominicanus. Most of the King Penguins
were hatched from eggs collected during the expedition to South Georgia,
described by Roger G. Sweeney in the Avicultural Magazine 104,4:169-
179. From the 117 eggs brought back to Loro Parque, 70 chicks were hatched
of which 51 were reared successfully. The other King Penguins, along with
the Rockhopper and Gentoo Penguins, were bred at Sea World in the USA.
A second exhibit displays 23 Humboldt Penguins Spheniscus humboldti
obtained from Penscynor Wildlife Park (south Wales, UK), which closed in
1998.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998341" page_id="56266277"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
87
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7034335" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266277" page_num="87" year="" vol="">
THE SOCIETY'S VISIT TO WEM
by Stewart Pyper
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.981568684210527" page_id="56266277"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
On Sunday, September 19th last year members of the Society and their
guests visited the collection of birds and mammals belonging to Will Harrison
and his wife Libby. Will, who has been a member of the Society for many
years, with his wife, maintains a large collection of birds ranging from small
passerines such as tanagers up to rheas. About 40 members and their guests
accepted the invitation and the collection was viewed during overcast
weather, with the sun eventually breaking through after a quite horrendous
morning of incessant rain.
There is a tropical house in which viewing the birds was at times difficult
due to the luxurious plant life, however, we managed to see tanagers,
zosterops, Roulroul Partridges and Golden Heart Doves. Within the
traditional walled garden, Chilean Flamingos and Demoiselle Cranes live at
liberty. The aviaries around the inside of the wall are spacious and well
planted, except those in which certain pheasants such as Monals are housed.
Here, we also saw White-cheeked Touracos and Red-winged Starlings both
of which had bred during 1999, also Violaceous Touracos. We also saw
laughing thrushes, Satyr and Temminck's Tragopans, Edwards' and Argus
Pheasants as well as species such as Black-necked Stilts.
A small temperate greenhouse houses Fairy Bluebirds, Emerald Starlings
and Luzon Bleeding Heart Doves, here again the vegetation was ideal for
the birds but not for viewing them. The emphasis is on breeding whenever
possible and with this in mind, the aviaries are not overstocked. Wonga
Pigeons were seen, also a breeding pair of Red-legged Seriema with their
youngsters. Snowy Owls which had bred in 1999 were seen, as were Stanley
Cranes and Sclater's Curassows.
There is quite a large collection of waterfowl amongst which are Red-
breasted Geese and a very aggressive pair of Cereopsis Geese, also White-
winged Wood Ducks. The latter, on loan from the Wildfowl and Wetlands
Trust, are regular breeders. This year, eight out of nine eggs hatched and six
of the young went to the trust's new Wetland Centre at Bam Elms, west
London.
A large paddock in front of the house has recently been enclosed with
fox-proof fencing and it is Will's intention to develop this area. We also
saw a selection of mammals, including Llamas, Red Squirrels, Malaysian
Prevost's Squirrels, Maras, Parma and Bennett's Wallabies, and Capybaras.
Our hosts very kindly provided tea after our tour of the collection, and
the Society thanked them for their kindness in inviting us to view their varied
collection.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997194" page_id="56266278"  page_num="88" year="" vol="">
88
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.981833" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266278" page_num="88" year="" vol="">
COUNCIL MEETING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989617777777778" page_id="56266278"  page_num="88" year="" vol="">
A Council Meeting was held Sunday, 12th March 2000 at Wargrave,
Berkshire.
The following members were present: Miss R. M. Ezra (President), R.
C. J. Sawyer (Vice President), K. J. Lawrence (Chairman), M. Ellis (Hon.
Editor), Mrs L. Gardner, R. E. Oxley, S. Pyper, J. Trollope, Ms R. Wiseman.
The Hon. Editor reported that the next magazine (No.l, 2000) would be
sent out shortly, and that he had enough material for the following magazine
(this issue). Material is needed, however, for future issues. The Hon. Editor
said that he is thinking of using a colour photo of the Bali Starling for the
front cover of the magazine, if he can find a high quality one which is suitable
for the purpose. The cost of publishing the magazine this year is likely to
remain unchanged and there will again be approximately 12 colour photos.
The Society has now purchased a fax machine for the Hon. Editor. The
number is:- +44 (0)1208 812260. He would prefer that it is used for short
communications only, and that full articles continue to be sent by post.
It was decided that the D. H. S. Risdon Award for the best article in the
magazine during the previous year should go to Greg Bockheim and Shannon
Mezzell for The Black Crake Amaurornis flavirostris an Effective
Cooperative Breeder at Disney's Animal Kingdom, Florida, USA (Avicultural
Magazine 105, 1:12-21). Eric Callaghan was awarded the Society's medal
for the first breeding of the Bearded Barbet Lybius dubius in Great Britain
and Ireland.
The Hon. Secretary/Treasurer missed the meeting due to illness, however,
Council Members were of the opinion that the Society is in a sound position
financially. This was confirmed later when the account for 1999 was
circulated to Council Members.
Since the subjects were discussed at the Council Meeting, Avicultural
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.790397111111111">
Society Vice Presidents, C. J. S. Marler and R. C. J. Sawyer, were among
the speakers at Avian 2000, which was supported by the Society, our website
(www.avisoc.co.uk) is up and running and the Society had a stand at The
Festival of Birds held Sunday, May 14th, at Shepton Mallet, and at Exotics
Quest 2000 held Sunday, May 21st, at Bristol Vet School.
The President's Garden Party will be held Sunday, July 16th, and the
Autumn Social Meeting, Sunday, September 17th at Twycross Zoo,
Leicestershire, followed after lunch there by a visit to Andrew and Audrey
Perkins' collection at Netherseal, Nr. Swadlincote, Derbyshire.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.996726" page_id="56266279"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
89
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9800655" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266279" page_num="89" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
THE SOCIETY"S WEBSITE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994407" page_id="56266279"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
The Society has now got a website - http://www.avisoc.co.uk -which we
hope you will visit and encourage others to visit too, who may be interested
in joining the Society.
As well as information about the Avicultural Society, the contents of the
current issue of the magazine, notes for authors and details of how to join
the Society, there is also a list of the contents of recent back issues. Eventually
we hope to list the contents of all the back issues we still have in stock,
however, this is likely to take a little time. We are keen to sell as many back
issues as we can, both to realise the money and because they take up so
much storage space. They are a fantastic source of information and cost just
#3 (roughly US$4.50) each, including post &amp; packing.
There is also a 'bulletin board' on the site, on which you are invited to
post items of interest to others. We have already received postings from the
USA, Canada and elsewhere. It is an especially quick way to promulgate
news of developments, such as your latest breeding results.
I would like include a 'swap shop-cum-marriage bureau' (for birds) -
called the 'nest site' perhaps - where members can list birds they require to
make-up breeding pairs and/or surplus birds others may be looking for to
make-up breeding pairs of their own. All arrangements for any such swaps
and matters arising from these will have to remain the responsibility of the
participants.
The website was designed by Richard Reeves, who would value your
comments. His e-mail address is: reeves@astronode.co.uk. The Society
hopes to shortly set-up its own direct e-mail link with members. It is also
considering accepting advertisements for inclusion on the website.
The Society reserves the right to remove any material posted on the
website that is considered unsuitable for whatever reason.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.599219" page_id="56266279"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.945612" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266279" page_num="89" year="" vol="">
HIGHLY RESPECTED AUTHOR
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.7491114" page_id="56266279"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
Derek Goodwin, the highly respected author of Pigeons and Doves of
the World and Estrildidfinches of the world , as well as numerous articles in
the Avicultural Magazine and other journals, had his 80th birthday earlier
this year and was recently elected an Hon. Life Member of the Avicultural
Society.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.990969" page_id="56266280"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
90
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.802369333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266280" page_num="90" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
JAILED FOR TWO AND A HALF YEARS
At Newcastle Crown Court on April 14th, Harry Sissens was found guilty
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9628041" page_id="56266280"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
of illegally importing into the UK three Lear's Macaws Anodorhynchus leari
and six Blue-headed Macaws Ara couloni. He was jailed for two and a half
years. He was also charged with illegally selling a Palm Cockatoo
Probosciger aterrimus and Hyacinth Macaws A. hyacinthinus , but cleared
of those charges on the orders of the judge. Harry Sissens was arrested after
Customs &amp; Excise officers raided his property in north Yorkshire, in April
1998, and seized more than 140 birds, including the nine macaws. He was
alleged to have bought birds on a number of trips to Yugoslavia and Slovakia
and smuggled them into the UK.
It was reported later that Harry Sissens planned to appeal against the
sentence, and that the Brazilian government has asked for the return of the
Lear's Macaws, and the hope is that they will become part of a controlled
breeding programme.
It was also reported, though less widely, that by November last year, 16
of the birds seized had died. This was reported to include a Red-vented
Cockatoo Cacatua haematuropygia, a Palm Cockatoo P. a. goliathia, Yellow-
tailed Black Cockatoo Calytorhynchus junereus, a Blue-headed Macaw, two
Blue-throated Macaws A. glaucogularis, two Red-fronted Macaws A.
rubrogenys, a Hyacinth Macaw and a Thick-billed Parrot Rhynchopsitta
pachyrhyncha.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.578792" page_id="56266280"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
* * *
FALCON GROUP
Dr Tom Bailey, who with Susan Anderson, wrote about Commonly
Encountered Hatching and Post-hatching Problems in Bustards ( Avicultural
Magazine 105,3:114-126), has sent a copy of Falco The Newsletter of the
Middle East Falcon Research Group, which he co-edits with Dr Nigel Barton.
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.970724181818182" page_id="56266280"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
Issue No. 15, January 2000, includes items about a new falcon hospital opened
by the National Avian Research Center in Abu Dhabi, trichinellosis in raptors
in the United Arab Emirates, veterinary aspects of a new falcon release
project, and falcon sales in Quatar.
The Middle East Falcon Research Group (PO. Box 45553, Abu Dhabi,
UAE) has also published Microchips and their use in Monitoring Movements
of Sakers and Peregrines in Asia and the Middle East, and is planning to
produce a short video of this microchipping scheme which will be distributed
to government departments in the exporting countries, CITES, IUCN,
TRAFFIC, environmental agencies in the countries of export and falcon
hospitals in the Middle East.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700019" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266281" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.985128" page_id="56266281"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
91
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.994017" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266281" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
ISLANDS OF HOPE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.960169733333334" page_id="56266281"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
On the Indonesian island of Seram, Project Bird Watch is helping bird
trappers find alternative means of income that will eliminate their dependence
on the trade in Moluccan Cockatoos Cacatua moluccensis and other wild
birds. A canopy platform has been built in Manusela National Park and
former bird trappers work there as guides, and admission fees go into a
local community development fund. To learn more about this, you can write
to Project Bird Watch, c/o Jeannie White, 345 Culver Blvd., Playa del Rey,
CA 90293, USA, or visit its website at www.tpp.org/pbw.
Described in Wildlife Conservation, April 2000, as 'the first new national
park of the new millennium', Morne Diablotin National Park on the
Caribbean island of Dominica, straddles the highest volcanic peak in the
Caribbean and will offer protection to two rare species, the Imperial Amazon
Amazona imperialis, of which fewer than 200 survive in the wild, and the
Red-necked Amazon A. arausiaca. The 10,000 acres (approx.4,000 hectares)
national park will afford protection to about 160 species of birds in all and
55 species of butterflies. If you would like to know more, you can write to
the Rare Species Conservatory Foundation, PO. Box 1371, Loxahatchee,
Florida 33470, USA, or visit its website at www.rarespecies.org.
You can also learn more about these two rare Amazons by reading Paul
R. Reillo's article about them in the latest issue of PsittaScene, Vol.12, No.l,
2000. In the same issue, the Editor, Rosemary Low, writes about the
discovery in Colombia of a third flock of 20 Yellow-eared Parrots or Conures
Ognorhynchus icterotis. This has brought the total of known individuals to
82 birds. Elsewhere in the same issue, Rosemary attacks the New Zealand
Department of Conservation's decision to attempt to eradicate by trapping
and killing (by breaking their necks or lethal injections), and by poisoning
and shooting, the feral population of Rainbow Lorikeets Trichoglossus
haematodus moluccanus that has become established in the Auckland area.
For those who do not know, PsittaScene is the magazine of the World Parrot
Trust, Glanmor House, Hayle, Cornwall TR27 4HP, England.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.242224" page_id="56266281"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.400446" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266281" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
VICE PRESIDENT RETIRES
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.829458285714286">
Avicultural Society Vice President, Christopher Marler, has closed
Flamingo Gardens and Zoological Park to the public after 42 years. He has
sold many of the birds, keeping only about 100, including flamingos, pelicans,
Bald Eagles Haliaeetus leucocephalus and lutino Ring-necked Parrakeets
Psittacula krameri. Christopher has also retained a 40-strong herd of white
Fallow Deer, his white wallabies and a pair of American Bison. He will
continue to be a Vice President of the Avicultural Society.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.994364" page_id="56266282"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
92
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.973662" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266282" page_num="92" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
WATERFOWL SALE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.984675" page_id="56266282"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
Bill Makins has put 220 acre (approx. 90 hectare) Pensthorpe Waterfowl
Park and Nature Reserve up for sale. The park, opened in 1988, has more
than 120 species of ducks, geese, swans and other waterbirds. The collection
includes King Eiders Somateria spectabilis, Harlequin Ducks Histrionicus
histrionicus, African Pygmy Geese Netta auritus and Red-breasted Geese
Branta ruficollis. Offers of more than #2.6 million (approx.US$4.1 million)
are being sought for the estate near Fakenham, four miles (6.4km) from the
north Norfolk coast, which as well as the waterfowl park and nature reserve,
includes meadows, lakes, woodland and farmland with four sites of scientific
interest, Pensthorpe Hall and three cottages.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.861461" page_id="56266282"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.804111" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266282" page_num="92" year="" vol="">
LOST BIRDS REDISCOVERED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.881846818181818" page_id="56266282"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
In a recent issue of The Shield magazine, members of five expeditions
reported on their experiences participating in the BP Conservation
Programme, a joint initiative between BP Amoco, BirdLife International
and Fauna &amp; Flora International. Jon Riley described how after searching
for six months, Action Sampiri rediscovered the Caerulean Paradise-
Flycatcher Eutrichomyias rowleyi, over 120 years after it was last seen on
the tiny Indonesian island of Sangihe, between Sulawesi and the Philippines.
Julia Jones described Project Diadema's expedition to New Caledonia, home
of the Kagu Rhynochetos jubatus, where members of the expedition
rediscovered the Owlet Nightjar Aegotheles savesi, which had not been seen
since it was discovered at the end of the nineteenth century.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.425399" page_id="56266282"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.633309" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266282" page_num="92" year="" vol="">
SIR PETER SCOTT'S LEGACY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.765827285714286" page_id="56266282"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
On the site of some redundant Victorian reservoirs beside the River
Thames in west London, on May 26th, The Wildfowl and Wetlands Trust
opened The Wetland Centre (website www.wwt.org.uk). Easily reached
from central London by public transport, it has a collection of captive
waterfowl, including Madagascar Teal Anas bernieri, New Zealand Blue
Duck Hymenolaimus malacorhynchos and Hawaiian Goose or Nene Branta
sandvicensis, and attracts wild species such as Shoveler A. clypeata, Pochard
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.750099">
Aythya ferina, Canada Goose B. canadensis. Lapwing Vanellus vanellus,
Kingfisher Alcedo atthis. Little Egret Egretta garzetta, and even Spoonbill
Platalea leucorodia and Ortolan Bunting Emberiza hortulana.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.699966" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266283" page_num="93" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.989268" page_id="56266283"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
93
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.97655" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266283" page_num="93" year="" vol="">
STEPPING DOWN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991554" page_id="56266283"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
Mike Reynolds, founder and Hon. Director of the World Parrot Trust, is
to stand down at the end of this year. Mike will be 70 in February next year,
and after more than a decade in charge, wants to make way for a new Director.
He has already handed over the running of Paradise Park, at Hayle, Cornwall,
to his son Nick and daugther Alison.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.836219" page_id="56266283"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.506143" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266283" page_num="93" year="" vol="">
BACKATTHE SHOW
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.975059" page_id="56266283"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
The Society again had a stand at the National Exhibition of Cage &amp;
Aviary Birds, held last December at the Telford International Centre. It
enables Officers of the Society to meet members both old and new, and to
publicise the Society. The stand, managed by Council Member Mike Curzon,
a Director of the Tropical Bird Gardens at Rode, Somerset, was somewhat
'tucked away' this time and as a result we were not as successful in enrolling
new members as in previous years.
The sunbird class was judged by Raymond Sawyer, who gave the first
prize to Mr &amp; Mrs A. Tugman's male Amethyst Sunbird Nectarinia
amethystina. This bird went on to be judged best nectar feeder, best foreign
bird and best bird in show, winning the Sir Richard Haddon Trophy.
This year's show is returning to the NEC in Birmingham on the weekend
of December 2nd 3rd. At the time of writing, it is yet to be confirmed
whether the Society will be offered a stand at the show. If as we hope, we
are, will anyone willing to help ran it contact Stewart Pyper at the address
given on the inside of the front cover of this magazine, or by telephoning
him on 01373 836293.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.4393355" page_id="56266283"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
* * *
PRIVATE EYE
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.922528" page_id="56266283"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
If you would like to keep a closer watch on what is (or is not) happening
in your nest-boxes and/or aviaries, PRO-CAM Ltd., John St. Works,
Brierfield, Nelson, Lancs. BB9 5NX (Tel:01282 697779/Fax:Q1282 698677/
E-mail:john@procamltd.com/website:www.procamltd.com), can supply
waterproof and dustproof, infra-red cameras specially designed for placing
in nest-boxes, as well as a comprehensive range other equipment suitable
for observation and security purposes.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998144" page_id="56266284"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
94
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.980009" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266284" page_num="94" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
CURL-CRESTED ARACARI BRED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.92758475" page_id="56266284"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
The Zoological Society of San Diego, 1999 Physical Inventory , has on
the front cover a colour photo of a Curl-crested Aracari Pteroglossus
beauharnaesii nestling hatched at San Diego last year. Other species hatched
there during 1999 included a Harpy Eagle Harpia harpyja, a Crowned Eagle
Stephanoaetus coronatus, a White-faced Pigeon Turacoena manadensis, a
Western Green-naped Pheasant Pigeon Otidiphaps nobilis nobilis, two
Superb Birds of Paradise Lophorina superba feminina and 10 Empress of
Germany's Birds of Paradise Paradisaea raggiana augustaevictoria.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.812236" page_id="56266284"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.883593" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266284" page_num="94" year="" vol="">
SOUTH AFRICAN PARRAKEETS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.945301555555556" page_id="56266284"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
The latest Newsletter of BirdLife South Africa, Vol.2, No. 1,2000, includes
references to several sightings of Ring-necked or Rose-ringed Parrakeets
Psittacula krameri. While Ron Searle describes passing a pair of large
parrakeets perched on telephone wires when driving north of Midrand, and
reversing to confirm that they were Ring-necked Parrakeets (which have
colonised the northern suburbs of Greater Johannesburg, but have not yet
been recorded in the Midrand area), only to discover that the birds were a
pair of Patagonian Conures or Burrowing Parrakeets Cyanoliseus patagonus.
You can visit the BirdLife South Africa website at http://www.birdlife.org.za.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.402001" page_id="56266284"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.541366" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266284" page_num="94" year="" vol="">
A POSSIBLE EXPLANATION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99535875" page_id="56266284"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
A possible explanation as to the origin of the two parrakeets perched on
the telephone wires mentioned in the previous item (above), may have come
recently in another news item published elsewhere about the opening of
Lory Park, described as: 'a new zoo dedicated to parrots and other birds,
located in Midrand.' It is claimed to be the largest bird zoo in Africa, and a
sanctuary and breeding centre for parrots, including macaws, Amazons,
cockatoos, lories and African species. It also aims to be an educational
venue for school children, the general public and bird enthusiasts.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99324" page_id="56266285"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
95
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.617664" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266285" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
DONATIONS RECEIVED IN 1999
</sectionHeader>
<construct confidence="0.825291076923077" page_id="56266285"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
The Society is most grateful to the following members for their generous
support:
D. R. Bayliss
Dr N. S. Bourne
R. A. Callaghan
Prof. J. R. Hodges
A. W. Gibbard
I. T. Forbes
M. E. Fidler
Mrs W. Duggan
K. W. Dolton
N. R. H. Dodds
R. F. d'Erlanger
</construct>
<listItem confidence="0.81687125" page_id="56266285"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
S. Dance
J. J. Mallet
N. O'Connor
J. R. Padgett
A. Perkins
P. J. Pheby
A. J. Pittman
D. P. Shearing
J. G. Thurlow
J. Trollope
J. K. Watson
J. W. W. Louwman
</listItem>
<table confidence="0.366244714285714" page_id="56266285"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
Dr H. Quinque
H. Kapyla
W. Iselt
Ms J. L. Pappas
R. L. Restall
Miss R. M. Ezra
R. C. J. Sawyer
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.841575" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56266285" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
DULCIE COOKE AWARD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993669357142857" page_id="56266285"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
Ken Ashken, the son of the late Dulcie Cooke, who was an enthusiastic
supporter of the Society and attended many social events and wrote for the
magazine, and whose Obituary was published in Vol.104, No.3, pp.143-
144, has generously given the Society a sum of money to create the Dulcie
Cooke Award in his late mother's memory. The Council has decided that
this award, in the form of an engraved plaque, will be awarded annually for
what in the Council's opinion is the best photo submitted to illustrate an
article in the magazine.
Mrs June Bailey has donated to the Avicultural Society on behalf of the
late Dulcinea Rogers, also known as Mrs Dulcie Cooke, and on behalf of
the late Mr Freddie Cooke, the royalties from their books about bird keeping
which were given to her.
The Society thanks Mrs J. Bailey and Mr K. R. Ashken for their
generosity.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996435" page_id="56266286"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
96
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.676426" page_id="56266286"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
T'ojy of the T *ree TeecCs ( f/ t As
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.394412">
Double Dutch
</subsectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.790776" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266286" page_num="96" year="" vol="">
PROFESSIONALS FOR THE SERIOUS AVICULTURIST.
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.945739258064516" page_id="56266286"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
offering Witte Molen, Voskes, Versele, Aves, Kasper ; Orlux &amp; Zupreem.
PARROTs - Parrot Premium "2000". Breeders Pulses. Parrot Grande.
Nutribird &amp; Zupreem pellets. Monkey Chow. Nutribird Handfeeds.
NECTARS - from Aves - Lorinectar. Sunhum ( Sunbirds &amp; Hummers),
Avesnectar ( White Eyes, Tanagers etc.).
FOREIGN FINCH - Witte Molen Australian Premium; Voskes Waxbill
&amp; Australian De Lux; Bullfinch/Rosefinch; Greenfinch/Hawfinch; Siskin;
Hooded Siskin; Bushwacker- Crossbill/Grosbeak, Savannah, Finch Soak.
SOFTBILL - Witte Molen Universal; Insect Diets, Exotica &amp; Pellets.
TOUCAN/TOURACO- Witte Molen Fruit; Versele Pellets. ZuLife Gel.
CRANE - OSTRICH - RHEA/CASSOWARY breeder &amp; maint.
SEA DUCK - FLOATING DUCK - FLAMINGO including floating.
MYNAH - PHEASANT - TRAGOPAN - TURTLE DOVE etc. etc.
INSECTS - Gammerus Shrimp; Concha; Fly Pupae; Crayfish, Ants Eggs,
Mexican Flying Larvae. Artie Krill, Daphnia. Even FROZEN FISH
NUTS &amp; FRUITS - WEST AFRICAN (not North African) Palm Nuts,
Macademias in shell, Raisins &amp; Apricots etc, Mixed and single nuts.
BERRIES - Mountain Ash, Hawthorn Juniper, Rose Hips, Saw Palmeto
STRAIGHTS - every one you could wish for. Include. Aniseed, Chicory,
Evening Primose. Fennel, Kelp, Millets, Panicum, Pollen, Pine Seeds, Pine
Nuts, Plantain, Pumpkin, Safflower, Sunflowers &amp; kemals, Teazle, Wild Seeds
AVES ADDITIVIES - Probiotic; AvesCARN- "25" Vits, Pssitamix:; Stress,
[for your birds long term health, we only sell products- mixes, handfeeds &amp;
additives from the E.C. and USA.- never the Third World and all, carry
ACTUAL ingredient % figures not just meaningless Mins, or Maxs.]
MAIL ORDER - 24 HOUR SERVICE - ALL CREDIT CARDS.
NOBODY SELLS WITTE MOLEN or ORLUX/PRESTIGE or AVES B. V
MAIL ORDER CHEAPER and THATS A FACT Now in our 9th year,
send for a comprehensive list - the biggest range of mixtures in the UK
Pheasants Nest Farm, Smorrall Lane, Bedworth, Warwickshire CV12 ONL
Tel 01676 540608 Fax: 01676 540408
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990761" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266287" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ROB GHARVEY SPECIALIST FEEDS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985736" page_id="56266287"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
We supply over 30 zoos with our range of top quality feeds.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.741641105263158" page_id="56266287"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Witte Molens famous PARROT PREMIUM (not a cheap copy) 15kg for #19.75, or 30kg for only #35.00
Witte Molen- Moist Eggfood -
Witte Molen- Hedgerow Eggfood -
Witte Molen- Universal Food -
Witte Molen- Low Iron for Touracos &amp; Toucans
Witte Molen- Eggfood Red -
Witte Molen- Low iron softfood with insects -
#14.25 5kg tub
#15.50 5kg tub
#14.25 5kg tub
#16.25 5kg tub WITTE
#15.50 5kg tub
#19 oo 3.5kg tub Main Distributor
-4r
TE 1-f MOLEN
We also sell a massive range of top quality clean seeds &amp; berries from Witte Molen such as:-
Mountain Ash, Juniper, Sesame, Pine seeds, Plantain, Perillas, Black Lettuce, Teasel, Hemp ,
Chicory, Milk Thistle, Siskin mix, Wild Seeds, Weed Seeds, Soakseed, British Finch Premium,
Canary Premium and many more.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.922118" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266287" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVI-PLUS PARROT HANDREARING FOOD used to raise
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994063333333333" page_id="56266287"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
over 10,000 parrots in South Africa last year - #6.95 kg.
Plus new formula with probiotics &amp;
spirulina for delicate chicks #6.95 kg
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.959667133333333" page_id="56266287"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avi-plus Lorikeet Special - used by many zoos - #5.95 kg
AVI-SUP SOLUBLE MULTIVITAMINS # 3.60 lOOg
AVI-STRESS #3.92 lOOg
AVI- SUPTWINPACK
MULTIVITAMINS &amp; MINERALS #4.35 200g
AVI-MED SAFE SPROUT #2.78 250g
HEMP ROPE
As used in zoos and bird parks.
Hang these ropes in your parrot
cage or aviary and give your
parrot hours of fun.
36mm #6.99 per metre
10m for #55!
24mm #3.45 per metre
10m for #27!
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.205202" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266287" page_num="" year="" vol="">
VETARK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.426122" page_id="56266287"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
We sell the whole range
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.799616375" page_id="56266287"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Post &amp; Packing
upto 30kg
only #3.95
Visit our website
&amp; advertise your
surplus stock
FREE
www.robharvey.com
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.932292" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266287" page_num="" year="" vol="">
INCUBATION COURSES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.979960166666667" page_id="56266287"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Rob Harvey will be running
one day incubation courses
in the next two months
which cover all aspects of
incubation. The cost of #75
includes lunch, a copy of
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.595608384615385">
Practical Incubation (rrp
#12.95) and various samples
and literature.
Please enquire for next
available date (Saturdays).
Mail order on all products.
For our price list or if you just want some advice please
contact Rob Harvey (ex-owner &amp; curator of Bird world
for over 20 years)
E-mail: admin@robharvey.com Tel: 01420 23986 Fax: 01420 23078
Rob Harvey, Kookaburra House, Gravel Hill Road, Holt Pound,
Farnham, Surrey, GU10 4LG. Vat No. 709 3341 43
Export &amp;Trade Enquiries Welcome
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.987771" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266288" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION LIBRARIES
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.915327916666667" page_id="56266288"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
3 9088 01769 6386
Ecuadorian Birds: Nesting Records and Egg Descriptions
from a Lowland Rainforest
by Ryan L. Hill and Harold F. Greeney.49
Watching Bali Starlings at Jersey Zoo
by Trace Williams..54
The Unique Fishing Techniques and Nest Building Behaviour of
Captive Hammerkops Scopus umbretta
by Greg Bockheim.56
Breeding the African Jagana Actophilornis africanus
at Disney's Animal Kingdom
by Susan Congdon and Bill Zima.62
Chester Zoo Bird Review 1999
by Roger Wilkinson.74
Waxbills and their Allies: The Lavender Waxbill
by Ian Hinze.80
The New Penguin Development at Whipsnade
by Nick Lindsay.85
The Society's Visit to Wem
by Stewart Pyper.87
Council Meeting.88
News &amp; Views.89
Published by the Avicultuml Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</table>
</algorithms>
