<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.964074428571429" page_id="56257292"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
GlU
,A H5T
7 Wicultural
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 118
No.l
2012
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990762" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257293" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.96126375" page_id="56257293"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2012: British Isles £21.00:
Overseas £24.00 (plus £6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the
Society later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of
the AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.701188333333333" page_id="56257293"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, SHERATON LODGE, STATION ROAD, SOUTHMINSTER,
ESSEX CM0 7EW, UK.
</construct>
<bodyText confidence="0.91745" page_id="56257293"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to&amp;apos; The Avicultural
Society Account, Barclays Bank, Southminster Branch. Please quote
Account No. 13296954, Sort Code 20 54 30, and ensure you send your
name as the account reference, or else we cannot match payments. In case
of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and Treasurer at the address
above, or e-mail: otusscops@talktalk.net
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have not
been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of a
particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history. Articles
should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the scientific
names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given. References
cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line drawings,
black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular point in
the article will be used where possible and should be clearly captioned. If
authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when submitting the
article and write their name on the back of each photograph. Tables and
graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be aware of
the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of the page
which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997594" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56257293" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982475333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.873104" genericHeader="method" page_id="56257294" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.88486" page_id="56257294"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 118-No. 1 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2012
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.866052666666667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56257294" page_num="" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE BUFF-NECKED IBIS Theristicus caudatus
AT BLACKBROOK ZOOLOGICAL PARK
by Nicola Sumbland
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.988509285714286" page_id="56257294"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Here at Blackbrook Zoological Park in Staffordshire we currently house
11 of the 27 species of ibis belonging to the family Threskiomithidae. Among
the species housed here is the Buff-necked Ibis Theristicus caudatus, which
is a particular favourite of mine. There are only about 20 remaining in
captivity and we believe we are the only zoo in the world currently housing
this species and are the first to have bred it. (See Editor’s Note at the end
of the article.)
The Buff-necked Ibis is widely distributed in South America, where it
forages in wet grasslands, marshlands, flooded agricultural fields, swamps
and along the banks of lakes and streams, feeding on small aquatic animals
such as fish, frogs and shrimps.
Identification
The Buff-necked Ibis is often wrongly identified and frequently mistaken
for the similar looking Black-faced Ibis I melanopus. However, when
you have both species alongside each other in captivity, as we have here at
Blackbrook Zoological Park, the two species can easily be distinguished
from each other.
The Buff-necked species can be identified by the following:
It has an area of white on the wings (see photo p.2).
The crown is a huffish-tan or rufous-buff colour, so too is the lower chest
(the Black-faced Ibis has a grey band across the lower chest).
It does not have a lobe beneath the chin, just a tight piece of black
skin.
The eyes are bright red with a black pupil
It can be sexed quite easily, as the male is taller and has a longer beak
than the female.
Our adult pair of Buff-necked Ibis was one of the first ever bred in
captivity. The two birds were hatched in May 2007 and were hand-reared
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.90027" page_id="56257295"  page_num="2" year="" vol="">
2
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.729497" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257295" page_num="2" year="" vol="">
SUMBLAND - BUFF-NECKED IBIS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.966879142857143" page_id="56257295"  page_num="2" year="" vol="">
Blackbrook’s breeding pair of Buff-necked Ibis.
Jo Jo showing the coloration of the underparts.
by members of Ibisring (website: www. ibisring. org). They would have been
only four to five months of age when Blackbrook bought them from a dealer
in October 2007.
Since being at Blackbrook the birds have been made comfortable in a
large enclosure which gives the pair plenty of outdoor space and has a large
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.469184" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257296" page_num="3" year="" vol="">
SUMBLAND - BUFF-NECKED IBIS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.944328" page_id="56257296"  page_num="3" year="" vol="">
3
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999622304347826" page_id="56257296"  page_num="3" year="" vol="">
The author with a young ibis.
pond for wading in. The birds also have access to a shed, which is always
left open, so that they can come and go as they please. There are two nesting
platforms built outside around the posts supporting the netting covering the
roof. These are approximately 10ft (3m) above the ground, one above the
pond and the other just above dry land. The ibis share the enclosure with a
pair of Purple Gallinules or Swamphens Porphyria porphyrio, which being
a ground nesting species, does not compete with the ibis for either of the
nesting platforms.
Early in April 2011 we found an ibis egg on the ground below one of the
nesting platforms, which we took to be an indication that the ibis had reached
breeding age. The egg was placed back in the nest, but was found on the
ground again the following day. We inspected the nest and decided that due to
the pair’s inexperience, the nest was inadequate and that the pair needed our
help to build a better nest. Although we knew the egg would not hatch, we
decided to leave it with the pair in the hope that it would encourage nesting
behaviour. After sitting on the nest for just over a week, the ibis came off
the nest that morning and showed no sign of returning. Late that afternoon
we took the decision to remove the egg. On closer inspection of the nest,
however, we discovered a further two eggs, making a clutch of three. No
longer confident that the the pair would hatch the eggs and rear the chicks,
we decided to remove the eggs and artificially incubate them and, if they
hatched, hand-rear the chicks.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.90264" page_id="56257297"  page_num="4" year="" vol="">
4
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.6247875">
SUMBLAND - BUFF-NECKED IBIS
Fig. 1. The growth rates of the two hand-reared chicks.
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.99903075" page_id="56257297"  page_num="4" year="" vol="">
We carefully cleaned the eggs and upon candling them discovered that
the two later eggs appeared to be fertile. These were placed on a rack in an
automated incubator which rotated the eggs every hour. The incubator was
set at a constant temperature of 37.5°C (99.5°F) and the humidity was not
allowed to drop below 50%. The eggs were inspected twice a day for any
signs of development. As we were not sure when the eggs had been laid,
we were unsure when they were likely to pip.
The first chick hatched after approximately 23 days of first being
incubated by the parents and then in the incubator. The chick, which we
named Billie, weighed 48g 24 hours after hatching. It was then taken out of
the hatcher and placed in a small tub lined with paper towelling to cushion
it and placed in a brooder set at 37.5°C (99.5°F) and 65% humidity. On
day one the chick was given small amounts of food every two hours from
8.30am-11.30pm (23.30hrs). The chick was fed using a syringe fitted with
a small silicone tube to ensure that the food did not enter the trachea.
By day two the chick was eating 3ml-5ml of formula every two hours,
and sometimes demanded more. Twigs were provided to act as a nest for
the chick to sit on and ensure that its legs and feet developed properly. Day
by day the routine gradually evolved as the chick demanded more food. By
day five it was eating 17ml-30ml of formula, but at longer intervals. The
chick weighed a healthy 116g.
The second chick hatched exactly seven days after the first chick hatched.
The second chick, which we named JoJo, weighed 40g, 24 hours after
hatching. It was placed in the brooder with the first chick and, except for
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.481446" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257298" page_num="5" year="" vol="">
SUMBLAND - BUFF-NECKED IBIS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.905661" page_id="56257298"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
5
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9958574" page_id="56257298"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
some slight changes, we followed the the same hand-rearing routine.
By the time that the first chick, Billie, had reached 12 days old, she was
eating small pieces of stint (small freshwater fish), as well as the formula.
She was placed in a separate brooder and over a period of 12 days the
temperature was gradually reduced to 25°C (41 °F). Once this was achieved
she was moved to a container full of twigs and with a heat lamp above. By
day 16 she was eating a mixture of the formula, whole stint and pinkie mice.
It was the last day that she received the formula. She weighed 721 g. On day
21 she was able to pick up food on her own from a bowl. From then on I fed
her only small amounts of food, leaving her slightly hungry to encourage
her to feed herself. After a few days she no longer needed to be hand-fed
and, therefore, on day 24 she was moved to an indoor aviary, which had
perches and heat. Other foods were slowly introduced, including rat pups,
chopped sprats and chopped, deyolked skinned chicks, until eventually she
was eating whole sprats and chopped chicks.
When the second chick, JoJo, was able to pick up her own food, she was
reintroduced to Billie. When the two young ibises reached approximately
1,150g the heat bulb was removed and a few days later they were introduced
into their new outdoor pen, which has an indoor shed and plenty of
perching.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.856715" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56257298" page_num="5" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989254466666667" page_id="56257298"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
I would like to say a massive thank you to Mark Rubery for giving me
the opportunity to work with such wonderful birds and for trusting me to
hand-rear the two chicks. I also wish to thank Nicole Rowley for helping
me with the night feeds.
Nicola Sumbland is a 23 year old keeper at Blackbrook Zoological
Park , Winkhill, near Leek, Staffordshire ST 13 7QR, UK. Website:www.
blackbrookzoo. co. uk
The First Breeding Records For Birds Reared To Independence Under
Controlled Conditions In The United Kingdom compiled by Dave Coles
(1986), states that the Buff-necked Ibis was first bred in the UK at Bird land
in 1982. However, no breeding account was published. 1 have also found
records of one bred in 1991 (collection unnamed) and two bred in 1992
(collection or collections unnamed). It is suggested that these birds were
Black-faced Ibis which had been wrongly identified. It is probably too late
now to resolve this matter one way or the other. - Ed.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.96592" page_id="56257299"  page_num="6" year="" vol="">
6
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9822105" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257299" page_num="6" year="" vol="">
DIETARY CONSIDERATIONS WHEN BREEDING
MONTEZUMA QUAIL Cyrtonyx montezumae
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.963488625" page_id="56257299"  page_num="6" year="" vol="">
by Jack Eitniear and Terry Becherer
Most North American quail (Odontophoridae) are easily bred in
captivity, some even at commercial facilities. Two exceptions, however,
are the Mountain Quail Oreortyxpictus and the Montezuma Quail Cyrtonyx
montezumae. This article describes our experiences with the Montezuma
Quail.
J. C. Eitniear
Adult male Montezuma Quail.
Our project began with the desire to produce enough quail to begin a
soft release programme in the Texas Hill Country, from which the species
was extirpated decades ago. After consulting with several aviculturists who
housed Montezuma Quail, we discovered that the species was not doing
well in captivity. Most of those who had a desire to breed this species,
consulted Upland Game Birds: their breeding and care by Hayes (1996) for
their general husbandry guidelines. According to Hayes and individuals we
consulted, first year pairs do not breed well. Furthermore, overall fertility
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.357127" page_id="56257300"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
EITNIEAR &amp; BECHERER - MONTEZUMA QUAIL
</equation>
<page confidence="0.991551" page_id="56257300"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
7
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.496784" page_id="56257300"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
J. C. Eitniear
Front view of the Montezuma Quail enclosure, showing potted plant and feeding and
nesting compartments at the rear.
J. C. Eitniear
Rear view of suspended enclosure. The nesting compartment is on the right and the
feeding area is on the left.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.471164" page_id="56257301"  page_num="8" year="" vol="">
EITNIEAR &amp; BECHERER - MONTEZUMA QUAIL
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.996978975609756" page_id="56257301"  page_num="8" year="" vol="">
was low at all ages, and their offspring were often skewed towards male
birds. Members of the Yahoo Neotropical Quail Captive Management Group
(http://pets.groups.yahoo.com/group/Neotrop-Quail) reported fewer than
five young per pair in 2008. With hopes of increasing the number produced,
we initially devoted our efforts to enhancing the diet and searching for
additional bloodlines.
The Montezuma Quail is principally a native of the grassy pine-oak
woodlands of Mexico, though the northern periphery of its range extends
into parts of Texas, Arizona and New Mexico in the USA. Montezuma
Quail lay six to 12 unmarked white eggs in a domed nest, generally during
the rainy season (late-April-late-September). The domed nest is thought to
offer protection from rain. Nests of this nature are also constructed by other
forest quail, such as those of the genus Dendrortyx.
In the wild, the diet of the Montezuma Quail consists of bulbs of Rusby’s
Flatsedge Cyperus rustbyi (sphaerolepis ) and Broadleaf Woodsorrell Oxalis
amphofolia (drummundii ), along with acorns Quercus sp., the seeds of
grasses such as Thin Paspalum Paspalum stramineum ( setaeum ) and the
flowers of manzanitas Arctostaphylos spp. Given that often there is a lack
of standing water within the quail’s habitat, plant bulbs (e.g. Oxalis spp.)
which are rich in moisture, likely meet the quail’s needs. Field studies have
shown an increase in the amount of insects in the diet during July. This not
only corresponds with the normal increase in insects after rain but also with
the increased need for protein during egg laying and for chick growth. The
only significant difference between the diet of the Montezuma Quail and
other (commonly bred) grassland quail is that the diet of the Montezuma
Quail includes acorns and plant bulbs. An analysis of bulbs of Oxalis alpino
concluded that they are an important source of energy with low quality protein
(6.82% fat, 6.92% protein). These bulbs provide moisture and calories
needed by the quail in order to survive the winter. A nutritional analysis of
acorns shows that they are high in fats (31 %) and carbohydrates (54%) and
low in protein (8%). Although the quail do not feed on acorns throughout
the year, they are considered to be a significant component of the diet (40%)
from April-September. During the breeding season the highest components
of the diet are acorns and insects. The nutritional value of insects varies
depending on their developmental stage. In general, however, insects range
from 40%-60% protein and 4%-55% fat. Additional dietary components
provide a number of vitamins and minerals. A typical gamebird diet,
however, (e.g. Mazuri™ Exotic Gamebird Breeder) fed during the breeding
season contains 20% protein and 2.5% fat. To more closely resemble the
wild diet, we felt that some modification to the captive diet was warranted
and decided that the diet would benefit from added protein and fat.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.360188" page_id="56257302"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
EITNIEAR &amp; BECHERER - MONTEZUMA QUAIL
</equation>
<page confidence="0.936354" page_id="56257302"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
9
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.489729">
Feeding trials
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986920333333333" page_id="56257302"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
From 2009-2011 we maintained three to nine pairs of adult Montezuma
Quail in suspended 1m x lm x 2m (approx. 3ft 9in x 3ft 9in x 6ft 6in)
enclosures with feeding and nesting compartments at the rear and an artificial
plant in the centre of the enclosure (see photos p.7). In 2009 the birds were
maintained on Mazuri Super Breeder™. In 2010 and 2011 the diet was
modified and the birds were fed the following mixture:
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.60093">
5 cups Mazuri Super Breeder™ (21 % protein, 4% fat)
4 cups ABBA™ canary mix (15% protein, 6% fat)
1 cup millet (11% protein, 5% fat)
3 cups Ultra Kibble™ ground in a food processor
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.917780833333333" page_id="56257302"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
(32.3% protein, 10.67% fat)
The eggs were collected daily and incubated at 99.5°F (37.5°C) with
35%-40% humidity. On day 22 the eggs were moved to a hatcher and the
humidity was increased to 65%. The chicks were fed a standard commercial
chick starter diet. The number of eggs laid, their fertility and the growth of
the chicks, as determined by wing length (see Fig.l), were noted.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.899072">
Results
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999481590909091" page_id="56257302"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
Following the diet modification described above, we observed significant
changes. Egg production increased from 10 eggs per pair on the standard
diet to 48 eggs per pair on the modified diet. The fertility of first year pairs
also increased from almost 0% to 20%. Likewise, with second year pairs,
not only did egg production increase but the percentage of fertile eggs went
up from 12% to 41%. We feel it is likely that total egg production is now
within the normal range for the species but the fertility rate should be closer
to 80%. The current low fertility rate is likely due to inbreeding within the
captive population. Inbreeding is also likely to be the cause of the skewed
sex ratio, although the wild population of this species is known to be male
biased. According to Brown &amp; Gutierrez (1980), under normal conditions,
populations of Montezuma Quail consist of about 60% males. Researchers
have also noted that the sex ratio varies from area to area. It is not known
if this is due to varying levels of predation or changes in plant communities
which result in nutritional differences. Some studies have shown that a
lack of vitamin E impacts fertility. Although this vitamin is often present in
commercial mixes it is not present in acorns. As most commercial diets are
based on poultry studies, it is the responsibility of aviculturists to supplement
the diet of their birds with whichever additional specific nutrients various
species may be lacking. With wild-caught birds this may be dealt with by
providing a variety of food items and then noting which of these the species
is consuming. With captive-bred birds this can be more difficult, as often
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.904113" page_id="56257303"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
10
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.722709">
EITNIEAR &amp; BECHERER - MONTEZUMA QUAIL
Fig. 1. Wing measurements of captive Montezuma Quail.
Fig. 2. Average total egg production (blue) and number of fertile eggs laid
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.972528" page_id="56257303"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
by captive Montezuma Quail (yellow).
1 = One year old breeders on standard diet.
2 = One year old breeders on modified diet.
3 - Two year old breeders on standard diet.
4 = Two year old breeders on modified diet.
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.354969" page_id="56257304"  page_num="11" year="" vol="">
EITNIEAR &amp; BECHERER - MONTEZUMA QUAIL
</equation>
<page confidence="0.998762" page_id="56257304"  page_num="11" year="" vol="">
11
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.930078551724138" page_id="56257304"  page_num="11" year="" vol="">
birds will not eat foods they were not fed when they were chicks. To prevent
this scenario from occurring, we suggest that the chicks of all Galliformes
be fed a variety of foods, including commercial chick starter crumbs, fruits
and vegetables, and a varied seed mix, including small finch and canary
seed, as well as larger grains.
Although our sample size may indicate that our results are not statistically
significant, the results are undoubtably encouraging. Aviculturists often
face the dilemma husbandry standards have not been established, yet the
number of pairs maintained preclude a statistically significant study being
conducted. With such species one needs to look at recent breeding successes
with related species and duplicate any common elements. With regard to the
diet, we suggest that rather than relying totally on commercial preparations,
one attempts, as far as possible, to replicate the natural diet. Often this is
only possible through the use of ‘cafeteria style’ experiments (offering the
birds a variety of choices). The results of such experiments should be well
documented and published in the avicultural literature. Only in this way
will the science of aviculture advance beyond being an endeavour which
relies on ‘tradition’ and ‘trial and error’ methods.
Bibliography
Allen, M. E. 1989. Nutritional aspects of insectivores . Doctoral dissertation, Michigan State
University, East Lansing, ML
Hayes, L. B. 1996. Upland Game Birds: their breeding and care Second edition. Hayes
Publications Inc.
Hernandez, C. Z., Martinez, G. D. M., Zimbron, S. L, Crosby Galvan, M. M., Sanchez, F. C.
and Aquilar Valdez, B. 2004. Composicion de la dieta de la codomiz Montezuma ( Crytonyx
montezuma ) en el noroeste del Estado de Mexico/Mexico. Diet composition of Montezuma
Quail in the northwestern Region in the State of Mexico/Mexico. Veterinaria Mexico 35,3:215-
236. [nutritional analysis of Oxalis bulbs].
Howell, S. N. G. and Webb, S. 1995. The Birds of Mexico and northern Central America.
</bodyText>
<affiliation confidence="0.425497">
Oxford University Press, New York.
</affiliation>
<table confidence="0.63911375" page_id="56257304"  page_num="11" year="" vol="">
Millet Dietary Information. Website:http://nutritiondata.self.com/facts/cereal-grains-and-
pasta/5701/2 [millet]
Nutrition Facts and Analysis for Nuts. Website:http://nutritiondata.self.com/facts/nut-and-seed-
products/3 083/1 [acorns].
</table>
<reference confidence="0.852170888888889">
Price, F. C. 1968. The effect of vitamin E deficiency on fertility of Coturnix coturnix. Poultry
Sci. 47:1037-1038.
Stromberg, M. Montezuma Quail. The Birds of North America online. Website: http ://bna. birds.
comell.edu/bna/species/524/articles/introduction
The authors hope that the above article will encourage members to
conduct detailed studies of the diets of their birds, rather than simply rely
on commercial preparations.
Jack Clinton Eitniear, Center for the Study of Tropical Birds, Inc., San
Antonio, Texas, USA. E-mail:jce@cstbinc.org/Website: www.cstbinc.org
</reference>
<page confidence="0.985473" page_id="56257305"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
12
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.551106666666667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56257305" page_num="12" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE SPECTACLED LAUGHXNGTHRUSH
Rhinocichla mitrata
by Llyr Davies
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.965164571428571" page_id="56257305"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
The Spectacled Laughingthrush Rhinocichla mitrata is found in forests,
at forest edges and among adjoining cultivation from 500m-3,200m (approx.
l,650ft-7,500ft) above sea level in south-east Asia. It is also known as the
Chestnut-capped Laughingthrush (and until recently was listed in the genus
Garrulax) and was previously treated as conspecific with the Chestnut-
hooded Laughingthrush R. teachery , with which it forms a superspecies.
Two subspecies are currently recognised: R. m. major , found in extreme
southern Thailand and Peninsular Malaysia, and R. m mitrata , which is
found on the Indonesian island of Sumatra (Collar &amp; Robson, 2007). The
Spectacled Laughingthrush is common in Peninsula Malaysia and on Mt
Kerinci in Sumatra.
This laughingthrush has apparently always been rare in western aviculture
with very few birds having been kept in the UK and Europe. During a recent
search of the ISIS database I could not find any listed in North American
zoological collections. The assumption must be that the majority of birds
trapped for the bird trade remain in south-east Asia.
Description
It is a medium-sized, dull grey laughingthrush, approximately 23cm (9in)
in length. It has a white eye-ring, chestnut on the head and vent and a bold
white wing-flash. The irises are usually red or often red-brown or chestnut,
or sometimes brown or dark brown. The bill, legs and feet are yellow. The
sexes look similar. The juvenile is duller and browner than the adult and
has less white streaking on the forehead.
Acquisition and pairing
Waddesdon Manor Aviary (WMA) purchased the female in 2004. She
was estimated to have been wild bom in 2000. This specimen and another
female made a nesting attempt in 2008. The 2004 female was observed
sitting in the nest, and a broken egg was found on the aviary floor.
In March 2011, a male, estimated to have been hatched in 2005, was
acquired on loan from Ronald Hoogervorst. Following quarantine, it was
paired with the female, which was the fittest of the two females we had at
WMA. In the morning, the male was introduced to the female in an off-show
aviary. This was 14ft long x 5ft wide x 7ft high (approx 4.2m long x 1.5m
wide x 2. lm high) and planted with box bushes and bamboo and had natural
perches. Mulch and mix was used as the substrate on the floor of the aviary,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.47245" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257306" page_num="13" year="" vol="">
DAVIES - SPECTACLED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999151" page_id="56257306"  page_num="13" year="" vol="">
13
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.971114325" page_id="56257306"  page_num="13" year="" vol="">
which was roofed at each end and had a small shelter attached.
Food
The birds were fed an insectivorous and a frugivorous diet. The
insectivorous mix consists of universal and low iron softbill foods, to which
was added finely grated carrot, finely diced apple, soaked raisins and minced
hard-boiled egg. The frugivorous mix consists of a variety of diced fruits
and low iron softbill pellets. Every other day the food was dusted with
Nutrobal multivitamin powder. Livefood, consisting of mealworms, crickets
and waxworms, was offered thrice daily.
Reproduction
Two nesting baskets were present in the aviary when the birds were
introduced and a third, placed at a height of 6ft Tin (2m) above the ground,
was added soon afterwards. The baskets were screened with Cupressus
leylandii. A nest constructed of coconut fibres was found in the third basket
on April 25th. One of the birds was observed sitting on the nest on May 16th
and, the following day, it was noted that there were two eggs in the nest,
which a day later were found broken on the aviary floor. A new cycle began
on May 24th and again resulted in two broken eggs being found. When an
undamaged egg was observed in the nest on June 6th, it was removed and
artificially incubated. On June 26th, the pair was recorded building in a
different nest basket.
Hand-rearing
After having been artificially incubated at 37.2°C (99°F) for 13 days,
the egg hatched on June 19th. The chick weighed 3g before its first f ^ed at
approximately 14 hours old. It was initially kept in a brooder set at 36.2°C
(97.2°F), the temperature of which was gradually reduced as the chick grew
older.
The hand-rearing diet, fed to it using tweezers, consisted of equal
quantities of pinkie mice and papaya, pureed and with an added pinch
of Nutrobal multivitamin powder. It is a diet we have used with much
success hand-rearing other passerine chicks, including those of other species
of laughingthrush. As the chick grew, increased quantities of ecdysed
mealworms (mealworms which had recently shed their skin), crickets and
small waxworms, were added to the diet.
The chick was fed at hourly intervals from 6.00am-10.00pm (22.00hrs)
for the first three days and gained 5.4g in weight during this period. Feather
development advanced up the neck on day two and was visible on the crown
the following day. The pins of the primary wing feathers had broken through
the skin by day three. The interval between feeds was increased to one-and-
a-half hours until day seven, by which time the chick had gained a further
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998558" page_id="56257307"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
14
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7736315" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257307" page_num="14" year="" vol="">
DAVIES - SPECTACLED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
Ian Edmans/WMA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9955392" page_id="56257307"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
The young laughingthrush at seven months of age. Until
recently this species was better known as the Chestnut-capped
Laughingthrush.
9.3g in weight. The pins had begun emerging on its shoulders and nape and
the eyes had begun slitting.
From then until the chick fledged, it was fed at two-hourly intervals,
except for the period between days 11-13, when for convenience’s sake, the
interval was reduced to one-and-a-half hours, to synchronise feeding times
with those of younger chicks being hand-reared. On day nine the feathers
had began unfurling from the pins on the wings. The following day the
chestnut cap was coming through and, by day 11, the eyes were fully open
and the chestnut vent was observed. The chick fledged from its nest pot on
July 12th. It was 14 days old and weighed 30.7g (Fig. 1 tracks its growth
rate). It was placed under a heat lamp in a small cage for fledglings.
After a few days in the cage the young laughingthrush was observed
pecking at insects and pieces of fruit. Following this, it was offered food from
tweezers only twice a day, at 7.00am and 7.00pm (19.00hrs). Once it was
fully independent, it was moved to a larger cage measuring approximately
5ft long x 4ft wide x 6ft high (1.5m long x 1.2m wide x 1.8m high), which
it shared with a younger hand-reared Spotted Laughingthrush Ianthocincla
ocellata. On August 17th the young Spectacled Laughingthrush weighed 50g
and some feathers were removed and sent for DNA testing, which revealed
that it is a female. On September 26th both young laughingthrushes were
moved to an outdoor off-show aviary, at which time the young Spectacled
Laughingthrush weighed 47g.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.434426" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257308" page_num="15" year="" vol="">
DAVIES - SPECTACLED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.898305" page_id="56257308"  page_num="15" year="" vol="">
15
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.649706">
Fig. 1. Chick’s growth rate from days one to 14.
Spectacled or Chestnut-capped Laughingthrush
</figureCaption>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.380687" genericHeader="conclusions" page_id="56257308" page_num="15" year="" vol="">
Conclusion
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.835515227272727" page_id="56257308"  page_num="15" year="" vol="">
There is the need for research into why the majority of eggs, having been
laid in a nest, are later being found broken on the aviary floor. It is hoped
that we can perfect the breeding requirements of this charismatic species
and, ideally, be able to produce parent-reared young in the near future.
We hope that the lessons learnt from breeding this species, which remains
common in the wild, can be applied to breeding endangered species, to which
captive breeding may prove significant in their recovery.
Products mentioned in the text
Nutribird T16 low iron pellets: Versele-Laga nv, Kappellestraat 70, 9800 Deinze, Belgium.
Nutrobal multivitamin powder: Vetark Professional, PO Box 60, Winchester, Hants S023
9XN, UK.
Reference
Collar, N. J. and Robson, C. 2007. Family Timaliidae (Babblers). In: del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A.
and Christie, D. A. (eds.). Handbook of the Birds of the World. Volume 12 - Picathartes to Tits
and Chickadees. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona.
Llyr Davies, Aviary Keeper, The Rothschild Foundation, Waddesdon
Manor Aviary, Waddesdon, near Aylesbury, Buckinghamshire HP 18 OJH,
UK. Website:www. waddesdon. org. uk
As described above, the Spectacled Laughingthrush Rhinocichla mitrata
has been bred at Waddesdon Manor Aviary. This is probably the first
successful breeding of this species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who
knows of a previous breeding is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997169" page_id="56257309"  page_num="16" year="" vol="">
16
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.833103666666667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56257309" page_num="16" year="" vol="">
LOOKING BACK AT RAYMOND’S FIRST TWENTY-FIVE
YEARS AT COBHAM
by Malcolm Ellis
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998746" page_id="56257309"  page_num="16" year="" vol="">
Following the sad death of our President Raymond Sawyer on February
21st (see The End of an Era and Memories of Raymond, pp. 45-47), it was
suggested to me that it might be a good idea to look back at his time at
Chestnut Lodge and the wonderful garden parties, while the memories are
still fresh in our minds.
In Vol.103, No.2, pp.49-66 (1997), Raymond wrote that the previous
year 1996, had marked a quarter of a century during which he and Ruth Ezra
(who later became his wife) had been keeping their wonderful collection at
Chestnut Lodge. During those first 25 years many birds were bred there.
These included 16 species which it was believed had never before been
bred in the UK and several others which had been bred for only the second
time in this country. There were also numerous other notable successes.
Of the many birds which had been bred there, it was with the wading birds
that they had been most successful. Several species bred successfully over
many years.
Raymond’s notes aimed to provide as much information as possible,
although, as he pointed out, in the case of some of the smaller species it
was difficult to write a great deal about the breedings, as the nests were
sometimes difficult to observe or it was thought best to leave the birds alone
and not disturb them.
The aviaries at Cobham were many shapes and sizes and various heights.
They were generally beautifully landscaped and planted to blend in with the
various trees and plants, etc. A problem had been that the growth was at
times very vigorous and the vegetation had to be pruned back, otherwise it
would have been difficult to see the birds. Subtle alterations had been made
to some of the flights but otherwise they had remained unaltered since they
had been constructed. The lay-out had taken about 20 years to complete.
At all times the birds came first and were all encouraged to breed.
Correct feeding is a vital part of breeding birds, wrote Raymond. Living
in mixed aviaries with a wide variety of foods available, meant that many of
the birds had a wider variety of foods to choose from than might otherwise
have been the case. Most aviaries had a supply of nectar and in some aviaries
there was a choice of more than one type of nectar. There were now many
nectar preparations available, all claiming to be the best and containing their
own particular combination of ingredients. At Cobham they preferred to
mix their own and provided it in open dishes, except in the case of the more
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.559392" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257310" page_num="17" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - RAYMOND SAWYER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999057" page_id="56257310"  page_num="17" year="" vol="">
17
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.995294219512195" page_id="56257310"  page_num="17" year="" vol="">
delicate nectar-feeders such as hummingbirds, sunbirds and honeycreepers,
for which they used hanging or clip-on plastic feeding tubes. Over the years
nectar had changed as research had improved. How appropriate it was, wrote
Raymond, that Ruth’s father Alfred Ezra, was the first to develop a nectar
mixture - which included Nestles Condensed Milk, Mellin’s Food and sugar
- on which nectar-feeders thrived. Some of the hummingbirds fed on it lived
for up to eight years in his collection.
Raymond was often asked for his opinion on the best softbill and
insectivorous mixtures. He had used a mixture of Haith’s Prosecto
Insectivorous Food and Bogena, but at the time was using a Witte Molen
product and high protein chick starter crumbs. The variety of foods available
was increasing all the time and there were even specially formulated diets
for certain specific groups of larger softbills. Raymond was a great believer
in mixing the softbill food with hard-boiled egg, including the shell, which
was apparently done in a food processor. This was then sprinkled with the
vitamin/mineral supplement Vionate and fed to the birds daily. There were
very few birds which did not take some of this, he wrote. Raymond was also
a great believer in using ox heart which was mixed with the insectivorous
food. Any food left over the following day was given to the cranes. The
art, he wrote, was to provide just enough food so that there was just a little
left over the next morning. All too often he felt you saw dishes so full of
food that you knew the birds had been given enough to last all week. When
a new keeper arrived, one of the first tasks was to teach him or her how to
judge the correct amount of food to give to the birds.
A wide variety of fruits were fed to the birds. Most were cut-up but
some others were chopped-up in the food processor. Certain fruits such as
grapes, apples and pears were used all year round but others were used only
seasonally. Oranges were never used for feeding the birds and, whereas a
lot of bird keepers put fruit on spikes, this was something Raymond never
did. Any uneaten fruit was removed the next day. Again the art was to have
just a little left over the next morning.
Once livefood had consisted of only maggots and mealworms, but
maggots were no longer used following problems with botulism in the 1970s.
Raymond used as great a variety of livefood as he could obtain, although of
course, there was not as wide a variety as we have available today. What a
difference mini-mealworms made to successfully rearing young birds, wrote
Raymond, especially during the first few days. Ants’ eggs were no longer
commercially available, and had not been for a long time.
Large parrots such as macaws and Keas Nestor notabilis were given
plenty of fresh fruit and nuts, plus small quantities of sunflower seed. The
Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber had carophyll added to their food during the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997836" page_id="56257311"  page_num="18" year="" vol="">
18
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.871032" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257311" page_num="18" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - RAYMOND SAWYER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.978599731707317" page_id="56257311"  page_num="18" year="" vol="">
moult in order to maintain their brilliant colour. The flamingos received a
proprietary diet. The waterfowl had their own food, consisting of wheat,
pellets, bread and sea duck food, which they seemed to thrive on, as did the
wild ducks, which all seemed to know when it was feeding time.
Raymond saw Emerald Starlings Lamprotornis iris for the first time in
1954 and thought they were quite the most spectacular and breathtakingly
beautiful birds, with their wonderful iridescent plumage. They were the first
to ever be imported. Twenty-six were brought back by the joint London
Zoo/BBC Zoo Quest Expedition to Sierra Leone, West Africa. Brought back
(along with the first White-necked Picathartes Picathartes gymnocephalus)
by David Attenborough, Jack Lester and my first Head Keeper, ‘Timber’
Woods, they were mostly in immature plumage. One pair went to Jean
Delacour and another pair to Alfred Ezra, but none to Raymond, something
for which he never quite forgave the zoo (I think he blamed the Director
Harrison Matthews). Years later David Attenborough told Raymond that
if he had known that he had wanted a pair, he would have given a pair to
him. Raymond eventually managed to obtain one which Ray Shingler, who
had been a keeper in the Bird House at London Zoo, brought back from
Sierra Leone in the early 1960s. This bird lived in Raymond’s collection
for many years.
In 1979, a dealer rang Raymond to say that he had some interesting
starlings, including the Emerald. Raymond wrote, that he almost had a fit,
and immediately went and bought four or six of these birds, which were all
that were available. These were housed in a large aviary and the following
year (1980) two young were reared. It was the first time the Emerald Starling
had ever been bred in the UK. Emerald Starlings are, wrote Raymond, a flock
or colony bird and it is possible to keep several together in a large aviary. A
breeding pair will become dominant but provided there is plenty of space
and cover, the others will be safe. Raymond noted that Emerald Starlings
often carry green leaves in their bills, but remained uncertain whether this
was for display or nesting purposes. I think the answer is possibly for both
display/pair-bonding and nesting purposes. Emerald Starlings went on to
breed at Cobham several more times though not on a regular basis. They
generally preferred a sloping-type nest box, with a flat bottom and with wire
mesh on the inside to assist the birds to get in and out. The eggs were typical
starling eggs, that is mainly light blue with brown/red blotching.
Emerald Starlings are, observed Raymond, highly nervous when first
received. They did not make good show birds as they spent their time on
the floor of the cage and their plumage became soiled. The same thing
happened in quarantine and at dealers’ premises and this could result in them
picking up infections. The first birds Raymond obtained were not perfect,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.55938" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257312" page_num="19" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - RAYMOND SAWYER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998996" page_id="56257312"  page_num="19" year="" vol="">
19
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.971701365853658" page_id="56257312"  page_num="19" year="" vol="">
but nothing was seriously wrong with them. They bathed a lot at first, as
lots of birds do when newly arrived. He recommended that the water should
be changed each time after they had bathed and considered bathing to be a
sign of a good healthy bird. His continued to bathe regularly in almost all
types of weather.
Raymond’s original pair of Splendid Starlings L. splendidus came from
my friends Tim and Jane Bamley, near Kitale, in Western Kenya, which is
at the eastern limited of the range of this principally West African species.
Raymond considered this starling to be most appropriately named. It is one
of the few starlings which is easily sexable, the male being more brightly
coloured and larger than the female. The original pair first bred at Cobham
in 1976, which was the first time this species had been bred in the UK.
However, Jean Delacour had bred the Splendid Starling two years earlier at
Cleres, which was probably the first ever captive breeding. Over the first
few years the Cobham pair regularly produced young, but was then stolen
and was never recovered. Raymond was able to obtain some more Splendid
Starlings and had occasional successes, including in 1992, when one was
hand-reared. Patrick Taplin, a keeper at the time, put a good deal of time
and effort into raising it. Raymond wrote, that whereas the Superb Starlings
L. superbus readily went to nest, albeit not always rearing the young, the
later Splendid Starlings carried green leaves around the aviary and perhaps
even built an incomplete nest, but seldom seemed to lay fertile eggs. This
was in marked contrast to the original pair which hatched every egg that was
laid and reared all the young. There were still six Splendid Starlings living
at Cobham in 1996 and Raymond knew of a few others in bird gardens and
private collections and hoped these would form the nucleus of a breeding
programme. Raymond failed to mention that the Splendid Starling is a most
wonderful mimic, far better than any parrot or hill mynah Gracula spp.
Superb Starlings bred at Cobham in 1996. The Golden-breasted Starling
Cosmopsarus regius though had yet to be completely successful. This
beautiful starling had reared young which were about to leave the nest but had
then died. Golden-breasted Starlings are very prone to getting gapeworms
and precautions needed to be taken when they were newly imported, wrote
Raymond. However, once established they did well, even in our damp
autumns. Amethyst or Violet-backed Starlings Cinnyricinclus leucogaster
had also got young to the stage of almost being about to fledge. Here again,
this species is easily sexable, although mistakes can occur because young
males take up to three years to lose their female-like immature plumage.
The Black-necked Stilt Himantopus mexicanus (the American species)
was bred at Cobham in 1992 and was another UK first breeding. The pair
was housed in a large aviary and fed on an insectivorous mix and minced ox
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.987393" page_id="56257313"  page_num="20" year="" vol="">
20
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.88009" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257313" page_num="20" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - RAYMOND SAWYER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999665375" page_id="56257313"  page_num="20" year="" vol="">
heart and, when they could be obtained, sand eels. The male stilt developed
a pink flush on the breast (which may not be noticeable in the wild), which
was a sign that he was coming into breeding condition. The display was
quite spectacular with the birds reminding Raymond of two ballet dancers.
The male danced around the female and then suddenly he mated with her.
The pair bred during only its second year at Cobham. The pair went on
to breed each year, producing a clutch of four eggs, all of which hatched
and all of the chicks were reared. It was a great success - with only one
drawback - when the pair had young all the other waders had to be removed
from the aviary and the stilts would even fly up and attack birds sitting on
the perches. They were wonderful parents who doted on their chicks and
they became one of Raymond’s favourite waders. A single clutch of eggs
was laid each year, which had a speckled dull green background colour and
mottled brown markings. The pair had nested in the same place each year
for the past five years.
The aviary had a stream running through it and was the same aviary in
which the Black-winged Stilts H. himantopus nested so successfully. These
first bred in 1979, which was another UK first breeding. Raymond believed
that the Black-necked species is the prettier and more attractive of the two.
The Black-winged received the same diet, but some of them developed a
gout-like condition which could lead to lameness. Both species were very
hardy and would roost standing in running water during the winter. In the
summer they roosted on the ground.
To Raymond’s surprise and delight, a pair hatched the previous year,
reared chicks successfully in its first year. Raymond was surprised that the
birds had matured so quickly. He greatly disliked paperwork and, because
of this, later disposed of the Black-winged Stilts and kept only the Black¬
necked species, as these did not require paperwork and could be disposed
of without permission.
Raymond was of the opinion that stilts require an aviary measuring not
less than 6m x 3m (approx. 20ft x 10ft), with a constant trickle of running
water. Stilts carry their food into the water to wash it and, if the water is
not moving, an oily film quickly develops on the surface of the water and
this gets onto their plumage. This had occurred with some Cobham-bred
birds which had gone to other aviculturists, but as soon as running water
was introduced the problem disappeared. Sexing stilts is not difficult as
the male has a more intense black on the back, with a sheen to the feathers,
whereas the female’s back has a brownish tinge. The young pair that bred
in 1996 could be sexed fairly early on, but generally it takes a year before
you can be certain of their sex, wrote Raymond.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.559477" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257314" page_num="21" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - RAYMOND SAWYER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997823" page_id="56257314"  page_num="21" year="" vol="">
21
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997069391304348" page_id="56257314"  page_num="21" year="" vol="">
Raymond feeding his flock of Avocets.
Avocets Recurvirostra avocetta bred regularly at Cobham almost up until
the time of Raymond’s death. He found it most gratifying when first time
visitors admired this instantly recognisable species which was once rare
in the UK, but is now once again breeding here in considerable numbers.
(Wild Avocets have nested at the WWT London Wetland Centre at Barnes,
close to Central London.) Back then before the widespread availability of
DNA sexing, Raymond found that Avocets needed to be surgically sexed
in order to find a true pair - and even this method was not always accurate.
He once had a supposed pair sexed again, only to discover that both birds
were the same sex. As with the stilts, Raymond found that when Avocets
have young they will dominate the other birds in the flight and, therefore, the
entire family was moved into a side aviary on its own. He added, that many
members who visited Cobham had noticed (and no doubt commented upon
the fact) that the grass in the aviaries was always mown around where the
waders nested. Once they get used to the mower, they appeared to have no
fear of it, he wrote. Much the same happened with the cranes which lived
at liberty in the garden, where it was possible to go right up to them with
the mower without frightening them.
The 1994 breeding of the Wattled Ja$anaJacana jacana was thought to be
another UK first breeding. If jananas are provided with the right conditions
they will thrive, wrote Raymond, but if they are kept in poor conditions foot
problems are inevitable. The pair at Cobham bred in an aviary which housed
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996961" page_id="56257315"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
22
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.879158" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257315" page_num="22" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - RAYMOND SAWYER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99880856097561" page_id="56257315"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
birds up to the size of the Purple-throated Fruitcrow Querula purpurata.
This jagana is, wrote Raymond, much tougher than the African Jagana
Actophilornis africanus though, of course, in a bad winter it ought to be shut
inside at night. At Cobham they were usually able to walk them in at night
or sometimes they went in on their own accord. Raymond was fascinated
to observe that the male did almost all the work. He built the nest with
only partial assistance from the female and incubated the eggs. Raymond
never saw the female on the nest. When the chicks hatched the male carried
them in his breast feathers. The female remained in the background, but if
a Sparrowhawk Accipiter nisus appeared on or above the aviary, she would
come forward and attempt to defend the chicks. Apart from this, she took
very little part in the proceedings and the male almost seemed to resent her
coming too close to defend the chicks or interfere with them in any way. In
the centre of the pond there were rocks and also lilies and blanket weed and
it was there that the nest was built. The eggs were a beautiful shiny bronze
colour. This species can easily be sexed by the fact that the female is larger
than the male. The young can also be sexed by their size. They attained
full colour after about 18 months.
Although jaganas are not as aggressive as stilts and avocets, the breeding
pair did drive off the old jaganas that Raymond had in the aviary and the
latter had to be removed. Four young were reared in 1994 and three in 1995.
Raymond tried the tiny chicks with mini-mealworms, but was uncertain
what they ate at first. Within a few days, however, the mini-mealworms
were being taken. Getting the young jaganas onto an artificial diet was not
too difficult. They had to mix livefood in with the softbill food and then be
patient. The main problem was that it was expensive to supply unlimited
livefood in a large mixed aviary.
Red-and-white Crakes Laterallus leucophyrrhus could, Raymond found,
be very aggressive and at times difficult to keep together. He imported a few
to go with the existing group at Cobham, but by the next morning the new
birds had been killed. In a large planted aviary with plenty of cover in which
to hide they can live happily, but every so often one or more will get picked
on. They climbed all over the place, wrote Raymond, one minute they were
on the ground and the next they were at the top of a bush. They bred several
times at Cobham and chose extraordinary nesting places, such as high in the
bushes or in half-open-fronted nest boxes. Raymond found them to be good
parents and the chicks enchanting. These crakes had, wrote Raymond, been
accused of being egg-eaters, but he had not found this to be the case. At the
time of writing, he was down to his last two crakes. They were no longer
breeding and were no longer available. He feared that this species would
not be seen again in our aviaries. He concluded by noting that it ate softbill
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.559281" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257316" page_num="23" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - RAYMOND SAWYER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998263" page_id="56257316"  page_num="23" year="" vol="">
23
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.980175136363636" page_id="56257316"  page_num="23" year="" vol="">
Grey Crowned Cranes Balearica regulorum in courting dance.
food and fruit, etc., as well as seed, including various millets.
The Crested Wood Partridge Rollulus rouloul, called then the Roulroul or
Roulroul Partridge, appeared to breed well for a short time, say about three
years, in Raymond’s experience, but then seemed to stop breeding. Back
in 1956, when he was living in London, Raymond had recorded wnat was
then only the second UK breeding of this popular species. (It was first bred
in the UK in 1927 by W. Whitley - presumably, Herbert Whitley’s brother
William.) Raymond’s young were parent-reared and the following year a
silky hen brooded and reared the young. At that year’s National Exhibition
of Cage Birds, held at Olympia, in London, Raymond won the award for
the Best Foreign exhibit with the male and one of his daugthers. It was the
first time that a UK-bred foreign bird had won this award at what was then
the UK’s premier exhibition of foreign birds. To the best of Raymond’s
knowledge this also included the Crystal Palace shows going all the way
back into the previous century. Over the years Raymond had several pairs
which had bred at Cobham. His latest pair laid but refused to incubate
the eggs. He believed there was a strong possibility that the pair was not
parent-reared and, in his opinion, this led to problems with both infertility
and the rearing of the young.
Raymond knew of several aviculturists who had achieved fleeting success
with a pair or two, after which nothing further happened. Most successes
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997997" page_id="56257317"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
24
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.879928" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257317" page_num="24" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - RAYMOND SAWYER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.955529341463415" page_id="56257317"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
appeared to be as a result of taking the eggs away to be hatched and then
artificially rearing the chicks. We seemed to have ended up with an egg layer
which did not know how to sit and incubate her own eggs, wrote Raymond.
His original pair was wild-caught and took nesting very seriously. Whereas
his latest pair was captive-bred and played about with the nesting material
and never made a proper domed nest. In 1996, the eggs were taken away and
placed in an incubator and five chicks hatched and were hand-reared. They
were raised under a lamp along with another chick for company. Raymond
found that the Crested Wood Partridge does not like cold weather and can
get frostbitten toes. He felt that in the UK climate it definitely needs some
form of shelter, such as a glass-covered, rather than an open aviary, in which
he had experienced problems with this species. He added, however, that it
is okay outside from April-October.
The UK first breeding of the Violet Turaco Musophaga violacea was
achieved at Cobham in 1984, after which the pair went on to breed for
several more years. Raymond commented on the fact that the young seem
to leave the nest awfully early and climb about on the branches of bushes.
He had not found this turaco aggressive until recently when the female, who
was not frightened of anyone, developed an absolute hatred of women and
would attack the female keeper.
Ross’s Turaco M. rossae was also bred at Cobham, although it was not the
first breeding, that honour having gone to Raymond’s friend Newton Steele,
who bred it in 1972. His pair was extremely aggressive and the male had
taken out one of the female’s eyes. Turacos can be very aggressive towards
each other when kept in a small flight, wrote Raymond. He added, that
they need to be watched when they are breeding, as the males sometimes
persecute the females. The Red-crested Turaco Tauraco erythrolophus bred
at Cobham most years and Livingstone’s I livingstonii had been bred there
and also Schalow’s I schalowi , as well as Fischer’s I fischeri which, at
the time, had only previously been bred once before in the UK (at Leeds
Castle Aviary). Raymond considered surgical sexing to be the best way of
sexing turacos (at that time) - the alternative being to let them choose their
own partner.
The Blue Whistling Thrush Myiophoneus caeruleus bred at Cobham in
1992 and was yet another UK first breeding. The pair, which built a typical
thrush-type nest, albeit a very large one in view of the size of the species,
went on to breed several more times, with the young leaving leaving the
nest looking like paler versions of their parents. The Blue W hi si mg Thrush
can at times be a killer and is not to be trusted with birds smaller than itself,
or even some birds of its own size, that is about 33cm (13in) in length. It
is definitely a species to keep a close eye on, even if there is just a pair on
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.559567" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257318" page_num="25" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - RAYMOND SAWYER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995607" page_id="56257318"  page_num="25" year="" vol="">
25
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999445268292683" page_id="56257318"  page_num="25" year="" vol="">
its own in a spacious flight. When she was nesting, the female at Cobham
would attack the keepers and eventually killed the male. Raymond had
noticed that yellow-billed birds were no longer being imported, but those
with black bills continued to be imported occasionally.
There was a pair of Island Thrushes Turdus poliocephalus in the collection
at Cobham, then some more were obtained and eventually a male and two
females were living in the same aviary. One of the females nested and
successfully raised young and then, to Raymond’s amazement, the second
female did the same - obviously the male had mated with both females. They
nested in half-open-fronted nest boxes, which was unusual for thrushes. It
was another UK first breeding.
Over the years the Laughing Kookaburra Dacelo novaeguineae often
bred at Cobham. Members who visited the collection may remember that
they bred first in a small enclosure by the garages. Mice and day old chicks
formed the bulk of their diet.
Another species which bred at Cobham on several occasions in recent
years was the Azure-winged Magpie Cyanopica cyana. In the past Raymond
had kept them in a flock and thought this may have galvanised them into
breeding. However, he had cut back the number in 1996 and, at the time of
writing, had only two pairs, one of which had reared five young. They are,
he observed, quite small birds when they moult their tail feathers.
The Red-tailed Minla Minla ignotincta was bred at Cobham in 1989 in
one of the range of six smaller aviaries. The pair was thought to be sitting,
then livefood was seen being taken into the nest and eventually two young
were seen in the flight. Of the other two species, the Blue-winged M.
cyanouroptera is a rather highly strung bird, whereas the Chestnut-tailed
M. strigula is a very confiding species. The Red-tailed is the only one of
the three where there is a slight difference between the plumage of the male
and female. Apparently, it was the first time for many years that this species
had been seen in the UK and Raymond knew of several others who had
succeeded in breeding it - no doubt helped by the fact that it could be sexed
relatively easily. In the Foreign Bird Club’s magazine, Bird Notes March
1915, there is a coloured plate of it painted by Goodchild. This was painted
from life from a male owned by Ruth’s father, Alfred Ezra. He described
the bird as the most fascinating softbill he had kept - it was full of curiosity
and not at all frightened by anything. This was an observation which was
confirmed by Raymond.
The breeding of the Southern Tit-Warbler Parisoma subcaeruleum was
another small softbill about which Raymond was able to provide very few
details. They too were housed in one of the six smaller flights, where in 1989
they built a small compact nest and reared two young. The sexes look alike
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.993371" page_id="56257319"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
26
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.880612" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257319" page_num="26" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - RAYMOND SAWYER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999432" page_id="56257319"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
and the young when they left the nest were merely duller versions of their
parents. The latter were sold to Raymond as tit-babblers and this species is
now known as the Chestnut-vented Tit-Babbler or Rufous-vented Warbler.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.562445">
Plumbeous Redstarts Rhyacornis fuliginosus bred successfully twice in
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.974786027027027" page_id="56257319"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
1988, rearing three young on each occasion. They too bred in one of the
six smaller flights, where they nested in a thick currant bush. Raymond was
unaware that they were nesting until the male went for Alan Lewis, who was
their keeper at the time. Others were later successful with this species which
is found from the Himalayas to northern Thailand and western China. The
male is basically a dark bluish-slate colour, with a bright chestnut tail. The
female is greyish-brown, with a white and brown tail. Often pictured in or
near water, the Plumbeous Redstart enjoys access to a stream or pool.
The Masked Crimson Tanager Ramphocelus nigrogularis bred
successfully in 1992, once again in one of the six smaller flights. The pair
nested in a half open fronted finch-type nest box and was tolerant of the
other occupants of the aviary. The pair took a lot of livefood while nesting.
Raymond found that this tanager did not like our damp autumn weather
and, although the six aviaries had heated shelters, it could not tolerate our
cold winters.
Not many woodpeckers were imported and few have been bred in
captivity here in the UK, but one which was bred successfully at Cobham
is the Black-cheeked Woodpecker Melanerpes pucker am from Central and
northern South America. The male and female look similar to each other,
except that the male’s cap is a stronger shade of red. This species was first
bred there in 1992. The pair nested in the trunk of a Silver Birch Betula
pendula, cut into three sections for ease of handling and moveability. Once
the pair had excavated the nest hole, there was nothing further to do but
wait and hope until they saw lots of food being taken into the nest and then
knew the pair had young. Eventually four emerged. Raymond believed
they remained in the nest for about three weeks. The pair went on to breed
successful ly on numerous other occasions, including in 1996. Over the years
Raymond found that woodpeckers enjoy nectar and always ensured that it
was available for them. He added, that as well as nectar, the Black-cheeked
Woodpeckers liked softbill food, fruit and livefood. At the time, the pair
shared the flight with a Scarlet-chested Sunbnd Meet arm la senegalensis and
Raymond got pleasure from watching the sunbird and woodpeckers drinking
from the same dish of nectar. He found it is not a particularly aggressive
species. When the pair first bred, it was sharing the flight with a pair of
Black-naped Fruit Doves Ptilinopus melanospila .
In 1960, Chat and Lindsay exhibited a pair of Blue-faced Honeyeaters
Entomyzon cyanotis barteri , from southern New Guinea and northern
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.559556" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257320" page_num="27" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - RAYMOND SAWYER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997509" page_id="56257320"  page_num="27" year="" vol="">
27
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997914317073171" page_id="56257320"  page_num="27" year="" vol="">
Queensland, at the National Exhibition of Cage &amp; Aviary Birds at Olympia,
in London, where the pair won the award for the Best Large Foreign Softbill.
The pair obviously caught Raymond’s eye, but it was not until 1991 that
he managed to obtain six of these honeyeaters. These were housed in an
aviary with a shelter which was heated during the winter. Two pairs nested
though only one pair did so successfully. They nested in a wire basket and
the young were not difficult to rear and were left with their parents. The
small colony was progressing well until Raymond attempted to introduce
some new birds into it. These new birds were resented and were attacked
and had to be removed. There were problems with egg-eating in 1994 and
1995, so in 1996 when a single honeyeater egg was found, it was taken
away and hatched in an incubator and the chick was hand-reared by Sheila
Becker. When it was newly-hatched, it was impossible to tell which species
it belonged to, but when the blue began to break through on the face, it
could be seen at once that it was a Blue-faced Honeyeater chick. The chick
was fed on a turaco diet, with papaya and added vitamins, together with the
squeezed out contents of mealworms and small grubs. The chick soon learnt
to pick up food for itself and all went well. Raymond preferred chicks to
be parent-reared, but in this case he had no choice.
Raymond obtained four Green Wood Hoopoes Phoeniculus purpureus ,
which he housed in a large mixed aviary next to the waterfowl avairy and
very quickly it became obvious that a pair was nesting in a box hung at an
angle. When they were rearing their young an enormous amount of livefood
was put into the aviary, until Raymond hit on the idea if putting Vim (12mm)
wire netting over the top of a large hook-on feeding pot and letting the wood
hoopoes use their long bills to reach in for the food, which remained out
of reach of the other birds. Raymond found them to be very good parents,
which made a great fuss of their young. He also noted that the other two
wood hoopoes helped the parents feed the chicks. On the downside, he
found that they did not like new birds being introduced into their aviary
and could be murderous to their own kind, if he attempted to introduce new
wood hoopoes into the group. In the case of other species, it was not that
they killed them, but that they pursued them around the aviary and interfered
with nest boxes and generally made the new birds feel insecure. At night
the wood hoopoes roosted in the nest box. He did not mention their very
distinctive musty smell.
Ringed Plovers Charadrius hiaticula nested successfully at Cobham for
several years. Raymond kept the pairs separate and wrote that his last pair
were excellent parents. The pair nested against the wire of the main aviary,
where the dogs walked up and down outside during the day. When the dogs
did this the plovers would fly against the wire and try to drive them away.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997245" page_id="56257321"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
28
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.881394" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257321" page_num="28" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - RAYMOND SAWYER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997873780487805" page_id="56257321"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
The plovers were great characters and were no problem to keep and were
very protective of their young. Unlike the stilts, they were not aggressive
towards other birds.
In 1992, Raymond had another first breeding, this time with the Masked
Lapwing Vanellus miles. He had and extraordinarily prolific pair, which had
three nests a year with a 100% success rate. He even had them sitting and
successfully rearing young when there was snow on the ground. Naturally
he would have preferred them to have nested later in the year, as the winter
days are so short and not usually conducive to good breeding. The nest was
a scrape in the ground lined with a few twigs.
A great disappointment to Raymond was the fact that he had failed to
breed pygmy geese. His original pair of African Pygmy Geese Nettapus
auritus displayed but went no further. It is, he wrote, the prettiest of the
pygmy geese but it is not a free breeder. He thought his pair might be the
oldest pair in captivity, for the pair was over 10 years old and this was
beginning to show. He had recently acquired two new pairs which were
housed in the waterfall aviary and shut into the shelter at night if it was at
all cold.
Doves had been quite successful at Cobham. The Black-naped Fruit Dove
had bred there for the past six years. The Beautiful Fruit Dove P pulchellus
had so far produced only male chicks. He had also been successful with
the Jambu P jambu and the Superb Fruit Dove P superbus . A pair of
Beautiful Fruit Doves had attempted to build its nest on a leaf and, although
they stitched a small basket to the leaf, this attempt was doomed to failure.
Raymond stressed that fruit for these doves needs to be cut-up very small,
otherwise it gets stuck all around their beak and face. Whereas if it is cut¬
up small its goes straight down and the birds do not get sores on the sides
of their mouth. They will, he wrote, also take livefood such as mealworms
and drink nectar.
The Cinnamon Ground Dove or Golden-heart Gallicolumba rufigula
and both the Luzon G. luzonica and Mindanao Bleeding-heart G. criniger
had over the years been bred at Cobham. His present pair of Mindanao
Bleeding-hearts had reared six young. His birds liked seed, peanuts and
insectivorous food, plus livefood. It was perhaps unnecessary to add that
doves are not very energetic birds and will sit in the same place for long
periods and, if they are panicked, will crash about and do untold damage,
especially when other birds are nesting. He added, that in our climate here in
the UK, heated accommodation is advisable during the winter and it is also
advisable to house only one pair of doves in a flight, unless it is particularly
spacious. This is especially true when they are nesting.
Raymond imported a pair of Black-billed Weavers Ploceus melanogaster
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.559483" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257322" page_num="29" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - RAYMOND SAWYER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998143" page_id="56257322"  page_num="29" year="" vol="">
29
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999063268292683" page_id="56257322"  page_num="29" year="" vol="">
direct from Kenya and achieved the UK first breeding with this species
in 1976. These weavers built a typical hanging nest and when they were
breeding were totally insectivorous and never appeared to eat seed. Many
years had passed since he had last seen this species. The Madagascar Fody
Foudia madagascariensis , which Raymond found did well when kept in
a small colony, had always been a favourite and had bred several times at
Cobham in the 1980s.
Raymond was not, as he himself wrote, well-known for breeding parrots,
but had over the years enjoyed a number of successes with these birds. Keas,
which he thought are perhaps the most interesting of all the parrots, had bred
there most years, always early in the year. The ancestry of a lot of the Keas
in the UK could, he wrote, be traced back to his original pair. The female
came from what was then Jersey Zoo and the male from New Zealand. The
pair had produced up to four young in a nest, but on the last occasion there
were only two. The male remained keen on mating, but they were probably
over 30 years old and by then too old to breed any more.
The nest box was constructed of breeze blocks, with paving slabs on
the top. When nesting the female gives out a scream if anyone approaches,
but otherwise Keas are secretive when nesting with, wrote Raymond, the
female being “sort of’ guarded by the male. They enjoyed a varied diet
which included nuts, fruit, lettuce and mealworms. Raymond wrote, that his
good friend the late Sydney Porter, who was first to breed the Kea in 1946,
visited New Zealand and could find no evidence that these very inquisitive
and highly active birds kill sheep. His Keas played all the time and especially
enjoyed playing with a cup. He had them in an aviary with running water
which they liked to run through.
Keas seem to enjoy calling at night, wrote Raymond, and Sydney Porter
got lots of complaints about this from his neighbours. He always said he
would dispose of them, but still had them 20 years after the complaints
started. He left them to Raymond when he died.
When Raymond bred Stella’s Lorikeet Charmosyna papou stellae, he
was the first person to breed it since E. J. Brook bred it before the First
World War. The pair used a typical upright nest box in a small aviary.
These lorikeets love to bathe, wrote Raymond, and enjoy rubbing their
plumage on wet leaves after it has rained. He was also successful breeding
the Red-flanked Lorikeet C. placentis , but quickly sold the parents after
he caught them attacking and eventually killing a Crested Jay Platylophus
galericulatus and a Blue-breasted Kingfisher Halcyon malimbica. Most
aviculturists had no trouble with them, wrote Raymond, and others he had
later proved to be trouble-free. It shows how car eful and observant you need
to be, he added. Philippine Hanging Parrots Loriculus philippensis bred at
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995947" page_id="56257323"  page_num="30" year="" vol="">
30
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.880016" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257323" page_num="30" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - RAYMOND SAWYER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998884048780488" page_id="56257323"  page_num="30" year="" vol="">
Cobham on numerous occasions. He had a small colony until some of them
disappeared in 1995. He never did find out what happened to them, but had
his suspicions. Early in 1996, the parents deserted a single chick on two
occasions, but just when he was considering h and rearing the chicks, if the
parents nested again, they surprised him by rearing three young.
Raymond had no luck keeping Salvador! &amp;apos;s Fig Parrot Psittaculirostris
salvadorii , Edwards’s P edwardsii and the Double-eyed Fig Parrot
Cyclopsitta diophthalma. He found they came into breeding condition
and looked beautiful, but then suddenly dropped dead and the post mortem
failed to reveal the cause of death. Vitamin K had recently been found
to be beneficial. London Zoo had no such trouble and had kept a female
Double-eyed Fig Parrot in a small cage in the Bird House for about 15 years,
I looked after this fascinating bird and can confirm that it ate millet, canary
seed, sunflower, hemp and peanuts, the same nectar as that given to the
hummingbirds, fruit, insectivorous/softbill food and mealworms, which it
chewed to extract the innards and then discarded the skin. At the time it was
the only fig parrot most people had ever seen. It was one of two females and
a male Plicated Hombill Rhyticerosplicatus brought back from New Guinea
by David Attenborough, along with a consignment of birds ••of-paradise which
Sir Edward Hallstrom presented to the zoo.
Raymond was not successful with Scarlet Ibis until 1996, when a chick
was hand-reared. The flamingos had always looked lovely but up until that
time only one had been bred. Vulturine Guineafowl Acryllium vulturinum
were allowed to wander free and had laid eggs and some of these hatched.
He recalled his old friend Donald Risdon telling him that all you had to do
was to catch the young along with their parents and put them in an aviary
until the young were big enough to release. However, Raymond found this
was not as easy as it sounded and after a time gave up and left the birds to
their own devices. Some aviculturists found these birds susceptible to foot
problems, wrote Raymond, which may have been related to their diet. It
was something he remembered Reg Partridge telling him about.
They had kept various species of cranes at Cobham and got immense
pleasure watching these stately birds wandering free in the garden. They
always seemed to be in peak condition, wrote Raymond, and loved to display
on the lawns. Sexing them was, of course, a problem and Raymond usually
relied on surgical sexing. Stanley or Blue Cranes Anthropoid.es paradisea
had always done well at Cobham and at the time they had a pet crane named
Emma, who members may remember. Demoiselle Cranes A. virgo were also
bred there, but sadly, neither the Black Crowned Crane Balearicapavonina
or the Grey Crowned Crane B. regulorum had bred at Cobham. In all the
years they had been there, try as he may, Raymond had never even seen
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.55932" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257324" page_num="31" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - RAYMOND SAWYER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999769" page_id="56257324"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
31
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.984398173913043" page_id="56257324"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
them mate.
Amongst the more unusual members of the pheasant family bred at
Cobham were the Palawan Peacock-Pheasant Polyplectron emphanum and
the Congo Peafowl Afropavo congensis. Raymond believed he was only the
second person in the UK to succeed in breeding the Congo Peafowl, which
were housed in a secluded aviary which they shared with the Red-billed
Choughs Pyrrhocorax pyrrhocorax. The Cobham birds had come from
Antwerp Zoo, where they had been kept in sandy pens in a dry environment
to help prevent disease. At Cobham they were offered a varied diet and their
plumage began to improve and the shine returned to their feathers, which had
begun to curl-up. Raymond’s main problem was that both males suffered
a burst main artery and died. Following the death of the second male, the
female was sent to London Zoo.
Raymond concluded his lengthy notes by referring to his pair of Andean
Cock-of-the-Rock Rupicola peruviana , which in August/September 1980
hatched two chicks which, sadly, lived for only a few days. If the greater
variety of livefood we have available today had been available then, he
wondered, whether there might have been a more successful outcome. The
male died soon after mating but the female, which came from Len Hill at
Birdland, Bourton-on-the-Water, lived at Cobham for several more years.
Raymond had another male which lived at Cobham for 16 years.
Species bred for the first time in the UK
during Raymond’s first 25 years at Cobham.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.962931352941176" page_id="56257324"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
Wattled Jacana Jacana jacana (1994)
Black-necked Stilt Himantopus mexicanus (1992)
Black-winged Stilt Himantopus himantopus (1979)
Masked Lapwing Vanellus miles (1992)
Violet Turaco Musophaga violacea (1984)
Black-cheeked Woodpecker Melanerpes puckeruni (1992)
Plumbeous Redstart Rhyacornis fuliginosus (1988)
Blue Whistling Thrush Myiophoneus caeruleus (1992)
Island Thrush Turdus poliocephalus (?)
Red-tailed Minla Minla ignotincta (1989)
Chestnut-tailed Tit-Babbler Parisoma subcaeruleum (1989)
(Listed in the original article as the Southern Tit-Warbler)
Blue-faced Honeyeater Entomyzon cyanotis harteri (1992)
Masked Crimson Tanager Ramphocelus nigrogularis (1992)
Splendid Starling Lamprotornis splendidus (1976)
Emerald Starling Lamprotornis iris (1980)
Black-billed Weaver Ploceus melanogaster (1976)
</table>
<page confidence="0.998589" page_id="56257325"  page_num="32" year="" vol="">
32
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998154" genericHeader="method" page_id="56257325" page_num="32" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE TOCO TOUCAN Ramphastos toco AND
BLACK-NECKED ARACARI Pteroglossus oracari
AT WELTVOGELPARK WALSRODE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989745638888889" page_id="56257325"  page_num="32" year="" vol="">
by Jurgen Vielguth, Kerstin Kirch hotel, Timo A Jlner
and Anne Hoppmann
Breeding toucans, aracari s and toucanets (birds of the Ramphastidae
family) in captivity remains a relatively rare event. At Weltvogelpark
Walsrode we have been working with these birds since the park first opened.
The Toco Toucan Ramphastos toco is the ‘heraldic bird’ of Weltvogelpark
Walsrode. It was chosen as the logo of Vogelpark Walsrode, the name by
which the park was previously known, and the Toco Toucan continues to
figure on our flyers, posters and entrance tickets. We were the first zoological
institution in the world to breed toucans. This was in 1965 just a few years
after the park first opened, when we succeeded in breeding the Green-billed
Toucan R. dicolorus for the first time. Four young were successfully reared
by their parents and a detailed description of the breeding was published in
the park&amp;apos;s Annual Report for that year.
In January 2010, five species of Ramphastidae arrived at the park from
Guyana, South America. Having successfully completed quarantine, the
different pairs were set up on and off-show. After having been here for
only a year, some of the pairs showed pronounced interest in the nest boxes
and displayed courtship and mating behaviour. Pairs of two of the species,
the Toco Toucan and Black-necked Aracari Pteroglossus aracari atricollis ,
have since bred successfully, with young of both species having fledged in
July 2011.
The Toco Toucan is found in the eastern parts of South America from
Guyana southwards to Paraguay and northern Argentina. Generally, it lives
at the edge of forests, near streams and rivers, in habitats with scattered trees
and on the savannah and in plantations. The largest member of the toucan
family, it is the only species that prefers more open habitats in preference to
rainforest. It feeds mainly on fruits and insects and may use its large bill to
rob the nests of other species and take their eggs and young - although recent
studies on the Pantanal, show this to be exceptional behaviour (R. Watson
pers. comm.). The Toco Toucan usually lays a clutch of two to four eggs,
which both sexes take turns to incubate for 17-18 days. At the beginning,
the chicks are fed mainly on insects, then as they grow older they are fed
more and more fruits, as well. They fledge after 43-52 days.
In spring 2010, one pair of young Toco Toucans was placed in a large,
densely planted enclosure in the pheasantry - on show and thus visible to
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.321887" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257326" page_num="33" year="" vol="">
HOPPMANM ET AL - TOCO TOUCAN &amp; BLACK-NECKED ARACARI
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.9993" page_id="56257326"  page_num="33" year="" vol="">
33
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999853073170732" page_id="56257326"  page_num="33" year="" vol="">
visitors to the park. In May, the following year (2011), the pair was already
showing great interest in the nest box, which was made from the base of a
tree trank. This was placed at a slight angle by the back wall of the outside
enclosure. To further stimulate the pair, before the beginning of the breeding
season, the amount of protein in the diet was increased and it was enriched
with additional vitamins. Relatively early on the pair showed territorial
behaviour and behaved aggressively towards other birds using the upper
branches of the enclosure. Therefore, the other birds were removed leaving
the two Toco Toucans the sole occupants of the enclosure.
On June 6th 2011, bird keepers in the tropical section found two eggshells
outside the nest box. So as not to disturb the brooding birds, cleaning and
maintenance were minimised. We were unsure how many young were in
the nest box and it was not until the end of June that we first heard begging
sounds coming from inside the nest box. While the young were growing up,
the parents removed the droppings from the nest box. The pair was provided
with fresh food throughout the day so as to ensure that the young birds had
sufficient food to eat. Shortly before they fledged the beak of at least one
of the young birds and then the whole body of one of the youngsters could
be seen at the entrance to the nest box.
The first young toucan left the nest box on July 21 st 2011. One day later
a second youngster fledged and a third youngster was seen for the first time
at the entrance to the nest box. The staff were very proud and happy about
this, as nobody had believed that there were three young Toco Toucans in
the nest box. The third youngster fledged on July 25th. One could see that
the young toucans differed from each other in body size but, nonetheless,
they were all able to fly from tree to tree. Upon fledging they flew directly
to the perches in the enclosure and began investigating their surroundings.
They were never seen to enter the nest box again and, even when it rained,
remained in the outside enclosure. On July 30th the oldest of the three
young was seen at the food dish feeding by itself. The young resembled
their parents, except that they had a smaller and duller coloured beak and
duller coloured plumage. Weltvogelpark Walsrode ? s first ever parent-reared
Toco Toucans, they were in very good body and feather condition and from
the beginning were very alert and curious. They were not fearful of the
keepers or the visitors.
The main conditions needed to successfully breed toucans are a
compatible pair and a suitable nest box which is acceptable to the pair.
We use nest boxes made from the bases of tree tranks which are specially
produced for the park. These are half filled with wood shavings. Here at
Weltvogelpark Walsrode we always try to let the parents rear their own young.
We believe that if they are able to follow their natural breeding behaviour,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997683" page_id="56257327"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
34
</page>
<table confidence="0.930253" page_id="56257327"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
HOPPMANN ET AL - TOCO TOUCAN &amp; BLACK-NECKED ARACARI
Adult Toco Toucans Ramphastos toco.
The first young Toco Toucan fledged on July 21st, the second a day later, and the third
on July 25th.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.465066" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257328" page_num="35" year="" vol="">
HOPPMANN ET AL - TOCO TOUCAN &amp; BLACK-NECKED ARACARI
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997265" page_id="56257328"  page_num="35" year="" vol="">
35
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999614956521739" page_id="56257328"  page_num="35" year="" vol="">
The four newly-fledged young Black-necked Ara^aris with one of the parents (far left).
this will contribute greatly to their welfare. Furthermore, the young toucans
are able to socialise with their parents and this increases the probability that
they will later succeed in breeding and rearing their own young. Toucans
which are hand-reared can be highly imprinted on humans, making it less
likely that when the time comes, they will have the necessary know-how to
rear their own young.
Two species of aragari, the Black-necked and the Green Aragari P.
viridis , are represented in the Weltvogelpark Walsrode collection and have
bred successfully. The Black-necked Aragari occurs from north-east South
America (eastern Venezuela) southwards to south-east Brazil. It inhabits
lowland rainforest, as well as gallery forest (forest bordering streams and
rivers) on the savannah and plantations of fructiferous trees such as papaya.
This aragari lays a clutch of two to four eggs, which both sexes take turns to
incubate for 16-17 days. When first hatched the young are naked and have
greyish coloured skin. They are fed by both parents - partly on regurgitated
food. The young fledge after approximately 40 days.
At almost the same time as the Toco Toucans were breeding, a pair of
Black-necked Aragaris also began breeding. This pair too, which was also
housed on view to visitors, had the amount of protein in the diet increased
and additional vitamins added at the beginning of the breeding season. This
pair also become very territorial and the other birds sharing the enclosure
were removed and housed in other aviaries. From mid-June, the pair was
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.815023" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257329" page_num="36" year="" vol="">
36 HOPPMANN ET AL - TOCO TOUCAN &amp; BLACK-NECKED ARACARI
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.947220409090909" page_id="56257329"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
observed to be spending most of the time in the nest box but, on June 20th,
was seen in the enclosure feeding and then directly returning to the nest box.
Later we could hear increased begging sounds coming from inside the nest
box, but had no idea how many young were in the nest. Eventually, a small
beak was seen at the entrance to the nest and, on July 20th, the first juvenile
was seen leaning out of the nest box. On July 31 st, three juveniles fledged,
followed a day later by a fourth juvenile.
In contrast to the Toco Toucans, the four young aracarrs left the nest box
at almost the same time and, during the first weeks after fledging, returned
to the nest box at night. Another difference was that in comparison to the
young Toco Toucans, the young ara^aris were highly active. Ara^aris are
lively characters and even the adults are considerably more active and agile
than the much larger Toco Toucan. Flying ability-wise, they were similar
- the young aracans and young Toco Toucans both flew directly from perch
to perch in their enclosures. The adult birds were very caring towards their
young and never let them out of their sight. The young were fed by both
parents, who tirelessly collected food from the inside enclosure and brought
it out to the young. Apart from their smaller body size and smaller, duller
coloured beak, the young resembled the adult birds.
This year Weltvogelpark Walsrode in northern Germany celebrates the
50th Anniversary of its opening. Website:www.weltvogelpark.de/E~mail:
anne. hoppmann@weltvogelpark. de
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.7707514" page_id="56257329"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
* * *
NEW UK RECORD KEEPER
Simon Matthews has taken over Dave Coles’s First Breeding Records
For Birds Reared To Independence Under Controlled Conditions In The
United Kingdom. All future enquiries regarding first breedings in the UK
</table>
<reference confidence="0.89413675">
should be addressed to: Simon Matthews, Senior Aviary Keeper and ARKS
Representative, The Rothschild Foundation, Waddesdon Manor Aviary,
Waddesdon, near Aylesbury, Buckinghamshire HP18 OJH. E-mail:Simon.
Matthews@nationaltrust.org.uk/Tel: 01296 6532
</reference>
<figure confidence="0.3283675" page_id="56257330"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
A FINAL NOTE ON THE DRAKENSBERG SISKIN
Pseudochloroptila symonsi
</figure>
<page confidence="0.998661" page_id="56257330"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
37
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998622108108108" page_id="56257330"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
by Neville Brickell and Trevor Konigkramer
When we previously wrote about this siskin (Brickell, 1986; Brickell
&amp; Konigkramer, 2000), it had yet to be successfully bred in captivity. We
described the hatching of nestlings in an aviary belonging to one of the
authors (T K), but on that occasion both nestlings disappeared within two
days, having possibly been taken by an alien species of gecko, which had
invaded our coastal towns and cities and driven out the indigenous Striped
Skink Mabuya striata (Brickell &amp; Konigkramer, 2000).
The pair was housed in a large aviary and nested in an approximately
one-third-open-fronted nest box measuring 12cm x 16cm x 14cm (approx.
4%in x 6%in x SVrin). The nest was built mostly of coir, in preference to
various grasses and, when completed, the top of the nest was level with the
lip at the front of the box, enabling the sitting female to have a clear view of
the approach to the nest. Two eggs were laid and incubated by the female
for 17 days. The nestlings had reddish-pink skin and creamy coloured down
on the head.
One of us (T.K.) discovered four nest sites in the wild in Lesotho in
February 2000. One nest, which had been abandoned, consisted of fine dry
grasses and tendrils and was lined with fine grasses and four dried leaves.
The nest measured 90mm in diameter x 55mm deep on the outside and the
inside (the cup) measured 58mm in diameter x 35mm deep. A second nest,
also by the Khatse River, contained three eggs, one of which measured 18mm
x 13mm and, like the two laid in the aviary, differed very little from those
described by Mack worth-Praed and Grant (1963) as: “white with fine brown
speckling and occasional larger spots of brown.” Maclean (1993) described
the eggs as: “white to pale greenish blue, sparingly spotted with brown and
grey mainly at the thick end.” Photos of a nest and the siskin’s habitat by the
Khatse River in Lesotho, along with colour photos of the male and female
Drakensberg Siskin, were included with our article published in 2000.
In November of the 2003/2004 breeding season, aviary pair A produced
a dutch of three white eggs with fine brown speckling, mainly at the thick
end. An incubation period of 17 days and a nestling period of 19 days were
recorded. Pair B produced a clutch of four eggs in January, for which an
incubation period of 16 days was recorded, with a nestling period of 20
days.
The successful breeding occurred in a budgerigar nest box which was
filled with earth to the rim of the entrance hole. It was lined with no more
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99454" page_id="56257331"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
38
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.380617" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257331" page_num="38" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL &amp; KONIGKRAMER - DRAKENSBERG SISKIN
Trevor Konigkramer
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993129833333333" page_id="56257331"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
The chick begs the male for food.
than two dried seeding heads of Guinea Grass Panicum maximum. Two pale
greenish-blue eggs, spotted with purplish-brown, were laid and incubated by
the female alone for 19 days. Only one of the eggs hatched and the chick
was raised to adulthood by both parents.
All of the captive birds have since been released on the border of
KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa and Lesotho.
Confined to the Drakensberg mountain range in the eastern Cape, northern
KwaZulu-Natal, north-east Free State and Lesotho, where it inhabits montane
heathlands, shrublands and grasslands, this siskin is treated now as a full
species, rather than as a subspecies of the Cape Siskin R totta, hence it was
previously listed as Serinus totta symonsi.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.94446" genericHeader="references" page_id="56257331" page_num="38" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.87868125">
Brickell, N. 1986. The Siskins of Southern Africa. Avicultural Magazine 92,1:37-39.
Brickell, N. and Konigkramer, T. 2000. Further Notes on the Drakensberg Siskin Serinus totta
symonsi. Avicultural Magazine 106,3:118-121.
Mackworth-Praed, C. W and Grant, C. H. B. 1963. Birds of the Southern Third of Africa.
Vol.2. Longman Green &amp; Co., London.
Maclean, G. L. 1993. Roberts’ Birds of Southern Africa. The Trustees of the John Voelcker
Bird Book Fund, Cape Town.
Neville Brickell, who lives in Durban, South Africa, says that the
</reference>
<bodyText confidence="0.9967098" page_id="56257331"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
government there plan to bring in stiffnew laws on the keeping of indigenous
birds. There is a nature reserve outside his window and, as he was writing to
me, he could hear two Purple-crested Turacos (Louries) Tauraco (Gallirex)
porphyreolophus calling to their mates in the tall trees below where they
feed next to a bowling green. - Ed.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998433" page_id="56257332"  page_num="39" year="" vol="">
39
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9909675" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257332" page_num="39" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEW
BIRD SENSE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998065594594594" page_id="56257332"  page_num="39" year="" vol="">
Prof. Tim Birkhead has written another book about birds that is scientific
yet a pleasure to read and contains a wealth of information and insights
relating to the behaviour of birds.
Although Bird Sense: What It’s Like to Be a Bird is about the senses of
birds, it is not a dry academic volume and includes detours into the author’s
travels and stories relating to his and other peoples’ personal experiences of
both wild and captive birds.
The format and chapter headings: Seeing, Hearing, Touch, Taste, Smell,
Magnetic Sense and Emotion, might suggest that this is an academic text
book. In that it covers so much of the history of the science of bird senses,
it could certainly assist in this purpose, but is clearly aimed at and able to
reach a much wider audience. The enquiring readers’ needs are met by a
notes section and extensive bibliography and a glossary assists with technical
terms which may be less familiar to some readers.
“Buggered is how most New Zealanders describe their bird fauna and it
is”, to quote the first line of the preface, which whilst perhaps not setting the
tone for the rest of the book, does indicate just how accessible this book is.
We get good science, the most up to date thinking and theories, combined
with a reader experience more akin to a compelling storybook.
Katrina van Grouw’s pencil illustrations, which are frontispieces to each
chapter, are excellent and enjoyable. At times the scientist in me would
have liked more illustrations related to the structure of sense organs and
the birder in me would have enjoyed more illustrations of some of the more
exciting birds. However, this would have interrupted the text and may have
distracted from the read.
I could not help but feel envious when reading of the author’s experiences
in New Zealand where he saw Kakapos, in Ecuador where he saw Oilbirds
and in the swamps of Florida where he saw Pileated Woodpeckers whilst
searching for the Holy Grail - the presumed extinct Ivory-billed Woodpecker.
Birders’ tales indeed and stories here and there about other engaging
ornithologists add additional interest to the book.
So do birds feel envy, pain, fear or pleasure? Well there is evidence
suggesting some birds may experience pain, fear and pleasure. Some of
these questions are taken up in the chapter on emotions, and others in the
chapter on touch. For ourselves this involves the appreciation and bringing
together of so many senses - both emotional and physical. Tim Birkhead
suggests that the brief touch of a “cloacal kiss” for many birds may suggest a
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.990239" page_id="56257333"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
40
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.95205" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257333" page_num="40" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEW
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99788303125" page_id="56257333"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
shorter and lesser experience. However, other birds including the Red-billed
Buffalo Weaver, copulate for a much longer period. He describes how one
of his research students stimulated a male buffalo weaver and brought it to
ecstatic orgasm by stroking its abdomen.
Most fascinating is the fact that the eyes of some birds have two foveas
(sensitive areas on their retinas where light is focused), the functions of
which are to enable the bird to have excellent distant vision and good close
vision, with one fovea for each purpose. Falcons and shrikes are two groups
of birds which have two foveas and we learn how Dutch birdcatchers once
employed shrikes to assist in detecting and catching falcons.
Perhaps as fascinating is the fact that birds may see differently with their
left and right eyes and use these for different tasks. Even more challenging
to understand is not only that some birds can sense magnetic fields but that
with one species, experimental work indicates this is sensed through the
bird’s right eye. How weird is that?
There are various theories to explain the amazing ability of birds to
navigate, these include smell, sight and learning landmarks, the use of a
sun compass and a star compass or combinations of these. In order to
navigate birds need both a map to determine where they are and a compass
to determine the direction which they should travel. Many birds, especially
oceanic seabirds, have a well developed sense of smell that may assist their
navigation and this is perhaps more surprisingly also true of homing pigeons.
Other theories attach greater importance to birds using vision or having a
magnetic sense. Recent experimental work suggests that the European
Robin requires both visual and magnetic senses through its right eye to
provide the compass direction needed to navigate. This may then be used
in combination with a map detecting the strength of the magnetic field by
providing magnetite receptors in the beak.
Are you still with me? This is really amazing stuff and although a theory
that remains controversial this, as with all science, must be retested and
validated. If this and similar questions about bird behaviour excite you as
much as they do me, then I can really recommend this book.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.6290326">
Bird Sense: What It s Like to Be a Bird by Tim Birkhead, with illustrations
by Katrina van Grouw, 265 pages, hardback, is published by Bloomsbury
Publishing, London, Berlin, New York &amp; Sydney. ISBN: 978-1408-2013-1.
It is also available as an e-book. ISBN: 978-1408-2871-7. Price £16.99.
Roger Wilkinson
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998703" page_id="56257334"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
41
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9823005" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257334" page_num="41" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
AN EXTRAORDINARY SUCCESS STORY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9794594" page_id="56257334"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
The world’s largest bird park, Weltvogelpark Walsrode (formerly
Vogelpark Walsrode) in Germany, celebrates its 50th Anniversary this year.
To mark the occasion, many new attractions are being unveiled including a
new hummingbird breeding centre.
As mentioned earlier (p.32), it was the first collection in the world to breed
toucans, when it succeeded in breeding four young Green-billed Toucans
Ramphastos dicolorus in 1965, a few years after the opening of the park.
Other species bred for the first time at Weltvogelpark Walsrode include
the Greater Bird-oL Paradise Paradisaea apoda , Secretary Bird Sagittarius
serpentarius , Giant Coua Coua gigas , Blue Coua C. caerulea , Knobbed
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.59243775" page_id="56257334"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
Hombill Aceros cassidix and Silvery-cheeked Hombill Bycanistes brevis.
* * *
A SAD FAREWELL
As Weltvogelpark Walsrode celebrates its 50th Anniverary (see first
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.991803318181818" page_id="56257334"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
news item), another famous collection, that at Leeds Castle Aviary in Kent,
has closed. According to the official guidebook it was opened by HRH
Princess Alexandra on May 25th 1988. Lady Baillie, the owner of Leeds
Castle, who died in 1974, had introduced Black Swans Cygnus atratus onto
the moat in the 1930s, but they appear not to have survived the Second
World War and a new pair arrived in the early 1950s. Lady Baillie also
kept Australian finches and was particularly fond of Australian parakeets
and the blue and yellow mutations of the Ring-necked Parakeet Psittacula
krameri. Her first bird keeper was Peter Taylor, who had previously been
a gardener on the estate.
The first Curator of Birds, David Franks, who I believe was an American
who had previously worked at either San Diego Zoo or Wild Animal Park,
or possibly both, described progress on the construction of The (new) Aviary
(in reality a series of aviaries) in the Avicultural Magazine Vol.92, No.l,
pp.50-51 (1986) and in Vol.95, No.2, pp.100-101 (1989), Ken Lawrence
described the society’s first visit in the summer of 1988.
Three notable UK first breedings were achieved in the 1990s, that of Von
der Decken’s Hombill Tockus deckeni in 1990, Fischer’s Turaco Tauraco
fischeri in 1992 and the Crowned Hombill T. alboterminatus in 1997. They
also succeeded in breeding the Toco Toucan Ramphastos toco. It is difficult
now to remember back to a time when Laura Gardner was not Curator of
Birds at Leeds Castle Aviary, so closely is she associated with it and its
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997912" page_id="56257335"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
42
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.928039" genericHeader="method" page_id="56257335" page_num="42" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99880375" page_id="56257335"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
breeding successes and for her work with the Blue-crowned Laughingthrash
Dryonastes courtoisi, both here and in China. After more than 23 years,
however, Laura has now left Leeds Castle and I am sure members will want
to send their best wishes to her for the future.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.824535" genericHeader="method" page_id="56257335" page_num="42" year="" vol="">
* * sjs
RARE DUCKLINGS HATCHED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9643826875" page_id="56257335"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
Eighteen Madagascar Pochard Ayihya innotata ducklings have been
hatched in Madagascar. The birds are part of a captive-breeding programme
overseen by staff from the Durrell Wildlife Conservation Trust (formerly
Jersey Zoo) and the Wildfowl &amp; Wetlands Trust (WWT).
This species was until recently thought to be extinct, but thee a small
surviving population was discovered on Lake Matsaborimena. This appears
to be far from ideal for them and initial investigations suggest there is
not enough food for the birds and this may explain why so few ducklings
survive. Some potentially more suitable lakes have been identified, but the
relocation of the species to these lakes will depend on the support of the local
community, many of whom earn their livelihood from fishing.
Contrary to some reports, these are not the first captive-bred Madagascar
Pochard ducklings. This species was bred by Jean Delacour in France and
was also bred in the Netherlands and the UK in the 1930s. The parents were
presumably birds collected by C. S. Webb on Lake Alaotra - who stated that
it was confined to that lake.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.855802" page_id="56257335"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.994544" genericHeader="method" page_id="56257335" page_num="42" year="" vol="">
AMONG THE FIRST TO BREED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997614307692308" page_id="56257335"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
Lorikeets are always among the first species to begin breeding at Loro
Parque and by mid-February, Rainbow Lorikeets Trichoglossus haematodus
moluccanus , Forsten’s Lorikeet I h. forsteni and the pale-headed/blue-
headed subspecies T h. caeruleiceps , the Scaly-breasted Lorikeet I
chlorolepidotus and Goldie’s Lorikeet Psitteuteles goldiei , as well as the
Yellow-streaked Lory Chalcopsitta sintillata. Black Lory C. atra and Purple-
bellied Lory Lorius hypoinochrous devittatus, already had young. So too
did a pair of Mindanao (Mount Apo/Johnstone’s) Lorikeets T Johnstoniae,
which was particularly pleasing. Concerned that all of its pairs of this species
were closely related, last year a new unrelated male was acquired and paired
with one of the females already at Loro Parque, and it is this pair which has
produced young. It is an important step forward in preserving this species
in captivity. It is kept now in only four European zoos, with the number
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700161" genericHeader="method" page_id="56257336" page_num="43" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99981" page_id="56257336"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997727333333333" page_id="56257336"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
fluctuating between 20-25 birds. It has more-or-less disappeared from private
collections. The European Breeding Programme (EEP) for this lorikeet is
coordinated by the Loro Parque Fundacion (LPF).
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.838273" page_id="56257336"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.63753" genericHeader="method" page_id="56257336" page_num="43" year="" vol="">
OF SIGNIFICANT CONCERN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.959278916666667" page_id="56257336"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
Following a meeting hosted by Chester Zoo in 2011 to discuss the
management of threatened Asian birds, which highlighted the Javan Green
Magpie Cissa ihalassina as a species of significant concern, Roger Wilkinson
the zoo&amp;apos;s Head of Field Conservation and Research and Andrew Owen, the
zoo’s Curator of Birds, travelled to Indonesia to help develop a project to
conserve this species. With the support of Chester Zoo, the Javan-based
Cikananga Conservation Center is developing a breeding programme for the
Javan Green Magpie using birds recovered from the bird trade. The project
also hopes to carry out further searches for this species in the wild, which
Roger and Andrew failed to find during their short stay.
Roger and Andrew travelled onto Bali to see the work that is being
done to conserve the Bali Starling Leucopsar rothschildi and discuss how
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.5502564" page_id="56257336"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
Chester Zoo can help. They visited the Begawan Foundation Bali Starling
Release Programme and took part in the project’s biannual bird census on
Nusa Penida.
* sfs
*
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.710139" genericHeader="method" page_id="56257336" page_num="43" year="" vol="">
ANIMALS IN THE BLOOD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.909032214285714" page_id="56257336"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
Animals in the Blood: The Ken Smith Story , a biography of “Gerald
Durrell’s Right-Hand Man” by Russell Tofts, has just been published by The
Bartlett Society, 6 Queen Street, Dawlish, Devon EX7 9HB, UK (website;
www.zoohistory.co.uk). Price £16.99, plus £3.99 p&amp;p.
Smith and Dune I! met when they were both trainee keepers at Whipsnade
Zoo and Smith accompanied Durrell on his second expedition to Cameroon
and his subsequent expedition to Guyana, as well as undertaking several
of his own expeditions. He later became Superintendent of Paignton Zoo,
helped set up Jersey Zoo (now the Durrell Wildlife Conservation Trust)
and had his own zoo at Exmouth in Devon. Frank Woolham remembered
working with him at Belle Vue Zoo, Manchester.
For many years, Ken Smith was a member of the Avicultural Society,
whose name often cropped up in News &amp; Views and who wrote several
articles which appeared in the magazine.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997799" page_id="56257337"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
44
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9785255" genericHeader="method" page_id="56257337" page_num="44" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
UNDER NEW OWNERSHIP
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.962595222222222" page_id="56257337"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
Umgeni River Bird Park, Durban, South Africa, opened in 1984 by the
late Dr Alan Abrey and sold in 1996, prior to his retirement, to Tsogo Sun
International, was in 2010, bought by the local municipality, which plans
to turn it into one of eThekwini’s leading attractions.
A lot of renovations have been made and many new species of birds
have been added to the collection. Those visitors can see include South
Africa’s National Bird the Blue or Stanley Crane Anthropoides paradisea ,
Blue-headed Macaws Primolius couloni , Palm Cockatoos Probosciger
aterrimus , a Nicobar Pigeon Caloena nicobarica (apparently the only one in
South Africa), Great Hombills Buceros bicornis , Southern Ground Hombills
Bucorvus leadbeateri and Pink-backed Pelicans Pelecanus rufescens. All
of the flamingos in a photo accompanying the story appear to be Greater
Flamingos Phoenicopterus roseus. Species breeding there are said to include
a Bam Owl Tyco alba , African Spoonbill Platalea alba , Golden Conure
Guaruba guarouba , Blue-winged Kookaburra Dacelo leachii and various
lorikeets.
The park has a free fl ight bird show, which has grown to be a favourite
amongst visitors, and also offers educational programmes.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.892557714285714" page_id="56257337"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
* * *
WHISTLING LIKE AN OTTER
Simon Bmslund, Curator of Birds at Loro Parque, has observed that the
male Edwards’s Fig Parrot Psittaculirostris edwardsii , whose aviary is just
in front of the enclosure housing the Asian or Oriental Small-clawed Otters
Amblonyx cinereus , mimics the whistles of these small otters.
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.952026" genericHeader="method" page_id="56257337" page_num="44" year="" vol="">
RUNNING FOR THE SPOON-BILLED SANDPIPER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990905833333333" page_id="56257337"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
Nigel Hewston completed the London Marathon in 4 hours, 19 minutes,
35 seconds, which was slightly slower than he had hoped. At the last count
Nigel had raised over £2,000 (approx. US$3,000), with hundreds more
promised. The Avicultural Society donated £200 (approx. US$300).
The money will go towards an ambitious conservation project to help
conserve the dwindling population of the Critically Endangered Spoon¬
billed Sandpiper Eurynorhynchus pygmeus , of which as few as 200 birds
may survive.
An expedition to Chukotka in eastern Siberia by the Wildfowl &amp; Wetlands
Tmst (WWT) and its Russian partners succeeded in rearing 13 birds, which
were brought to the UK and are now housed in a purpose-built breeding
facility at Slimbridge and should be old enough to breed next year
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997309" page_id="56257338"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
45
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.971219666666667" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257338" page_num="45" year="" vol="">
OBITUARIES
RAYMOND SAWYER
THE END OF AN ERA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.973650416666666" page_id="56257338"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
Raymond Sawyer, President of the Avicultural Society, died on February
21st 2012, He was 87 years old. Raymond joined the Avicultural Society
in 1949 and succeeded his late wife Ruth as President in 2007, having
previously been a Vice President for several years and a long-serving
Council Member.
There must be very few people in the world of aviculture in the past 50-60
years who Raymond did not know. He had been a friend of almost all of the
notable aviculturists of the period. Jean Delacour (the doyen of aviculturists)
had been a dear friend, so too had Dick de Quincey and Sydney Porter (who
in 1946 had been the first aviculturist in the UK to breed the Kea), other
friends included Ruth’s father Alfred Ezra, John Spedan Lewis, The Duke
of Bedford and Herbert Whitley (the founder of Paignton Zoo). Sir David
Attenborough, a long-time friend, was among the guests who gathered at
Chestnut Lodge to celebrate Raymond’s 87th birthday last August, so too
were Dr Henry Quinque and his wife, who flew over from France specially
to join the celebration.
In the mid-1950s, when I began working in the Bird House at London
Zoo, Raymond was a regular visitor and was a leading exhibitor, who took
most of the top awards at the leading bird shows. He won the Supreme Award
at the National Exhibition of Cage &amp; Aviary Birds four times in the 1950s:
in 1952 with a Ruby-Topaz Hummingbird, in 1955 with a King Bird-of-
Paradise, in 1958 with an Andean (Scarlet) Cock-of-the-Rock and in 1959
with a Streamer-tailed Hummingbird.
For several years Raymond was responsible for the livestock kept in
the parks and open spaces of the Greater London Council, which included
the zoos at Crystal Palace and Battersea Park. In Vol.103, No.2, pp.49-66
of the magazine (1997), Raymond wrote about the first twenty-five years at
Cobham, during which he succeeded in breeding 16 species for the first time
in the UK. These included the Splendid and Emerald Starlings, the Violet
Turaco, Masked Crimson Tanager, Blue Whistling Thrush, Black-necked and
Black-winged Stilts and Wattled Japana. The Blue-bellied Roller (1998) and
more recently the Long-toed Lapwing, along with some as yet undocumented
species, may bring the final total to 20 or more UK first breedings.
Raymond often became tearful when recalling his many friends who are
no longer with us, but we also laughed a lot. He recently recalled how in the
1950s he persuaded the actress Jayne Mansfield (the US blonde bombshell
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997069" page_id="56257339"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
46
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.932307" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257339" page_num="46" year="" vol="">
OBITUARIES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9632619" page_id="56257339"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
and a big star at the time) to open his local bird show in East London and
after the show invited her and her husband back to his home for tea. As they
were leaving, Jayne Mansfield lost her footing on the narrow staircase and
fell on top of Raymond. Her husband, the strongman Mickey Hargitay (Mr
Universe 1955), tried to save her but also lost his footing and he too landed
on top of Raymond at the foot of the stairs. Fortunately nobody was hurt and
Raymond turned a potentially serious accident into an hilarious story.
Raymond loved to talk about the “good old days” and just a few weeks
before he died, I had promised to go up and spend two or three days with
him at Chestnut Lodge.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.285789">
Malcolm Ellis
</subsectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.715994" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56257339" page_num="46" year="" vol="">
MEMORIES OF RAYMOND
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.935578222222222" page_id="56257339"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
A LUMINARY OF THE BIRD WORLD
I first got to know Raymond in the 1960s when I worked for John
Yealland, Curator of Birds at London Zoo. Raymond was already one of
the luminaries of the bird world in England and he and fellow aviculturists
such as Viscount Chaplin, Newton Steele, Harry Horswell, Fred Johnson
and Alfredo Marques exchanged birds and told wonderful stories.
As well as a love of birds, Raymond and I also shared a love of horses.
Raymond had been a successful show jumper in his teens and had competed
against both Pat and Stirling Moss. When I first visited the home he shared
with his father, I was struck by the large aquariums of freshwater and
tropical fish and the wonderful aviaries he had set up in the small back
garden. Not only was Raymond an expert in the care of rare and beautiful
birds, his talent extended to the wonderful way in which he had planted out
the aviaries. He always said that his love of birds was sparked by a canary
given to his mother, which he took over and cared for when he was just five
years of age. His first exotic bird was a hill mynah purchased from Palmers
Pet Stores in Camden Town.
Later in life, visits to Palmers (which was just down the road from
London Zoo) became a staple of his Saturday outings with his good friend
David Attenborough, as they scoured London for unusual birds and tropical
fish. His mother died when Raymond was in his late teens and Raymond
remained with his father and cared for him until his father’s death. It was
then that Ruth Ezra invited Raymond to live at Chestnut Lodge and, with
Ruth’s encouragement, Raymond used his extraordinary talent to transform
the grounds into the magical place everyone so adored.
Raymond will be greatly missed by the avicultural world and especially
those of us who were lucky enough to be his friends.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.250098">
Jane Cooper
</subsectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.826035" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257340" page_num="47" year="" vol="">
OBITUARIES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994202" page_id="56257340"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
47
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.972562" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56257340" page_num="47" year="" vol="">
THE WORLD’S LEADING SOFTBILL SPECIALIST
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9234475" page_id="56257340"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
Raymond was acknowledged as the world’s leading exotic softbill
specialist. It seems unlikely that any other individual kept more species or
had a greater depth of knowledge on the subject. At Chestnut Lodge, with
its park-like grounds, he was able to keep a wide range of birds but it was
always the softbills which were closest to his heart. A few parrots featured
in the collection, including mutation kakarikis and rosellas, as well as a pair
of Eclectus and he formerly bred Keas.
Raymond was known primarily as an aviculturist but his true genius lay
with plants. He had an unmatched gift for creating extraordinarily beautiful
yet natural settings in aviaries and on the patios where his remarkable
collection of bonsai, cycads, shrubs and plants formed such a wonderful
display that no one who saw it could ever forget. An aviary bigger and
more beautifully planted than the average lawn, a tropical house filled with
gems such as cotingas and sunbirds among flowering vines and palms,
and numerous smaller aviaries, some enclosed to protect the more delicate
species, delighted the eye.
The President’s Garden Party was always the highlight of the society’s
social calendar and, like Ruth before him, with great generosity Raymond
donated to the society all of the money raised by ticket sales. He regularly
opened the garden to local organisations for charity and as the fame of the
collection grew, literally thousands of people visited it as part of the National
Gardens Scheme.
Raymond was also an aquarist of note, keeping the then difficult Discus
Fish back in the 1960s. He never lost his interest in tropical fish. The Koi pond
at Chestnut Lodge was always a focal point. Raymond had a deep love of
animals, especially dogs and was a successful show jumper in his youth.
Those who knew him well, as I had done since 1962, relished his (often
wicked) humour and will miss him sorely. Everyone is saying the same: “It is
the end of an era.” The days of big collections in park-like settings have now
gone, along with a remarkable man who was truly a unique individual.
Rosemary Low
PROF. J. R. HODGES
Recently the weekly publication Cage &amp; Aviary Birds (February 15th,
p.2, 2012) reported that only 21 Orange-bellied Parrots survive in the wild.
Recent research undertaken at Melaleuca in Tasmania, where the birds breed
(which Bob and his wife and two friends visited in October 1997), found
only eight females among the surviving group of birds. All hope is now
pinned on a captive breeding programme.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997918" page_id="56257341"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
48
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.931069" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257341" page_num="48" year="" vol="">
OBITUARIES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.992182142857143" page_id="56257341"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
Knowing Bob’s strongly held view that a captive breeding programme
involving reputable aviculturists should have been instituted many years ago,
I cut out the report and posted it to Bob and was saddened to leam from his
daughter Kos, that her father had died peacefully on February 9th 2012. Bob
joined the Avicultural Society in 1947. He took a keen interest in all groups
of birds but, I believe, specialised in grass parakeets (and possibly Gouldians)
and in VoL81,No.2, pp.61-63 (1975) wrote about his experiences obtaining
and breeding the blue mutation of the Splendid Grass Parakeet.
Following the death of Mary Harvey, after a prolonged period of poor
health, Bob stepped in and picked up the pieces and, despite the difficulty
he had getting sufficient material, edited the magazine from 1991-1993.
He was elected a Vice President in 1985, became Chairman of the Council
following the death of Harry Horswell in 1990 and was later elected an
Hon. Life Member.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.403742">
Malcolm Ellis
</subsectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.888553" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56257341" page_num="48" year="" vol="">
WENDY DUGGAN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.979047" page_id="56257341"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
We regret to report the death of Wendy Duggan of Putney on February
21st. Wendy was known for her great affection for parrots, especially
cockatoos, with whom she shared her home - probably since at least the
1950s. For many years she worked for the BBC in connection with children’s
programmes. Her Sulphur-crested Cockatoo, named Katoo, became famous
for his regular appearances on the children’s TV programme Playschool.
Wendy joined the Avicultural Society in 1961 and was a familiar face at the
wine and cheese evenings at the Linnean Society and at other gatherings
and was also an active member of the Southern Foreign Bird Club from its
inception in 1963. She exhibited cockatoos at the annual shows and won
many awards with them. She was also a Fellow of the Zoological Society
of London.
Wendy was always delighted to see friends and always interested in their
news. She had a fund of stories from the past and was a most entertaining
raconteur. Wendy and her husband shared an interest in art and antiques
- especially any object connected with birds and other animals. Rumour
has it that when the Queen Mother decided she would like a cockatoo, she
asked Wendy for one and in exchange Wendy received several bottles of a
very expensive brandy!
In recent years Wendy had sadly suffered from very poor health.
Condolences are offered to her husband Ron.
Rosemary Low and Rosemary Wiseman
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.984511" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56257342" page_num="" year="" vol="">
COLLABORATING ON NEW TECHNIQUE
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.286287">
Loro Parque Fundacion of Tenerife, Spain and the University of Giessen
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996494958333333" page_id="56257342"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
in Germany are collaborating on the use of a new technique, using sperm
collection and artificial insemination (AI), in an attempt to increase the
number of Spix’s Macaws Cyanopsitta spixii being bred.
There are fewer than 80 captive birds in the recovery programme and
reproduction within the population is slow. The main objective therefore
is to increase the number of young birds being bred. Although successful
with humans and with many other mammals and some other types of birds,
sperm collection and artificial insemination has had only very limited success
with parrots. However, the use of this new technique shows very promising
results and, hopefully, will lead to improved breeding success with this
incredibly rare macaw.
The initial phase of the project began in 2009/2010 and during that time
the technique was used successfully for the first time to collect sperm from
birds at the Spix’s Macaw Breeding Centre of the Loro Parque Fundacion.
Successful artificial insemination, however, is yet to take place. Loro
Parque Fundacion has nine macaws, which are on loan from the Brazilian
Government, which gave its permission for the technique to be tested. Trials
will also take place on birds at Al Wabra Wildlife Preservation in Qatar.
During the same period, the new technique was used to successfully
collect semen and artificially inseminate over 100 species of large parrots in
the large and diverse Loro Parque Fundacion collection. It is a significant step
forward and, this pioneering first phase, will act as an excellent foundation for
establishing a method of cryopreservation (frozen storage) and the eventual
establishment of a parrot sperm bank.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.577278" page_id="56257342"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.938159" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56257342" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AUTUMN SOCIAL MEETING
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.884925333333333">
The Autumn Social Meeting &amp; AGM will be held on Saturday, September
22nd, at Christopher Marler’s collection at Weston Underwood, Olney,
Buckinghamshire MK46 5JR. Further details will follow later.
</reference>
<table confidence="0.955498535714286" page_id="56257343"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
3 9088 01663 2655
CONTENTS
J
Breeding the Buff-necked Ibis Theristicus caudatus
at Blackbrook Zoological Park
by Nicola Sumbland.1
Dietary considerations when breeding Montezuma Quail
Cyrtonyx montezumae
by Jack Eitniear and Terry Becherer.6
Breeding the Spectacled Laughingthrush Rhinocichla mitrata
by Llyr Davies.12
Looking back at Raymond’s first twenty-five years at Cobham
by Malcolm Ellis.16
Breeding the Toco Toucan Ramphastos toco and
Black-necked Aracari Pteroglossus aracari at
Weltvogelpark Walsrode
by Jurgen Vielguth, Kerstin Kirchhofel, Timo Allner
and Anne Eloppmann.32
A final note on the Drakensberg Siskin Pseudochloroptila symonsi
by Neville Brickell and Trevor Konigkramer.37
Book Review
Bird Sense.39
News &amp; Views.41
Obituaries
Raymond Sawyer.45
Prof J. R. Hodges.47
Wendy Duggan.48
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
</table>
</algorithms>