<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.7109084" page_id="56259740"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 116
No. 4
2010
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99074" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259741" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.944229375" page_id="56259741"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2010 as for 2009: British
Isles #18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please).
The subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the
Society later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of
the AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.685591" page_id="56259741"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, SHERATON LODGE, STATION ROAD, SOUTHMINSTER,
ESSEX CM0 7EW, UK.
</construct>
<bodyText confidence="0.9140586" page_id="56259741"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Barclays Bank, Southminster Branch. Please quote
Account No. 13296954, Sort Code 20 54 30, and ensure you send your
name as the account reference, or else we cannot match payments. In case
of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and Treasurer at the address
above, or e-mail: otusscops@talktalk.net
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have not
been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of a
particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history. Articles
should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the scientific
names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given. References
cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line drawings,
black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular point in
the article will be used where possible and should be clearly captioned. If
authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when submitting the
article and write their name on the back of each photograph. Tables and
graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be aware of
the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of the page
which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997594" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259741" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982475333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7945055" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259742" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.287155" page_id="56259742"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 116 - No. 4 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2010
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.902427" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259742" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE RAINFOREST DRAGONS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.977190733333333" page_id="56259742"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Jo Gregson
There are three species of cassowary. The largest is the Southern
Cassowary Casuarius casuarius found living in New Guinea and the Aru
Islands and also north-eastern Queensland, Australia. Then there is the
Northern (Single-wattled or One-wattled) Cassowary C. unappendiculatus
found living in the lowlands of New Guinea, Yapen Island and west Papuan
islands, followed by the Dwarf Cassowary C. bennetti found living in New
Guinea, Yapen Island and New Britain. As many as 42 subspecies have
been described.
Walter Rothschild (1901) described eight species and 17 subspecies.
The plates by John Keulemans that accompanied Rothschild's notes were
published in the Transactions of the Zoological Society of London of that
year. Keulemans worked from live birds, so one would assume that they
are accurate. From Rothschild's descriptions of those imported into Europe,
many would seem to have been C. c. beccarii and C. c. violicollis , both
found on the Aru Islands. These are big and aggressive birds with two red
markings running from the base of the lower mandible to the top of the
wattles. More recently birds from the Aru Islands have been grouped together
and reclassified as a single subspecies C. c. aruensis. However, within the
current European zoo population there is quite a lot of variation in size and,
I suspect, there is a mix of birds from different parts of the New Guinea
region. Australian birds have a plain blue throat and are often smaller and
seem to be more biddable (docile) than some of the others.
All three species are under pressure, with the primary threats coming from
deforestation, busy roads, domestic dogs and feral pigs. In some areas they
are also hunted by man for food. On top of this climate change is playing
a part with the rainforests beginning to become drier.
In captivity
There is a good number of cassowaries still being held in zoos. They can
live for up to 40 years, although it is unlikely that females continue to lay
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999315" page_id="56259743"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
146
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.863568" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259743" page_num="146" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - CASSOWARIES
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.47238">
Keuleman's illustration of
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97208325" page_id="56259743"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
Casuarius c. beccarii published in 1901.
Many of those imported into Europe seem
to have been Casuarius c. beccarii and
Casuarius c. violicollis (above).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.792593" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259744" page_num="147" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - CASSOWARIES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999033" page_id="56259744"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
147
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998228571428571" page_id="56259744"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
Casuarius c. australis, the Australian
subspecies, later became
Casuarius c. johnstonii.
A trio of Southern Cassowary chicks three to four weeks of age.
eggs beyond 20 years of age and probably stop some time before this.
If the large ratites have any claim to intelligence, then the flag-bearer
is the cassowary. Very fast, powerful birds, with an air of indifference,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998928" page_id="56259745"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
148
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.957782" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259745" page_num="148" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - CASSOWARIES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998536463414634" page_id="56259745"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
cassowaries can and have killed people. Females are especially ill-tempered
and even the males keep out of their sight until their services are required
for mating, incubating the eggs and rearing the chicks.
Cassowaries can run at speeds approaching 50km/h (30mph) and jump
1.5m (approx. 5ft) from a standstill. The legs are robust with three toes on
each foot and with each toe armed with a long, stout claw. When annoyed
cassowaries display their full throat colour and make loud, gutteral rasping
noises and attack by jumping up and kicking forward with both feet. It
had been said that the mythical dragon stories arose from early sightings of
cassowaries. It is not easy to know when a cassowary is in a bad mood, as
they often stand quietly preening prior to an attack. It is advisable to err on
the side of caution and manage them by means of gates and sliding doors.
Cassowaries being forest creatures need plenty of cover and like many
rainforest animals their feet cannot cope with hard, dry surfaces and, for
this reason, they should have access to mud and a pool of water. Given the
opportunity, they will spend much of their time standing in water. In the
past collections often exhibited these birds quite poorly and not in keeping
with their natural history.
At least two paddocks are required to safely manage and breed
cassowaries. Here at Paignton Zoo we have five paddocks, all connected to
each other, so that we can move the birds without the need to capture them.
The connecting gates are fitted with thumb latches and can, if need be, swung
closed quickly from the outside of the paddock. Each paddock has a heated
house, which is connected by a dividing door to the next stall.
Cassowaries are prone to slip on hard, smooth surfaces and their legs can
become splayed. To help prevent this all house floors and pools must have
a rough finish with a wooden float. Likewise, the floor of any crate used to
transport them must have a slatted floor. The use of limestone as a hard-
standing substrate should be avoided, as cassowaries will avoid walking on it
and will soon become lame if forced to stand on it for any length of time.
For much of the year cassowaries live a solitary life and need to be
housed separately. They do not acknowledge each others' presence until
early spring, when they are seen standing close together against the fence
that separates them. Pairing can be a dangerous time for the male. He is
safe so long as he stands close to the female and, therefore, rarely leaves
her side during courtship. After he has copulated with her, she will attack
him and, for this reason, it is important that there is thick vegetation in the
enclosure. If he can run away and get out of sight of her, he will soon be
forgotten. Eventually, he will work his way back to her side and the process
will begin again.
The female chooses the nest site and lays up to five green eggs. If she
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.792591" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259746" page_num="149" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - CASSOWARIES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999321" page_id="56259746"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
149
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.962961740740741" page_id="56259746"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
selects an unsuitable site, it is possible to move the clutch after the last egg
has been laid and before the male begins incubation. The eggs range in
size from 149mn&gt; 140mm x 99mm-96mm. Here at Paignton Zoo we have
recorded the following egg weights: 850g, 838g, 847g, 824g, 735g 762g,
754g. The first eggs laid are usually smaller. The female is removed before
hatching takes place.
Chicks
Chicks are reared on a low protein fruit diet. Foods that are coloured red
or yellow are eagerly investigated and help get them feeding during the first
few days. Within the first week, as the chicks become steadier on their feet,
they are taken outside each day for light exercise. To rear strong chicks it is
important that they grow slowly and get plenty of exercise.
As they grow stronger, each day they are taken for longer walks in our
woodland and allowed bathe in a stream. By the time they reach 10 months of
age they need to do a lot of walking and have a run each day. Chicks will walk
with a keeper until they are about 18 months of age, after which it becomes
harder to engage their attention and prevent them from wandering.
From 18 months of age cassowaries can be sexed by someone with an
experienced eye. Females are larger and longer-backed by then and are
already showing signs of becoming stroppy. At three years of age they have
acquired full black plumage and at this age keepers no longer work in the
enclosures with them.
All in all, cassowaries are very rewarding birds to display and so long
as they are managed correctly can be high profile exhibits.
Jo Gregson is Curator of Birds at Paignton Zoo Environmental Park,
Totnes Road, Paignton. Devon TQ4 7EU. UK. She is European Studbook
Co-ordinator for the Wrinkled Hornbill, Co-Chairman of the EAZA
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.866638166666667" page_id="56259746"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
(European Association of Zoos and Aquaria) Pigeons and Doves TAG
(Taxon Advisory Group) and Vice-Chair of the EAZA Ratites TAG. E-mail:
jo.gregson@paigntonzoo. org. uk
* * *
SOCIAL MEETINGS 2011
On Saturday, May 7th, the society has been invited to visit Richard
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.569667" page_id="56259746"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
Abrey's collection at Edwardstone, Sudbury, Suffolk.
The President's Garden Party will be held on the afternoon of Saturday,
July 16th, at Chestnut Lodge, Cobham, Surrey.
It has now been confirmed that the Autumn Meeting will be on Saturday,
September 24th, at Paultons Park, Ower, Romsey, Hampshire.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.959344" page_id="56259747"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
150
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.521158" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259747" page_num="150" year="" vol="">
THE CUCKOO FINCH Anomalospiza imberbis
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.943992352941176" page_id="56259747"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
by Neville Brickell
Introduction
This most attractive species is unfortunately rarely seen in captivity,
except in the aviaries of local birdkeepers here in South Africa. It was first
described from East Africa by Cabanis in 1868 and described originally as
a new species of canary Crithagra imberbis. Thirty-six years later, in 1904,
however, on the basis of its wing shape, the outer primaries being like those
of the bishops/weavers Euplectes spp. and Quelea spp., it was thought instead
to be related to the weavers (Ploceidae) and in some recent field guides can
still be found alongside them listed as the Parasitic Weaver. Payne (1997)
wrote that preliminary molecular studies of mtDNA sequences indicate that
the Cuckoo Finch and the viduine whydahs and indigobirds are each others'
closest relatives. Clements (2007) places it at the end of the 20-strong
Viduidae family, but retains the name Parasitic Weaver.
Description
Length AViin-Sm (11 cm-13cm). In the field the male can easily be
confused with a canary ( Serinus sp.), except that he has a short bill that is
very thick at the base. It is black during the rainy season and pale brown
in the dry season. (Cuckoo Finches in West Africa have noticeably smaller
bills than those in East and southern Africa.) In the dry season, when males
are in fresh plumage they are olive greenish above, including the crown,
and unstreaked yellow below. During the rainy season, when they breed,
males are in worn plumage and are brighter, paler and more streaked above,
with the head, especially the forehead and face, yellow. The adult female
has tawny-buff or buffy-brown upperparts, broadly streaked with black, a
yellowish-buff face with a blackish eye-stripe and finely streaked cheeks,
a buffy-white throat and a buffy-brown breast, with faint streaking on the
flanks; the belly and under tail-coverts are whitish. As the plumage becomes
worn, she becomes paler and less tawny, with sharper streaking. She looks
similar to the female Red Bishop E. orix , but has a much stubbier bill (and
a much harder bite). The juvenile Cuckoo Finch looks similar to the adult
female, but with the face, throat and breast, rich tawny-buff or orange-buff
to yellowish-buff. The belly and flanks are buff, the latter sometimes finely
streaked with black. The characteristic stubby bill is yellowish below. The
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.50834875" page_id="56259747"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
juvenile Cuckoo Finch superficially resembles a juvenile cisticola.
Voice
Various calls have been described, including a high, thin, sibilant
" tissiwick " (rising) and " tissiway " (falling), often followed by a " djzing -
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.651576" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259748" page_num="151" year="" vol="">
BKICKELL - CUCKOO FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.993575" page_id="56259748"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
151
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.349372">
Neville Brickell
Male Cuckoo Finch.
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997193" page_id="56259748"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
ji-ji" as well as a separate " dzi-bee-chew " (Zimmerman et al. 1996). The
flight call is a thin, high, hard &apos;&quot;jit-jit" or "tjkka tikka Unlike the whydahs
and indigobirds, young Cuckoo Finches do not mimic the begging calls of
the host species.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999155" page_id="56259749"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
152
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.870394" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259749" page_num="152" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - CUCKOO FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.96487275" page_id="56259749"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
Distribution
Clements (2007) lists two subspecies: A. i, imberbis found from Ethiopia
through East Africa, including Pemba Island and Zanzibar, to southern Zaire
(Democratic Republic of Congo) and south-central Africa to South Africa;
and A. L butleri found from West Africa to southern Sudan and northern Zaire
(Democratic Republic of Congo). It is generally uncommon in West and East
Africa, but becomes more plentiful in Zambia, Zimbabwe, Mozambique and
Swaziland, and uncommon again in the South African provinces of Gauteng
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.534177">
and KwaZulu-Natal
Habitat
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.975366294117647" page_id="56259749"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
Open and lightly wooded grassland with short or tall grass, especially
near damp areas, also floodplains and cultivated land, including rice paddies,
pastures and old cotton fields, as well as airfields.
Habits
Solitary, in pairs or in small or large flocks in all seasons. In non-breeding
season, forms flocks of eight to 50 birds and, occasionally, up to 200-1,000
birds (in Hwange National Park in Zimbabwe). When disturbed, often flies
up and perches on shrubs, low trees, fences and telephone wires. Roosts
in reedbeds in flocks of 300-500 birds or, more rarely, up to 1,200 birds in
non-breeding season. In south-central Africa, it is regarded as a resident
and a local, nomadic species or migrant, moving about according to the
rainfall, with numbers varying from year to year. In Zambia, large flocks
gather at permanent wetlands during the dry season and disperse during the
rains, possibly moving substantial distances. Large flocks arrive in southern
Zambia in late November, with up to 6,000 roosting in reedbeds, but all
dispersing by mid-December. The Cuckoo Finch's flight is direct and rapid,
like that of a weaver bird.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.563079">
Feeding
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999843833333333" page_id="56259749"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
Forages on the ground, pecking seeds from the surface of the soil and
also perches on the upright stems of grasses and herbs, taking seeds directly
from the seed heads. It has been recorded feeding on Golden Bristle Grass
or Golden Setaria Setaria sphacelata and Common Wild Sorghum Sorghum
verticilliflorum , as well as feeding on the large, hard and difficult to crack
seeds of sedges Scirpus spp. and sunflowers Helianthus spp The host
species rear the young on insects such as grasshoppers and caterpillars, but
the adults eat mostly grass seeds, but have been observed hawking insects
from reed stems at dusk.
In captivity in South Africa, the Cuckoo Finch is usually offered Japanese
millet, red manna, white or yellow millet and shelled sunflower seeds. In
the summer it is also offered the inflorescences of Guinea Grass Panicum
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.636167" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259750" page_num="153" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - CUCKOO FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999541" page_id="56259750"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
153
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.948518384615385" page_id="56259750"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
maximum , Barnyard Grass Echinochloa crus-galli , Jungle Rice E. colona and
Common Wild Oats Avena fatua , in both the ripe and half-ripe milky stages.
Finely ground cuttlefish bone and/or oystershell are also provided. Livefood
consists of the winged form of the Common Fungus-growing Termite
Odontotermes badius and workers of the Large Fungus-growing Termite
Macrotermes natalensis and Snouted Harvester Termite Trinervitermus sp.
It is vital that the soldiers are removed, as they can become lodged in birds'
throats and birds rarely survive their bite.
Breeding
The Cuckoo Finch breeds during the rainy season at the same time as the
grass warblers Cisticola spp. and Prinia spp., which are its host species. In
Ethiopia nestlings have been seen in August and November and in Tanzania
in May. In Zambia it breeds from January-April; in Zimbabwe it lays from
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.853400818181818" page_id="56259750"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
November-March (with 19 out of 25 records in December-February); in
Botswana from February-April; Mozambique in February; and north-eastern
South Africa from September-January/February (with 12 out of 14 records
in December-January).
The list of host species include: the Cloud Cisticola C. textrix , Croaking
Cisticola C. natalensis , Desert Cisticola C. aridulus , Fan-tailed or Zitting
Cisticola C.juncidis , Levaillant's or Tinkling Cisticola C. tinniens , Neddicky
or Pipping Cisticola C.fiulvicapilla , Pale-crowned Cisticola C. cinnamomeus ,
Pectoral-patch Cisticola C. brunnescens , Rattling Cisticola C. chiniana ,
Red-faced Cisticola C. erythrops. Singing Cisticola C. cantans , Winding
or Rufous-winged Cisticola C. galactotes and Wing-snapping Cisticola C.
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.998712117647059" page_id="56259750"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
ayresii , along with the Black-chested Prinia P. flavicans and Tawny-flanked
Prinia R subflava , most of which live in wet grassy areas.
Cisticolas usually nest close to the ground or at ground level in a tuft of
grass or a low shrub. All build an enclosed, ball-shaped nest, using blades
of dry grass to make the outer shell and incorporate live plant stems into
the walls and roof; the nest is lined with plant down. Most have a side
entrance. So far as is known, the female does most or all of the nest building
and incubation without the assistance of the male, but both sexes feed the
young. The Tawny-flanked Prinia usually nests less than lm (3ft Sin) above
the ground in a leafy shrub, sapling or tall tuft of grass or sedge, often over
shallow water or damp ground, whereas the Black-chested species usually
chooses a small, thorny tree or shrub, usually one that stands alone. Both
prinias' nests, which are made from thin lengths of green grass, which soon
fade to a dry grass colour, are oval- to pear-shaped, with an entrance near
the top of one side.
The female Cuckoo Finch lays one egg a day in sets of one to four
eggs, with a few days between sets. A total of about 30 eggs may be laid
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999697" page_id="56259751"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
154
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.883551" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259751" page_num="154" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - CUCKOO FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99427372" page_id="56259751"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
during a breeding season. The eggs vary from bluish white to greenish blue
or pale turquoise. Occasionally they may be unmarked, but are usually
spotted, speckled or blotched with red, reddish brown or purplish brown
over underlying lilac and grey markings. They measure 16.1mm-18.3mm
x 12.2mm-13mm (Hockey et al. 2005). They can usually be distinguished
by differences in colour and markings and their larger size.
The Cuckoo Finch removes one or all of the host species' eggs before
laying, sometimes before the host species' clutch is complete. One or two
Cuckoo Finch eggs may be laid in a nest, but it is not known whether or not
this is a result of more than one female laying in the same nest. They hatch
within about 14 days.
The skin of the newly-hatched chicks is dark purple above and a dark
flesh colour below, with white down on the crown, back and wings. The
gape flanges are deep orange-yellow. The tongue is purplish pink, with
large black spots near the rear. By 13 days the face and heavy eye-stripe are
cinnamon-orange, as is the throat, with the underparts fading to yellow on
the belly. The chicks, which are fed mainly insects, have an upright begging
posture, without any twists or turns of the head and neck.
The nestling/fledgling period lasts 18-20 days. They are fed for at least
10 days after fledging, then begin to feed themselves, but remain under the
care of the host species for several weeks. Two Cuckoo Finch chicks may
be reared in the same nest, but the host species' chicks rarely survive.
Natal Avicultural Society's only captive record dates back to 1966 when
two eggs, collected from the wild, were hatched and the chicks reared by a
pair of second-generation Brimstone Canaries S. sulphuratus.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.937697" genericHeader="references" page_id="56259751" page_num="154" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.940498083333333">
Clements, J. F. 2007. The Clements Checklist of the Birds of the World Sixth Edition.
Christopher Helm, London.
Hockey, R A. R., Dean, W. R. J., Ryan, P. G. (eds.) 2005. Roberts - Birds of Southern Africa
Seventh Edition. The Trustees of the John Voelcker Bird Book Fund, Cape Town.
Payne, R. B. 1997. Field identification of the brood-parasitic whydahs Vidua and Cuckoo Finch
Anomalospiza imberbis. Bulletin of the African Bird Club 4,1:18-28.
Zimmerman, D. A., Turner, D. A., Pearson, D. J. 1996. Birds of Kenya and Northern Tanzania.
Christopher Helm/A &amp; C Black, London.
Neville Brickell lives in Durban, KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa and
is Director of the Indigenous Bird Breeders Society and a Foundation
Member of the Natal Bird Breeders Society and the Rare Finch Conservation
Group.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999259" page_id="56259752"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
155
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.986845" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259752" page_num="155" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE MAGPIE SHRIKE Corvinella melanoleuca
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9819085" page_id="56259752"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
by Gary Bralsford
The Magpie Shrike is a long-tailed shrike measuring approximately
45cm (\lV 2 \n) in length, of which about 30cm (12in) is accounted for by its
long tail. Both sexes are black with white scapulars that form a V-shaped
pattern on the back; the rump is greyish-white; the secondaries and primaries
are tipped with white and there is a variable patch of white at the base of
the primaries. The female can be distinguished from the male by a patch
of white on her flanks. The juvenile is dull black above, finely barred with
rufous-brown, with the whitish scapulars tipped with brown and the flanks
blackish with brown barring and some buffy-white feathers.
It is found in Africa from south-eastern Angola in the west and south-
west Kenya and Tanzania in the east, southwards down into South Africa and
eastern Swaziland. Three subspecies are recognised: C. m. aequatorialis ,
C. m. expressa and C. m. melanoleuca. They differ from each other by the
amount of white on the wings, the shade of grey of the rump and the length of
the tail. They inhabit open acacia and broad-leaved woodland with scattered
trees, short grass and bare ground.
These shrikes are sociable birds that usually live in small groups of six
or so birds, but larger groups of 10-12, or even up to 19 (in the winter) have
been recorded. The individuals within the group interact with one another.
This appears to be based on a dominance hierarchy, with the breeding
female being the most dominant bird. Although generally shy and difficult
to approach, my birds soon settled down to aviary life. They perch as high
as possible and sit upright and often flick their tails while calling. When
my birds come together on a perch or on the ground they face one another
and perform a greeting display. This involves bowing, raising the wings
and flicking the tail, while making various whistling calls. My young birds
always perform the same greeting before begging to be fed, even after they
are weaned. The territorial behaviour is similar, with the breeding pair giving
loud whistles which usually take the form of a duet. The pair fly at intruders
and I had to wear a hat, especially when there was young in the nest, as the
pair attacked me when I went in to feed them.
In the wild these shrikes often choose a conspicuous perch on the top of
a bush or tree, from which they can scan the ground below and swoop down
on their prey. Groups tend to leave a bush or tree one by one, following
each other to the next bush or tree. Their distinctive, fluttering, undulating
flight reminds me of that of the Hoopoe Upupa epops. My birds behave in a
similar way in the aviary. I put in tubs of livefood and they swoop down and
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999562" page_id="56259753"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
156
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.862886" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259753" page_num="156" year="" vol="">
BRALSFORD - MAGPIE SHRIKE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999519902439024" page_id="56259753"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
take it - the dominant bird always being the first down. They occasionally
hawk flying insects and I sometimes throw morio worms up in the air for
them to catch. I also give them dead day-old chicks, mice and pinkies. Most
of the food is carried in the bill, but they always use a foot to hold it down
and tear off pieces.
In the wild the Magpie Shrike is confined to Africa south of the Equator,
where breeding has been recorded from August-April; the majority of
breeding though occurs from September/October-January. My birds began
breeding in March and continued through until July. They displayed with
the male feeding the female and then the two singing in duet. The female
often begged for food from the male like a youngster would, crouched in a
horizontal position with the wings slightly open, drooped and fluttering.
I bought my six Magpie Shrikes from a dealer in the Midlands (here
in the UK) and kept them together as a group. I placed them in a planted
aviary measuring 10ft x 10ft (approx. 3m x 3m). I provided several nesting
places consisting of half-open nest boxes and an old fruit bowl. The metal
fruit bowl, I fixed securely up in a comer and placed quite a few sticks in
the bottom of it and also put in some coconut fibre. Having watched an
internet video of these shrikes nesting, I realised that this would probably
be my best chance of persuading them to nest.
Several weeks later I noticed that one of the females had become very
dominant and was begging one of the males to feed her. When this happened
there was great excitement amongst the other members of the group. A week
later I noticed that the fruit bowl had been partly lined with coconut fibre
and animal hair. I watched the birds' activities on a CCTV camera I had
installed and saw that the female was doing most of the building. Following
the completion of the nest she sat in it for 10 days but no eggs were laid. I
can only put this down to what is sometimes referred to as "nest warming,"
prior to the eggs being laid. The first egg was laid a few days later. In all, a
total of four were laid over consecutive days. They were buff or yellowish,
spotted with brown and greys.
The female sat for 16 days. The male took no part other than stand
guard over the nest. When the eggs hatched there was great excitement
in the group and lots of calling and whistling. I provided tubs of small
locusts, crickets, mini-mealworms and waxworms, along with chopped-up
pinkie mice and minced (ground) beef. It was amazing to witness all of the
members of the group taking food to the nest for the chicks. There was no
aggression whatsoever.
All went well until the tenth day, when two of the chicks went missing. I
could find no trace of them and can only think that they died and were eaten.
The remaining two chicks grew rapidly and continued to be fed by all of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.591735" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259754" page_num="157" year="" vol="">
BRALSFORD - MAGPIE SHRIKE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999203" page_id="56259754"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
157
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999590676470588" page_id="56259754"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
members of the group. After 19 days in the nest one of the nestlings came to
the edge of the nest. It looked like a smaller, duller, brownish, short-tailed
version of the adults. I was excited about getting the young shrikes to this
stage, but realised that I still had a little way to go. My excitement came
to an abrupt end when on checking, I found the second chick dead in the
bottom of the nest. The older chick was stronger and was a really dominant
bird and I presume that the second chick was unable to compete with it. The
remaining chick fledged successfully but continued to be fed by members
of the group. It continued to beg for food right up until it was four months
old and was well able to look after itself.
The Magpie Shrike is a long-lived species that with careful management
can live for 10 years or more. If a dominant bird dies, another member of
the group takes its place. This happened with my birds when, while sitting
on a second clutch of eggs (there were three eggs in the second clutch), the
dominant female died. She had looked really fit and I could think of no
reason why she had succumbed. Another female paired up with the male
and the nest was relined and a clutch of three eggs was laid, but all three of
the eggs were clear.
The birds then began to moult, with the long tail feathers being shed first
and I realised that without their long tail feathers they are fairly small birds.
They are amongst the most fascinating birds I have kept. It is wonderful to
observe their social behaviour. You need to keep them in a group to observe
and study this, you would not get the same results keeping only a pair.
I have found that the only drawback to keeping shrikes is the amount
of livefood they consume, along with dead chicks and pinkie mice, which
can make them quite expensive to feed. I have tried to get them to take
softfood, but have had only limited success and have found that it is only
taken if it stuck to meat. They sampled fruit and soaked dog biscuits, but
after a while seemed to lose interest in these. Any stray mouse that ventures
into the aviary is quickly caught and eaten.
As described above, the Magpie Shrike Corvinella melanoleuca has been
bred by Gary Bralsford. This is possibly the first successful breeding of
this species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who knows of a previous
breeding is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999672" page_id="56259755"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
158
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.859992" page_id="56259755"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
W. J. C. (WILFRED) FROST: AN INCOMPLETE
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.720216" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259755" page_num="158" year="" vol="">
BIOGRAPHY
by Malcolm Ellis
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998552944444444" page_id="56259755"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
Having decided to attempt to write some biographical notes about the
late W. J. C. (Wilfred) Frost, I found it difficult to know where to begin and
very like trying to find the pieces of a jigsaw and then fit them together.
Frost was one of the small band of men who, in the days before air travel
became commonplace, sailed to the tropics and returned with collections
of exotic birds for patrons such as E. J. Brook, Alfred Ezra, Jean Delacour,
John Spedan Lewis, Herbert Whitley (the founder of Paignton Zoo) and
London Zoo. He seems to have only ever written two articles, one which
was published in the Avicultural Magazine in 1910 and the other in 1930.
In addition, a letter from him to a member of the society was quoted from
in the magazine in 1925 and a long letter from him was published in the
magazine in 1936. Otherwise, he seems to have shunned publicity. My
old Head Keeper, Don Newson, who began working in the Bird House at
London Zoo in 1935, told me that when Frost arrived back at the zoo with his
collections, there was always a pile of mail awaiting him, which invariably
included requests from newspapers and magazines for interviews, he also
remembers him being invited to be on the popular Saturday evening BBC
radio programme In Town Tonight , but said that Frost always threw such
invitations and requests straight into the bin.
I have failed to discover when and where he was bom, but judging by the
fact that he was said to have been aged 82 in November 1957, he was probably
bom in 1875. Similarly, I have failed to discover precisely when and where
he died, except that it was in the first half of 1958, perhaps in Singapore or
Borneo. I have also failed to find a photograph of him. There are no photos
of him in the zoo archives or any letters from him, or anything else arising
from his long association with London Zoo. Don Newson is convinced that
Frost would never have let anyone take a photo of him. It came as a great
surprise, therefore, to discover from Don, that when Frost and Ted Tanner
(who worked at the zoo from 1908-1956) argued about exactly when Frost
had brought back such and such a bird, Frost would consult notebooks and
diaries in which he kept meticulous records - and was usually proved right.
Unfortunately, it is likely these were lost during the later years of his life
or following his death.
To compile these notes I have relied heavily on reports of his collecting
expeditions in the pages of the magazine (and may have missed one or two),
his two articles and the letters referred to earlier, as well as references by
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.271389">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999543" page_id="56259756"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
159
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.986365024390243" page_id="56259756"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
authors to birds brought back by Frost - or "Mr Frost" - as they often called
him. Raymond Sawyer, who bought birds-of-paradise from him, remembers
him well, so too does Don Newson, who I have already mentioned, and
one or two others who worked at the zoo during that era. It was there that
I met him fleetingly in 1957, on what turned out to be his last trip back to
England. He was then an old man of 82. He was about 5 ft lOin (not quite
1.8m) tall and probably weighed about 11st (1541bs or 70kg), or perhaps a
little more, but not much. He wore an old, brown trilby hat, horn-rimmed
or tortoiseshell-rimmed glasses and had a nicotine-stained moustache, from
constantly smoking cheroots. Like Raymond Sawyer, I remember that his
skin was pale and silky, without any hint of a suntan - you would never have
suspected that he had spent much of his life in the tropics.
He was a character who even/one seemed genuinely fond of - because he
was such a character - yet nobody trusted him. He was, Don says, an "old
crook." He recalled how Frost once asked him to swap one of his (Frost's)
less than perfect birds for a far better one belonging to the zoo. Don said,
that even if he had been inclined to do so (which he was not), he would not
have done it for Frost, who he is sure would have "shopped him" if it had
suited his purpose.
In The Birds of Paradise by Frith &amp; Beehler (1998), Appendix 2 lists
collectors of birds-of-paradise - it refers mainly to museum specimens, but
also includes some live birds. Frost figures mainly as a collector of museum
specimens and through these it is possible to trace a number of the places
where he collected and the dates. The most interesting revelation is that
in November 1906 he collected specimens on the island of Salawati (one
of the islands off the coast of western New Guinea), specimens that are
now in the Royal Ontario Museum in Canada. It is the earliest published
reference to him that I have been able to find. Whether he went to these
places specifically to collect birds for museums, I somehow doubt, I suspect
that he was collecting live birds, but if any died, they were skinned and along
with any other specimens he may have acquired, were brought back for Lord
Walter Rothschild. He is not listed as having collected any bird-of-paradise
skins after 1937, the year that Lord Rothschild died. Frost told a fellow
keeper in the Bird House at London Zoo, that he used to bring back young
cassowaries for Lord Rothschild, which grew up at the zoo and acquired their
adult coloration, and eventually ended up in Lord Rothschild's museum at
Tring. Lord Rothschild was particularly proud of his cassowaries. In the
early 1930s, when he needed a large sum of money, because he was allegedly
being blackmailed over an adulterous affair, he offered his collection of
bird skins (the largest collection in the world) to the American Museum of
Natural History for US$225,000 (roughly #150,000 at the current exchange
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.9983" page_id="56259757"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
160
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.977895976190476" page_id="56259757"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
rate), but refused under any circumstances to part with his cassowaries (and
other ratites) (Meams &amp; Meams, 1998; Beolens et al. 2009).
When Wilfred Frost joined The Aviceltural Society in July 1908, his
address was listed as 103 Goldhawk Road, Shepherd's Bush, W. (London).
The following year he had moved to Ravenscourt Park, which like two of
his other later addresses, at Chiswick Park (1913-1920) and Fulham (1920-
1929), is also in West London. He had been proposed as a member of the
Avicultural Society by Frank&apos;F. Andrews, whose address was listed as
"Zoological Society Gardens, Regent's Park" and, in October 1911 (probably
shortly after having returned from Guyana with a collection of birds that was
deposited at London Zoo), his address was listed as "c/o Zoological Society,"
which point to Frost having been associated with London Zoo from early in
his career. Don Newson thinks it was Alf 'Timber' Woods, his predecessor
as Head Keeper of the Bird House at London Zoo, who told him that Frost
had been a scenery shifter in the theatre (perhaps at the Shepherd's Bush
Empire!) and as a sideline had trapped British birds, when bird trapping was
still legal in the UK. This probably brought him to the attention of some
of the men who were later to become his wealthy patrons, men such as Sir
William Ingram, founder and owner of the Illustrated London News , and
Lord Walter Rothschild.
Frost was not living at 103 Goldhawk Road at the time of the 1901
census, but interestingly, living at 105 Goldhawk Road, which was probably
the house next-door, was an Edward Frost, aged 39, described as a carpet
warehouseman, bom in Brighton, Sussex, and his wife Sarah, aged 36, bom
in Cambridge. They were probably too young to have been his parents,
but Edward could have been an older brother or other close relative. Don
Newson told me recently how having read in a newspaper that Frost had
arrived at London Zoo with another collection of birds, a brother who was
in the Navy had got a train from Portsmouth to London and went to the zoo
to see Frost, who point-blank refused to see his brother, who had to travel
back to Portsmouth without having seen him.
In extracts of a letter from Frost published in the magazine (Crosse,
1925a) disputing an earlier statement about Yellow-backed Lories Lorius
garrulus flavopalliatus associating in large flocks, Frost wrote of having been
watching, trapping and caring for lories for nearly 20 years. So, his first
overseas expedition may well have been the one to Salawati in 1906. At the
same time as Frost was collecting birds-of-paradise on Salawati (November
1906), Walter Goodfellow was collecting birds-of-paradise on the nearby
island ofWaigeo (Frith &amp; Beehler, 1998), which leads me to wonder whether
this was merely a coincidence or whether perhaps Frost was working under
the guidance of Goodfellow, who was already an experienced collector.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.271275">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999004" page_id="56259758"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
161
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.996033146341463" page_id="56259758"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
We know (Ingram, 1911) that in 1909, Frost took 48 Greater Birds of
Paradise Paradisaea apoda to the West Indian island of Little Tobago, which
Sir William Ingram had bought as a sanctuary for this species when he feared
it might become extinct because of the large number of males being killed
for their plumes which were being used in the millinery trade. Sir William
wrote: "some years ago over 3,000 male full-plumaged birds were imported
to Europe every year, but that number has gradually fallen off, until at the
present time little more than two or three hundred skins are collected." I
had believed that it had been Frost who had been responsible for collecting
the birds for Sir William Ingram, but Sir William wrote that to collect the
live birds for him he had engaged Mr Stalker "the well-known naturalist,
who unfortunately lost his life while employed on the British Dutch New
Guinea Expedition" (the British Ornithologists' Union (BOU) Expedition to
New Guinea, led by Walter Goodfellow). He added that Mr Stalker received
"much valuable assistance from Mr Frost" and that they were able to send
home from the Aru Islands over 56 live specimens.
A few of the birds died on the journey and some were retained in England,
leaving 48 to be released on Little Tobago. The majority were freed at the
end of September 1909. A few of the weaker ones were released later,
followed by, according to his son (C. Ingram, 1914), two more in 1910 and
a third in 1912, these having been procured from "M. Pauwels, the well-
known Belgian aviculturist."
On the voyage to Little Tobago, Frost was assisted by a sailor named
Robert Herold, who was later engaged as caretaker to watch over the released
birds and sent monthly reports back to Sir William. He reported, for example,
that at the beginning of December he had found two males fighting. They
had become entangled with each other and he had to separate them, but
one died immediately afterwards, the other male's claws having lacerated
its bowels. Later he found the carcasses of two males that he thought must
have died two or three months earlier, possibly being weaker birds that had
succumbed to the "boisterous weather" at that time. A weak male that would
not eat died overnight, after having been given a dose of castor oil.
One of Sir William's concerns seems to have been that although nearly all
the birds released showed no trace of male plumage, most would eventually
turn out to be males. This was based on his experience of having imported
into England and kept a large number of birds-of-paradise of different species,
many of which when first imported had sombre female plumage, but very
few of which eventually proved to be females.
Having at different times described his first caretaker as "a most
intelligent Swiss sailor" and "a very intelligent Swiss sailor," Sir William
(Ingram, 1917) offered no explanation and expressed no sorrow (at least
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999453" page_id="56259759"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
162
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.986762642857143" page_id="56259759"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
when writing in the magazine) over the death of Robert Herold, noting only
that having "gave out that he was Swiss," Herold when he was dying had
disclosed that he was the runaway son of a Bohemian Professor.
Robert Herold's successor, who objected to a lonely life on the island,
took with him for company someone else's wife. The woman's disgruntled
husband came after them and murdered her and the man's son, and left the
man himself "with very little breath in his body."
In 1917, his third caretaker was an ex-policeman and Sir William
reproduced in the magazine extracts from the man's diary. His routine duties
seemed to consist mainly of bringing water for the birds, patrolling the island
and shooting hawks. May 1st 1917, Jno. H. Hamilton (the caretaker) wrote
of having seen several young birds-of-paradise feeding on the berries of the
parasol trees which were plentiful on the island. He drew attention to what
he said had been a great increase in the number of young birds since he had
taken charge 13 months earlier. He continued to give glowing accounts of
the increasing number of young but expressed surprise that he had failed
to find any nests. He also made much of the number of hawks he had shot,
though noting that the birds-of-paradise seemed unconcerned by them. Am
I being cynical in suggesting that he was perhaps telling Sir William what
he thought he wished to know?
It seems safe to assume that from Little Tobago, Frost travelled to
mainland South America, for at the beginning of 1910 he was in Georgetown,
the capital of Guyana, enquiring where he might find Cock-of-the-Rock
Rupicola rupicolal
His account of his quest (Frost, 1910) is notable for its description of the
species' nest and eggs, the nest site and, most importantly, his description
of the courtship dances performed by several males which gather together
at what he called dancing places but which we now call leks. Just over 50
years later it remained the only first-hand description of the courtship display
that could be found by C. J. O. Harrison, when he was trying to explain the
strange behaviour of the hand-reared male Cock-of-the-Rock living in the
Bird House at London Zoo (Harrison, 1961).
Frost revealed little about his method of catching these birds other than
that he used his nets in preference to the methods used by the Indians. They
used a blow pipe and poisoned arrows to shoot them, then administered an
antidote, which in the majority of cases, according to Frost, failed to work;
or snared them in fine string nooses that when they were sprung were apt to
break or dislocate their limbs.
Some of Frost's freshly captured birds would sulk and no matter what
they were offered, would refuse to eat, others would feed on berries and
chopped banana as soon as they were caged. One took the end of a cigarette
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.271386">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999522" page_id="56259760"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
163
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998843487804878" page_id="56259760"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
from between Frost's fingers, when he was holding the bird in one hand and
resetting the net with the other. They despised the insectivorous mixture
and were indifferent to mealworms and other insects, but would eat any
and every berry, ripe or unripe. They also liked papaya (pawpaw), mango,
banana and boiled pumpkin. Some grew fond of boiled rice sweetened
with condensed milk, especially if it had been coloured with blackberry or
blackcurrant jam.
Later in the magazine it was reported (Anon., 1910) that Frost had been
collecting in Guyana for Sir William Ingram. The birds he returned with
were deposited at London Zoo. These included four adult and two immature
male Cock-of-the-Rock which attracted great attention. This species had,
however, been exhibited at the zoo before and the '&apos;greatest novelty" was a
female Blue-backed Manakin Chiroxiphia pareola , the first example of this
group to have been imported into the UK.
Frost next it seems arrived back in England in May 1913, when he
arrived back with what was described (Anon., 1913) as "Major Horsbrugh's
Indian Collection"..."a wonderful collection of birds which were principally
inhabitants of the Himalayas." Major Horsbrugh (about whom I know little
more than what appears here) had travelled to Genoa, Italy, to meet the ship
and had brought back some of the more delicate birds by rail. The writer
(whose identity I have failed to discover) had joined him at Milan and
acted as interpreter and "had the privilege of seeing the collection of 400
birds on board the steamer after she had come alongside the quay." Those
who remember Frost will surely be amused to know that when the writer
shouted up to him "Any Red-headed Titmice?", his response was to hold
up two fingers!
All of the birds were housed on the upper deck under canvas, with one
end of the improvised tent open. By the time they got on board it was late
and there was no electric light. Through the gloom the first things they saw
were three large cages full of sunbirds. One held no fewer than 40 Crimson
Sunbirds Aethopyga siparaja. There were also Purple-ramped Nectarinia
zeylonica and Black-throated Sunbirds A. satumta. The writer, who "carried
off' a splendid Hooded Pitta Pitta sordida , thought he or she could remember
having seen one some years before at the Crystal Palace Show, and thought
that this one brought back by Frost was probably the only one in Europe.
The account included a list of birds that were brought back. A number,
including the Velvet-fronted Nuthatch Sitta frontalis , were said to have
been new to aviculture. Some of the new species he had earlier been
said to be returning with (Anon., 1913), such as the Spotted Forktail
Enicurus maculatus and tiny Chestnut-headed (-crowned) Tesia Tesia
castaneocoronata , were missing from the list, suggesting that they did not
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999823" page_id="56259761"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
164
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997846952380953" page_id="56259761"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
survive the long sea journey.
In April 1914, he collected a Greater Bird-of-Paradise at Bian River in
southern New Guinea and unspecified birds of-paradise in May 1914, at
Golili in the Am Islands, the former is in the Royal Ontario Museum and the
latter are in the Natural History Museum at Tring (Frith &amp; Beehler, 1998).
Later that year the First World War broke out and there seems to have been
no further mention of him until 1920, when it was reported (Anon., 1920) that
for some months past he had been in New Guinea and surrounding islands
collecting for London Zoo and in October had arrived there with some 130
mammals and birds. Amongst the latter were 13 King Birds-of-Paradise
Cicinnurus regius, two Greater, three cassowaries, eight Nicobar Pigeons
Caloenas nicobarica and various parrots including Rosenberg's Lorikeet
Trichoglossus haematodus rosenbergii. It was probably the first importation
of this subspecies. Maxwell (1940) wrote: "Mr. Frost brought the first living
example home in 1910." He must have meant 1920 or it may have been a
typographical error, as in 1910 Frost was collecting in Guyana.
August 1921, Frost arrived back at London Zoo with another collection
from New Guinea. Under the heading Stray Notes (Anon., 1921), it was
reported that there were 14 birds-of paradise, including Greater, Lesser,
Red P, rubra , King and Twelve-wired Seleucidis melanoleuca. The zoo
was said to have been "particularly glad" to have obtained a fine example
of the last species. Described as "another very acceptable addition to the
collection" were five Am Island Giant Kingfishers Dacelo tyro , this species
having apparently never before been imported alive. Three other species
that had not been seen before at London Zoo were the Chestnut-bellied Rail
Eulabeornis castaneoventris. Brown-backed Emerald Dove Chalcophaps
stephani and Orange-fronted Fmit Dove Ptilinopus aurantifrons . A Pesquet's
Parrot Psittrichas fulgidus was sent to the USA.
It was four years later that extracts were published of a letter a member,
Miss D. G. Crosse, had received from Frost. This was the letter mentioned
earlier, that had been prompted in part by a reference in an ornithological
periodical to Yellow-backed Lories associating in large flocks. He was
emphatic that "lories never flock" but "invariably travel in pairs, or couples."
Many hundreds may assemble in a tree or trees to feed on blossom or fruit,
he wrote, but all eventually depart, as they arrived, in pairs. Nearly 20 years
of watching, trapping and caring for lories of every species then introduced
to aviculture had, he added, enabled him to form an accurate idea of their
"little ways and temperament."
Frost's knowledge of the Yellow-backed Lory was though less than
perfect. In his letter to Miss Crosse, when writing about her lory, which was
obtained in 1918 and was illustrated in the magazine in 1925, he told her:
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.27132">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999243" page_id="56259762"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
165
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998245243902439" page_id="56259762"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
"The bird to which you refer {L. flavopalliatus) was probably purchased at
Temate, and no doubt originally from Halmaheira" (now spelt Halmahera).
Frost continued: "L. flavopalliatus and L. garrulus occur also on Batchian,
and I have even met with a few stray specimens on the north coast of Obi."
Later, he added: "As far as I can gather, the Yellow-backed Lory is as plentiful
on Batchian as on Halmaheira, but curiously enough I have never met with
a specimen in captivity there." If he meant he had never met with a Yellow-
backed Lory in captivity on Halmahera, that would make sense because, of
course, flavopalliatus does not occur on the island of Halmahera. It is L. g.
garrulus (the Chattering Lory) that lives on Halmahera.
Frost seemed to believe that flavopalliatus and garrulus , which appear
to have been treated as separate species, occurred alongside each other
on the same islands. This is, of course, not the case, but was perhaps an
understandable mistake, as the two must look almost identical when seen
flying overhead and feeding high in the trees. It is difficult to know how much
of his information was based on first-hand experience and how much relied on
what he had been told by others. Miss Crosse (1925b) was somewhat better
informed, because she wrote that her Yellow-backed Lory had come from
either Batchian (Bacan), Obi, Morotai or Raou (Rau). It could, of course,
also have come from Kasiruta or Mandiole, though perhaps not Moratai or
Raou (Rau). Birds from these two islands are now regarded as belonging
to a third subspecies L. g. morotaianus.
Temate was, Frost told her, merely a more or less dormant volcano, with
no resident lory of its own, where at any time scores of Yellow-backed Lories
could be purchased from people from Halmahera who, when ships arrived,
sailed across the bay to meet them in canoes loaded with White-crested
Cockatoos Cacatua alba , Great-billed Parrots Tanygnathus megalorhynchos,
Eclectus Eclectus rotatus , Yellow-backed Lories and immense numbers of
Violet-necked Lories Eos squamata. The conclusion must be that if they
were indeed brought across from the nearby island of Halmahera, they
were not what we know now as the Yellow-backed Lory, but belonged to
the nominate subspecies L. g. garrulus. However, nowhere did Frost use
the name Chattering Lory, in fact, I suspect, the name did not exist at that
time. His reluctance to use an English common name for garrulus may
have been because, it seems, it was known then as the Ceram Lory, which
as he pointed out was a misnomer, because it was (and remains) completely
unknown on that island (now spelt Seram). He may have been correct about
Temate having no resident lory of its own, for although Clements (2007)
lists L. g. garrulus as occurring on Halmahera, Widi and Temate, there is a
suspicion that birds seen nowadays on Temate are descendents of escaped
caged birds.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999759" page_id="56259763"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
166
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.995118142857143" page_id="56259763"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - W.J.C. LROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
Frost concluded by telling her that he had two old friends that always
accompanied him, a Rajah Lory Chalcopsitta atra insignis and a Yellow-
streaked Lory C. scintillatus. The former was the first of its kind he had ever
met with and talked and acted, and was altogether "a wonderful chum."
Referring again to Frith &amp; Beehler (1998), I discovered that in August
1925 he collected birds-of-paradise on the Aru Islands. These are in the
Natural History Museum at Tring as is, they record, a Greater Bird-of-
Paradise nest (BMNH N. 193.225) collected by Frost at Waboa in the Aru
Islands in October 1925. He is listed as having collected a Lesser Bird-
of-Paradise at Yapen Island, Geelvink (Cendrawasih) Bay on April 15th
1926 and other birds-of-paradise on Batanta and Salawati Islands during
July-November 1926. In May 1927, he collected birds at Wanumbai on the
Aru Islands. The latter are in the Royal Ontario Museum, as are the Lesser
Bird-of-Paradise and some of the birds collected on Batanta and Salawati
Islands, other are in the Natural History Museum at Tring.
Later in 1927, he returned to England after what was said to have been an
absence of three years. During that time he had amassed quite a collection.
It included 33 birds-of-paradise of six different species, nine Palm Cockatoos
Probosciger aterrimus , 70 lories, 40 crowned pigeons, 40 Fairy Bluebirds
Irena puella , seven Banded Pittas Pitta guajana , two cassowaries, 11
egrets "and so on", wrote The Editor, David Seth-Smith, in his Avicultural
Notes (1927). There were several birds that were new to aviculture, these
included the Rajah Lory, Javan Kingfisher Halcyon cyanoventris , Rufous-
bellied Kookaburra D. gaudichaud and Black-legged Falconet Microhierax
fringillarius . Rosenberg's Lorikeet had been imported in 1920, so should
not have been included with them.
In March 1929, on Kobroor, one of the Aru Islands, about 7ft (approx.
2.1m) above the ground in a hole in a small tree, Frost discovered the nest
of a King Bird-of-Paradise. Over 75 years later it appears to remain the
only published description of a nest of this species in the wild. No other
species of bird-of- paradise had been (or is) known to nest in a hole in a tree
(Frith &amp; Beehler, 1998).
The nest contained two eggs. Black and white photographs of one of
the eggs accompanied his notes in the magazine on the nesting habits of
this species (Frost, 1930). He expressed disappointment not to have got a
"snapshot" of the female entering or leaving the nest and of letting her slip
through his fingers when he was taking the eggs. He was obviously keen
to provide as much proof as possible, following the extreme scepticism
which had greeted his earlier suggestion that some birds-of-paradise might
be hole-nesters.
Seeking further corroboration, on his "return" to Surabaya (which he
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.271298">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999139" page_id="56259764"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
167
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.932251487804878" page_id="56259764"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
spelt Sourabaia) on the island of Java, he provided a nesting log for the
pair "deposited" at the zoo there. (In 1929 and 1930 his address was listed
in the magazine as c/o Chartered Bank of India, Sourbaya. The latter was,
I think, yet another way of spelling Surabaya, which is a port on the east
coast of Java.) It was not until he was "obligated to leave Java again for
some months," that the female evidentally nested in the log and when a
thorough investigation was made, two dead youngsters badly damaged by
ants were discovered inside. Later the female nested in the same log, but
in a larger aviary. On that occasion she laid only one egg and never sat on
it. By the New Year (1930) he hoped to be in New Guinea again, and with
luck collect further data.
In January 1930, he is recorded (Frith &amp; Beehler, 1998) as having
collected buds- of paradise near Oliphantsburg, in the 'Bird's Neck 5 region
of New Guinea, which is immediately north of the Am Islands. Febraary-
March he collected in north-west New Guinea and between February-May
he also collected on Batanta and Salawati Islands. The specimens from
these expeditions are in the American Museum of Natural History, Natural
History Museum at Tring and Royal Ontario Museum.
They give no credence to Frost's claim (in Rothschild, 1930) that a
Trumpet Manucode Manucodia keraudrenii egg in the nest of a Greater Bird-
oL Paradise was laid by a manucode behaving as an avian brood parasite.
Frost was, they suggest, encouraged to believe this by his observation that
Trumpet Manucodes often appeared to follow female -plumaged Greater
Buds of Paradise. We now know, they state, that this latter activity typically
has to do with mixed-species foraging and not with nest parasitism.
Later that year, D. S-S. (David Seth Smith) (1930) reported that "Mr.
Frost" had returned recently with several birds of paradise of four species,
Wilson's C. respublica , Magnificent C magnificus , Lesser and what was
almost certainly the species we now call the Western Parotia P. sefilata.
Perhaps of even more interest were several species probably never before
seen alive in the UK, namely the White-crowned Forktail Enicurus
leschenaulti , Chestnut-capped Thrush Zoothera interpres, Black-browed
Barbet Megalaima oorti, Papuan Frogmouth Podargus papuensis , White-
naped Pheasant Pigeon Otidiphaps nobilis aruensis , Bronze-tailed Peacock-
Pheasant Polyplectron chalcurum , Yellow-fronted White-eye Zosterops
flavifrons and Black Butcherbird Cracticus quoyi . I suspect that the "Am
Boobook Owl Spiloglaux aruensis" may now be Ninox rufa aruensis , but
have yet to identify the "Rose-breasted Fruit Dove Ptilinopus rosecollisP
Frith &amp; Beehler (1998) record that in July -1931, he collected birds of
paradise near Sorong, north-west New Guinea and on Halmahera during
the same month. The former are in the Natural History Museum at Tring,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999537" page_id="56259765"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
168
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.995307047619048" page_id="56259765"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
as are some of the latter, others are in the Royal Ontario Museum and the
Peabody Museum at Yale University.
In the Avicultural Magazine (Anon., 1931), it was noted that Frost had
returned to London with another fine collection. It included 10 species of
bird-of-paradise. He was said to have had "several examples of most of them"
and it seems likely that among them were the two Wallace's Standardwing
Semioptera wallacii "still in moult" and a young Twelve-wired "coming
into colour" which Hopkinson (1931) saw at Paignton Zoo and a Wallace's
Standardwing, a parotia and an adult King Bird-of-Paradise, that Gurney
had at Keswick Hall in December of that year (Martin, 1931). Frost arrived
back with three birds, the Ivory-breasted (or Giant) Pitta P. maxima , Red-
breasted (Macklot's) Pitta P. erythrogaster and Yellow-and-green Lorikeet
T. flavoviridis , that had probably never before been imported. (Wallace's
Standardwing had first arrived in Europe with Goodfellow in 1926 and was
kept at London Zoo (Hopkinson, 1930).)
According to Sydney Porter (1933), Frost went specially to the island of
Halmahera to get the Ivory-breasted (Giant) Pitta and, though several were
obtained, only two, he believed, reached England. One was purchased by
London Zoo but did not survive for long, even though the bird appeared to be
in perfect condition. The white of its breast appeared "glossy and polished
like the finest china" and the red of the underparts was like "port wine with
a light shining through," wrote Porter.
As well as his notes on rare pittas, he was the author of a series of articles
entitled Wanderings in the Far East. One of these brought a long letter from
Frost (1936) wanting to correct what he considered were Porter's mistaken
or misleading comments concerning conditions in Chinese bird shops in
Singapore, the scarcity of lories on the eastern market, the leg shackling of
lories and parakeets and the trapping of pheasants. There is little point in
going over the arguments again here, except to say that Frost thought legs
rings were a practical way of keeping lories and parakeets and had used that
method to keep a Rajah, a Yellow-streaked and another lory. He wrote: "For
several years, these three birds accompanied us through Malaya, Sumatra,
and Java, Siam, Indo-China, the Moluccas, and New Guinea, eventually
reaching England in 1927."
Frith &amp; Beehler (1998) record that during April-May 1934, Frost collected
bird-of-paradise skins on Batanta, Waigeo and Salawati Islands. These are
in the Natural History Museum at Tring, as are those he collected in north-
west New Guinea during the same period.
Reviewing the history of the Philippine Eagle Pithecophaga jefferyi
(formerly the Monkey-eating Eagle) in zoos. Block (2004) wrote that the
second live specimen seen outside the Philippines was "captured in 1934 by
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.271348">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999359" page_id="56259766"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
169
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.982052365853659" page_id="56259766"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
Wilfred J. C. Frost" and sent to Rome Zoo for its reopening as a donation
from Jean Delacour. It lived there until 1976 and holds the longevity record
for this species in captivity.
The eagle outlived Frost by some 18 years. It is the first indication I
have seen that he may have travelled to the Philippines. In the absence of
further evidence though, I am inclined to believe that he probably bought the
bird elsewhere. It seems that from about 1920 onwards, he regularly sailed
to various Indonesian islands (then the Dutch East Indies), travelling as far
east as New Guinea and the Aru Islands, and probably bought many of his
birds in markets along the way and in Singapore. Don Newson said, Frost
talked of having a network of contacts including ships' captains and crew
members, as well various officials, from whom he obtained birds.
The next mention of him I have been able to find was by Sherri ff (1937),
when writing about a pair of Long-tailed Sibia Heterophasia picaoides
simillima (called then the Grey Sibia Sibia simillima, a bird new to aviculture)
that had been imported from Sumatra by "Mr Frost" in the early part of
1936. A painting of the birds by Miss M. Dovaston was the frontispiece in
that issue of the magazine.
After a 16 day incubation period the pair hatched two chicks in an aviary
belonging to the author, who having successfully bred the Black-headed
species H. capistrata by allowing the parents their liberty, repeated the
experiment with the Sumatran birds, only for the male to disappear on the
second night, after which the female failed to rear the young without his
assistance.
On November 17th 1937, Frost is listed as having collected bird-of-
paradise skins at Sorong, north-west New Guinea. These are in the American
Museum of Natural History (Frith &amp; Beehler, 1998). It was the last occasion
he is listed as having collected birds-of-paradise skins, which may or may
not have been related to the fact that Lord Rothschild had died on August
27th 1937.
Lord Tavistock (1938) referred to a consignment of seven Desmarest's
Fig Parrots Psittaculirostris desmarestii occidentalis (which he called
Desmarest's Dwarf Parrots and which the caption to the frontispiece of this
species by Roland Green called the Western Golden-headed Dwarf Parrot)
"brought over recently" by Frost, who had introduced "a species entirely
new to aviculture." Lord Tavistock seems to have obtained four, which lived
almost entirely on fruit - apple, pear, grapes and banana - the latter having
been, he believed, the food they were imported on. They drank a little
nectar, which he suspected they would have got on perfectly well without
and would not look at seed. They did though like removing the bark from
green sycamore twigs and were very fond of mealworms and chewed up
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998329" page_id="56259767"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
170
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.994093785714286" page_id="56259767"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
iodine nibbles faster than almost any other birds in his collection.
An unnamed author (1938), writing in the magazine about the Short-billed
Minivet Pericrocotus brevirostris , which was the subject of Roland Green's
frontispiece in that issue, wrote of having had a very fine male which had
been brought over by "Mr Frost" and which had lived for over a year in one
of the author's greenhouses and would probably have lived longer had it not
been fed so many mealworms.
On July 2nd 1939, both Frost and Shaw Mayer arrived in London with
large collections, having travelled from "the East" on the same boat. Shaw
Mayer had been taken ill shortly before reaching London and on arrival
had to be taken to hospital. Frost cared for Shaw Mayer's birds as well as
his own and, on reaching London, took both collections to the zoo. A short
note on the collections appeared in the August issue of the magazine (D.S-
S, 1939), followed later by a more detailed account by Mrs Wharton-Tigar
(1939), which is the one I have relied on here.
Mrs Wharton-Tigar (who Raymond Sawyer thinks was South American
and whom he recalls very much lived up to the second part of her double-
barrelled name) remarked on the fact that Mrs Frost had accompanied her
husband on this occasion and that "perhaps may have contributed to the
splendid condition of his collection." It included four species of birds-of-
paradise, the King, Wilson's, Western Parotia and Lesser. (Shaw Mayer
had nine species including Wahne's Parotia P. wahnesi, Huon Astrapia A.
rothschildi and Emperor P. gulielmi. His collection also included a Philippine
Eagle, only the second ever imported into the UK, which went to Paignton
Zoo, Bulwer's Pheasant L. bulweri and a "magnificent" Blue-headed Pitta
P. baudii.) There were also what Mrs Wharton-Tigar described as the "big
heavy crested" subspecies of the Victoria Crowned Pigeon G. victoria
beccarii and "G. coronata " (presumably the species known now as the
Blue Crowned Pigeon G. cristata ), a pair of what she called "Molluscan
Crimson Wings," Edward's and Mitchell's Lorikeets T. h. capistrata and I
h. mitchellii respectively, the Dusky Lory Pseudeos fuscata and Iris Lorikeet
Psitteuteles iris , the last named being described as "a first importation." A
baby Purple-winged Roller Coracias temminckii was another interesting
importation. There were also some "lovely" Javan Kingfishers.
Described as "not previously imported" was Gracula religiosa veneratus;
Frost also had examples of G. r. intermedia and the Black-collared Starling
Gracupica nigricollis , as well as the Grosbeak Starling Scissirostrum dubium
and several Bali Starlings Leucopsar rothschildi. The "King Crows" to
which Mrs Wharton-Tigar referred were, as I suspected, not crows but
drongos. Frank Woolham helped me identify them as Black Drongos
Dicrurus macrocercus , a migratory species found on Java and Bali. Frost's
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.270667">
ELLIS - WJ.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998755" page_id="56259768"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
171
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.989997146341463" page_id="56259768"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
"Javan Cissas" must have been Cissa t. thalassina , the nominate form of the
Short-tailed Magpie and his "Sumatran Cissas" must have been C. chinensis
minor , a subspecies of the Green Magpie. Similarly, his "Red Mesias" were
probably the Sumatran subspecies of Leiothrix argentauris, the underparts
of which are bright red. His "Yellow-headed Fraitsuckers ( Chloropsis
ictemcephala)" look to have been what is regarded now as a subspecies of
the Blue-winged Leafbird C. cochinchinensis ictemcephala , also found on
Sumatra as well as in southern Malaysia.
He again had Long-tailed Sibias, the bird he had been first to import from
Sumatra a few years earlier. There were also scimitar babblers Pomatorhinus
sp., Fairy Bluebirds and the "loveliest little" Purple-throated (Van Hasselt's)
Sunbird Nectarinia sperata. He also had a number of Timor Sparrows Padda
fuscata , described as "new," Five-coloured Munias Lonchura quinticolor,
described as "another new importation" and the "dwarf form" of the Zebra
Finch Taeniopygiag. guttata or T castanotis (Clements, 2007) "from Timor."
There was a Maleo Macrocephalon maleo and some Salvador! 5 s Pheasants
Lophura inornata , as well as quite a number of the plover-like "Nile Courser
or Crocodile bird" (presumably Egyptian Plovers Pluvianus aegyptius he
had acquired on the voyage home).
A note from R H. Maxwell (1940), stated that Frost had brought back
seven Grosbeak Starlings, of which he had been lucky enough to have
obtained two. Later that year, E. H. (1940) added a few random notes on
the recent list of birds new to the London Zoo collection. The list, taken
from the Annual Report , included several birds brought back the previous
year by Frost. Top of the list was the Grosbeak Starling, which E. H. (Dr
Emilius Hopkieson) thought was new to any collection. The "Timor Zebra
Finch," regarded then as a separate species "T. insularis " (and treated again
as a separate species called the Chestnut-eared Finch by Clements (2007)),
had previously been imported into the Netherlands, while there was a plate
of the Five-coloured Munia in Reichenbach's Singvogel, but nothing was
said there about it in captivity. Other species new to the zoo collection were
the Long-tailed Sibia and the Timor Crimson-winged Parakeet Aprosmictus
jonquillaceus (presumably Mrs Wharton-Tigar's "Molluscan Crimson
Wings"), which E. H. thought might be the first importation anywhere.
Writing about how after four years of war, visitors to London Zoo could
not fail to be impressed by the number and variety of parrots still on view,
Prestwich (1943) noted that amongst those living in the flights outside the
Parrot House were no fewer than five Timor Crimson-winged Parakeets
(presumably brought back by Frost in 1939). (The flights also housed a
pair of Spix's Macaw Cyanopsitta spixii.) Writing from the USA, Delacour
(1943) mentioned that Frost had brought him "a cock and three hens" of the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999441" page_id="56259769"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
172
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.995315523809523" page_id="56259769"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
very rare Salvadori's Pheasant from Sumatra. These must have perished
during the Second World War, Cleres having been heavily bombed during
the last week of May 1940 and lost entirely by June of that year.
Following the fall of Singapore to Japanese forces in 1942, Frost was
interned as a civilian in Changi Camp. Don Newson told me that Frost was
put in charge of the rice store and because of his old age - he must have
been about 67 when first interned and possibly as old as 70 when released
- he was the only man allowed into the women's compound and used to take
notes from husbands to their wives and vice versa. The rice store must have
attracted lots of rats, which in turn attracted snakes. A report of his death
by H.M.S. (Helen May Sidebottom) in The Daily Telegraph in 1958, noted
that while interned in Changi, he had trapped rats and snakes to help feed his
fellow prisoners and had his appendix removed with a "knife and fork"!
Miss Knobel for many years Hon. Secretary and Treasurer of the society,
wrote (Knobel, 1943) that members would be glad to learn that after a wait
of many months she had on September 10th received a long letter from
Shaw Mayer confirming that he was safe and well, serving in the Army
"somewhere in Australia." He confirmed that Frost was interned in Changi
Camp and wrote that he had heard recently from Mrs Frost, who was with
her son Michael in Western Australia.
Don Newson believes that Michael was about 12 years of age when he
was taken to Australia. He remembers how after the war Frost frequently cut-
out newspaper reports about bad weather in England, recalling particularly
one showing part of the zoo flooded after a downpour one Bank Holiday, and
sent these to his wife to discourage her from wanting to return to England.
There was an older son, who had lost an arm, who Don believes was
from an earlier marriage and had been a photographer with an Army unit
in Egypt during the war, who after the war worked for the BBC or some
similar organisation. Towards the end, when Frost was no longer so welcome
at the zoo, in the evenings he used to go back to this son's home in West
London.
It seems that when Frost returned to England in 1939, he sent the British
Museum a large collection of mammal specimens from what were then the
Dutch East Indies. When he returned to England after the war, he found a
few more specimens that he had failed to send in 1939. These included a
fruit bat that he had collected at Tamalanti, western Sulawesi (Celebes) in
1938 or 1939, which was subsequently named the Small-toothed Fruit Bat
Neopteryx frosti by Hayman in 1946. It remained the only known specimen
until 1985, when three others were collected (Watkins pers.comm.). So far
as I am aware, it is the only animal named after Frost.
Listing additions to the London Zoo collection, Prestwich (A. A. P.,
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.271385">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
</reference>
<page confidence="0.99952" page_id="56259770"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
173
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.996215682926829" page_id="56259770"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
1947) wrote that in the month of September the most important new arrival
had been a Javan Pond Heron Ardeola speciosa, a species new to the
collection, brought home by Frost. In the first magazine of 1948, he was
listed as having rejoined the society and his address was again given as
"c/o Zoological Gardens, Regent's Park, London N.W.8." Later that year,
under the heading Personalia (1948), it was reported that W. J. C. Frost
the "indefatigable collector," who had returned recently from Singapore
with a collection of birds and other creatures, had left for New Guinea in
search of birds-of-paradise and did not expect to return to England until the
following summer.
Towards the end of the following year, again under the heading
Personalia, A. A. P. (1949) wrote that Frost had returned from New Guinea
with a good collection of birds. Included were 13 male birds-of-paradise, 10
Greater and three King birds, along with 12 crowned pigeons, "four Pleasing
Lories and six Gold-crowned Bulbuls, etc." The Pleasing Lories were what
we now call Red-flanked Lorikeets Charmosyna placentis , I learned from
Rosemary Low. The bulbuls were, I presume, the species now called the
Straw-headed Bulbul Pycnonotus zelanicus , a non-New Guinea species he
must have picked up along the way.
November 9th 1949, His Grace the Duke of Bedford, Lady Spencer-
Jones, wife of the Astronomer Royal, pianist and actress Yvonne Amaud
and Frost, were among the guests at the British Aviculturists' Club dinner
in London, after which Gerald lies showed films of animals at Belle Vue
Zoo, Manchester, Vincennes Zoological Park in Paris and the zoos at Zurich
and Basle.
Eddie Orbell, who in the late 1940s and early 1950s worked in the zoo's
quarantine station, a former indoor riding school in nearby Park Village East,
remembers Frost's nicotine-stained moustache and how he used to store a lot
of his "kit," including spears and bows and arrows which he brought back
to sell, up on the balcony of the quarantine station. The late Joe McCorry
remembered Frost having a fold-up wooden camp bed covered with an old,
tiger skin, on which he slept in one of the dens of the Sanatorium (the old
animal hospital behind the Bird House). When the keepers in the Bird House
took their morning and afternoon tea breaks, he would come across and join
them for a cup of tea. Joe, who insisted that Frost was called William or
Bill, wrote (pers. comm.) that he did not confide in many people at the zoo,
but if he did talk to you, he had lots of stories to tell. Unfortunately, those
that Joe told me, are unsuitable to repeat here.
Don Newson said that Frost did not have much time for "chiefs and
bigwigs" and much preferred to have a "wet of tea" and "swop yams" with
the lads (the keepers). Frost was, he said, careful with his money and did not
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999823" page_id="56259771"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
174
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9835474" page_id="56259771"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
give much away. The only thing he ever gave Don was a can of Australian
Red Cardinal beef dripping, which Don still clearly remembers. He also
recalls how, when Peter Rice, who was working at the zoo and had helped
Frost, told him he was getting married, with uncharacteristic generosity,
Frost gave him #5 (approx. US$8 at the current exchange rate), which was
probably the equivalent of about two weeks' wages in those days. Frost
had, said Don, a special arrangement with the manager of Barclays Bank
at nearby Camden Town, allowing him to take his money down to the bank
in biscuit tins. Afterwards, Don said, he would go around the comer to
Inverness Street, which was (and still is) lined with market stalls selling
cheap "fruit and veg" and would collect the bmised and discarded fruit to
take back to the zoo to feed his birds. Don remembers how, after the war,
Frost complained that people out in the Far East were no longer willing to
work for a "handful of beads," but wanted the "full union rate of pay" for
making the travelling boxes and crates for his birds.
There appears to be no record of him having brought back a collection
in either 1950 or 1951. Perhaps to make up for that, he brought back two
collections in 1952. He was listed as having been amongst the guests at
the British Aviculturists' Club meeting in London on March 12th 1952
(Prestwich, 1952) and in the March-April issue of the magazine, in his
London Zoo Notes, John Yealland (1952a) wrote: "As to be expected, the
arrival of Mr. Frost with a collection of Indo-Malay sian birds resulted in the
addition of some attractive specimens to the Society's collection." These
included a Sri Lanka Mynah G. ptilogenys , a species new to the collection,
a pair of Blue-winged Leafbirds C. c. nigricollis , a subspecies new to the
collection, plus two Fairy Bluebirds I. p. turcosa, a Greater Bird-of-Paradise,
a Timor Crimson-winged Parakeet and a Green Junglefowl Galius varius.
In the May-June issue, P. H. Maxwell (1952a) wrote of having recently
acquired a young Rosenberg's Lorikeet from Frost. In News &amp; Views
in the September-October issue that year, it was reported that Frost had
returned recently from his "49th" collecting expedition with 26 birds-of-
paradise, comprising Greater, Red, Twelve-wired, Wilson's and King. There
were four species of hombill, the Great Buceros hicornis , Rhinoceros B.
rhinoceros , Wrinkled Aceros corrugatus and Plicated A plicatus , as well as
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.923676428571429">
Nias (Island) Mynahs G. rohusta and what we now call Purple Swamphens
Porphyrio porphyrio, plus single specimens of the Southern Cassowary
Casuarius casuarius , Pesquet's Parrot, Black Lory C. atra, Long-tailed
Parakeet Psittacula longicauda , Pink-headed Fruit Dove P. porphyreus and
Red-breasted (Macklot's) Pitta. (A. A. P., 1952)
One of the Nias (Island) Mynahs was presented to the zoo by Frost
(Yealland, 1952b). It was a species that had not previously been represented
</reference>
<reference confidence="0.27134">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999318" page_id="56259772"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
175
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.987983487804878" page_id="56259772"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
in the London Zoo collection. It may have been the bird with only one eye,
that was living in the Bird House when I began working there in January
1956. I remember it being almost the size of a small crow and having an
enormous gape and an ear-splitting screech. It would incline its head to one
side and with its long wattles hanging down, would chatter away in what
must have been an Indonesian dialect.
Writing about his new Pesquet's Parrot living in the Parrot House at
Whipsnade Zoo, Maxwell (1952b) noted that the bird was collected by Shaw
Mayer and brought to England with the rest of his collection by Frost in July
that year. Shaw Mayer had for some reason been unable to accompany what
must have been his last collection to reach England. The following year
he took charge of Sir Edward Hallstrom's aviaries at Nondugl in the Wahgi
Valley of Papua New Guinea.
There appears to be no record of which of the birds on the above list
were Frost's and which were Shaw Mayer's, but Shaw Mayer's involvement
helps explain how Frost managed to bring over a second collection - and a
sizeable one at that - so soon after his "Indo-Malaysian" collection. It may
have been the occasion that he arrived back with several Wilson's Birds of
Paradise. Raymond Sawyer cannot remember the exact number, but thinks
that Frost had more than 10 of these.
In the 1950s, Raymond was enjoying great success with his birds on the
show bench, where they regularly took the top awards at "the National" and
other leading bird shows. Determined to beat him, his main rival, a scrap
metal dealer from "the Midlands," arranged to buy all of the Wilson's Birds-
of Paradise from Frost. However, living in London, Raymond usually got
first pick of Frost's best birds and Frost agreed to sell him one of the male
Wilson's Birds of Paradise so long as he did not tell his rival that he had
got it from him. Raymond was amused by this because, as he said, it would
be obvious that he had got it from Frost. Despite Raymond's rival having
bought all the other birds, however, it was Raymond's bird that won the class
for birds of paradise and bowerbirds at that year's National Show.
Writing about the show, presumably held in December 1952, E. N. T.
Vane (1953) noted that on show were no fewer than four Wilson's Birds-
of Paradise, as well as a pair of Twelve-wired. Raymond was disappointed
not to have got the Red-breasted (Macklot's) Pitta brought back by Frost,
which went to Viscount Chaplin (who at the time was Hon. Secretary of the
Zoological Society of London and in 1935 edited the Avicultural Magazine)
who, Raymond said, did not have the #10 (approx. US$16) to pay for it and,
eventually, tired of the bird and gave it to the zoo.
Raymond remembers how, on another occasion, when paying Frost for
some birds, his rival overpaid him by #20 (approx. US$32). It was a lot of
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999755" page_id="56259773"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
176
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.989108952380952" page_id="56259773"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - W.J.C. LROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
money in those days and Frost pocketed it without saying a word. However,
Raymond's rival was Frost's equal and, when Frost returned from the Far
East with his next collection and, he again bought some birds from him,
he underpaid Frost by #20 (approx. US$32) and, again, Frost pocketed the
money without saying a word.
In early June 1953 Frost returned to the UK with yet another collection.
A. A. R (1953) reported that it consisted mainly of birds he had purchased
from local people in the Far East, where bad weather had prevented him from
using his "usual trapping methods." This made me smile, as several times
Don Newson has told me: "Of course, Frost never trapped his own birds, he
used to tell us that he had a string of contacts who he got his birds from."
This is hardly surprising, however, as in 1953 he must have been about 78
years old and must have long ago stopped shinning up trees to set nets.
The list of birds included five cassowaries, eight crowned pigeons
(probably G. cristata), 16 Pied Imperial Pigeons Ducula bicolor , three
Plicated or Blyth's Hombills, a Ceylon Grey Hombill Ocyceros (formerly
Tockus ) gingalensis , two Nias (Island) Mynahs, two "Sunda Island Mynahs"
(G. r. venerata), two Bali Starlings, a Green-billed Malkoha Phaenicophaeus
tristis longicaudatus , what was listed as a "Large-billed Blue-winged Pitta"
(possibly the Mangrove species P. megarhyncha rather than the smaller
billed P. moluccensis) and five "Golden-crowned Bulbuls" (again probably
the Straw-headed species). Also on the list were six Purple-naped Lories L.
domicella, four Black-capped Lories L. lory , four Black Lories, four "Ceram
Lories" (this seemed to be the common name of L. garrulus but was, as
Frost pointed out, a misnomer, because it does not occur on the island of
Ceram, now spelt Seram), two Red Lories E. bornea , two Black-winged
Lories E. cyanogenia , three Violet-necked Lories, five Forsten's Lorikeets
T. h.forsteni, five Ornate Lorikeets T. ornatus , four Plum-headed Parakeets
P cyanocephala , two Emerald-collared or Layard's Parakeets P. calthorpae
and a Moustached Parakeet P alexandri.
In his London Zoo Notes in the first issue of the magazine the following
year, Yealland (1954) wrote that four Ornate Lorikeets, five Forsten's
Lorikeets, a Black Lory, three Black-capped Lories, three Purple-naped
Lories, a Chattering Lory and three Yellow-backed Lories (probably the
"Ceram Lories" on the above list) had been deposited at the zoo, together
with four Crowned Pigeons G. cristata , 10 Pied Imperial Pigeons, a Javan
Mynah (probably G. r. religiosa ) and three "Yellow-crowned Bulbuls
Trachycomus ochrocephalus ." The suspicion must be that these were the
unsold remnants of the above collection. It is difficult to understand why
so many of the lories and lorikeets remained unsold, unless it was due to
restrictions leading up to the ban on the importation of parrots, which was
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.271303">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999159" page_id="56259774"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
177
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.988426117647059" page_id="56259774"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
imposed on November 1st 1953. It was relaxed a little later but not fully
revoked until 1966.
Describing the first breeding in the UK of the Purple-naped Lory in 1954,
Tom Spence (1955) wrote that his pair was imported for him "under license
by Mr Frost" and along with three others appeared to be the only specimens
of this species brought to the UK for many years.
Frost was amongst the guests at the 43rd meeting of the British
Aviculturists' Club in South Kensington on September 8th 1954, at
which Walter Higham showed his film of birds of the Scottish Highlands
(Prestwich, 1954). This points to the fact that Frost had probably arrived
back with his latest collection in August or the first week of September, but
for some reason it was not until the November-December issue that the list
of birds was published in the magazine. It reveals that he returned with a
"Westermann's Cassowary" (which if I understand correctly has a white
occipital patch on the head and comes from the Vogelkop region (also known
as the Bird's Head or Cendrawasih Peninsula) of New Guinea and should,
some believe, be assigned the scientific name C. bennetti westermani), a
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.933500666666667" page_id="56259774"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
Northern (One-wattled) Cassowary C. unappendiculatus , a Palm Cockatoo, a
Salawati King Parrot Alisterus amboinensis dorsalis , a Narcissus Flycatcher
Ficedula narcissina, five "Black-chinned Laughingthrushes" (probably the
Black-throated Garrulax chinensis ), 15 Painted Quail Coturnix chinensis, a
Plicated Hombill, three Nicobar Pigeons and 20 birds-of-paradise - Lesser,
Twelve-wired, King, Hunstein's Magnificent C. magnificus hunsteini and
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.971029166666667" page_id="56259774"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
Wilson's (A. A. P., 1954).
By the time the list was published, Frost had already set off on another
expedition. On November 9th the following year, he attended the 49th
meeting of the British Aviculturists' Club in South Kensington, at which
Iris Damton showed a film of her and her husband's two-month safari to
Uganda the previous year (Prestwich, 1955), so I am assuming that he had
probably returned to England with another collection towards the end of
August or in September. I have, however, been unable to trace any details
of such a collection.
I think it was probably at the end of 1955 or early in 1956 that Tommy
Sangster, a keeper in the Lion House at London Zoo, took some Pere David's
Deer Elaphurus davidianus from Whipsnade Zoo to China and during a stop
at Singapore visited Frost. He was, I think, shocked by the conditions in
which he found him living. He went to the address he had been given, only
to discover that Frost was living in what was described as, "a shed at the end
of someone's garden" in the poorest part of Singapore. Whereas Raymond
Sawyer recalled (pers. comm.) that when Jean Delacour visited Fred Shaw
Mayer in the highlands of New Guinea, Shaw Mayer got out his best bone
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999524" page_id="56259775"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
178
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.915548404761904" page_id="56259775"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
china, Frost offered Tommy Sangster tea in an old tin can or mug and seeing
his reluctance to drink it - because there were so many insects floating on the
top - took it from him and with a stick, flicked them off and handed it back
to him. I would love to have asked Tommy Sangster about the occasion he
visited Frost, but to my great regret, by the time I got his phone number and
called it, it was no longer in use and I subsequently discovered that he had
died a few months earlier.
When I began working in the Bird House in January 1956, keepers
often talked about (and laughed about) an incident when a man named Jack
Indge, who was both an aviculturist (he was awarded the society's medal
for breeding the Red-sided Eclectus E. r. polychloros) and a dealer at the
time, came to see Frost's latest collection. Apparently, he was peering
into the various boxes and suddenly stopped, turned around and said, "Ah,
Rothschild's Grackles eh, Frost, how much?" A deal was quickly concluded
and he triumphantly carried off the box of birds, no doubt convinced
that he had got one over on his rivals. It was not until a few days later
that he discovered that they were not the much sought after Rothschild's
Grackles (i.e. Bali Starlings that were far rarer in aviculture in those days
and consequently commanded a high price), but the then still common
Black-winged species Sturnus melanopterus , for which there was little or
no demand. He immediately returned to the zoo with them and demanded
his money back. Frost took great satisfaction in pointing out that it was
him (Indge), who had said they were Rothschild's Grackles (Bali Starlings)
and, he had therefore not misled him, and had no intention of giving him
his money back.
He did not come to England in 1956, but returned the following summer.
In News &amp; Views A. A. R (1957) reported that on the last day of August,
Frost had arrived back on the P&amp;O vessel Shillong with the results of his
"53rd" collecting expedition. The list of birds included Greater and King
Birds-of-Paradise, Great, Wreathed A. undulatus , Plicated and "Malayan
Pied Hornbills" (the last named presumably Anthracoceros albirostris
convexus ), New Guinea Bronzewings Henicophaps albifrons schlegeli
(see later), Nicobar and Partridge Pigeons ( Geophaps smithii , presumably,
from the northernmost part of Australia), bleeding-hearts Gallicolumba
sp., Bronze-tailed Peacock-Pheasants and Bornean Crested Firebacks L.
ignita. Other birds on the list included Banded Pittas, Blue-winged Pittas P
moluccensis. Fairy Bluebirds, Bali and Black-necked Starlings, Fire-tufted
Barbets Psilopogonpyrolophus, rosefinches Carpodacus sp. and Mitchell's
Lorikeets.
Frost's collection was housed behind the Mappin Terraces, in a building
which until recently had been the Chimps' Nursery. On the left-hand side
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.271352">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999377" page_id="56259776"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
179
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.992188780487805" page_id="56259776"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
as you went in, there were three (or possibly four) white-tiled chimp cages
behind glass screens (like those in the Monkey House). Frost's collection,
still in its travelling crates, was stacked in one of the cages. I can remember
four male Greater Birds-of-Paradise, their plumes stained red by the wood
shavings on the floor of their cages, some Fire-tufted Barbets, Blue-winged
Pittas, possibly one or two hombills and, I think, a Binturong Arctictis
binturong. (Raymond Sawyer remembers buying Binturong and Mouse
Deer (or Lesser Malayan Chevrotain) Tragulus javanicus from Frost when
he (Raymond) was in charge of the LCC (London County Council) Parks
Department zoos at Crystal Palace and Battersea Park.) Raymond and Don
Newson have both commented on the fact that when Frost was feeding and
watering his birds, probably because of failing eyesight, he put a finger into
the water pots to check that there was enough water in them.
As an inexperienced 17 year old keeper, I was instructed that should he
come to the Bird House when I was there alone, I should not let him help
himself to mealworms, I should keep the fruit cupboard locked and should
make sure that he did not creep along the passage and help himself to seed
- such was his reputation. I was led to believe that if I turned my back on
him for more than a few seconds, he would almost certainly empty the
mealworm bin and clear out the fruit cupboard.
Sure enough, the first Sunday afternoon I was left on my own for an
hour or so, the smell of a cheroot came drifting along the passage and a few
moments later Frost appeared. He was wearing an old, brown trilby hat,
horn-rimmed or tortoiseshell-rimmed glasses, a white or creamy-white shirt,
a tie and, I think, a waistcoat, with perhaps a watch or pocket watch, a green
tweed jacket, grey flannel trousers badly stained with fruit juice or something
more unpleasant, and brown shoes and was, of course, smoking a cheroot.
He did not introduce himself or anything like that, he simply handed me a
tin, I think it was an old cocoa tin, and said, "put some mealworms in this."
Mindful of what I had been told, I carefully rationed out some mealworms
and handed the tin back to him. He took one look in the tin and handed it
back to me and said, "you will need to put in a lot more than that otherwise
they will get in the comers and sweat."
Writing about the birds at Darenth-Hulme (her and Arthur Prestwich's
home at Oakwood, North London), Bonner (1957) wrote that the most
important recent arrivals were four "Black Bronze-winged or White-capped
Ground Pigeons" brought from the Am Islands by Frost. This species is
known now as the New Guinea Bronzewing.
In mid-November 1957, Frost, aged 82, and with failing eyesight, left
London for Borneo on yet another expedition. I am surprised that it did
not strike me as in any way extraordinary at the time. It is only now that
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997967" page_id="56259777"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
180
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.984623166666667" page_id="56259777"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
I am considerably older, that I realise how extraordinary it really was that
at the age of 82, Frost was setting off back to the rainforests of Borneo. It
was, or would have been, his "54th" such expedition, though it is difficult
to work out how he, or perhaps Prestwich (A. A. R), arrived at that figure.
Either he began well before 1906, or, more likely, it included a number of
mini-expeditions perhaps from Singapore or Java to other parts of the region;
for example, I found a reference in the magazine to him taking a collection
of crowned pigeons and other birds to the zoo in Colombo, Sri Lanka, but
failed to note it down and have failed to find it again.
In January 1958, Frost continued to be listed as a Hon. Life Member of
The Avicultural Society, but by the September-October issue of the magazine,
when writing in News &amp; Views, A. A. P. (1958) referred to the "late W. J.
C. Frost." I cannot recall how news of his death first reached us in the Bird
House at London Zoo, but remember that there was a brief report of his death
in The Daily Telegraph , which was cut-out and saved, but not even that, so
far as I can recall, stated when and where he died. Nobody ever mentioned
whether or not his wife and son Michael returned to the UK after the war,
or whether he ever went to Australia to visit them.
In News &amp; Views the following year, A. A. P. (1959) referred to a lorikeet
brought back by Frost on his last expedition. The lorikeet which went to
Wassenaar had it seemed been bought by Frost at a small port on the west
coast of what was then Portuguese Timor. It was quite new to him and it
seems it remained unidentified until 1959, when E. N. T. Vane identified it
as Trichoglossus haematodus flavotectus, confined to the islands of Wetar
and Roma, just to the north of Timor. Apparently there was no reference to
any previous importation of this subspecies, no illustrations, and no skins
of it in the British Museum (Natural History) or the museum at Leiden in
the Netherlands. A. A. P. wrote that it is somewhat similar to Weber's T k
weberi , though larger in size. Forshaw and Cooper (1973) described it as
similar to Edward's T. h. capistratus.
Of Frost's contemparies, Walter Goodfellow died in 1953, C. S. Webb
died aged 66 on April 10th 1964 at his home in Nairobi, Kenya and Fred Shaw
Mayer died on September 1st 1989 in his native Australia, 25 days short of
his 90th birthday. Charles Cordier died in September 1994 in Switzerland.
He was aged 97 and had sent his final collection from Bolivia in 1983.
I have never heard anyone say a bad word about Cecil Webb. Don
Newson said that if he had a fault, it was that he was too nice - he was a
gentleman. Webb and Shaw Mayer were, he said, far more discerning than
Frost and brought back only the choicest birds and, by all accounts, always
landed them in perfect condition without a feather out of place. Cliff and
Dawn Frith told me that Shaw Mayer's bird-of-paradise skins they have
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.261854">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST; AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
</reference>
<page confidence="0.99913" page_id="56259778"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
181
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.950216625" page_id="56259778"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
examined in museums are beautifully prepared and have a lot of important
details (more than you usually find) recorded in his own handwriting on
the labels.
Author's note
I have in most cases used current common and scientific names in place
of the older names used in many of the older published accounts. I have also
in most, though not in all instances, used the modem names of the countries
in which Frost collected.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.940648" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56259778" page_num="181" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9921915625" page_id="56259778"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
I have relied heavily on reports of Frost's collecting expeditions by
D. S-S. (David Seth Smith), A. A. R (Arthur Prestwieh), Mrs Wharton-Tigar
and a number of other authors, some of whom I have failed to identify.
Without these and Frost's two articles, the letter quoted by Miss Crosse and
Frost's letter to the magazine, along with the more recent annotated list of
collectors of birds-of-paradise in Appendix 2 of The Birds of Paradise by
Frith and Beehler (1998), the above biography (albeit incomplete) would
have been impossible to compile and there would have been virtually no
record of Frost's long career. I am also grateful to Don Newson, Raymond
Sawyer, Eddie Or be 11, Joe McCorry and others for sharing with me their
memories of Wilfred Frost; to Fred Bamicoat, Paul Boulden and Stewart
Pyper for providing me with copies of articles, letters and reports of Frost's
collections in back issues of the magazine that I do not have easy access
to; to Michael Watkins for the information on the Small-toothed Fruit Bat;
Rosemary Low and Frank Woolham for help identifying birds; and Russell
Tofts for providing a reference I had failed to retain.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.953657" genericHeader="references" page_id="56259778" page_num="181" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.9943532">
A. A. P. 1947. Notes. Avicultural Magazine 53,6:232.
A. A. P, 1948. Personalia. Avicultural Magazine 54,6:209.
A. A. P. 1949. Personalia. Avicultural Magazine 55,6:227-228
A. A. P. 1952. News and Views. Avicultural Magazine 58,5; 186.
A. A. P. 1953. News and Views. Avicultural Magazine 59,4:144.
A. A. R 1954. News &amp; Views. Avicultural Magazine 60,6:243.
A. A. P. 1957. News and Views. Avicultural Magazine 63,6:209.
A. A. P. 1958. News and Views. Avicultural Magazine 64,5:149.
A. A. P. 1959. News and Views. Avicultural Magazine 65,4&amp;5:140.
Anon. 1910. Mr. Frost&apos;s Collection. The Avicultural Magazine Third Series, 1,9:290.
Anon. 1913. Another Indian Collection. The Avicultural Magazine Third Series, 4,7:220.
Anon. 1913. Major Horsbragh's Indian Collection. The Avicultural Magazine Third Series,
4,8:232-235.
Anon. 1920. A Collection from New Guinea, Etc. The Avicultural Magazine Third Series,
11,11:194.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.9993" page_id="56259779"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
182
</page>
<reference confidence="0.98748837254902">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
Anon. 1921. Stray Notes. The Aviculiurai Magazine Third Series, 12,10:152-153.
Anon. 1931. Messrs. Frost's and Mayer's Collections. The Avicultural Magazine Fourth
Series, IX, 11:324.
Anon. 1938. The Short-billed Minivet (with coloured plate). The Avicultural Magazine Fifth
Series, 111,8:205-206.
Beolens, B., Watkins, M., Grayson, M. 2009. The Eponym Dictionary of Mammals. The Johns
Hopkins University Press, Baltimore.
Block, E. 2004. A Species Extinct in Zoos - The Philippine Eagle. International Zoo News
51/6:340-343.
Bonner, K. 1957. Darenth-Hulme, 1957. Avicultural Magazine 63,6:1^3-1^9.
Clements, I. F. 2007. The Clements Checklist of the Birds of the World Sixth Edition,
Christopher Helm, London.
Crosse, D. G. 1925a. The Habits of Lories. The Avicultural Magazine Fourth Series, 3,8:190-
191.
Crosse, D. G. 1925b. Some notes on the Yellow-backed Lory (. Lorius flavopdWjatus ). The
Avicultural Magazine Fourth Series, 3,4:102-103.
Delacour, J. 1943. Pre- and Post-World-War Pheasantries. Avicultural Magazine Fifth Series,
Yen111,5:121-122.
D. S-S. 1930. Mr. Wilfred Frost's Importation. The Avicultural Magazine Fourth Series,
Yen111,11:308.
D. S-S. 1939. The Collections of Mr. Shaw Mayer and Mr. W. I. C. Frost. The Avicultural
Magazine Fifth Series, IYen,8:272.
E. H. 1930. An Index-Guide to The Avicultural Magazine (p.45). The Avicultural Society.
E. H. 1940. Notes. Avicultural Magazine Fifth Series, Yen,9:241-242.
Editor, The. 1927. Avicultural Notes. The Avicultural Magazine Fourth Series, 5,10:273.
Forshaw, J. M. and Cooper, W. T., 1973. Parrots of the World. Doubleday &amp; Company, Inc.,
Garden City, New York.
Frith, C. B. and Beehler, B. M. 1998. The Birds of Paradise. Oxford University Press, Oxford,
New York, Tokyo.
Frost, W. 1910. The Cock of the Rock Rupicola crocea. The Avicultural Magazine Third
Series, 1,11:319-324.
Frost, W. J. C. 1930. The nesting habits of the King Bird of Paradise. The Avicultural Magazine
Fifth Series, Yen111,2:33-35.
Frost, W. I. C. .1936. Mr Porter's "Wanderings in the Far East." The Avicultural Magazine
Fifth Series, 1,12:338-339.
Harrison, C. J. O. 1961. Display from a captive Cock-of-the-Rock. Avicultural Magazine
67,3:102-106.
Hopkinson, E. 1931. The Birds at Paignton Zoo. The Avicultural Magazine Fourth Series,
IX,9:242-251.
Ingram, C. 1913. Birds of Paradise in the West Indies. The Avicultural Magazine Third Series,
5,1:35-41.
Ingram, Sir W. 1911. The Acclimatization of the Greater Bird of Paradise {Paradisea apoda)
in the West Indies. The Avicultural Magazine Third Series, 2,11:142-147.
Ingram, Sir W. 1917. The Great Bird of Paradise on the island of Little Tobago (with Caretaker's
Diary). The Avicultural Magazine Third Series, 8,12:341-361.
Knobel, E. M&gt; 1943. Notes. Avicultural Magazine Fifth Series^ Yen111,5:137.
Martin, A. 1931. The Birds at Keswick. The Avicultural Magazine Fourth Series, IX, 12:334-
339.
Maxwell, R H. 1940. Notes. Avicultural Magazine Fifth Series, Yen,1:32.
Maxwell, P. H. 1952a. &apos;Notes. Avicultural Magazine 58,3:116.
</reference>
<reference confidence="0.271578">
ELLIS - W.J.C. FROST: AN INCOMPLETE BIOGRAPHY
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999312" page_id="56259780"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
183
</page>
<reference confidence="0.970376">
Maxwell, P. H. 1952b. Notes. Avicultural Magazine 58,6:232.
Meams, B. and Meams, R. 1998. The Bird Collectors. Academic Press, San Diego, London,
Boston, New York, Sydney, Tokyo, Toronto.
Porter, S. 1933. The Giant Pitta Pitta maxima. The Avicultural Magazine Fourth Series,
XI, 1:6-7.
Prestwich, A. A. 1943. After Four Years of It! Avicultural Magazine Fifth Series, VIII,6:160-
162.
Prestwich, A. A. 1952. British Aviculturists' Club. Avicultural Magazine 58,5:184-185.
Prestwich, A. A. 1954. British Aviculturists' Club. Avicultural Magazine 60,5:180-181.
Prestwich, A. A. 1955. British Aviculturists' Club. Avicultural Magazine 61,6:325-327.
Rothschild, Lord W. 1930. Exhibition of eggs of the Paradise-Crow (Lycocraxpyrrhopterus
pyrrhopterus ) and Phonygammus keraurenii. Bulletin of the British Ornithologists ' Club
51:9.
Sherriff, A. 1937. The Grey Sibia (with coloured plate). The Avicultural Magazine Fifth Series,
11,12:333-334.
Spence, T. 1955. Breeding the Purple-capped Lory (Domicella domicella). Avicultural
Magazine 61,1:14-17.
Tavistock, Lord. 1938. The Western Golden-headed Dwarf Parrot (with coloured plate). The
Avicultural Magazine Fifth Series, 111,6:149-150.
Vane, E. N. T. 1953. Notes. Avicultural Magazine 59,1:41-42.
Wharton-Tigar, N. 1939. Rarities collected by F. W. Shaw Mayer and W. J. C. Frost. The
Avicultural Magazine Fifth Series, IV,12;299-301.
Yealland, J. J. 1952a. London Zoo Notes. Avicultural Magazine 58,2:79-80.
Yealland, J. J. 1952b. London Zoo Notes. Avicultural Magazine 58,5:190.
Yealland, J. J. 1954. London Zoo Notes. Avicultural Magazine 60,1:33-34.
</reference>
<table confidence="0.442826888888889" page_id="56259780"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
* * *
VISIT TO GERMANY 2011
The Avicultural Society is planning a visit to Germany over the weekend
of September 9th-September 12th 2011. Members will have the opportunity
to visit Wuppertal Zoo, Ludger Bremehr's collection and Koln Zoo. Further
details are available from: Karli Lisiecki, Howard Travel, 12/13 Church
Walk, Trowbridge, Wiltshire BAM 8DX. Tel:01225 777227/E-mail:
karli@howardtravel.com
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.947764" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259780" page_num="183" year="" vol="">
PEKIN ROBIN GROUP
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97774975" page_id="56259780"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
We have set-up a Special Interest Group for those who keep and breed
Pekin Robins Leiothrix lutea. It is being coordinated by Chris Dunn, whose
article about keeping and breeding Pekin Robins will be published in the
next issue of the magazine. If you are interested in participating in this
group, perhaps to exchange birds or find a mate for an unpaired bird, you can
contact Chris by E-mail:chrisdunnl987@hotmail.co.uk/Tel:07413 522485.
The full list of Special Interest Groups and their coordinators can be viewed
on our Website: http ://www.avisoc.co.uk
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999556" page_id="56259781"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
184
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.731499" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259781" page_num="184" year="" vol="">
AN INTERESTING AND UNUSUAL HYBRID
by Fred Bamicoat
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998885421052631" page_id="56259781"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
In 2008, a strange young bird unexpectedly appeared in Peter
Brummage's garden aviary in Benoni here in South Africa. It proved to
be the offspring of an odd male Jacarini Finch or Blue-black Grassquit
Volatinia jacarina and a single female Cuban Finch or Cuban Grassquit
Tiaris canora. It clearly shows features of both its parents, being a small
finch predominately of varying shades of black, with an olive-green back.
The face is jet black, surrounded by the typical crescentic neck-frill of the
Cuban Finch, which is dark grey instead of yellow. Its black chest fades
into grey on the lower belly. A few yellow spots on the side of the head
somewhat detract from the harmony of its appearance. The tail is noticeably
longer and broader than that of its Cuban Finch mother and its dull black
beak is midway between the short conical beak of the Cuban Finch and more
elongated beak of the Jacarini Finch. This hybrid is almost certainly a male
and has an exceptionally loud and penetrating call, more so than either of
its parents. Like its paternal parent it keeps low down and hidden among
the aviary vegetation. I am not aware of any previous record of a hybrid
of the Jacarini Finch and the Cuban Finch only with the congeneric Black-
faced Grassquit T. bicolor. This hybrid underlines the affinity of the genus
Volatinia and the genus Tiaris.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.835554" page_id="56259781"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
* * \0x2756
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.890779" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259781" page_num="184" year="" vol="">
FORESTS OF HOPE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.955406923076923" page_id="56259781"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
BirdLife International is urgently appealing for funds to support its work
in the forests of Western Siem Pang, Cambodia, one of the last remnants of the
ecosystem that once covered large areas of central Indochina. The forests are
extensive and BirdLife International has identified a key site covering over
150,000 hectares (approx. 375,000 acres), with 90% of the habitat still intact
and five Critically Endangered species of bird, the White-shouldered Ibis
Pseudibis davisoni. Giant Ibis Thaumatibis gigantea , White-ramped Vulture
Gyps bengalensis, Slender-billed Vulture G. tenuirostris and Red-headed
Vulture Sarcogyps calvus. This Important Bird Area (IBA) was threatened
by plans to log the forest and convert it into a biofuel plantation, but BirdLife
International has succeeded in having the logging license revoked and
hopes to conserve the forest and manage it under a new agreement with the
government of Cambodia.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998879" page_id="56259782"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
185
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.994899" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259782" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
PARROTS OF THE WORLD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999598884615385" page_id="56259782"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
A field guide dedicated to a group of birds is an unusual concept. Field
guides tend to cover a specific area whereas parrots, of course, are found
throughout the tropics and beyond. Parrots of the World in the excellent
Helm Field Guide series will be welcomed by birdwatchers and bird keepers
alike.
This is the third book with this title by Joseph Forshaw, the renowned
authority, and the second illustrated by Frank Knight. The previous
collaboration, published in 2006, was sub-titled An Identification Guide
and was much too large to handle in the field. The layout of the two books
is similar (with a colour plate on the right and the brief text and map on the
left) but, in this recent publication, the text is limited to the facing page with
the addition of 15 introductory pages.
So how else does this book differ from the 2006 volume apart from
being a paperback and having a different publisher? The colour plates are
virtually identical, but there is the addition of common names and a slight
rearrangement of some images to allow for the smaller page size. There
are also a few alterations to species' order - e.g., hanging parrots now come
before pygmy parrots.
For those who do not have the earlier volume, this will be an extremely
useful and informative book and its smaller size and lighter weight makes
it easier to handle. Frank Knight's plates have an amazing clarity but here
the illustrations are reproduced a fraction darker than the originals. New
subspecies have been added, such as the tucumana race of the Mitred
Conure, with the former subspecies alticola elevated to full species and the
very closely related Hocking's Conure described for the first time. In other
words, this book reflects all the latest taxonomic changes.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.40775525" page_id="56259782"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
Parrots of the World by Joseph Forshaw ISBN 978-1-4081-3034-6,
Helm Field Guides, 336 pages, numerous illustrations, is published by
Christopher Helm Publishers Ltd. Price #24.99.
Rosemary Low
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.923984" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259782" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
LIVING WITH PARROTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9854334" page_id="56259782"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
I had only reached page 10 of Living with Parrots of Different Sizes when
I found myself congratulating the authors out loud! When they decided to
buy two Amazons as pets, they weighed up the pros and cons of parent-reared
and hand-reared young. They decided on parent-reared. The Red-lored
Amazons were six months of age and straight out of their parents' aviary,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999393" page_id="56259783"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
186
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.971481" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259783" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9826042" page_id="56259783"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
yet after six and ten days they were taking seed from the authors' fingers
and after 16 days the male was sitting on the hand. They proved to be easy
to train and to handle.
The Swedish authors, Birgitta Magnusson and Peter Tossberg, had for
some years kept Budgerigars and Cockatiels before deciding to keep larger
parrots. The book describes in a most appealing way their experiences
with their birds. It is also full of practical information. Advice is given
on important decisions that many parrot owners must make. They debated
whether to take on a captive-bred, 11 years old Blue-fronted Amazon
named Morty whose owner was on the point of having him euthanised due
to his aggressive behaviour. They decided to give him a chance although
several previous attempts to rehome him had failed. Morty proved to be
unpredictable and attacked and bit "quicker than a cobra". Despite some
serious injuries they persevered and - suddenly - Morty fell in love with
Birgitta and became totally devoted to her.
I like this book a lot because it describes problems that many parrot
owners face, and how they were successfully overcome. Some of their
observations, with which I totally agree, are rarely published elsewhere.
For example, the authors felt it was important to show a Cockatiel her dead
mate, so that she could understand he had gone. Otherwise she might scream
for a long time, not knowing where he was. The authors ask: "How many
veterinarians are aware of this?"
The section on Budgerigars as pets is outstanding. Their huge popularity
of the 1950s and 1960s declined when larger parrots became available.
Like the authors, I have always maintained that they are perfect pets, being
intelligent, charming and easy to manage. It was interesting to read that
under Swedish law, Budgerigars must live with at least one of their parents
for the first six weeks of their lives, to ensure that they are fed properly.
The photographs by Peter Tossberg (one or more to a page) are superb.
He took an incredible 40,000 shots to achieve the desired results. Those of
the Blue-fronted Amazon in flight show the full beauty of this species. All
their birds are in such perfect feather condition that the photos alone are
worth the price of the book. Cockatiel and Budgerigar owners will enjoy
the enchanting photos of chicks at different stages of their development and
of adults in flight.
I would describe this as a book of extremely useful and very readable
reminiscences, and can recommend it unreservedly.
Living with Parrots of Different Sizes by Birgitta Magnusson and Peter
Tossberg ISBN 9789197847322, published by Tossmet, hardback, 144 pages,
290 photographs, is available price #23.50 via the following website: www.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.7347105" page_id="56259783"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
bokus.com/bok/9789197847322/living-with-parrots-of-different-sizes/
Rosemary Low
</figure>
<page confidence="0.998532" page_id="56259784"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
187
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.981675" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259784" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
CHRISTMAS COCKS-OF-THE-ROCK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98151" page_id="56259784"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
Each year I look forward to receiving a Christmas card from Josef and
Natalie Lindholm with the latest news from the Dallas World Aquarium in
Texas. In this year's card, Josef wrote to say that if the Andean Cock-of-
the-Rock Rupicola peruvianus eggs due to hatch on Christmas Day did so
successfully, the chicks would be the 28th and 29th hatched there since 2007.
Two other breeding females were thought to be about to lay.
Dallas World Aquarium again had a very successful year with araqaris,
with multiple clutches of Curl-crested Pteroglossus beauharnaesii, Ivory-
billed P. azara and Green Araqaris P. viridis. A subspecies which Josef calls
Humboldt's Letter-billed Aragari P inscriptus humboldti hatched young for
the first time at the Dallas World Aquarium.
Quite a number of new species were added to the collection during
the year, these included Flame-faced Tanager Tangara parzudakii.
Saffron-crowned Tanager T. xanthocephala and Beryl-spangled Tanager T.
nigroviridis , Montezuma or Meam's Quail Cyrtonyx montezumae and a pair
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.840692" page_id="56259784"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
of Bronze-winged Pionus Pionus chalcopterus .
* * *
A MIXED BAG
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.785819727272727" page_id="56259784"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
In the 2010 breeding season Bernard Sayers bred: one Chaco Owl Strix
chacoensis , three Burrowing Owls Athene cunicularia, seven Boobook
Owls Ninox boobook , two White-faced Owls Ptilopsis leucotis , three Indian
Scops Owls Otus bakkamoena , three Tropical Screech Owls Megascops
choliba , two Black-winged Lories Eos cyanogenia , five Black-cheeked
Lovebirds Agapornis nigrigenis , two Grey Peacock-Pheasants Polyplectrom
bicalcaratum , 10 Triangular-spotted or Speckled Pigeons Columba guinea ,
three Lemon Doves Aplopelia larvata, one Emerald Dove Chalcophaps
indica and about 20 Java Sparrows Padda oryzivora of the grey wild-type.
By Bernard's high standards it was not, he wrote, " a brilliant breeding
season," but there were "just enough babies" to keep him "amused."
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.349131" page_id="56259784"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.399766" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259784" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
NEW DIRECTOR GENERAL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8578586" page_id="56259784"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
Dr Mark Pilgrim, who joined Chester Zoo as a bird keeper in 1988
and is European Studbook holder for the Equadorian Amazon Amazona
autumnalis lilacina, became the zoo's new Director General on October 1st
2010, taking over from Prof. Gordon McGregor Reid, who stepped down
after 18 years at the zoo.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998715" page_id="56259785"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
188
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.980546" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259785" page_num="188" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
AN EARLIER UNSUCCESSFUL ATTEMPT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.929226115384615" page_id="56259785"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
Chester Zoo which currently has five Red Birds-of-Paradise Paradisaea
rubra , two males and three females, succeeded in breeding the Red Bird-of-
Paradise for the first time in the UK in 2003, when two chicks fledged in its
Islands in Danger exhibit (see Vol 110, No.l, pp,20-27 (2004)), At the time,
I was unaware (as I suspect most other members were) that there had been
an earlier unsuccessful breeding attempt at Paignton Zoo in the 1930s,
Looking through back issues for articles by or references to the late
Kenneth Smith for a biography being prepared by Russell Tofts, in the
first of three obituaries to Herbert Whitley by H. S. Stokes, Kenneth Smith
and C. H. Trevisick the owner of Ilfracombe Zoo Park (Vol.61, No.6,
pp.318-322 (1955)), I was surprised to read that a Red Bird of Paradise
had hatched chicks at Paignton Zoo, but had evidentally failed to rear them
to independence. Clifford and Dawn Frith, who were then writing their
book Birds of Paradise: Nature, Art &amp; History (Frith&amp;Frith, 2010), wanted
to know more details, such as which year this breeding attempt occurred
but, apparently, Whitley only kept records of his domestic animals - not his
wild ones.
Following the death of Frank Woolham (who worked with Kenneth
Smith at Belle Vue Zoo in the 1940s), his wife Meg sent me a few bits and
pieces that she thought might be of interest to me, amongst which was a
copy of a magazine called The Foreigner (Vo).4, Part 3, May-June 1937)
published by Keston Foreign Bird Farm, It has an article on the King Bird-
of-Paradise Cicinnurus regius by John Yealland (pp. 105-106) in which he
mentioned that Herbert Whitley had almost succeeded in breeding the Red
Bird of Paradise - in 1936 - but, unfortunately, lost one chick at nine days
old and the second chick at 12 days old.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.538653" page_id="56259785"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.813241" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259785" page_num="188" year="" vol="">
RECENT ARRIVALS AT CHESTER ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.959724272727273" page_id="56259785"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
Recent arrivals at Chester Zoo include four Black-necked Weavers
Ploceus nigricollis , Red-and-yellow Barbets Trachyphonus erythrocephalus
and Brazilian Tanagers Ramphocelus bresilius , all from Copenhagen Zoo,
Denmark. A male Collared Grosbeak Mycerobas affinis has arrived as a
mate for the zoo's lone female and Brown Wood Owls Strix leptogrammica
have arrived from the Cotswold Wildlife Park.
Keepers used a very realistic looking West African Black Crowned
Crane Balearica p. pavonina puppet when rearing three chicks and to
assist the conservation of the crane's West African coastal habitat, the zoo
has provided #7,925 (approx. US$12,000) as part of its support for in situ
conservation initiatives.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.993522" page_id="56259786"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
189
</page>
<table confidence="0.701481266666667" page_id="56259786"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
Contributors to Volume 116 - 2010
Bamicoat, Fred
An interesting and unusual hybrid.......184
Bertagnolio, Paolo and Racheli, Luigi
Anew parrotlet from Colombia, Forpusflavicollis........................... 128
Bralsford, Gary
Breeding the Magpie Shrike Corvinella melanoleuca .155
Breeding the Taiwan Yuhina Ynhina hrunneiceps .38
Keeping and breeding the Tropical Mockingbird
Mimus gilvus gracilis .......97
Brickell, Neville
The Cuckoo Finch Anomalospiza imherbis .....150
Bruslund Jensen, Simon
Weltvogelpark Walsrode - the beginning of a new era...25
Bruslund Jensen, Simon and Kirchoffel, Kerstin
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.817147545454545" page_id="56259786"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
The successful breeding of the Blue-necked or Azure-headed Tanager
Tangara cyanicollis at Weltvogelpark Walsrode, Germany...74
de Chabannes, Pierre
Diary of a week spent photographing birds at Weltvogelpark Walsrode 109
The bird collection at Taipei Zoo......63
The spirit of Jean Delacour lives on at Parc de Cleres ....16
Ellis, Malcolm
W. J. C. (Wilfred) Frost: an incomplete biography.158
Elston, J. J., Unger, K. and Dunn, R.
Reproductive behaviour of the Saddle-billed Stork Ephippiorhynchus
senegalensis and developmental behaviour of the chicks.100
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.6937075" page_id="56259786"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
Gibson, Derek
Hand-rearing a White-crowned Robin-Chat Cossypha albicapilla
at Exmoor Zoo.....30
The White-naped Crane Grus vipio ..............78
</figure>
<page confidence="0.995375" page_id="56259787"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
190
</page>
<table confidence="0.965962291666667" page_id="56259787"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
Contributors to Volume 116 - 2010 (cont'd)
Gregson, Jo
The Mousebirds ......... 40
The Rainforest Dragons ....... 145
Madindou, Ireene and Mulwa, Ronald
Grey Parrot Report II: Some conservation aspects concerning the
African Grey Parrot Psittacus erithacus in Kakamega Forest, Kenya:
assessment of trade and habitat destruction.... 88
Matthews, Simon
A note on the courtship behaviour of the Collared Grosbeak
Mycerobas affinis ...............43
Breeding the Moustached Laughingthrush Ianthocincla cineracea
at Waddesdon Manor.........59
Nji, Ajaga, Tamungang, Simon A., Asong, W. L., Fidelia, Mbafor,
Antoine, Tsafack and Nji, Sabi B.
Challenges and opportunities for sustainable wildlife management
in Cameroon: the story of Peggy an African Grey Parrot..........2
Restall, Robin
Is the Pin-tailed Whydah Vidua macroura a brood-parasite of the
Black-faced Grassquit Tiaris bicolor on Puerto Rico?....49
Silva Moraton, Derian A.
Breeding the Yellow-shouldered Amazon Amazona barbadensis .35
Stocks, Peter
The Rufous-legged Owl Strix rufipes ....133
</table>
<page confidence="0.998948" page_id="56259788"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
191
</page>
<table confidence="0.678883875" page_id="56259788"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
Index to Volume 116 - 2010
Amazona barbadensis , former pet birds breeding.......35
Amazon, Yellow-shouldered, former pet birds breeding...35
Anomalospiza imberbis, related to the Vidua whydahs and indigobirds 150
Book Reviews
International Zoo Yearbook, Volume 44...135
Living with Parrots of Different Sizes.....185
Parrots of the World...........185
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.924053590909091" page_id="56259788"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
While Flocks Last.............. 44
Cassowaries, in captivity, keeping, breeding, rearing of young.145
Casuarius spp., in captivity, keeping, breeding, rearing of young.145
Colius spp., keeping, breeding, hand-rearing young.40
Corvinella melanoleuca, possible first breeding in the UK.....155
Cossypha albicapilla , hand-reared at Exmoor Zoo ..... 30
Crane, White-naped, its keeping and breeding at Exmoor Zoo.78
Ephippiorhynchus senegalensis , breeding, development of chicks.100
Finch, Cuban, a female x male Jacarini Finch hybrid.... 184
Finch, Cuckoo, related to the Vidua whydahs and indigobirds.. 150
Finch, Jacarini, a male x female Cuban Finch hybrid........ 184
Forpus flavicollis, a new parrotlet from Colombia...128
Frost, W. J. C. (Wilfred), an incomplete biography of the collector.158
Grassquit, Black-faced, can it hatch and raise whydah chicks? ......49
Grassquit, Blue-black, a male x female Cuban Grassquit hybrid.184
Grassquit, Cuban, a female x male Blue-black Grassquit hybrid.184
Grosbeak, Collared, notes on courtship behaviour......43
Grus vipio, its keeping and breeding at Exmoor Zoo...78
Hybrid, an unusual example in a South African aviary .. 184
lanthocincla cineracea, breeding at Waddesdon Manor.....59
Laughingthrush, Moustached, breeding at Waddesdon Manor.59
Mimus gilvus gracilis , keeping and breeding...97
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999002" page_id="56259789"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
192
</page>
<table confidence="0.84940695" page_id="56259789"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
Index to Volume 116 - 2010 (cont'd)
Mockingbird, Tropical, keeping and breeding.... 97
Mousebirds, keeping, breeding, hand-rearing young.....40
Mycerobas affinis , notes on courtship behaviour............... 43
News &amp; Views.....45,96,136,187
Obituaries
Claude Payne OBE.....143
Frank Woolham.........142
Owl, Rufous-legged, Chaco, comparative newcomers to aviculture..... 133
Parc de Cleres, the spirit of Jean Delacour lives on.16
Parrot, Grey, in Cameroon, the story of Peggy.2
Parrot, Grey, in Kakamega Forest, Kenya.... 88
Parrotlet, a possible new species from Colombia......... 128
Psittacus erithacus, in Cameroon and in Kenya.....2,88
Robin-Chat, White-crowned, hand-reared at Exmoor Zoo.30
Shrike, Magpie, possible first breeding in the UK.155
Stork, Saddle-billed, breeding, development of chicks ... 100
Strix rufipes , S. chaoensis, comparative newcomers to aviculture.133
Tanager, Blue-necked or Azure-headed, bred in Germany.74
Tangara cyanicollis , bred in Germany.74
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.562194" page_id="56259789"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
Tiaria bicolor , is it used as a host by Vidua macroura on Puerto Rico?.. 49
Tiaris canora, a female x male Volatinia jacarina hybrid.184
Vidua macroura , is it a brood parasite of Tiaris bicolor on Puerto Rico? 49
Volatinia jacarina , a male x female Tiaris canora hybrid.184
Weltvogelpark Walsrode, photographing birds at.................................. 109
Weltvogelpark Walsrode, the beginning of a new era........25
Whydah, Pin-tailed, can its chicks be hatched and raised by a grassquit?. 49
Yuhina brunneiceps , breeding..............38
Yuhina, Taiwan, breeding........ 38
Zoo, Taipei, the bird collection...... 63
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99725" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259790" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONCERN OVER GREY PARROTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.902122481481482" page_id="56259790"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
David Waugh, Director of Loro Parque Fundacion, reports that following
the work of Melo and O'Ryan and additional work by BirdLife International's
Taxonomic Working Group, based on genetic, morphological, plumage and
vocal differences, the African Grey Parrot has been split into two seperate
species: the Grey Parrot Psittacus erithacus and the Timneh Grey Parrot
P. timneh. The latter, of course, having previously been regarded as a
subspecies of the former.
Whereas estimates of the number of Grey Parrots in the wild vary from
680,000 to 13 million, it is believed there may be as few as 120,000 Timneh
Grey Parrots remaining in the wild. Therefore, Loro Parque Fundacion
is financing a three to four years study which will attempt to assess its
distribution and abundance and the impact of trade and habitat changes on
the wild population, which is found from southern Guinea to Sierra Leone,
Liberia, Mali and Cote d'Ivoire, west of the Comoe River.
Dr Waugh also expressed concern about the increased number of wild-
caught Grey Parrots being exported from countries such the Democratic
Republic of Congo and Guinea, both of which have exceeded their permitted
quotas. The Democratic Republic of Congo is permitted to export 5,000
per year, but exported more than 12,000. The main destinations for legally
caught Grey Parrots are South Africa (33%), the Middle East (27%), Serbia
(22%) and Asian countries (17%). Many more, however, are thought to be
exported illegally.
On December 24th 2010, 730 wild-caught adult Grey Parrots, part of a
consignment of 1,650 of these parrots, caught in the Democratic Republic of
Congo and exported to South Africa, were found dead in their crates, when
the flight from Johannesburg landed at Durban. Ten more died later. The
cause of death was unknown.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.486134" page_id="56259790"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.722722" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259790" page_num="" year="" vol="">
BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.8684675">
All future enquiries regarding back issues should be addressed to: Peter
Stocks, Hon. Secretary and Treasurer, The Avicultural Society, Sheraton
Lodge, Station Road, Southminster, Essex CM0 7EW. E-mail:otusscops@
talktalk.net/Tel:01621 772427
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.77837" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259791" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.961076266666667" page_id="56259791"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Rainforest Dragons
by Jo Gregson.145
The Cuckoo Finch Anomalospiza imberbis
by Neville Brickell.150
Breeding the Magpie Shrike Corvinella melanoleuca
by Gary Bralsford.155
W. J. C. (Wilfred) Frost: an incomplete biography
by Malcolm Ellis.158
An interesting and unusual hybrid
by Fred Bamicoat.184
Book Reviews
Parrots Of The World.185
Living With Parrots.185
News &amp; Views.187
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
</table>
</algorithms>
