<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.7246166" page_id="56253543"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 114
No. 4
2008
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253542" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.984827516129033" page_id="56253542"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2008 as for 2007: British
Isles #18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please).
The subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the
Society later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of
the AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, ARCADIA, THE MOUNTS, TOTNES, DEVON TQ9 7QJ,
UK.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TN13 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; SortCode:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail: Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have not
been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of a
particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history. Articles
should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the scientific
names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given. References
cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line drawings,
black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular point in
the article will be used where possible and should be clearly captioned. If
authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when submitting the
article and write their name on the back of each photograph. Tables and
graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be aware of
the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of the page
which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997594" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56253542" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982475333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<figure confidence="0.7453662" page_id="56253541"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
Vol. 114 - No. 4 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2008
THE WIDENING DISTRIBUTION OF THE RED AVADAVAT
Amandava amandava ,
WITH AVICULTURAL NOTES
by Ian Hinze
Other names
Include: Avadavat, Tiger Finch, Strawberry Finch and Red Munia.
Description
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.997316826086956" page_id="56253541"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Length 10cm (4in). The male A. a. amandava in breeding plumage
usually has the forehead, face, throat, sides of the neck, breast, flanks, rump
and upper tail-coverts a deep scarlet red, but this can vary from coppery red to
crimson. There is a black stripe from the gape to the eye and a short, narrow
white stripe below the eye. The sides of the lower neck and breast, flanks,
rump and upper tail-coverts are spotted with white, each feather possessing
a single white spot near the tip. The top of the head and the nape are usually
a slightly less bright shade of red and have the dark brown basal part of the
feathers showing. The mantle and back are dull brown with a bronzy red or
dull scarlet fringe to the feathers. The general appearance of the upperparts
may vary from mainly brown to mainly red. The wings and tail are blackish
brown with white terminal spots on the coverts, inner secondaries and outer
tail feathers. The lower belly and under tail-coverts are brownish black, with
some of the feathers having a reddish tip. The under wing-coverts are buff.
When very new, the red feathers have a distinct chestnut or coppery tone,
but later become pure red. The irides are reddish orange to red. The bill is
red with part or all of the ridge of the culmen dusky or blackish. The legs
and feet are fleshy brown.
The female is dull earth brown to greyish brown on the upperparts,
except for the wings, rump and upper tail-coverts, which are like those of
the breeding male, but with the red parts usually slightly less bright. The
facial markings are also like those of the breeding male, except that the
stripe below the eye is creamy (rather than white) and less prominent. The
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999508" page_id="56253540"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
146
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.981376404761905" page_id="56253540"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
HINZE - RED AV AD A VAT
sides of the face, neck and upper breast are light brownish grey. The throat
and most of the underparts are whitish or pale buff, with the latter colour
suffusing the grey of the breast and shading to yellowish buff or even huffish
orange on the belly.
The male resembles the female when he is in his eclipse or non-breeding
plumage. The subsequent moult back into breeding plumage is thorough
and involves the wing and tail quills. Based on observations of captive birds
it is possible that many males in the wild begin moulting back into the red
plumage before the non-breeding plumage is complete.
The juvenile is dull greyish brown, shading to huffish white below, with
two conspicuous pale wing bars formed by the huffish tips to the median
and greater wing-coverts. The irides and bill are at first a dull colour.
Young males moult from juvenile into non-breeding plumage, often with
some dusky and huffish barring on the flanks. The first moult is a complete
moult. The nestling is dark skinned with brownish down and has multiple
mouth markings.
Amandava a. flavidiventris is a little smaller and males in breeding
plumage have the red on the breast slightly less bright and shading through
pinkish orange to golden or yellowish buff, more or less suffused with orange
on the belly. The white spotting extends across the front of the breast and
lower neck, with some feathers having whitish shaft streaks. The female
has the breast more yellowish drab than grey and the belly is a deeper buff
and usually strongly tinged with orange.
Amandava a. punicea is similar in size to A. a. flavidiventris. In breeding
plumage the male is usually a brighter red than A. a. amandava and has
smaller white spots. It lacks or has only a slight black mark from the gape
to the eye.
The Avadavat's generic name, Amandava , is a corruption of Ahmadabad,
the name of the town in Gujerat, India, from where the first examples were
brought.
Field guide
The male in breeding plumage is a tiny, bright or coppery red bird, with
conspicuous white spots and a red bill, which distinguish it from all other
sympatric small finch-like birds. The female and male in non-breeding have
dull brownish upper parts , with darker wings and lightly spotted wing bars,
light brownish grey underparts with a whitish or huffish throat and belly,
and a red rump and upper tail-coverts.
Voice
There is some geographical and possibly individual variation in the
song, which is very sweet-sounding and varied, though shortish, and on a
descending scale (Goodwin, 1982). The female also sings but less often and
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.310841" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253539" page_num="147" year="" vol="">
HINZE - RED AVADAVAT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99905" page_id="56253539"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
147
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.94790915" page_id="56253539"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
her song is shorter; it also lacks the clear loud notes of the male (Trollope,
1983). Clement et al (1993) stated that the song is a feeble or weak but
high-pitched warble, with softer and sweeter twittering notes, delivered by
the male usually from the top of a reed or a similar prominent perch. Trollope
(1993) wrote that the song is a pleasant rather melancholy series of fluting
notes, ending in a clear whistle, which can be heard from some distance.
Roberts (in Cramp &amp; Perrins, 1994) recorded a male singing from the top of
a Typha reed in Pakistan. It had a rather weak, soft song, comprising rather
spaced-out groups of very thin, high-pitched "tsi" calls interspersed with
much louder, drawn-out whistles, some rising in pitch at the end, some falling
slightly; then another series of "tsi" calls, followed by a rather more rapid
pretty fluting phase on a descending scale; the whole sequence amounting to
" tsi-tsi-tsi twe-e-e-e-h tsi-tsi- twe-e-e-h tw~o~o~k tsi-tsi twe-twe-te-dee-slu",
repeated four to five times. There is a shrill 44 &apos;chirp" call-note (Lekagul &amp;
Cronin, 1974); the call is usually a thin "teeF or "tsF, but there is also a
variety of high-pitched chirps or squeaks, or rather shrill but sweet-sounding
calls, uttered in several situations, such as when the bird is perched or in
flight. These calls are usually monosyllabic but several may be repeated at
very short intervals. A rather loud, long drawn version of its usual call is
given when attacking or when threatening a rival, but not when repulsing
a lower-ranked individual A still louder version is given by parents when
they perceive their fledged young to be in danger. A rapidly repeated 'run-
together 5 series of notes, in a very excited tone and on a descending scale
is often given, normally while the bird is in a typical rather upright singing
posture, with the belly feathers somewhat erect and those of the crown
sometimes erect and sometimes appressed. Such a series of shrill notes
appears to function as an alternative song. A foraging male's contact call,
when he was separated from his mate, consisted of a short " &apos;psee, pswee " in
a rapid staccato repetition. The nest call is a series of soft, rapidly repeated
notes, " tee-tee-tee " or u teh-teh-teh-teh..# f (Clement at al 1993; Cramp &amp;
Perrins, 1994; Goodwin, 1982). Cramp and Perrins (1994) provided an
audiospectogram of the calls.
Status and distribution
Common or locally common. Global population trends have not been
quantified, but the species is not believed to approach the thresholds for the
population criterion of the IUCN Red List (i.e. declining more than 30% in
10 years or three generations). For these reasons, the species is evaluated
as of Least Concern.
Amandava a. amandava: central and western Pakistan to southern
Kashmir and throughout India (except the east and south-west coastal areas)
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998646" page_id="56253538"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
148
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.678211" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253538" page_num="148" year="" vol="">
HINZE - RED AVADAVAT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.925759025" page_id="56253538"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
north to the foothills of the Himalayas, southern Nepal east to Assam and
Bangladesh.
Amandava a. flavidiventris : south-west China (southern Yunnan and
possibly also east to Kweichow) south to Myanmar (Burma) and the Lesser
Sunda Islands (Lombok, Flores, Sumba, Roti and Timor).
Amandava a. punicea: south-east Thailand, southern Kampuchea,
extreme south-east China (south-east Kwangtung and Hainan), Vietnam,
Java and Bali.
Introduced distribution
Spain, Portugal, Italy, southern Israel (Eilat?), Egypt, Saudi Arabia
(Riyadh?), South Africa, Reunion, Mauritius, Hong Kong, Malaysia
(Singapore), Sumatra, Japan (Honshu, Kyushu and Shikoku), Philippines
(Luzon and Manila), Fiji (Viti Levu), Hawaiian Islands (Oahu), Guadaloupe,
Martinique, Puerto Rico and the Dominican Republic. It has also been
introduced unsuccessfully into the UK, France, Germany, the Comoros, Sri
Lanka, South Andaman Island and Tahiti (Clement et ah 1993; Costa et al.
1997; Cramp &amp; Perrins, 1994; Raffaele et al. 1998; Lever, 1987).
In the UK in the late 1940s, about 30 individuals believed to have escaped
from a consignment of imported birds at Heathrow Airport (London),
appeared later at nearby Perry Oaks Sewage Farm. It was a wonderful old-
fashioned sewage farm, with stinking, bird-rich, morasses of activated sludge
in various stages of drying out, jungles of long grass, docks, thistles and other
vegetation. The Avadavats thrived throughout the summer and evidently
managed to breed, as juveniles were later seen on the wing. However, by late
November, after competing for the decreasing seed supplies with the autumn
influx of Reed Buntings Emberiza schoeniclus and Tree Sparrows Passer
montanus (which, like so many other birds, were then much commoner in
southern England than they are now), as well as having to withstand the colder
weather and the shorter hours of daylight, only one wretched bird, alone and
desperately calling for company, remained. From the mid-1950s-1960s other
escapees, often in the company of Asiatic munias and African waxbills, could
be seen flying about the sewage farm and marshy areas outside the perimeter
of the airport. However, not a solitary individual is known to have survived
an English winter (Goodwin, 1993; Trollope, 1983).
In France (date of introduction unknown) the species survived for
several years in the wild near Orleans before eventually dying out in 1974
(Lever, 1987). It has also bred in Germany, feeding mainly on the half-ripe
seeds of the grasses Panicum crus-galli and Phleum arenarium but, as in
England, probably succumbed in the winter (Goodwin, 1982). In Spain,
the Red Avadavat was first noticed in the wild in 1974, in Arganda, about
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.310539" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253537" page_num="149" year="" vol="">
HINZE - RED AVADAVAT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998061" page_id="56253537"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
149
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.995542170731707" page_id="56253537"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
15km (9 miles) south-east of Madrid, where the species was still present and
breeding 10 years later. The Red Avadavat was first captured in the wild in
1978, in the Extremadura region, south-west of Madrid. It is now known to
be breeding in large numbers in marshland along the rivers of the Guadiana
basin from a point 10km (approx. 6 miles) south of Badajoz (close to the
border with Portugal) to beyond Villanueva de la Serena, a distance of some
110km (approx. 68 miles). Cramp and Perrins (1994) reported that in the
Guadiana basin, in Extremadura, it occupies wetlands dominated by Typha
reed mace and Phragmites reeds, as well as meadows and irrigated crops
such as lucerne, maize and tomatoes. In Granada it is found in sugar cane
plantations and reed beds. It breeds from August-November, before the
onset of the autumnal rains. In January 1984 the population was estimated
to number 4,000 and, choosing swampy ground to nest and being primarily
granivorous, it did not appear to be competing with any native species. It
is continuing to increase and expand its range. In Portugal it appears to
have become established in the Eastern Alentejo, along the Guadiana River
in the Elvas-Campo Major region and at Barroco Marsh. It has also been
recorded at Barrinha de Esmoriz, the Sado Valley, Baixo Alentejo and in
the Algarve, where an individual was ringed (banded) in 1978 and where
it is now recorded regularly in the vicinity of Faro, Silves and Portimao.
In 1994 it was estimated that the maximum number at Barroco Marsh was
10-15 individuals and, in March 1995, in the Elvas area, where the species
is common, there were at least 100 individuals. At Barrinha de Esmoriz it
is currently seen only in small numbers and only in summer. It frequently
associates with the Common Waxbill Estrilda astrild , with the latter
predominating (Costa et al. 1997).
In Treviso, Italy, in 1987, escaped or deliberately released cage birds
and/or their descendents were reported by Mezzavilla and Battistella (in
Cramp &amp; Perrins, 1994) to be occupying reed beds and stands of rush Juncus
and sedge Carex. They often favour clay pits, especially those filled with
water. Three hundred birds were recorded including, in 1983-1985, 80-90
breeding pairs along the River Sile. Survival through cold winters presents
severe problems but the species appears able to recover from these. It has
been observed on the grasses Phleum , Lolium , Elymus and also on reeds
Phragmites and reed mace Typha.
In Egypt, A. a. amandava was mentioned first by Antonori, who shot
several near Alexandria in 1861, these presumably having escaped or been
deliberately released from captivity. On May 15th 1903 and on January
13th 1905 Walter Innes collected specimens near Cairo. He also mentioned
that Avadavats were often absent from Giza Zoological Gardens for several
months but returned in large flocks late in the year to breed. They were
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.992619" page_id="56253536"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
150
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.985069166666667" page_id="56253536"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
HINZE - RED A V AD A VAT
also found later inland at El Faiyum in February 1924. From at least 1914-
1924 the species was apparently common and breeding at several localities
- such as near El Giza, Inhas el Rami, Bilbeis and around the Delta Barrage
- within a 30km (approx. 18 miles) radius of Cairo. However, for some
unexplained reason, it disappeared thereafter, although some were noted
in 1928 at Luxor. January-February 1974 the species reappeared and was
reported 4km (approx. 21/2 miles) south-west of Isma' iliya towards El
Wasifiya and Abu Suweir on the west bank of the Suez Canal, with flocks
of five to 10 individuals frequently being observed. Since the late-1970s
Avadavats have been noted with increasing frequency in the Nile Delta, the
species clearly being widely distributed in the region. In 1978 several were
noted at Asher Talaaf, 30km (approx. 18 miles) south-west of Alexandria.
Near Suez it is presently well established in reed beds, where up to 100
have been observed regularly since 1980. On April 10th 1982 a female was
spotted at this locality carrying nesting material. On February 4th 1981,25
birds were recorded at El Saff, six were spotted on September 27th 1985 at
a few localities between Mazghuna and El Wasta and a lone bird was seen
the following day south of Beni Suef. Since autumn 1983 avadavats have
been noted at Lake Qarub, where they were found breeding in November
1983. Up to 30 birds, including immature birds, were observed between
May-July 1986 in reed beds near Alexandria. The species is common along
the river just south of Cairo. In April 1997, 60 individuals were counted at
Crocodile Island, Luxor and January 12th-January 20th 2001, small flocks
were seen between Korn Ombo (50km (approx. 31 miles) north of Aswan)
and Nag Hammadi. In May 2002 at least three colonies were found in
reed beds between Luxor and Qena, where the species was presumed to be
breeding (Fry &amp; Keith, 2004; Grieve, 1997; Goodman &amp; Meininger, 1989;
El Din, 2001; Lever, 1987).
Clement et al. (1993) listed it as having been recorded at Eilat in southern
Israel, but I can find no further information on this. Paz (1987) did not
include it in his work on the birds of Israel, so it is likely to have been after
1987. Clement et al. (1993) also listed the species as having been recorded
in Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.
In South Africa it has been reported as breeding in old weaver and bishop
nests at Rosherville, Gauteng (Hockey, Dean &amp; Ryan, 2005). However,
Andre Marx (pers. comm.), who has been involved in collating regional
rarity records for that part of South Africa, said, the species is unknown in
Gauteng and he has not heard it mentioned in the past 20 years.
In the nineteenth century, the Red Avadavat was imported onto the
Comoros Islands, off the coast of East Africa, where specimens were
collected on Mayotte in 1884 and on Moheli in 1904. It has since died out
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.310805" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253535" page_num="151" year="" vol="">
HINZE - RED AVADAVAT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998913" page_id="56253535"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
151
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999323024390244" page_id="56253535"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
on these islands. It is believed Red Avadavats were taken to Mauritius as
aviary birds early in the eighteenth century, possibly by the first French
settlers in 1715 and survived there until they were wiped out by a cyclone
in 1892, or about 1896. They were also imported onto the island of Reunion
(possibly by the early colonists in 1664 or later from Mauritius) where, in
1987, they were still established but rare (Lever, 1987).
The nominate subspecies^, a. amandava , is known to have been exported
from Bengal, India, to Sri Lanka (Ceylon), prior to 1874 and escapees were
established in Colombo but have subsequently disappeared (Lever, 1987).
Colonel R. C. Tyler is attributed with having released 25 Red Avadavats at
Port Blair on South Andaman Island at the time of the establishment of a
penal colony there in 1858, but they all died out (Lever, 1987).
Clement et al. (1993) listed the Red Avadavat as having been introduced
to Singapore. In 1880 it was said to have been abundant on Singapore Island
and was still common there up until 1924. Thereafter it disappeared but
large numbers were imported after the Second World War. Those seen there
in the wild today are probably escaped or released cage birds. Amandava a.
punicea is believed to have been the subspecies that was introduced. This
subspecies is also the one believed to have been introduced to Sumatra
prior to 1947, but natural colonisation from Java is also a distinct possibility
(Lever, 1987).
Strange (2002) listed the Red Avadavat as having been introduced
in Kota Kinabalu, Sabah, but gave no further details. In the Philippines,
Red Avadavats are believed to have escaped from captivity and become
established in the environs of Manila, on the island of Luzon, prior to 1946,
but Clement et al. (1993) reported that the species has not been seen in the
wild in recent years.
The precise status of the Red Avadavat in Hong Kong has yet to be
determined. It has been observed at Mai Po, with flocks of over 30 birds
found regularly on the marshes at Long Valley, where they probably bred and
may also have bred occasionally elsewhere. The birds may have escaped
or been deliberately released or could be natural vagrants of the subspecies
A. a. flavidiventris from the mainland (Lever, 1987).
In Japan this species was imported to the island of Honshu as a cage bird
prior to 1940 and has since become established in the Gihu, Aiti, Tokyo,
Saitawa and Tiba prefectures. In 1974 the Japanese Ornithological Society
reported that although there seemed to have been few recent records, the
species continued to breed in Honshu and, up until 1981, probably also on
Kyushu and Shikoku. Up until 1985 the most notable sites for the species
were at Oikoen and Tamagawa near Tokyo, and from Kanto southwards
it had become quite common in its preferred habitat of tall grasses, marsh
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998884" page_id="56253534"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
152
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.679756" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253534" page_num="152" year="" vol="">
HINZE - RED AVADAVAT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998951487804878" page_id="56253534"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
reeds, riverbanks and rough land, with flocks of up to 200 being reported
(Lever, 1987).
In Fiji, the species became established in the suburbs of Suva on the
south coast of Viti Levu, having it is believed been imported by the Hon.
Mr Remenschneider sometime before 1906. In reports from 1966-1982, it
was listed as common in agricultural, urban, suburban and grassland habitats
on the main island and of being a bird of open country, agricultural land and
gardens, but also found at the forest edge and in substantial clearings, on
Viti Levu and Vanua Levu. On these islands it is common, though usually
occurring only in small groups but, on occasion, and especially on the way
to communal roosts, sometimes forming large flocks. The subspecies is
believed to be A. a. flavidiventris . It has been recorded raiding seedling
rice, however, a contrary report written later stated that although the Red
Avadavat is especially partial to Jungle Rice Echinochloa colenum , it rarely
feeds on cultivated varieties.
In 1938, Eastham Guild released the species on Tahiti, where it nested
successfully shortly thereafter, but has since died out (Lever, 1987).
The Red Avadavat is believed to have been imported as a cage bird to
the island of Oahu in the Hawaiian archipelago in the first few years of the
1900s and to have become established for many years in and around Pearl
Harbour, where it was once reported as being nowhere particularly common.
The Hui Manu (Bird Society) is said to have brought more in between 1930-
1968 and, in 1963, the population was estimated to be approximately 100.
In 1975 the Hawaiian Aubudon Society reported that some were established
in grassland near sugar cane plantations on the Waipo Peninsula in Pearl
Harbour where, however, they were much less abundant in the West Loch area
than the more recently imported Black-headed Mannikin Lonchura malacca.
In 1976 the Red Avadavat was listed as local and uncommon in agricultural
and pastureland (away from the peninsula) on Oahu. In 1977 its presence
as a long-established and breeding resident was confirmed and, by 1981, the
species was said to be increasing its range on Oahu (Lever, 1987).
The British or French probably introduced it onto the West Indian island
of Guadeloupe as a cage bird in the eighteenth century. It was first seen in
the wild, in recent times, about 1965, in the vicinity of Pointe-a-Pitre on the
south-west coast of Grande-Terre. Later it appeared in the Baie de Forte-de-
France on the west coast of Martinique, where it became established from
Le Lamentin in the north southwards to Riviere-Salee and the Usine Petit-
Bourg. Up until 1987 the Red Avadavat was and, most likely still is, the
most widespread exotic bird on Guadeloupe and has probably colonised the
whole of Grande-Terre and the west-north-west of Basse-Terre. It favours
low-lying damp areas, the edges of ponds, roadside verges and the borders of
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.310836" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253533" page_num="153" year="" vol="">
HINZE - RED AVADAVAT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999564" page_id="56253533"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
153
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.992267780487805" page_id="56253533"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
fields. Generally it occurs in pairs or small family groups, though sometimes
it is seen in flocks of up to 50 individuals. It feeds largely on Panicum
maximum , which was introduced many years ago from West Africa and has
taken over disused sugar cane fields - wherein the Red Avadavat is believed
to nest - and roadside verges. Along with other introduced estrildids, the
Red Avadavat is thought to compete to the disadvantage of the Indigenous
Black-faced Grassquit Haris bicolor (Lever, 1987). According to Raffaele et
al(l 998) it was recorded on Martinique for the first time in 1970 and is now
common on both Guadeloupe and Martinique. On Puerto Rico the species
is believed to have been introduced in the late 1960s and is now reported to
be locally common in the lowlands and, in the Dominican Republic, a flock
was reported in 1997 (Raffaele et ah 1998).
Habitat, general behaviour and feeding
It particularly favours riparian or marshy areas of tall grass, reed beds,
bushes or other rank growth, but also frequents sugar cane fields, grassy
clearings in jungle, open woodland, cultivated areas and similar places,
as well as gardens (Goodwin, 1982). Generally a lowland species, it also
occurs up to 1,500m (approx. 4,920ft) on the islands of Java and Bali and
up to 2,400m (approx. 7,875ft) on the Lesser Sunda Islands (Clement et
ah 1993). It is usually observed in pairs or small flocks of up to 30, but at
certain times of the year flocks can exceed 100 individuals, sometimes in
the company of munias, sparrows or buntings. It roosts communally in reed
beds and sugar cane. It is fast and agile in flight and when disturbed it often
rises quickly at a steep angle and flies rather high. It feeds largely on grass
seeds, primarily picking them off the ground or plucking them from low
growing or prostrate plants, but it also takes seeds from tall stems. Insects,
too, are most likely taken (Clement et al. 1993; Goodwin, 1982).
Courtship display
In the courtship display, which may be performed by either sex, the bird
holds a piece of grass or a feather by the firmest end of its stem or shaft and,
with its body fluffed out, bows slowly, sings, and bows again. The bows
are usually first to one side of its body and then to the other. The displaying
bird may be beside, in front of or at an angle to its mate and hop around it
between bows. Copulation, which does not normally follow the display, may,
but not always, be initiated by the male pecking at the female&apos;s nape and/or
her soliciting with her tail quivering. The male also has a display, which is
not unlike that of the begging of the fledged young, in which he crouches
and raises and flutters one or both wings. Sometimes his tail is pressed to
the ground, but at other times it may be twisted towards the female. This
display may be accompanied by a soft twittering which is similar or identical
to the nest call or he may sing during or immediately afterwards, or even
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999604" page_id="56253532"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
154
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.675012" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253532" page_num="154" year="" vol="">
HINZE - RED AVADAVAT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.977821225" page_id="56253532"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
at intervals between his crouching and wing raising. This display may be
directed towards females to whom he is not paired or may be performed by
a paired male, and may be followed by a brief attack on them or some other
bird. However, at least one observer is convinced this display is a specific
pair formation display (Goodwin, 1982).
Nesting
The nest, which usually starts off as a flatfish platform of grass stems
and/or blades of grass, is roundish and strongly built and, as well as stems
and blades of grass, is made using flowering or seeding grass heads and
sometimes other plant material, and is lined with vegetable down, fine
grasses, flower heads of grasses and/or feathers. There is usually a side
entrance or a short tubular entrance. Both sexes construct the nest, though
usually only the male brings the outer materials, and both collect feathers
for the lining. The nest is well-concealed and normally constructed near the
ground, such as in or at the base of a bush or a thick clump of grass, or may
be built on the ground itself. A captive male belonging to I. and M. Chamock
(1988) always carried a white feather or some other material when returning
to the nest and this was then used to cover the entrance hole.
A clutch of four to six eggs are laid, which both sexes take turns to
incubate by day, with the female alone incubating them at night. The
incubation period is 11-12 days and the young fledge approximately 20-21
days later. Both parents feed the young after they have fledged (Goodwin,
1982; Trollope, 1983).
Aviculture
Since the European import ban greater efforts have been made to breed
this species regularly here in the UK. Once a frequently imported species, it
was first bred in the UK by the Reverend Charles Druce Farrar, way back in
1895. If its husbandry requirements are not met it is prone to melanism and
its normally bright red plumage may turn almost black, yellowish brown, dull
orange or at best a fiery orange. Correct feeding alone will not halt the change
in coloration, it also requires a high temperature and access to sunshine.
Czechowsky (in Goodwin, 1982) found that a captive male repeatedly
moulted into shining red plumage when it was kept at a temperature of about
40*C (104*F). When kept at 30*C (86*F) its new plumage was yellowish.
These temperatures, however, are way above what the birds require for good
health and breeding. My own birds were kept and bred successfully at 15*C-
22*C (60*F-70*F) and, although the males' coloration never matched the
regal attire of their wild counterparts, they nevertheless remained extremely
attractive. It is interesting to note that Robin Restall (1975) described how a
male A. a. punicea grew progressively darker and duller with each passing
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.310853" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253531" page_num="155" year="" vol="">
HINZE - RED AVADAVAT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999337" page_id="56253531"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
155
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99932975862069" page_id="56253531"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
year until, quite inexplicably, it moulted out into a brilliant nuptial plumage
which was equal to that of any freshly-caught specimen.
The Red Avadavat is an excellent avicultural subject, whose husbandry
requirements are virtually identical to those of the Golden-breasted Waxbill
Sporaeginthus subflavus (formerly A. subflava). It is an excellent bird
for beginners, who have first gained experience with the Golden-breasted
Waxbill and who strictly adhere to its husbandry requirements. The Red
Avadavat is a bird that will grace any seed-eater collection and has, I
believe, much potential for domestication. However, unfortunately, it is yet
another species that in the main, once bred, tends to be passed over for more
challenging species. Pope (in Restall, 1975) bred it in a cage to at least the
tenth generation, as an exercise to prove that it could be domesticated by
a seriously interested aviculturist. Sadly, though, nobody was. No doubt
because, at the time, it continued to be imported in fairly large numbers and
sold at ridiculously cheap prices.
Although wild-caught, imported birds, were at breeding time best
provided with a varied diet which included livefood, as well as a variety of
ripe and unripe seeds, once established the Red Avadavat can be bred without
the need for livefood to rear the young. Here in the UK, David Jones and
Kevin Bell (pers. comm.) have had great success offering their birds a British
finch seed mixture, blended with white and yellow millets, and the addition
of millet on the spray and a commercial eggfood. Jones also provides peri I la,
whereas Bell augments the diet of his birds with sprouted seeds from a basic
seed mixture and gives them groundsel and chickweed.
Breeding birds are best kept alone in pairs. A regular check must be
kept on the length of their claws, which tend to grow rather quickly and can
become entangled in the nest or get caught in the aviary mesh, etc.
Captive birds are known to mimic the songs of other birds, particularly
other wax bills.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.954955" genericHeader="references" page_id="56253531" page_num="155" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.992078">
Chamock, I. and M. 1988. Tiger Finch. Newsletter of the FBBA Issue 88/1:484-486.
Clement, R, Harris, A. and Davis, I. 1993. Finches and Sparrows. Christopher Helm,
London.
Costa, H., Elias, G. L. and Farinha, I. 1997. Exotic birds in Portugal. British Birds
Vol.90,12:562-568.
Cramp, S. and Perries, C. M. 1994. Handbook of the Birds of Europe the Middle East and
North Africa. Vol.III. Oxford University Press, Oxford.
El Din, M. B. and S. B. 2001. In: Recent Reports, Bull. ABC 8/2:149.
El Din, M. B. and S. B. 2002. In: Recent Reports, Bull. ABC 9/1:67.
Goodman, S. M. and Meininger, P. L. (eds.) 1989. Birds of Egypt. Oxford University Press,
Oxford.
Goodwin, D. 1982. Estrildid finches of the world. British Museum (Natural History),
London.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999461" page_id="56253530"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
156
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.660734" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253530" page_num="156" year="" vol="">
HINZE - RED AVADAVAT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.981324555555556" page_id="56253530"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
Goodwin, D. 1993. Red Avadavat. The Estrildian 1,2:4-10. Estrildian Forum.
Grieve, A. 1997. In: Recent Reports, Bull. ABC 5,1:71.
Hockey, R A. R., Dean W. R. I. and Ryan, RG. (eds.) 2005. Roberts - Birds of Southern Africa,
Seventh edition. Trustees of the John Voelcker Bird Book Fund, Cape Town.
Lekagul, B. and Cronin, E. W. 1974. Bird guide of Thailand. Kuraspha, Bangkok, Thailand.
Lever, C. 1987. Naturalized birds of the world. Longman, S. &amp; T,, Essex.
Paz, U. 1987. Birds of Israel Christopher Helm, London.
Raffaele, H., Wiley, J., Garrido, O., Keith, A. and Raffaele, J. 1998. A Guide to the Birds of
the West Indies. Princeton University Press.
Restall, R. 1975. Finches and other seed-eating birds. Faber, London.
Strange, M. 2002. A Photographic Guide to the Birds of Southeast Asia. Christopher Helm,
London.
Trollope, J. 1983. The care and breeding of seed-eating birds. Blandford, London.
Sadly, Ian , whose special interest was the Estrildidae species (Waxbills
and their allies) and who had spent several years writing a book on these
species, which he hoped would be published in 2009, died on December 20th
2008, just a few days after the above article had been preparedfor inclusion
in this issue. An obituary appears on p. 188.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.60361725" page_id="56253530"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
* * *
ON THEIR WAY BACK
Seven Socorro Doves Zenaida graysoni bred at Paignton Zoo
Enviromental Park and five bred at Edinburgh Zoo, as part of a European
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.9699481" page_id="56253530"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
zoos captive-breeding progamme, were flown from the UK to Los Angeles
on October 17th and from there were transported to the US Department of
Agriculture's quarantine station at San Diego, where they were isolated for
the required 30 days before being transported to Albuquerque Zoo in New
Mexico. They will later be taken to Socorro Island, where the Mexican
Navy and local conservationists have built a breeding station. It is hoped
that their offspring will be the first Socorro Doves to fly free on their native
island - 600 miles (approx. 965km) off the Pacific coast of Mexico - since
the dove was last sighted in the wild in 1972 (it was declared extinct in the
wild in the early 1980s).
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.8894986" page_id="56253530"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
* * *
WANTED
Dick Jaquest - Tel:01273 584737/E-mail:d-jaquest@toucansurf.com
- is trying to locate a female Lilac-breasted Roller Coracias caudatus. Can
you help?
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.842655" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253529" page_num="157" year="" vol="">
THE BLUE-CROWNED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<keyword confidence="0.55757">
Dryonastes courtoisi:
</keyword>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.866643" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56253529" page_num="157" year="" vol="">
RESULTS OF A 2007 HUSBANDRY QUESTIONAIRE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998892" page_id="56253529"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
157
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.904379333333333" page_id="56253529"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
by lan Edmans
The principle aim of this study was to determine which captive husbandry
practises promote the best breeding results. Two investigations were
conducted, one into enclosure design and the other into breeding success.
Both use data obtained from a husbandry questionaire sent out in 2007.
Enclosure design
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.900049">
Method
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997253916666667" page_id="56253529"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
All 17 European institutes that housed the Blue-crowned Laughingthrush
were sent a questionaire in February 2007. We asked that a questionaire
be completed for each enclosure housing this species. Each completed
questionaire was to contain the breeding data for one year. Further copies of
the questionaire were available for previous years, however, each institution
was to complete only one questionaire for each enclosure. Sixteen institutions
responded and returned a total of 19 completed questionaires, therefore we
received information on 19 enclosures. Of those, one respondent omitted
important information and four others included enclosures housing either
single birds waiting to be paired or social groups. These were omitted to
lessen bias. The remaining 14 were managed as single breeding pairs and
used to compare data (see Table 1).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.962087">
Results
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9997988" page_id="56253529"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
Data on the 14 enclosures showed the median flight height to be 2.7m
(approx. 9ft). This was used to split the study group into two: those referred
to as taller &gt;2.7 (N=7) and those referred to as shorter &lt;2.7 (N=7). Nesting
was attempted in six of the taller enclosures and six of the shorter enclosures.
Chicks were produced in five of the shorter enclosures as opposed to four
of the taller enclosures. In the 14 enclosures a total of eight chicks were
reared to independence, four chicks in the taller enclosures and four in the
shorter enclosures.
In total, from all questionaires, 26 nests were reported, that included
naturally-built nests and those built in nesting receptacles. The average
height from the ground of the nests was 2.19m (approx.7ft 2%in). The
height from the ground of the nests compared to height of the enclosures is
shown in Fig. 1 and demonstrates that the taller the enclosure is, the higher
the birds will nest and, given the opportunity, they can nest 8m (approx.26ft)
above the ground.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998662" page_id="56253528"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
158
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.311292" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253528" page_num="158" year="" vol="">
EDMANS - BLUE-CROWNED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<tableCaption confidence="0.955334">
Table 1. Single paired birds.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.984827607142857" page_id="56253528"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
Enclosure
(V-14)
Aviary
F/Hl
F/H2
F/V 1
Nesting
N/A
C/H
C/R
A
2.3
No
19.3
Yes
0
0
B
3
Yes
456.0
Yes
0
0
C
2
No
10.0
Yes
4
0
D
3
Yes
18.0
No
0
0
E
2.6
No
24.8
Yes
1
1
F
2
No
40.0
Yes
4
0
G
2.6
No
118.5
Yes
13
1
H
2.6
No
122.6
Yes
8
2
I
2.8
Yes
58.8
Yes
0
0
J
2.4
No
29.5
No
0
0
K
6
Yes
294.0
Yes
7
2
L
4.5
Yes
72.0
Yes
3
0
M
3
Yes
84.0
Yes
6
2
N
4.5
Yes
72.0
Yes
3
0
F/Hl flight height (m); F/H 2 flight height higher than median;
F/V flight volume (m 3 ); NA nesting attempted;
C/H number of chicks hatched; C/R number of chicks reared.
Discussion
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.9902624" page_id="56253528"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
The survey did not take into account the height of the vegetation suitable
for nesting in the enclosures and the results could be bias towards lower nests,
as such sites are more easy for keepers to provide. Though the study size
was small, it does appear to show that the size of the aviary has little or no
affect on whether Blue-crowned Laughingthrushes will nest in it.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.8511285">
Breeding success
Method
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9738215" page_id="56253528"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
Chick mortality was investigated in 17 enclosures, including those
housing single pairs and social groups (see Table 2).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.864835">
Results
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999215" page_id="56253528"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
A total of 114 chicks were recorded as having been hatched, of which
only 23 were reared. There was, therefore, 79.8% chick mortality. The
hatching of chicks was reported in 12 enclosures, in five of which chicks
were never reared. Fifteen chicks were recorded as having died under 15
days old. The average age at which chicks died was five and a half days,
with five days being recorded most often.
The study also looked into the provision of nesting receptacles, defined
as artificial structures used by laughingthrushes in which to build a nest.
It found that nine enclosures in which a nesting receptacle was provided,
seven chicks were hatched in them and six were reared, as opposed to eight
enclosures in which nesting receptacles were not provided, in which five
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.434018" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253527" page_num="159" year="" vol="">
EDMANS - BLUE-CROWNED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999368" page_id="56253527"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
159
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9697665" page_id="56253527"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
chicks were hatched and only one was reared.
It was found that even by removing enclosure No.4 - in which nesting
receptacles were provided and 50 chicks were reported as having been
hatched (believed to be wrongly included data from previous years) - to
create a 50/50 split between receptable use and non-receptacle use, 46 chicks
were hatched in nesting receptacles and 18 were not.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.984501">
Table 2. Investigation of chick rearing success.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.990695561538462" page_id="56253527"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
Enclosure
No.
Age of
chicks at
death
(&lt;15days)
Chicks
hatched
Chicks
reared
Nesting
receptacle
used
No. of
chicks
hatched
No. of
chicks
reared
1
No
No
No
0
0
2
No
No
No
0
0
3
3,3,8,8
Yes
No
Yes
4
0
4
Yes
Yes
Yes
50
11
5
No
No
Yes
0
0
6
Yes
Yes
Yes
1
1
7
5,5,5.5
Yes
No
No
4
0
8
Yes
Yes
Yes
13
1
9
Yes
Yes
Yes
8
2
10
Yes
No
No
2
0
11
2
Yes
Yes
Yes
13
4
12
5
No
No
Yes
0
0
13
No
No
No
0
0
14
3,8,9,9
Yes
Yes
Yes
7
2
15
2
Yes
No
No
3
0
16
6
Yes
No
No
3
0
17
5
Yes
Yes
No
6
2
Total
</figure>
<page confidence="0.9630665" page_id="56253527"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
114
23
</page>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.824603">
Discussion
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999783818181818" page_id="56253527"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
It is unclear why enclosures with nesting receptacles produce a higher
number of chicks than those without them. It has though been observed
by the author that one bird in a pair may be disruptive and pull apart an
almost completed nest and, therefore, the provision of nesting receptacles
may reduce this. The support provided by the nesting receptacle may also
encourage further nesting attempts.
Unless post mortem examinations are carried out, the reasons for the
high level of chick mortality will likely remain unknown. This study did
not investigate the feeding regimes of adults with chicks, as these were
believed to be similar in all institutions. On reflection, however, this may
have produced some interesting results.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.975365" page_id="56253526"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
160
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.6748495">
EDMANS - BLUE-CROWNED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
Fig. 1. Height of nests in comparison to height of aviaries.
</figureCaption>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.526542">
Conclusions and recommendations
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9538862" page_id="56253526"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
The Blue-crowned Laughingthrush will nest in enclosures of various
sizes, but shows a preference for nesting at higher elevations, as its natural
behaviour suggests (Yuan-hua et al. 2003). Just being housed in a large
enclosure is not enough, however, and having suitable vegetation for nesting
at higher elevations is required. Nesting receptacles should be provided
within suitable high vegetation, giving these laughingthrushes a secure place
within which to build their nest.
With the high mortality of chicks, the hand-rearing of first clutches would
seem to be a sensible method of ensuring population growth at this time.
Reference
Yuan-hua, H. et al. 2003. Little-known Oriental Bird: Courtois's Laughingthrush. Available
online at: http://www.orientalbirdclub.org/publications/bullfeats/crtois.html (accessed
01/02/07).
At the time the study was undertaken, lan Edmans was an aviary keeper
at Waddesdon Manor, near Aylesbury, Buckinghamshire HP 18 OJH, UK.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994838" page_id="56253525"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
161
</page>
<table confidence="0.525073571428571" page_id="56253525"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
THE FAWN-BREASTED WAXBILL Estrilda paludicola
by Simon Espley
The Fawn-breasted Waxbill Estrilda paludicola is a common species of
the central African subtropical/tropical (lowland) wet grassland habitats. Yet
it is not well-known amongst the bird keeping fraternity.
Simon Espley
Estrilda paludicola marwitz from western Tanzania.
</table>
<page confidence="0.998459" page_id="56253524"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
162
</page>
<table confidence="0.8598435" page_id="56253524"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
ESPLEY - FAWN-BREASTED WAXBILL
Nest of Fawn-breasted Waxbill.
Simon Espley
It is found on forest fringes and can be seen crossing tracks and clearings.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.427279" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253523" page_num="163" year="" vol="">
ESPLEY - FAWN-BREASTED WAXBILL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999326" page_id="56253523"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
163
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.996072925" page_id="56253523"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
It was approximately three years ago that I first obtained a small flock
of six wild-caught birds of the subspecies E. p. marwitz. They came from
a local importer who had kept them back for his own private collection.
After some persuasion, however, he agreed to sell them to me and so began
a relationship with what has become my favourite waxbill I was later lucky
enough to obtain a few more wild-caught birds and with consistent breeding
I now have two separate flocks.
During various birdwatching trips to Uganda I have been lucky enough
to observe this species in its natural environment. There it is always found
in tall reeds and grasses on forest fringes and one can generally hear the
birds' contact calls and/or see them trailing one after another across tracks
and clearings.
The Fawn-breasted Waxbill (sometimes called the Marsh Waxbill) is
easily distinguished from the closely related Orange-cheeked Waxbill E,
melpoda. Although field guides may suggest that the main distinguishing
feature is the latter's orange cheeks, in reality the two are very different
- certainly in the case of E,p. marwitz.
The Fawn-breasted Waxbill has a very white throat, chest and belly,
whereas the Orange-cheeked Waxbill has these areas coloured various
shades of grey.
E, p, marwitz has a brown crown (as does E. p. roseicrissa ), whereas
that of the Orange-cheeked Waxbill is grey. (E. p. paludicola , however,
has a grey crown suffused with brown and E, p. benguellensis has a
dark grey crown with little or no brown suffusion. E. p. ochrogaster
(see below) has the top of the head "browner" and E. p. ruthae was not
described by Goodwin (1982), as he had not seen a specimen of this
subspecies.)
The back is a more reddish shade of brown than that of the Orange-
cheeked Waxbill.
The beak is a deeper shade of red than that of the Orange-cheeked
Waxbill
The red on the rump is brighter than that of the Orange-cheeked
Waxbill and more extensive, often extending to the vent and lower belly
areas.
Both are petite waxbills, but with the Fawn-breasted slightly larger
and bulkier than the Orange-cheeked species.
The two species' distributions are largely exclusive, with the Orange-
cheeked Waxbill occurring farther to the west, though there is an overlap
area in west central Africa.
Clements (2007) listed six subspecies (see above), which have varying
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999235" page_id="56253522"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
164
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.695216" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253522" page_num="164" year="" vol="">
ESPLEY - FAWN-BREASTED WAXBILL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987297333333333" page_id="56253522"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
Interior of one of the author's aviaries housing Fawn-breasted Waxbills,
combinations of the above attributes. Sinclair &amp; Ryan (2003), however,
treated ' ochrogaster ' as a separate species, the Abyssinian Waxbill E.
ochrogaster.
Here in South Africa I have found the Fawn-breasted Waxbill to be a
regular breeder and in this respect it is similar to the Orange-cheeked species.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.401017" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253521" page_num="165" year="" vol="">
ESPLEY - FAWN-BREASTED WAXBILL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.930895" page_id="56253521"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
165
</page>
<table confidence="0.674018" page_id="56253521"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
Black-billed juvenile Fawn-breasted Waxbill
Simon Espley
</table>
<page confidence="0.99922" page_id="56253520"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
166
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.776649" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253520" page_num="166" year="" vol="">
ESPLEY - FAWN-BREASTED WAXBILL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9936755" page_id="56253520"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
Like the Orange-cheeked Waxbill it prefers to be in a flock, with the birds
constantly calling to keep in contact with each other. The calls of the two
species are similar, although those of the Fawn-breasted species are more
strident and harsher than those of the Orange-cheeked Waxbill. Young Fawn
-breasted Waxbills have a distinctive rattling call like a Tittle machine gun.'
I find the Fawn-breasted species to be more confiding and inquisitive than
the Orange-cheeked species. If I hang around in their aviary, sooner or later
the entire flock will come filtering through the reeds, comfort-calling to each
other, flicking their tails and checking me out. When I walk pass my aviaries,
the first alarm calls are generally those of the Fawn-breasted Waxbills.
Another difference between the two is that the Fawn-breasted Waxbills take
sofifood more easily than my Orange-cheeked Waxbills. Both species readily
take livefood (termites), but I have found that the Fawn-breasted species is
more likely to take termites even when not breeding.
I try as far as possible to mimic their wild habitat in my aviaries.
Therefore, both flocks of Fawn-breasted Waxbills are housed in large aviaries
with plenty of tall grass, reeds and other cover, and spend most of their time
in the reeds. Both aviaries are shared with other birds of a similar size or
those that are slightly larger. It is a peaceful species that gets on well with
its own kind and other species.
My aviaries are covered with 6mm x 6mm (14m x !4in) mesh on the
outside and shade netting is used for the inside walls. Walls at the sides and
12mm x 25mm (Lain x lin) mesh buried under the floor provide protection
against rats and other rodents. The aviaries are well insulated against the
elements, with 80% of the roof covered in fibre glass or tin. They are thickly
planted with reeds, grasses, herbs and weeds. The floor covering is a mix of
sand, soil, stone chips and chipped bark. The drinking and bathing water is
refreshed four times a day via an automatic timer and mist sprays come on
twice a day during the summer.
My birds receive the following diet:
A dry seed mix of red manna, pannicum millet, white millet, Japanese
millet, canary seed, niger, rape, linseed and shelled sunflower seeds.
A wild grass seed mix, consisting of very small seeds and grass chaff,
supplied by local farmers.
Sprouted seeds (every second day).
Bunches of freshly picked wild seeding grasses (every second day, when
available).
Moistened softfood mix, consisting of commercial softbill pellets, finch
crumbs and dried eggfood, to which I add cod liver oil, wheat germ oil
and Spimlina.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.4264" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253519" page_num="167" year="" vol="">
ESPLEY - FAWN-BREASTED WAXBILL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996489" page_id="56253519"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
167
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.924094466666667" page_id="56253519"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
A shredded vegetable mix of carrot, broccoli, miniature com and various
berries (every second day).
English cucumber and papaya.
Termites (twice a day).
A mix of crushed charcoal and oystershell, to which I add baked chicken
eggshells.
Calcium powder sprinkled over seed (weekly).
My austerity diet involves withholding termites and all greenfood for the
three months prior to the beginning of the breeding season.
My tips for successful breeding are:
Providing privacy and protection against the elements.
Providing densely planted aviaries, using mainly reeds and tall
grasses.
Not overcrowding aviaries.
Providing a variety of food options, including plenty of livefood.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.845919" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56253519" page_num="167" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.952982692307692" page_id="56253519"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
Clements, J. F. 2007. The Clements Checklist of the Birds of the World , Sixth Edition. Helm,
London.
Goodwin, D. 1982. Estrildid finches of the world. British Museum (Natural History),
London.
Sinclair, I. and Ryan, P. 2003. A comprehensive illustratedfield guide Birds of Africa south of
the Sahara. Struik Publishers, Cape Town.
Simon Espley is the Director of The Rare Finch Conservation Group
(website:www.rarefinch.co.za). He lives in Cape Town, South Africa and
specialises in the breeding of African finches, although he also dabbles
with other species. His passion is to ensure that bird keepers, scientists
and those working for government agencies, combine their skills for the
benefit of birds in the wild. Simon can be contacted by e-mail:simon@
africageographical. com
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.6297875" page_id="56253519"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
*
* *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.548701" genericHeader="introduction" page_id="56253519" page_num="167" year="" vol="">
FOR SALE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8263508" page_id="56253519"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
The society has been contacted by an elderly gentleman, who has for
sale bound volumes of the Avicultural Magazine for the years 1956-1987
and Foreign Birds , the Foreign Bird League magazine for the years 1956-
1970. All are, he says, in first class condition. If you are interested in the
first instance please contact the Hon. Editor.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997833" page_id="56253518"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
168
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.551298" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253518" page_num="168" year="" vol="">
THE BLUE-THROATED CONURE Pyrrhura cruentata
by Derek Gibson
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.981909" page_id="56253518"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
Exmoor Zoo has had a relatively short association with the Blue-throated
Conure, our first pair having been loaned to the zoo by one of our supporters
in May 2002. The pair arrived with a rather chequered history of producing
eggs only occasionally and never incubating them, thus never breeding.
While the pair was held in one of our quarantine aviaries, it was very
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.782298">
Derek Gibson
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9818716" page_id="56253518"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
Adult Blue-throated Conure at Exmoor Zoo.
noticeable that the female was a very assertive character. She was always the
first to feed and always the first to investigate anything new. This seems to
have been a character trait of other females we have had since then and has
been so whether they have been hand-reared or not. The males have been a
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.372322" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253517" page_num="169" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - BLUE-THROATED CONURE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999281" page_id="56253517"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
169
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999004642857143" page_id="56253517"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
little bit more hesitant and more inclined to keep their distance.
Upon completion of the quarantine period, the pair was transferred to
one of our aviaries for South American birds. It measures 2.5m x 1m x 1.5m
(approx. 8ft Sin x 3ft Sin x 5ft). To encourage the birds to fly the maximum
distance, it has perches at either end. The birds settled in immediately, with
the female announcing her arrival by trying to pick an argument with the
pair of Yellow-shouldered Amazons Amazona barb a dens is living in the next
aviary. The pair was observed mating for the first time on July 2nd 2002.
The female took up residence in the nest box on July 15th 2002. The first egg
was seen on July 20th 2002. Eventually there was a clutch of five eggs. One
was clear, one chick was dead in the shell and the remaining three hatched
successfully, but one chick was later found dead on the aviary floor. The
remaining two were transferred to the zoo's Incubation and Rearing Centre,
where both were successfully hand-reared.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.770554">
Derek Gibson
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99530525" page_id="56253517"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
Twenty-five days old.
No further young were produced over the next couple of years. Eggs
were laid at irregular intervals, but all proved to be clear. I wondered if this
could have been because of the female's assertive nature. The male and
female were returned to their original owner on September 3rd 2005. The
two chicks from 2002 were DNA sexed and found to be a male and a female.
The male was exchanged on January 28th 2004 for an unrelated male hatched
on May 23rd 2003 at Paradise Park, Hayle, Cornwall.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995089" page_id="56253516"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
170
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.80889" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253516" page_num="170" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - BLUE-THROATED CONURE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.978109585365854" page_id="56253516"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
The new pair was placed together in one of the zoo's quarantine aviaries
and later transferred to the aviary that the older pair of Blue-throated Conures
had occupied. Again the female was quite a fearless little thing, with the
male more than happy to join in, though at wing's-length. Mating was
first observed on September 29th 2005 and on October 6th three eggs were
present in the nest box. These were checked on October 23rd 2005 and were
unfortunately all found to be clear. No further breeding activity was noted
that year or the following year, although both birds seemed well bonded.
The year 2007 started really well with six eggs in the nest box on
February 10th. The female was sitting tight and the male was spending
a considerable amount of time in the nest box with her, though more for
company, we suspected, than to help with incubation duties. The nest box
was inspected again on March 1st and two chicks were seen, both were
very vocal and both had food in their crops. A third chick hatched two days
later and soon caught up with the other two (the remaining three eggs were
clear). It was interesting to note that the female's rather fearless disposition
was only evident when the aviary was entered. Every time the nest box and
youngsters were inspected from outside the main aviary, she remained in
the box and watched.
All three chicks thrived. The first fledged on April 22nd 2007, the second
on April 23rd and the third on April 30th. One was observed eating out of
the food bowl on May 7th and was joined by its fellow nest mates over the
following week. All three youngsters were removed from the aviary on June
6th and housed on their own in an off-display aviary.
The same day that the youngsters were removed, the adult pair was noted
mating and from June 19th onwards the female began to spend more time in
the nest box. The first egg of the pair's second clutch was laid on July 4th.
When the nest box was next checked on July 15th, it contained seven eggs.
These began to hatch on August 1 st. When the nest box was checked on
August 4th the fourth egg had hatched, followed by the fifth egg on August
6th. The remaining two eggs were clear, but were left in the nest box to
help prevent the youngest chick from being squashed. Both parents were
observed taking food into the nest box.
All five young were reared successfully. A male went to Twycross Zoo
in Warwickshire and the other four remain here. This year, 2008, the pair
which was restricted to rearing just one brood, raised five young, one of
which died at the weaning stage.
More of the Exmoor-bred young will, it is planned, go to other collections,
some in exchange for unrelated birds to set up new pairs here at Exmoor Zoo
so that, along with other collections, we can work towards the long-term
survival of this most engaging little conure.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.371659" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253515" page_num="171" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - BLUE-THROATED CONURE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995364" page_id="56253515"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
171
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.6663525" page_id="56253515"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
Diet
The adults are fed at 9.00am and, if required, again at 4.00pm.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.6849645">
30g Parakeet mix
30g Seasonal fruits and vegetables cut into 1cm x 1cm (approx. Vain x
</footnote>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.214133">
Vain) cubes
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.958236882352941" page_id="56253515"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
Soaked millet sprays are offered once a week.
15g Mineralised grit is offered once a week.
When the birds are breeding they are offered (EMP) eggfood, in addition to
the above mix and, when there are young in the nest, they are fed at 8.00am,
12 noon, 3.00pm and 5.30pm.
Vitamin supplements used are Avi-Mix and Abidec.
Fresh browse, either willow or beech, is placed in the aviary at least two
to three times a week during the summer months.
Nest box design
Our old nest box for the conures measured 15cm x 15cm x 30cm (approx.
6in x 6in x 1ft). It was made of plywood and had a front-facing opening
measuring 5cm (2in). In early 2005 a new design was adopted. It is again
made of plywood and is of the same dimensions, but has a tunnel fitted to the
entrance. This design seems to work well, as our breeding results indicate.
The substrate we use is woodchips to a depth of 3cm (1 %in). After the young
have fledged and left the nest box, the old material is removed, the box is
sterilised and fresh woodchips are placed in it.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.731258">
Derek Gibson is Head Keeper at Exmoor Zoo, South Stowford, Bratton
Fleming, Barnstaple, Devon, UK. Website:www.exmoorzoo.co.uk/E-mail:
derek.r.gibson@btinternet. com
</footnote>
<table confidence="0.413385" page_id="56253515"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
* * *
SOCIAL MEETINGS 2009
On Saturday, March 28th, there will be a visit to Colchester Zoo in Essex,
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.943014857142857" page_id="56253515"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
to which members are invited and may bring guests. Following the Council
Meeting, there will be the 2009 AGM followed by lunch, after which there
will be a conducted tour of the collection.
The President's Garden Party will be held on the afternoon of Saturday,
July 18th, at Chestnut Lodge, Cobham, Surrey.
On Saturday, September 19th, there will be a visit to Arnold Zwetsloot's
waterfowl collection near Sandy, Bedfordshire.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998701" page_id="56253514"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
172
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.988135" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253514" page_num="172" year="" vol="">
UNPRECEDENTED USE OF A NEST LOG
BY A FEMALE GREEN BROADBILL Calyptomena viridis
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993034117647059" page_id="56253514"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
by J. J. Elston, C. Sky, G. Quinones, C. Tybor, C. Plasse
and T. Hettinger
Introduction and background
The Green Broabill Calyptomena viridis 1 is a small, frugivorous bird
native to the tropical forests of south-east Asia. Both the male and female
are bright green in colour, with the green of the male slightly more vibrant
and with black markings on the head and wings. This species makes an
eye-catching resident in zoo aviaries. Though specialising in a fruit diet, the
Green Broadbill opportunistically consumes insects and parents commonly
feed insects to their offspring during rearing (del Hoyo et al. 2003). In the
wild the Green Broadbill constructs a round or gourd-shaped hanging nest
by weaving together plant materials and typically suspends it from a tree
branch over an open area (del Hoyo et al. 2003).
Few reports of successful reproduction in captivity have been
documented. Two zoological institutions reported female Green Broadbills
nesting in suspended artificial domed nests or constructing their own hanging
nests, with variable success in producing chicks (see Lewis, 1996; Gossett
&amp; Beseke, 1997). In May 2002, Disney's Animal Kingdom, Lake Buena
Vista, Florida, USA, received four Green Broadbills, two males and two
females. These were housed together in an off-display aviary and given
the opportunity to form their own pair bonds, after which one pair was
moved to a separate, mixed species aviary that was open to the public. No
breeding behaviour was observed by either pair. In May 2004, all four were
reunited in an off-display, mixed species aviary, in an attempt to encourage
reproductive activity. Also living in the aviary was a pair of Long-tailed
Broadbills Psarisomus dalhousiae. March-May 2005 and again in January
2006 both females engaged in nest building behaviour, but neither completed
a nest or laid eggs. The Green Broadbills were observed destroying and
consuming eggs of a pair of Jambu Fruit Doves Ptilinopus jambu living in
the same aviary. In March 2006, keepers observed aggressive behaviour
directed towards one male Green Broabill by the other male Green Broadbill
and the male Long-tailed Broadbill, which consisted of both chasing and
bodily contract. As a result, the recipient of the aggression and his female
partner were moved to a separate aviary which housed an Indian Pygmy
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.368728">
1 The name Lesser Green Broadbill seems to have faded from use, see e.g.
The Clements Checklist of the Birds of the World , Sixth Edition (2007) - Ed.
</footnote>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.608543" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253513" page_num="173" year="" vol="">
ELSTON ET AL - GREEN BROADBILL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996863" page_id="56253513"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
173
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.405202">
Christy Sky
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996626" page_id="56253513"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
Hand-reared chick aged 18 days. It proved to be a male.
Goose Nettapus coromandelianus. At the edge of a pond, in an upright
position on the ground was a nest log, placed there originally for Indian
Pygmy Geese.
In late December 2006, the female Green Broadbill began constructing
a nest inside the nest log. Keepers having observed this unusual behaviour
began videotaping it. Little documentation exists regarding the reproductive
behaviour of captive broadbills, in addition to which the use of a nest log by
broadbills was unprecedented. Therefore, our objective was to document the
nesting activity of this pair of Green Broadbills. Data from this study will
we hope provide valuable information on the reproductive behaviour of the
Green Broadbill and assist others in their efforts to propagate this species in
captivity. In addition, this paper provides a protocol for hand-rearing Green
Broadbill chicks which will we hope prove helpful to those attempting to
hand-rear this species.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.9160175">
Materials and methods
Animals and housing
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.955661" page_id="56253513"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
An adult pair of Green Broadbills was housed off-display at Disney's
Avian Research Center in a 9m x 3m x 2m (approx. 29ft 6in x 9ft 9in x 6ft
6in) outside aviary with a single female Indian Pygmy Goose. The pair had
resided together in the aviary for nine months prior to this study. The aviary
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999354" page_id="56253512"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
174
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.498002" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253512" page_num="174" year="" vol="">
ELSTON ET AL - GREEN BROADBILL
</sectionHeader>
<figureCaption confidence="0.967667">
Fig. 1. Percentage of time female spent throughout the day on nest
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.981563692307693" page_id="56253512"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
construction phase and incubation phase (period).
contained natural vegetation and perching, as well as a nest log. The latter
was in a vertical position on the ground. It was lm (approx. 3ft Sin) tall
and 27cm (approx. 10!/2in) in diameter, with the entrance hole 9cm (3!4in)
in diameter, less than lm (3ft Sin) above the ground. Pine shavings had
been placed in the nest log and raffia, coconut fibres and bamboo fibres were
placed in the aviary as nest building materials.
Twice daily at 8.00am and 12 noon they were provided with a diet of
Mazuri parrot breeder soaked in water, Toronto Zoo Small Carnivore Diet
mixed with Mazuri insectivore diet, fruit, including avocado, and crickets,
mealworms and waxworms. Grapes were provided for enrichment. Pinkie
mice were offered, but were discontinued because the birds showed a lack
of interest in them. As the aviaries are outside, they were also able to catch
insects living in the wild.
In early January 2007 the female laid a clutch of three eggs in the nest
log. It was the first clutch of eggs the female had ever produced. The eggs
were laid at two day intervals. Eight days after the first egg was laid and
four days after the last egg was laid, keepers removed the eggs and placed
them in an incubator. The decision was taken to artificially incubate the eggs
and hand-rear the chicks as, even though the female consistently entered the
nest log and incubated the eggs, she occasionally sat on the opposite side
to the eggs, which resulted in them being left all or partly uncovered. They
were replaced with three artificial eggs to encourage the female to continue
her incubation behaviour. Therefore, the behavioural data collected during
the remainder of the incubation process, applies to the artificial eggs, which
replaced the original eggs in the nest log.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.609454" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253511" page_num="175" year="" vol="">
ELSTON ET AL - GREEN BROADBILL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998164" page_id="56253511"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
175
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.974427195121951" page_id="56253511"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
Data collection
A video camera was positioned to focus on the outside of the nest log
and a bullet camera was inserted inside the nest log. Video recordings were
made between 6.00am and 8.00pm (06.00l.irs - 20.00hrs) daily using a VCR.
Video recording began when nest construction was first observed and ended
when the artificial eggs were removed from the log by keepers after the
chicks hatched in the incubator. Tapes were scored for all visits to the next
log (behavioural sampling: Martin &amp; Bateson, 1993), along with the time
and length of each visit. Data was recorded over 32 days, with an average
of 10 hours recorded per day, for a total of 322.56 hours.
Hand-rearing protocol
The eggs were incubated for 19 days in a Grumbach incubator set at
100.4*F (37 8*C) with approximately 58% humidity. They were turned
by keepers four times per day. Upon hatching the chicks were placed in
a brooder. The brooder room was kept dark, except during feeding. The
hatchlings were kept in a small cup approximately 8cm x 8cm x 6cm (3 Ain
x 3 Ain x .2 Ain) with tissue for bedding and cover on days one and two. They
were moved to a larger cup approximately 15cm x 15cm x 4cm (6m x 6in
x 1 Ain) on day three and wood wool was used for bedding. The brooder
temperature was 96*F (35.5*C) on days one and two, and was decreased by
1 *F every two days during the rearing period. Humidity was maintained at
80%-82% from day one to day 11 and was reduced to 40% on day 12 and
remained at that level for the remainder of the rearing period. The humidity
level was achieved by placing wet towels on the floor of the brooder and by
misting the brooder with water.
As only one of the chicks survived (see Results), the following
information on the rearing diet and feeding schedule is based on the protocol
established for the surviving chick only. Food was offered to the chick every
two hours from 6.00am-6.QQpm (06.00hrs 18. OOlirs), i.e. seven times per
day, during the first 10 days after hatching. During the first two days, the
chick was offered various items, including chopped pinkie mice, Purina cat
chow, two-week old crickets or large cricket abdomens, waxworm pieces,
papaya and grapes. Food items were soaked in Pedialyte. As a guideline,
keepers attempted to feed the chick 45%-65% of its body weight during each
feeding (on a wet matter basis). However, it was more or less dependent
on how hungry or not the chick was. In addition, it received a vitamin B
supplement (one drop per 5g of body weight) once per day. The chick began
to pass loose faeces on day four and, as a result, on day five was fed only
chopped pinkie mouse soaked Pedialyte. On day six, Mazuri parrot breeder
was added to the diet. By day 10 the chick's faeces had returned to normal
and its feeds were reduced to five per day (one every three hours). Avocado
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998896" page_id="56253510"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
176
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.488047" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253510" page_num="176" year="" vol="">
ELSTON ET AL - GREEN BROADBILL
</sectionHeader>
<figureCaption confidence="0.9989715">
Fig. 2. Growth rate of two hand-reared chicks.
Fig. 3. Food intake (on a wet matter basis) as a percentage of body weight
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.9702105" page_id="56253510"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
of two hand-reared chicks (all weights were in grams).
was added to the diet on day 11 and on subsequent days grapes and papaya
were included. On day 19 the chick was moved to a cage measuring 51cm
x 51 cm x 51 cm (approx. 1 ft 8in x 1 ft 8in x 1 ft 8in) with perches. Food was
provided four times per day. Feather analysis was used to determine that
the young broadbill was a male.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.927255">
Results
Adult behaviour
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99715025" page_id="56253510"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
Only the female engaged in nest construction. She weaved together a
nest inside the nest log and completed it in approximately nine days. During
the nest construction phase, the female spent an average of 18.91% of her
time on nest construction during the day and visited the nest log an average
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.609586" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253509" page_num="177" year="" vol="">
ELSTON ET AL - GREEN BROADBILL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99878" page_id="56253509"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
177
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997109371428571" page_id="56253509"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
of 9.71 times per hour. Visits to the nest log occurred throughout the day,
though primarily in the morning and early afternoon, and less often in the
late afternoon and evening.
During the incubation phase, only the female entered the nest log and
engaged in incubation behaviour. After the female had laid her first egg,
she spent an average of 44.90% of her time inside the nest log each day
until she had produced her entire clutch, after which this increased to an
average of 88.79% of her time each day. The female incubated the eggs
throughout the day (see Fig.l). While the female was inside the nest log,
the male was observed chasing the Indian Pygmy Goose, when it landed on
the top of the nest log.
Egg and chick data
The eggs (N=3) were white with a small number of dark brown spots.
The mean length and width were 27.5mm x 20.3mm and the mean weight
was 5.92g. Candling revealed that two of the eggs were fertile and one was
infertile. Two chicks hatched after the eggs had been in the incubator for
19 days. The first chick to hatch (chick 1) grew steadily throughout the
rearing period (see Fig.2). It consumed a variable percentage of its body
weight in food per day and its weight increased unsteadily until day seven,
followed by a unsteady decline (see Fig.3). The second chick to hatch
(chick 2) began to produce loose faeces on day two and, as a result, fruit
was removed from its diet. During the first two days of its life, chick 2 had
appeared to be following a similar pattern to that of chick 1 with regard to
its food intake as a percent of its body weight per day. However, between
days three and four it lost 10% of its body weight and on day five died from
a bacterial infection.
On day four a feather tract was visible on the back of chick 1 and by
day five pin-feathers covered its body. The chick's eyes began to open on
day six. By day 16 the chick began to become selective about its food and
began to refuse the parrot pellets. On day 17 the chick began making adult-
like vocalisations and by day 18 was fully feathered (see photo p. 173). The
chick fledged, i.e. left the artificial nest cup on its own, aged 19 days. By
the time it was aged 32 days, the chick was consuming food on its own and
was moved to a 1.5m x 3m x 2m (approx. 5ft x 9ft 9in x 6ft 6in) outside
aviary. Feather sexing revealed it was a male.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.813403">
Discussion and conclusions
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9944428" page_id="56253509"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
The male Green Broadbill did not assist the female with nest construction
or incubation, which is similar to the behaviour reported for the male Green
Broadbills at San Diego Zoo (Lewis, 1996) and Lincoln Park Zoo (Gossett &amp;
Beseke, 1997). The male did, however, appear to engage in nest protection
when the female was in the nest; as indicated by his chasing away the pygmy
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99879" page_id="56253508"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
178
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.855861" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253508" page_num="178" year="" vol="">
ELSTON ET AL - GREEN BROADBILL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998815170731707" page_id="56253508"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
goose when she landed on the nest log. Guarding behaviour by the male
Green Broadbill when his female partner occupied the nest was also observed
at Lincoln Park Zoo (Gossett &amp; Beseke, 1997).
In the wild, Green Broadbills reportedly replace lost clutches during
the breeding season (del Hoyo, 2003). Long-tailed Broadbills at Disney's
Animal Kingdom have been observed to lay replacement clutches (re-clutch)
several times during a breeding season (Elston unpublished data) and a pair
of Green Broadbills reportedly produced three clutches during a breeding
season at San Diego Zoo (Lewis, 1996). In 2007, a pair of Green Broadbills
laid several replacement clutches and produced five chicks (Webster (Toledo
Zoo) pers. comm.). However, the female Green Broadbill in this study did
not re-lay after the artificial eggs were removed from the nest log. Gossett
and Beseke (1997) also reported that the pair at Lincoln Park Zoo produced
only one clutch during the breeding season. The second pair of Green
Broadbills housed off-display at Disney's Animal Kingdom has failed to
produce a clutch during the past four years. Failure to be able to rely on
Green Broadbills to produce a clutch of eggs and subsequently lay again
during a breeding season illustrates two of the complications when trying to
breed this species in captivity and emphasizes the importance of maximizing
chick survival when offspring are produced.
During this study the eggs were removed from the nest because the female
failed to consistently sit on all three of them. It is possible that the nest she
constructed inside the log was too big. In the wild, Green Broadbill nests are
small and generally the female sits inside with her head outside of the nest
(del Hoyo, 2003). Therefore, should such a situation arise again, it may be
necessary for keepers to manipulate the nest after it has been constructed to
ensure that it is smaller, so that the female's body fills the nest and she covers
all of the eggs. However, her failure to cover all of the eggs may have been
due to parental inexperience, given that it was the female's first clutch.
Both chicks passed loose faeces early in the hand-rearing period and,
although the ultimate cause remains unknown, a slight modification to
the diet appeared to reduce the problem in chick 1. Although adult Green
Broadbills are frugivorous, the young may depend less on fruit and more on
high quality, easily digestible protein rich foods, during early growth and
development, however, this hypothesis remains to be tested.
The female Green Broadbill in this study behaved in an atypical manner
by nesting in a standing nest log, rather than using a suspended nest. Perhaps
seclusion is a desirable nesting component for Green Broadbills in captivity
and the nest log provided that element. Efforts to increase privacy and
promote a 'sense of security' may be important steps towards encouraging
reproduction by Green Broadbills.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.60982" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253507" page_num="179" year="" vol="">
ELSTON ET AL - GREEN BROADBILL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997542" page_id="56253507"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
179
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.978754" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56253507" page_num="179" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8649635" page_id="56253507"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
This study was a joint effort by the Aviary Team and the Animal Research
and Technology Team at Disney's Animal Kingdom. We wish to thank Paul
Schutz and Robert Webster for developing the hand-rearing protocol and
Kevin Graham and Susan Nelle for assistance with chick rearing. Thanks
are also extended to Sue DuBois for video equipment support and Heather
Pollard for project assistance. Christy Sky took the photo.
Products mentioned in the text
Brooder: Animal Intensive Care Unit, Lyon Electric Company, Inc., Chula Vista, California,
USA.
Feather analysis/tissue sexing: Avian Biotech International, Tallahassee, Florida, USA.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.730058066666667" page_id="56253507"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
Grumbach Incubator: Swan Creek Supply, Inc., Saginaw, Michigan, USA.
Mazuri parrot breeder: PMI Nutrition International, St Louis, Missouri, USA.
Mazuri insectivore diet: PMI Nutrition International, St Louis, Missouri, USA.
Pedialyte: Abbott Laboratories, Abbott Park, Illinois, USA.
Purina cat chow: Nestle Purina Pet Care Company, St Louis, Missouri, USA.
Toronto Zoo Small Carnivore Diet: Milliken Meat Products Ltd., Scarborough, Ontario,
Canada.
Vitamin B: Quicko Daily V, Sun Seed Company, Inc., Bowling Green, Ohio, USA.
References
del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A. and Christie, D. (eds.). 2003. Family Eurylaimidae (Broadbills). In:
Handbook of the Birds of the World Vol.S. Broadbills to Tapaculos. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona,
Spain.
Gosset, J. and Beseke, C. 1997. Breeding Lesser Green Broadbills at Lincoln Park Zoo.
Avicultural Magazine 103,1:15-19.
Lewis, E 1 . 1996. Captive Breeding of the Lesser Green Broadbill. Avicultural Magazine
</table>
<footnote confidence="0.817794">
102,1:1-5.
Martin, P. and Bateson, P. 1993. Measuring behaviour: an introductory guide. Second edition.
Cambridge University Press, New York, NY, USA.
1 The correct name of the author is Ed Lewins, but due to an error somewhere along the line,
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.657114" page_id="56253507"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
it appeared in the magazine as Ed Lewis.
The unprecedented use of a nest log by a female Green Broadbill
(described above) occurred at Disney's Animal Kingdom, PO Box 10000,
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.903339142857143">
Lake Buena Vista, Florida 32830, USA. Contact: Chelle Plasse, Assistant
Curator of Birds. Tel:(+1) 407 939-7339/E-mail: Chelle.Plasse@disney.
com. At the time of the study Jennifer J Elston, PhD, was a Research
Fellow at DAK. Jennifer Elston is currently Curator of Conservation and
Behavior, Fort Worth Zoo, 1989 Colonial Parkway, Fort Worth, Texas 76110,
USA . Tel:(+1) 817 759-7315/Fax:(+1) 817 759-7501/E.-mail:jelston@
fortworthzoo. org
</reference>
<page confidence="0.995402" page_id="56253506"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
180
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.943752666666667" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253506" page_num="180" year="" vol="">
REVIEWS
GUIDE TO PARAKEETS OF THE GENERA
Neophema AND Neosephotus AND THEIR MUTATIONS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997419567567568" page_id="56253506"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
I have a vivid memory of seeing a pair of Splendid Grass Parakeets
(Scarlet-chested Parrots) at the National Exhibition of Cage Birds at Olympia
in London in the early 1950s. Rather than being placed amongst the general
show exhibits they were still considered to be so rare and delicate as to need
extra protection and security and were displayed in a decorated, glass-fronted
cabinet, with its own lighting and the cabinet was set into the wall. From
these fragile beginnings here in the UK, the species eventually became a
common sight, even in the aviaries and birdrooms of novice breeders. The
Splendid Grass Parakeet was once considered extinct in the wild and this
- together with its association in the 1930s-1940s with King George V, the
Duke of Bedford and then Keston Foreign Bird Farm - gave the bird its special
aura amongst parakeet breeders in the 1950s and 1960s. Their efforts to
breed more and more of these delightful birds, resulting in a massive increase
in the aviary population around the world, is one reason for the eruption of
the number of colour varieties now in existence.
The species which present the greatest number of colour varieties are
the Splendid Grass Parakeet and the Turquoisine, the two which were
considered most rare and desirable around 50 years ago. There is no denying
that these colour varieties are nothing less than spectacular - especially now
the violet factor is being brought into the picture. No less attractive are the
carmine, pink, cream, fawn, blue and white shades presented in the series
of colour varieties of Bourke's Parakeet. Also included are the Elegant and
its predominantly yellowish varieties, the Blue-winged with its attractive
blue mutation, the aviculturally rare Rock Parakeet and the Endangered
Orange-bellied species.
Skilful colour photography is used to show all the existing colour varieties
to their greatest advantage and in the finest detail. The photos are invaluable
for clear identification and might be considered the most important feature of
A Guide to... Neophema &amp; Neopsephotus Genera &amp; their Mutations, which
covers all aspects of keeping these popular little birds. General management,
housing, feeding, disease, explanation of plumage pigments and information
on the genetics of the varieties are all included in a compact format.
Considering its otherwise comprehensive coverage of the subject, there
do appear to be some omissions to the sections on inheritance of the colour
varieties. Though I could find reference to the existence of several mutations
of genes occurring at the same locus, which are described as alleles, I could
find no examples of pairings showing the expectations when allelomorphs
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.907185" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253505" page_num="181" year="" vol="">
REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998502" page_id="56253505"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
181
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.993562521739131" page_id="56253505"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
are cross-bred. It would have been useful to have explained the effects of
cross-breeding the three main types of blue Splendid Grass Parakeet, which
are presumed to be alleles. Explaining the theory behind cross-breeding
where alleles are concerned (as simply as possible) would have also explained
the reasons why there are examples which are partway between these bluish
phases. In this case the blue to green-blue colour is caused by factors which
result in either a lessening or a complete loss of yellow and red pigments in
the plumage. Likewise, it could be surmised that there might also be alleles
among those varieties of grass parakeets which lessen or negate melanin
pigment (as for example with the Peach-faced Lovebird).
Dismissing this minor technical criticism on my part, ABK Publications
is to be congratulated on publishing this English language revised edition of
Dr Alain Campagne's French title Les Euphemes , which provides a visual
treat for grass parakeet enthusiasts. Dr Terry Martin BVSc (author of A Guide
to...Colour Genetics and Mutations in Parrots also published by ABK) acted
as a consultant and adviser for the sections on genetics and colour varieties
and Dr Bob Doneley BVSc FACVSc provided the excellent section on health
and disease, which includes a very helpf ul set of charts showing symptoms
of illnesses and detrimental conditions and their possible causes.
A Guide to ... Neophema &amp; Neopsephotus Genera &amp; their Mutations by
Dr Alain Campagne MD, English Revised Edition translated by Christine
Leah, is bound to stimulate an even greater interest in grass parakeets. It
has 224 pages and 300 photos and is published by ABK Publications, PO
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.90678975" page_id="56253505"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
Box 6288, Tweed Heads South, NSW 2486, Australia. Soft cover (ISBN
978 0 98049224 1 5) Australian $60.00, hard cover (ISBN 978 0 98049224
0 8) Australian $70.00.
Jim Hayward
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.371955" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56253505" page_num="181" year="" vol="">
WHERE TO WATCH BIRDS IN SPAIN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.910651333333333" page_id="56253505"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
This updated second edition of Where to Watch Birds Northern &amp;
Eastern Spain by Michael Rebane and Ernest Garcia covers all of Spain
except for Extremadura, Andalucia and Gibraltar (which are covered in a
complementary volume in this popular series). The guide which is the subject
of this review covers a huge geographic area and provides details of a total
of 112 major sites and short notes on a further 75 sites.
The introductory chapter on visiting northern and eastern Spain includes
useful tips on planning a birding trip and includes areas most easily accessible
from the main tourist centres of Barcelona and Madrid. A section on internet
sites available to help with planning birding trips is also useful. The main
hazards, including fighting bulls, dogs, pickpockets and traffic police, also
get mentioned.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998636" page_id="56253504"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
182
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.971113" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253504" page_num="182" year="" vol="">
REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993206071428571" page_id="56253504"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
For each site a map is provided that shows general site details, but gives
no visual indications of the best areas for target species. For information
on the best locations for individual species one needs to consult the text.
This however is pretty comprehensive and gives the conservation status
of the site, that is whether it is a National Park or Protected Area, plus
a comprehensive site description - covering geography and habitat. The
species sections contain valuable information on the birds and for some of
the sites also the mammals.
As noted by Richard Meyer in his recent review of Where to Watch Birds
in Wales (Vol. 114, No.2, pp.92-93 (2008)), a frustration of this format is that
if you are planning a birding trip and are especially interested in seeing a
particular species, the only way to find that information is to use the species
index and work through an often large list of site accounts that include the
particular species. At many of these sites the sought after species may be
rarely encountered or be quite unlikely to be seen. It would have been really
helpful and more user-friendly to have had an extra chapter that focused on
the more sought after species and indicated the best sites and times of the
year and the day to seek them. This information is included in the guide - it
is just not that easy to find.
However, this minor point aside, this updated guide is very well written
and unless one is very familiar with the country and its changing landscapes,
is absolutely essential for anyone planning a birding trip to Spain and, at
#16.99, is excellent value for money. Additional details may be gathered
from various internet sites and trip reports, but I would not want to plan a
trip without this guide and would expect to frequently refer to it during a
trip. I look forward to being able to put it to the test in the field on my next
trip to Spain.
Where to Watch Birds Northern &amp; Eastern Spain , Second Edition, by
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.50908625" page_id="56253504"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
Michael Rebane and Ernest Garcia (ISBN 978-0-7136-8315-8), paperback,
367 pages, with numerous maps and black and white illustrations is published
by Christopher Helm, an imprint of A&amp;C Black (website:www.acblack.com).
It is distributed by MDL: Tel.01256 302699.
Roger Wilkinson
THE Rcom 20 DIGITAL INCUBATOR
This year was the first time I used a Rcom 20 digital incubator here at
Paignton Zoo Environmental Park, having first noticed these incubators
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.941574333333333" page_id="56253504"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
being used to hatch eggs of Griffon Vultures Gyps fulvus at Jerusalem Zoo,
where this species is being raised for release into the wild.
The Rcom 20 was delivered ready for use. It measures 50cm x 35cm
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.907176" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253503" page_num="183" year="" vol="">
REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999306" page_id="56253503"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
183
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.978886414634146" page_id="56253503"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
x 14cm high (approx. 1ft 8in x 1ft 2in x 6in high) and was preset at the
factory to run at 37.5*C (99.5*F) with the humidity set at 55%. Changing
the settings is fairly straightforward. The 15-page booklet that comes with
it is very informative and generally easy to follow. Although the English
translation was not always clear to me, the workings of each section are amply
explained through the use of diagrams. The Rcom 20 has the capacity to
hold approximately 20 chicken eggs, 52 quail eggs or 10 turkey eggs.
Other than the need to add water each day, pretty much everything else
about this incubator is automatic. The eggs are turned every hour and the
temperature and humidity are controlled digitally. My overall impression
is that it is a well made, good quality incubator, that looks professional and
is a welcome addition to the incubator room.
The viewing panel on the top provides a clear view of all the eggs and
also serves as the lid to the incubator. A few seconds after it is removed,
the machine switches off automatically and starts up again automatically
when the lid is placed back on. I have found this very useful, as I have lost
count of the number of times I have double checked the on/off switches on
other incubators. Several partitions are supplied to hold the eggs firmly in
place and allow several different sizes of eggs to be incubated at the same
time, making it an ideal machine for the small-scale hobbyist or the keeper
of a large mixed collection. It is compact enough to easily be moved from
one site to another.
At the onset of 2008, having run a trial using an assortment of poultry
eggs, we went on to use the Rcom 20 to incubate the eggs of several important
species, including Argus Pheasant Argusianus a. argus , Grey-winged
Trumpeter Psophia crepitans , Lapwing Vanellus vanellus and Abyssinian
Ground Hombill Bucorvus abyssinicus. I have not used the Rcom 20 as a
hatcher yet. However, I can see no reason why it should not prove to be a
good hatcher. It holds the humidity well and, I believe, that the floor has a
non-slip surface. The machine is also easy to dismantle and clean.
During the course of the 2008 breeding season, I found it to be a very
good incubator. There is just one thing I found that needs to be watched,
that is the narrow plastic tube that carries the water from the reservoir to
the evaporation sponge. The tube easily gets blocked with debris if you
do not keep the reservoir clean. For this reason it is important to use only
distilled water.
The Rcom 20 digital incubator is made in Korea by Auto Elex Co. Ltd
(website:www.autoelex.com). At the time of writing (August 2008) it is
available from various distributors in the UK. Price approximately #240
including VAT.
Jo Gregson
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999538" page_id="56253502"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
184
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9813565" genericHeader="method" page_id="56253502" page_num="184" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
EARLY SUCCESS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.913158666666667" page_id="56253502"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
At least two young Kuhl's or Rimatara Lories Vini kuhli have fledged
on Atiu in the Cook Islands, a matter of months after 27 of these birds were
translocated there from Rimatara in French Polynesia (see News &amp; Views
Vol. 113, No.3, p. 140 (2007)). The first youngster to emerge was attacked by
Common Mynahs Acridotheres tristis (an introduced species), but survived
the attacks and two days later was joined by a second youngster. The
behaviour of a second pair suggested that the pair had young in the nest.
In August 2008, several biologists from San Diego Zoo and the Cook
Islands Natural Heritage Trust returned to Atiu to document these nests and
Alan Lieberman and Gerald McCormack's account, together with several
colour photos of adults and young, can be found in PsittaScene, the magazine
of the World Parrot Trust, November 2008, pp.8-11. The project is indebted
to several organisations and individuals, including the British Birdwatching
Fair, BirdLife International, San Diego Zoo, Loro Parque, the World Parrot
Trust and American Lory Society.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.378369" page_id="56253502"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.986828" genericHeader="method" page_id="56253502" page_num="184" year="" vol="">
SEEN THROUGH AMERICAN EYES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994743941176471" page_id="56253502"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
It has been fascinating to read Josef Lindholm's account of the visit he
and his wife, Natalie, made to nine German zoological collections in April
and May 2008. Josef reckons he saw well over 800 species and subspecies,
perhaps closer to a thousand, of which at least 110 he had never before seen
in captivity.
At Cologne Zoo he saw his first Rose-coloured Starlings Sturnus roseus
(a species once common in European aviaries and one that occasionally
turns up in gardens and on bird tables here in the UK) and Ringed Plovers
Charadrius hiaticula. He also saw hill mynahs Gracula sp. which have,
he wrote, now become a rarity in the USA, and the Vietnamese Pheasant
Lophura hathinensis , which is not represented in any of the public collections
in the USA.
Sharing the vast walk-through area with Rodriques Fruit Bats Pteropus
rodricensis in Cologne's Regenwald (rainforest) building, a tropical house
housing birds, but primarily mammals, reptiles and other creatures from
the rainforests of south-east Asia, Josef saw several species which had bred
there the previous year: Roulroul Partridges Rollulus rouloul , Scheepmaker's
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.90857875">
or Southern Crowned Pigeons Goura scheepmakeri sclateri , Beautiful and
Superb Fruit Doves Ptilinopuspulchellus &amp; P. superbus , Purple-naped Lories
Lorius domicellus, Bali Starlings Leucopsar rothschildi , Fairy Bluebirds
Irena puella and Red-whiskered Bulbuls Pycnonotus jocosus.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700184" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253492" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99894" page_id="56253492"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
185
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.955143777777778" page_id="56253492"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
A pair of Great Hombills Buceros bicornis occupy an enormous aviary
in the building and other aviaries house birds such as Renauld's Ground-
Cuckoos Carpoccocyx renaudi , Palm Cockatoos Probosciger atterimus and
Fawn-breasted Bowerbirds Chlamydera cerviniventris . Curator of Birds
Bernd Marcordes, formerly at Walsrode, took Josef on a tour of the off-
exhibit aviaries, whose residents included White-rumped Shamas Copsychus
malabarica , Red-tailed Laughingthrushes Garrulax milnei , the Blue-crowned
species Dryonastes courtoisi and, from Walsrode, Blue Couas Coua caerulea
and Madagascar Blue Pigeons Alectroenas madagascariensis.
Josef was greatly impressed by a series of outdoor aviaries housing a
variety of species. Two of them especially stand out in his memory, one
housing a pair of Siberian Cranes Grus leucogeranus , Northern Lapwings
Vanellus vanellus and European Rollers Coracias garrulus and the other a
colony of Ruffs (and Reeves) Philomachus pugnax , together with a flock of
Avocets Recurvirostra avosetta, a breeding flock of Common Terns Sterna
hirundo and the Ringed Plovers and Rose-coloured Starlings mentioned
earlier. The six Ruffs in full breeding plumage were a "breathtaking" sight,
wrote Josef. Other inhabitants of the series of aviaries include Magpie
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.832238" page_id="56253492"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
Shrikes Corvinella melanoleuca, Socorro Doves Zenaida graysoni, breeding
White-fronted Bee-eaters Merops bullockoides (see Vol.103, No.l 1 pp.20-
27 (1997)), Bearded Barbets Lybius dubius , Madagascar Fodies Foudia
madagascariensis , Madagascar Crested Ibis Lobhotibis cristata , Crested
Couas C. cristata , a big flock of Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber , breeding
White-backed Australian Magpies Gymnorhina tibicen hypoleuca and
Yellow-rumped Caciques Cacicus cela , and a breeding pair of Goliath
Herons Ardea goliath. Also housed in these aviaries are Boat-billed Herons
Cochlearius cochlearius, Hammerkops Scopus umbretta , Great Curassows
Crax rubra , breeding Congo Peafowl Afropavo congenesis and Swift Parrots
Lathamus discolor (an Australian species which has never been abundant
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.916777" page_id="56253492"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
in US aviculture). Josef was disappointed not to see the Channel-billed
Cuckoos Scythrops novaehollandiae and had to wait until they visited Berlin,
to see this strange bird.
Cologne Zoo has a large collection of waterbirds, with Magellanic
Flightless Steamer Ducks Tachyeres pteneres , Orinoco Geese Neochen
jubata and White-winged Wood Ducks Cairina scutulata , among the 61
taxa of ducks, geese and swans. Marabous Leptoptilos crumeniferus have
produced several young, as have Eastern or Great White Pelicans Pelicanus
onocrotalus. The zoo has flocks of the three larger flamingos Phoenicopteus
spp., but plans to evenually concentrate on the Caribbean species P. ruber ,
of which it presently has nearly 60 - most of them males. Seven Humboldt
Penguins Spheniscus humboldti were hatched in 2007 and, for the first
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999247" page_id="56253493"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
186
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.913399" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253493" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9419575" page_id="56253493"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
time, the zoo's small colony of Little Penguins Eudyptula minor produced
a chick.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.569919" page_id="56253493"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.866549" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56253493" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
NEWS FROM A MALAYSIAN ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.912364291666667" page_id="56253493"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
Chris Brack in Germany has managed to obtain a copy of the Annual
Report for 2007 of Zoo Negara, Kuala Lumpar, Malaysia. While admittedly
perhaps a little out of date now, it nevertheless makes interesting reading.
Zoo Negara has well over 300 Painted Storks Mycteria leucocephala and,
of the 16 species of birds bred there in 2007, not surprisingly perhaps, the
Painted Storks were the most prolific. Other species which bred there in 2007
included Milky Stork M. cinerea, Argus Pheasant Argusianus argus , Malayan
Peacock-Pheasant Polyplectron malacense , Mountain Peacock-Pheasant P.
inopinatum, Crestless Fireback Pheasant Lophnra erythropthalma and White
or Umbrella Cockatoo Cacatua alba.
The zoo exhibits several species of hombill. Nine are listed in the census:
Oriental Pied Anthracoceros albirostris. Black A. malayanus, Wrinkled
Aceros corrugatus , Wreathed A. undulatus , White-crested Berenicornis
cometus , Bushy-crested Anorrhinus galeritus. Great Buceros bicornis ,
Rhinoceros B. rhinoceros and African Southern Ground Hombill Bucorvus
leadbeateri. Most of the birds exhibited are from the region, but there are
also a few other African species including a male White-bellied Go-away
Bird Corythaixoides leucogaster , a Grey Parrot Psittacus erithacus and
lovebirds Agapornis spp. as well as, from Central and South America, three
species of macaw Ara spp., etc.
As part of its conservation work, Zoo Negara has released captive-bred
Milky Storks - a rare species vulnerable to global extinction - in Kuala
Selangor Nature Park and at Kuala Gula, Perak. Further releases were
planned for 2008.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.8195622" page_id="56253493"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
* * *
SUPPORTING PARROTS AROUND THE WORLD
At the Annual Board Meeting of Loro Parque Fundacion (LPF), the
Scientific Advisory Committee allocated a record sum of [euro]840,000 (approx.
#770,600 or US$1,095,000) to support parrot conservation around the world
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.8846415" page_id="56253493"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
in 2009. The money will be used primarily to help those parrot species in
the most urgent need. The LPF lists the Yellow-eared Parrot Ognorhynchus
icterotis, Lear's Macaw Anodorhynchus leari and the Philippine or Red-
vented Cockatoo Cacatua haematuropygia amongst the species whose
populations have been helped along the road to recovery, thanks to its
determined support.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.70016" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253494" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998708" page_id="56253494"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
187
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9964836875" page_id="56253494"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
At the two-day meeting, LPF President Wolfgang Kessling, officially
opened the fundacion's new Spix's Macaw Breeding Centre, which
increases its potential capacity for breeding this rare macaw. Although at
present the LPF has only six Spix's Macaws, it means it now has eight large
interconnecting aviaries able to accommodate eight separate pairs or capable
of being opened up to create one or more larger flights. The areas between
the aviaries have been planted and safety precautions, including cameras
and a manned guardhouse, have been installed.
At the beginning of November, Curator Dr Matthias Reinschmidt and
Inge Feier, represented LPF at a large exhibition in Chemnitz, Germany,
where the LPF stand attracted an enormous audience. Dr Reinschmidt
gave three presentations on the work of LPF in the wild and at Loro Parque,
Tenerife. The exhibition provided an excellent opportunity for LPF to
establish direct contact with private breeders, who zoological collections are
increasingly coming to realise, have an important role to play in conservation
breeding programmes.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.797219" page_id="56253494"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.802875" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56253494" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
INTO DOUBLE FIGURES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.960522666666666" page_id="56253494"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
In their Christmas card, Josef and Natalie Lindholm, listed 10 taxa
of ramphastids bred during 2008 at the Dallas World Aquarium in Texas.
They were: Toco Toucan Ramphastos toco , Saffron Toucanet Baillonius
bailloni , Blue-throated Emerald Toucanet Aulacorynchus prasinus
caeruleogularis (possibly a world first captive-breeding), Crimson-rumped
Toucanet A. haematopygus , Guianan Toucanet Selenidera culik. Green
Aracari Pteroglossus viridis, Chestnut-eared P. castanotis, Curl-crested P.
beauharnaesii, Pale-mandibled P. torquatus erythropygius and Ivory-billed
Aracari P. azara flavirostris. One pair of Pale-mandibled Aracaris produced
three broods of chicks and three other pairs of the same species each hatched
two broods.
It has also been extraordinarily successful breeding Andean Cocks-of-
the-Rock Rupicola peruvianus - its thirteenth and fourteenth chicks were
hatched in November. Jane Cooper, in California, learned from Josef that
seven Andean Cocks-of-the-Rock were raised this year and one Guianan
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.971966714285714">
Cock-of-the-Rock R. rupicola.
Two Ornate Hawk-Eagles Spizaetus ornatus were bred, as well as
Little Tinamous Crypturellus soui and Chiriqui Quail-Doves Geotrygon
chiriquensis. Josef confirmed that they have two subspecies of Ivory-
billed Aracari, P. a. flavirostris and P. a. mariae , the latter bred by Jerry
Jennings in California. This subspecies has not yet bred at the Dallas World
Aquarium.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998741" page_id="56253495"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
188
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.975876" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253495" page_num="188" year="" vol="">
OBITUARY
IAN HINZE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997086542857143" page_id="56253495"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
Ian became unwell on the evening of his 55th birthday, Thursday,
December 18th, and was hospitalised later that evening. He was suffering
from pneumonia, a complication arising from his treatment for lymphoma
(cancer of the lymph nodes), which had undermined his immune system.
He passed away two days later at 8.00am on Saturday, December 20th, Rene
Schrader learned from Ian's wife Claire. Rene had never met Ian personally,
he and Ian had got in contact with each other following the death earlier
in 2008 of their mutual friend Derek Goodwin. All shared a passion for
waxbills, so had "a lot to say to each other," wrote Rene.
When preparing Ian's article on the Red Avadavat for inclusion in this
issue (pp. 145-156), I sent four or five e-mails to him asking him to clarify
minor points and referred to the introduction of the Red Avadavat to Sabah
and, each time, got a prompt response from him. So, imagine my shock,
when on the afternoon of Saturday, December 20th, the Hon. Secretary/
Treasurer Paul Boulden phoned to ask if I had heard that Ian had died? An
hour or so later, when checking my e-mails, I was further shocked to discover
that I had a unread e-mail from Ian, which must have been sent on the day
he became unwell or the day before. In none of his e-mails did Ian mention
his health problems and was obviously looking forward to 2009 when, he
hoped, his waxbill book, which he had been working on for several years,
would finally be published.
Ian was a prolific author, whose articles appeared regularly in such
publications as Cage &amp; Aviary Birds and Australian Aviculture and was also,
I gather, a frequent contributor to website forums. He wrote mostly about
waxbills and related species of the family Estrildidae, though recently in
Cage &amp; Aviary Birds , Ian wrote about how in the 1980s, which he called a
"glorious decade for birdkeepers," his collection had included White-rumped
Shamas, Magpie Robins, Rufous-bellied Niltavas and Japanese Blue-and-
white Flycatchers and how, when Fairy Bluebirds became available, he "just
had to acquire some."
Ian was the first person in the UK (and perhaps anywhere else) to breed
the Mali or Kulikoro Firefinch Lagonsticta virata , for which he received
the society's first breeding medal, of which he was extremely proud (see
Breeding the Mali or Kulikoro Firefinch Lagonsticta virata , Vol. 107, No.l,
pp.27-34 (2001)).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.47509">
Malcolm Ellis
</subsectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996197" page_id="56253496"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
189
</page>
<table confidence="0.476953461538462" page_id="56253496"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
Contributors to Volume 114 - 2008
Barn:coat, Fred
The Madagascar Buttonqeail Turnix nigricollis ..................................... 79
Bricked, Neville
Breeding the Javan Munia Lonchura leucogastroides .......................... 129
Burton, John F.
Memories of Derek Goodwin ................................................................142
Edmans, lan and Owen, Andrew
Breeding the Brown-throated Barbet Lybius melanopterus
at Waddesdon Manor .............................................................................118
Edmans, Ian
The Blue-crowned Laughingthrash Dryonastes courtoisi:
results of a 2007 husbandry questionaire...............................................l57
Elston, Jennifer ) , Sky, Christy, Quinones, Gloried, Camey, Jennifer,
Plasse, Chelle and Bettinger, Tammie
Parental behaviour by two pairs of Guam Micronesian Kingfishers
Halcyon cinnamomina cinnamomina ......................................................15
Elston, J. J., Sky, C., Quinones, G., Tybor, C., Plasse, C and
Bettinger, T.
Unprecendented use of a nest log
by a female Green Broadbill Calyptomena viridis ............................... 172
Espley, Simon
The Fawn-breasted Waxbill Estrildapaludicola ...................................161
Gibson, Derek
Breeding the Bare-faced Curassow Crax fasciolata at Exmoor Zoo.......84
The Blue throated Conure Pyrrhura cruentata .....................................168
</table>
<page confidence="0.877592" page_id="56253497"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
190
</page>
<figure confidence="0.779750333333333" page_id="56253497"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
Contributors to Volume 114 - 2008 (Cont'd)
Gregson,Jo
Herbert Whitley - the founder of Paignton Zoo..........134
Hinze, lan
The widening distribution of the Red Avadavat Amandava amandava ,
with avicultural notes.......145
Jerrard, Jim
Breeding the Rufous-collared Sparrow Zonotrichia capensis .13
Karsten, Peter
The European Robin Erithacus rubecula -
its care and breeding in aviculture ..................101
Lament, Myles
The nesting behaviour of the Musophagidae..........2
The nesting behaviour of the Musophagidae - Part 2....63
Lindholm, Josef
Notes on the IV International Symposium
on breeding birds in captivity.49
Low, Rosemary
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.5460925">
Goldie's Lorikeet: hand-rearing and parent-rearing...24
Meldrum, J. and Wisniewski, P. J.
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.862803333333333" page_id="56253497"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
Goosander x Eider hybrids at WWT Martin Mere.......123
Owen, Andrew
A visit to Cikananga Wild Animal Rescue Centre, Java, Indonesia.97
Breeding the Black-and-white Laughingthrush Garrulax bicolor ...........70
Schofield, Philip
The Spring Social Meeting at the Hawk Conservancy, April 2008 .........37
</figure>
<page confidence="0.998609" page_id="56253498"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
191
</page>
<table confidence="0.8635021" page_id="56253498"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
Index to Volume 114 - 2008
Amandava amandava , widening distribution and avicultural notes...... 145
Avadavat, Red, widening distribution and avicultural notes ................. 145
Bat bet, Brown-breasted, breeding at Waddesdon Manor...................... 118
Book Reviews
A Guide to ...Neophema &amp; Neopsephotus Genera &amp; their Mutations 180
A Photographic Guide to the Birds of Japan and North-East Asia ...... 40
International Zoo Yearbook, Volume 41 &amp; Volume 42........................ 90
Parrots of Africa................................................................................... 91
Rare Birds Yearbook 2008 ................................................................... 39
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.715478263157895" page_id="56253498"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
Where to watch birds in Northern &amp; Eastern Spain........................... 181
Where to watch birds in Wales............................................................. 92
Breeding birds in captivity, notes on international symposium............... 49
Broadbill, Green, unprecedented use of nest log................................... 172
Buttonquail, Madagascar, keeping and breeding..................................... 79
Calyptomena viridis, unprecedented use of nest log ............................. 172
Cikananga Wild Animal Rescue Centre, Java, a visit to.......................... 97
Conure, Blue-throated, at Exmoor Zoo.................................................. 168
Crax fasciolata , breeding at Exmoor Zoo................................................ 84
Curassow, Bare-faced, breeding at Exmoor Zoo ..................................... 84
Dryonastes courtoisi , results of husbandry questionaire....................... 157
Eider, European, hybridising with Eurasian Goosander........................ 123
Erithacus rubecula , care and breeding in aviculture ............................. 101
Estrildapaludicola , care and breeding in South Africa......................... 161
Garrulax bicolor.................................................................................... 137
Garrulax bicolor, breeding at Waddesdon Manor................................... 70
Goodwin, Derek, memories of............................................................... 142
Goosander x Eider hybrids, at WWT Martin Mere ............................... 123
Halcyon cinnamowiina cinnamomina , parental behaviour....................... 15
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.96609425">
Hybrids, Goosander x Eider, at WWT Martin Mere.............................. 123
Kingfisher, Guam Micronesian, parental behaviour................................ 15
Laughingthrash, Black-and-white.......................................................... 137
Laughmgthrash, Black-and-white, breeding at Waddesdon Manor......... 70
</reference>
<page confidence="0.99931" page_id="56253499"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
192
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.4736025" page_id="56253499"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
Index to Volume 114 - 2008 (Cont'd)
Laughingthrush, Blue-crowned, results of husbandry questionaire.. 157
Lonchura leucogastroides , breeding........ 129
Lorikeet, Goldie's, hand-rearing and parent-rearing.24
Lybius melanopterus, breeding at Waddesdon Manor... 118
Mergus m. merganser x Somateria m. mollissima hybrids.. 123
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.9506474" page_id="56253499"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
Munia, Javan, breeding.....129
Musophagidae, nesting behaviour.......2
Musophagidae, nesting behaviour - part 2.....63
News &amp; Views...... 42,94,138,184
Obituaries
Derek Goodwin.....45
Anthony J. Mobbs ........47
Pat Wisniewski, John Leonard Martyn.48
lan Hinze...............188
Officers &amp; Council Members, as from April 5th 2008.1
Review
Rcom 20 digital incubator.....182
Robin, European, care and breeding in aviculture...101
Somateria m. mollissima , hybridising with Mergus m. merganser .123
Sparrow, Rufous-collared, breeding.13
Spring Social Meeting, at the Hawk Conservancy, April 2008.37
Trichoglossus goldiei , hand-rearing and parent-rearing.24
Turacos, see Musophagidae, nesting behaviour.2,68
Turnix nigricollis , keeping and breeding...79
Walsrode Birdpark, news from. 32
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.604083333333333" page_id="56253499"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
Waxbill, Fawn-breasted, care and breeding in South Africa.161
Whitley, Herbert, the founder of Paignton Zoo...134
Zonotrichia capensis, breeding. 13
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9976345" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253500" page_num="" year="" vol="">
WADERS IN AVICULTURE
ASURVEY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990399565217391" page_id="56253500"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Waders, members of the suborder Charadrii, are a diverse group of birds.
They vary in their physical form; have a wide geographical distribution and
a range of breeding and feeding habitats. They seem to indulge in almost
every avian reproductive strategy recorded and have amazing physiological
adaptations that enable them to feature in the record books for their migratory
skills. They are often long-lived and, in general, reasonably sized birds that
frequently congregate in open areas making them easy to observe; as a result
they have been studied more than any other group of birds.
The body of ornithological and general scientific knowledge available
on free-living waders is vast. It is surprising, therefore, that the avicultural
literature contains very little information regarding the captive management
- accommodation needs, nutritional requirements, breeding, health and
disease - of these birds.
Despite the lack of published information, I am sure that there is a large
reservoir of knowledge within the avicultural community that once collected
and collated will help establish good husbandry guidelines for maintaining
those birds that are currently under captive management and for any species
which as time progresses, is unfortunate enough to require ex situ help in
its conservation.
I would like to ask those aviculturists who keep or have kept waders in
their collections to help with this research project and share their knowledge
by completing a questionaire. This can be done online or by hard copy.
Please take part and visit:
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.7046153" page_id="56253500"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
www.wadersurvey.com
or contact
Brian Stockdale MRCVS,
Meadow Lane Veterinary Centre,
9 Meadow Lane,
Loughborough LE11 1JU,
UK.
Tel:+44 (0)7711 750579
E-mail: brian.stockdale @ wadersurvey.com
Brian Stockdale, who is a practising avian vet and visiting lecturer at
</figure>
<affiliation confidence="0.353053">
Nottingham University and has been a member of the Avicultural Society
</affiliation>
<bodyText confidence="0.8903235" page_id="56253500"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
for more that 25 years, hopes to publish the results of the survey in a future
issue of the Avicultural Magazine.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.979809" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253501" page_num="" year="" vol="">
SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION LIBRARIES
</sectionHeader>
<address confidence="0.493902">
3 9088 01463 3762
</address>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.946278" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56253501" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9202205" page_id="56253501"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The widening distribution of the Red Avadavat
Amandava amandava , with avicultural notes
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.882992608695652" page_id="56253501"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Ian Hinze. 145
The Blue-crowned Laughingthrush Dryonastes courtoisi:
results of a 2007 husbandry questionaire
by lan Edmans.157
The Fawn-breasted Waxbill Estrilda paludicola
by Simon Espley.161
The Blue-throated Conure Pyrrhura cruentata
by Derek Gibson.168
Unprecedented use of a nest log
by a female Green Broadbill Calyptomena viridis
by J. J. Elston, C. Sky, G. Quinones, C. Tybor, C. Plasse
and T. Bettinger...172
Reviews
A Guide to...Neophema &amp; Neosephotus Genera
&amp; their Mutations.180
Where to Watch Birds in Northern and Eastern Spain.181
The Rcom 20 Digital Incubator.182
News &amp; Views.184
Obituary - Ian Hinze .188
Contributors to Volume 114 - 2008.189
Index to Volume 114 - 2008.191
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</table>
</algorithms>
