<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.7048066" page_id="56337103"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 114
No. 3
2008
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337104" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.984815548387097" page_id="56337104"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2008 as for 2007: British
Isles #18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please).
The subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the
Society later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of
the AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, ARCADIA, THE MOUNTS, TOTNES, DEVON TQ9 7QJ,
UK.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TNI 3 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail: Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have not
been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of a
particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history. Articles
should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the scientific
names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given. References
cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line drawings,
black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular point in
the article will be used where possible and should be clearly captioned. If
authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when submitting the
article and write their name on the back of each photograph. Tables and
graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be aware of
the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of the page
which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997594" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56337104" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982475333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.669898" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337105" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<construct confidence="0.35686875" page_id="56337105"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
VoL 114-No. 3 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2008
A VISIT TO CIKANANGA WILD ANIMAL
RESCUE CENTRE, JAVA, INDONESIA
by Andrew Owen
</construct>
<bodyText confidence="0.960510137931035" page_id="56337105"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Following the kind invitation from David Jeggo, Chair of the EAZA
Passerine TAG Group (European Association of Zoos and Aquaria Passerine
Taxon Advisory Group) and Roland Wirth, Director of ZGAP (Zoological
Society for the Conservation of Species and Populations), based in Munich,
Germany, I spent three weeks in February 2008 at the Cikananga Wild
Animal Rescue Centre on the Indonesian island of Java. I was asked to visit
the centre to assist with the establishment of protocols for a captive-breeding
programme for the Black-and-white Laughingthrash Garrulax bicolor , a
rare species of passerine endemic to the neighbouring island of Sumatra.
In the previous issue of the magazine (VoL 114, No.2, pp.70-78 (2008))
I described the first breeding in the UK of the Black-and-white Laughing-
thrash, at Waddesdon Manor aviaries, near Aylesbury, Buckinghamshire.
It is one of only two collections known to have bred this species, the other
being Paultons Park in Hampshire. There is only a very small population
of this species in European collections and there is extreme concern for it in
the wild, due to the capture of wild birds for the cage bird trade.
In addition to working at Cikananga with the laughingthrushes, I assisted
Resit Sozer, Cikananga's Director and Pavel Hospardarsky, an experienced
aviculturist from the Czech Republic, based in the Philippines, who was
establishing a captive breeding group of Black-winged Starlings Sturnus
melanopterus , an Endangered species from Java, Bali and Lombok.
Cikananga, in the west of Java, is the largest animal rescue centre in
Indonesia and is dedicated to the conservation of Indonesian wildlife,
facilitating the enforcement of wildlife laws, by playing a key role in the
confiscation, rehabilitation and release of wild animals. Many species of
confiscated animals, including primates, Sun Bears Helarctos malayanus,
Leopards Panihera pardus , Tigers P. tigris and a wide variety of birds, are
kept at the centre. The recent focus, however, has been on the establishment
of captive breeding programmes for a number of highly threatened
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999516" page_id="56337106"  page_num="98" year="" vol="">
98
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.816999" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337106" page_num="98" year="" vol="">
OWEN - CIKANANGA WILD ANIMAL RESCUE CENTRE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99271556097561" page_id="56337106"  page_num="98" year="" vol="">
Indonesian species, primarily the Black-winged Starling, Black-and-white
Laughingthrash and Javan Warty Pig Sus verrucosus, with the eventual aim
of releasing captive-bred stock into suitable protected wild areas,
I worked closely with Pavel, Resit and the bird keeping staff. Guidelines
were drawn up for the care and management of the birds, with special
attention given to aviary management, diet and breeding requirements.
There are a large number of very good aviaries at the centre, and a large
part of our time was spent modifying these to suit the needs of breeding
birds. Several aviaries, particularly those that were designated for the
laughingthrushes, which are generally rather secretive and require thick
vegetation in which to nest, are heavily planted with shrubs and small trees,
collected from around the grounds.
The founding stock for the breeding programmes consisted of five
Black-and-white Laughingthrushes and nine Black-winged Starlings, A
further 12 starlings were acquired during my time there and, hopefully,
additional laughingthrushes will be added to the programme soon. Two
pairs of Spectacled Laughingthrushes Rhinocichla mitrata have also been
established at the centre. Although this Sumatran (Malaysian) species is not
considered threatened, it was thought that these birds could be useful as a
model species to provide the aviary keepers with valuable experience with
another species of laughingthrash with which to perfect their husbandry and
captive breeding skills. These skills can then be applied to the management
of G. bicolor .
Pavel and I spent a lot of time closely observing the birds 5 behaviour,
in an attempt to pick out potential breeding pairs. Once the aviaries
were prepared the birds were measured, weighed and, if necessary, ringed
(banded) and, in the case of the laughingthrushes, feathers were removed
for DNA sexing at a UK laboratory when I returned home.
Resit, Pavel and I flew to central Java, to the district of Klaten, near
Yogyakarta, to observe the work of a group of bird keepers who have set up
a consortium with the aim of breeding passerines for the cage bird market.
Approximately 60 people from several villages in the district have formed
a cage bird breeding society and there are an additional 60 or so others who
breed birds, but are not members of the society. The skills they have acquired
and the techniques they use produce astonishing numbers of passerines, on
a scale that must be unique anywhere in the world.
The breeders focus on the most popular species, normally those that have
a melodic song or make good pets. Some breeders specialise in just one
species, while others produce several Altogether about 10 or so species
are bred, with the most popular being the Asian Pied Starling S. contra ,
Magpie Robin Copsychus saularis, White-ramped Shama C. malabaricus ,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.580898" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337107" page_num="99" year="" vol="">
OWEN - CIKANANGA WILD ANIMAL RESCUE CENTRE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995741" page_id="56337107"  page_num="99" year="" vol="">
99
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.965663731707317" page_id="56337107"  page_num="99" year="" vol="">
Black-winged Starling, Chestnut-capped Thrush Zoothera interpres and
Straw-headed Bulbul Pycnonotus zeylanicus.
The society appears to be very well organised. Everyone uses exactly
the same technique to rear each particular species of bird. They all have
the same size aviaries, use the same food, provide identical nest boxes and
baskets and use the same nest material. The eggs are removed from the nest
a day or two before they are due to hatch or the chicks are removed soon
after hatching and the young are hand-reared. As these birds are reared
purely for commercial reasons, it is important to them to rear as many as
possible from each pair and, by hand-rearing the chicks, the breeding pairs
produce several clutches each season. Another reason for removing the
chicks for hand-rearing, appears to be because chicks left in the nest are
often predated by ants.
All of the young are fitted with closed rings (bands), unique to the year
and the breeder. All are hand-reared on a similar diet, consisting of finely
ground chicken broiler crumble and, Kroto, a mixture of the larvae and
eggs of the local weaver ants. This food is available in the numerous bird
shops, however, many breeders culture their own ants in mango trees in
their gardens.
An amazing number of birds are reared. One breeder produces 25 Asian
Pied Starlings a week for the market and another rears 30 Magpie Robin
chicks per pair per year. I would be amazed if that many Magpie Robins
were bred in the whole of the UK in a year, let alone by one breeder from
one pair!
Because they are producing these birds purely for commercial reasons,
they obviously push their birds hard to obtain the highest number of young.
In my opinion their aviaries are probably a little too small and the diet
they feed their birds is extremely basic - chicken crumbs, crickets and the
occasional bit of fruit for the fruit-eaters - but the skill and dedication of
these aviculturists is extremely impressive.
It is also interesting to note that many of these breeders were formerly bird
trappers or bird hunters. Now they are making a good living supplying the
market with large numbers of captive-bred birds, that are more popular than
the wild-caught ones, so there is a real conservation element to their story
too. If people prefer captive-bred birds then, hopefully, it will encourage
more people to breed them, rather than take them from the wild.
It was great to share our bird breeding experiences with the breeders
of Klaten. Resit, Pavel and I left there with our heads spinning with the
knowledge we had gained and with ideas on conservation work these people
can possibly help us with in the future. Further captive-bred pairs of Black-
winged Starling were acquired for the breeding programme and plans were
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.96677" page_id="56337108"  page_num="100" year="" vol="">
100
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.800446" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337108" page_num="100" year="" vol="">
OWEN - CIKANANGA WILD ANIMAL RESCUE CENTRE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.983978333333333" page_id="56337108"  page_num="100" year="" vol="">
made to send at least one of the Cikananga bird keepers to Klaten to learn
their hand-rearing techniques.
Cikananga Wild Animal Rescue Centre is a very good facility at which
to carry out in situ captive breeding programmes and with future support,
funding and guidance from overseas zoological collections, these early
breeding programmes have every chance of succeeding.
The conservation fund set up at Waddesdon Manor aviaries will assist
with initial funding for the captive breeding programme for the Black-and-
white Laughingthrush at Cikananga.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.890937" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56337108" page_num="100" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.940929285714286" page_id="56337108"  page_num="100" year="" vol="">
I would like to thank Waddesdon Manor's Director Fabia Bromovsky
and Curator of Birds Ian Hadgkiss for allowing me the opportunity to visit
Java and for assisting with the cost of the flight to Indonesia. Thanks also
to Roland Wirth and ZGAP for covering half of my travel costs and the
Avicultural Society and Geoff Masson at Paultons Park, for donations
towards the laughingthrush project. Finally, a big thank you to Resit Sozer,
Pavel Hospardarsky and the staff at Cikananga for making my visit such a
productive and enjoyable one.
Postscript
On July 21 st 2008, Andrew received the following update from Java: "At
present 30 Black-winged Starlings are housed at Cikananga Wild Animal
Rescue Centre. Seven of these were confiscated over the period 2002-2006
by the Indonesian Government in Jakarta, West Java and Bali, as the species
is protected by nationa 1 law. Thirteen captive-bred birds have been obtained
from the village of Klaten in central Java during the past two years, and 10
birds have been successfully reared at Cikananga since February 2008."
Andrew Owen was, until very recently, Senior Aviary Keeper at
Waddesdon Manor aviaries, near Aylesbury, Buckinghamshire HP 18 OJH,
UK. He is now Curator of Birds at Chester Zoo. If you would like to make
a donation or learn more about the breeding programmes you can contact
him there via E-mail:a. owen@ chesterzoo.org
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998303" page_id="56337109"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
101
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.546281" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337109" page_num="101" year="" vol="">
THE EUROPEAN ROBIN Erithacus ruhecula
ITS CARE AND BREEDING IN AVICULTURE
by Peter Karsten
Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999152114285714" page_id="56337109"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
In the context of aviculture the European Robin is a softbill.
Taxonomically it is grouped with the thrushes in the subfamily Turdidae.
It ranges throughout Europe and western Asia and has eight subspecies.
It measures about IVim (14cm) in length and weighs 12g-20g. The
forehead and chest are orange-red and this colour extends to the sides of
the neck and below the eyes. The orange chest is partly bordered by a faint
bluish-grey band. The back and wings are olive-grey to brown, the belly is
whitish, the under tail-coverts are a cream colour and the upper tail-coverts
are light brown. Some adults have ochre coloured tips to the greater wing-
coverts, which is a prominent feature of the juvenile plumage. Juveniles have
spotted plumage until they obtain their adult plumage in the fall (autumn).
The sexes look alike, although some aviculturists feel that there are slight
differences, such as the width of the orange band on the forehead, which is
considered to extend higher up on the male. In a pair I obtained this was
not evident, in fact the female seemed to have a broader band, which misled
me until a DNA test determined the bird's gender. By carefully studying
the extent of the orange patch of nine birds raised by the same parents, it
seemed to me that the orange reached further up under and beyond the eyes
of the birds that I had determined to be males. Determination of sex was
done by observing the higher levels of aggression and dominance over
siblings just prior to separating the young and housing them in individual
enclosures to avoid serious conflicts and by dominant behaviour patterns
after separation. The perceived males regularly came out into the open to
take up observation posts from which they could see other European Robins
in neighbouring enclosures. During October-November of their first year,
especially if I whistled to them, they would often sing, but the song was
barely audible and was detectable by the movement of the throat feathers
and less by the vocalisation. The males were braver in approaching me at
feeding time. Juvenile females generally stayed back and went to the food
after I had turned and left. I could at times entice males to sing by playing
taped song of the European Robin. Females did not respond and even
retreated. These behavioural observations were made on juveniles during
September-November when they were three to four months old. In the
spring, the more prominent singing of the males and a protruding nipple-like
papilla of the cloaca are a good means of establishing a bird's sex (other
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999235" page_id="56337110"  page_num="102" year="" vol="">
102
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.958668" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337110" page_num="102" year="" vol="">
KARSTEN - EUROPEAN ROBIN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.965035170731707" page_id="56337110"  page_num="102" year="" vol="">
than by a DNA test). Housed in side-be-side aviaries a male and female will
by their gender related behaviour also provide clues, as described below.
The European Robin lives in the shrub level of forest, woodland and in
cultivated garden environments. It searches on the ground for invertebrates,
often by turning over fallen leaves and other ground litter. Besides insects
and arthropods, it eats small slugs and snails and segmented worms. Various
berries are taken in the fall (autumn) and winter.
It is a highly territorial species and will aggressively defend its feeding
grounds and nesting territory against intruders of its own kind and to some
extent also against other softbills. This behaviour will inevitably lead to
losses if two European Robins are put together in the same aviary, regardless
of their sex, unless the birds have established their breeding territory as a
pair. From an avicultural perspective this is perhaps the most critical point
in caring for this species. Once the birds are paired up they will jointly
defend their territory against intruders.
In the wild the nest is built close to the ground or often on the ground,
but may also be built in a cavity high in a tree, in a hole in a wall or in a half-
open-fronted nest box above 6ft (approx. 2m). The female seeks a location
where the nest will be roofed. Nests in tin cans, mailboxes and other man-
made objects are not rare. Nesting material includes leaves, grasses, moss
and animal hair. Hair is used to line the nest cup.
A clutch normally consists of five to six eggs, which are cream coloured
with fine rust-brown spots. The incubation period is 13-14 days and the
nestling period is the same. Typically, two clutches are reared per year. The
young are reared by both parents. The male does most of the feeding of the
fledged chicks if the female starts another nest. In an avicultural setting, it
is important that the earlier clutch of chicks are weaned prior to the hatching
of the next clutch. This is to ensure that the parents give sufficient attention
to the newly-hatched chicks. Adults give priority to the most vigorous
and advanced offspring as a form of species survival strategy. If the state
of independence of the chicks is in doubt, the male and the chicks can be
moved to a separate enclosure, leaving the feeding of the newly-hatched
chicks to the female.
Avicultural experience
Acquisition
I obtained two European Robins of undetermined sex from an importer
on February 18th 2005. One was in good condition while the other had lost
about 20% of its upper mandible, the nail on the left hind toe was missing
and the foot joints and toes were swollen. Articular gout was suspected.
The bird favoured its right leg. There was no conclusive difference in the
coloration of the plumage of the two birds, although the orange colour on the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.910589" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337111" page_num="103" year="" vol="">
KARSTEN \0x25A0 EUROPEAN ROBIN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999672" page_id="56337111"  page_num="103" year="" vol="">
103
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.980994024390244" page_id="56337111"  page_num="103" year="" vol="">
forehead of the intact bird seemed to extend further. DNA testing proved that
this bird was a female and the injured bird was a male. They were housed in
side-by-side enclosures separated by 14m (12mm x 12mm) wire mesh.
Feeding
European Robins are basically insectivores, that during the fall (autumn)
and winter will eat berries in the wild. At bird feeding stations they accept
suet or margarine mixed with poppy seeds and finely chopped nuts. I feed
them crickets, waxworms, buffalo worms and wild moths, but very few
mealworms. The exception being those that have freshly shed their skins,
i.e. white-skinned mealworms and pupae which are picked from the cultures
whenever possible. Crickets are provided in plastic storage boxes with
lOin-llin (25.5cm-28cm) high sides to prevent escapes. Waxworms are
also placed in these containers to give the birds enough time to capture them
before they crawl out of the containers to find hiding places to pupate. At
low ambient temperatures waxworms become lethargic and remain in small
food dishes. A home-made softbill mix is offered regularly and some of it is
consumed, particularly during the winter months (for recipe see Appendix).
I would not depend on the softbill mix as the sole food supply. Earthworms
and beetle grabs are given when available. The birds find some of these
on the aviary floor where they turn over the ground litter. The literature
suggests offering strips of cooked or raw beef heart. I breed and offer my
birds a consistent supply of insects (livefood) and have not fed them beef
heart. The insects are dusted with vitamin/mineral supplements twice a
week and a dish of crushed eggshell is available. During the rearing of
the chicks the insects are dusted every second day with Nekton products,
Nekton S and Nekton MSA.
European Robins are not swift at picking up food, they typically tilt their
heads and look at a food item before they lunge forward and seize it. This
needs to be considered if tits Pams spp. and/or Pekin Robins Leiothrix lutea
cohabit with European Robins. Unless there is an ample supply of livefood
the other species will easily out compete the latter. Tits and Pekin Robins
feed in pairs and groups and intimidate the European Robin, which is a
solitary feeder. Providing insects at dusk and dawn helps the crepuscular
European Robin to obtain food when the other species are not active.
Housing
The layout of the author's enclosures has evolved through the consecu-
tive construction of the various components (see diagram of layout). Aviary
No.l is 6ft x 12ft x 8ft high (approx. 1.8m x 3.6m x 2.4m high). It was built
as a breeding enclosure for Pekin Robins and heavily planted with shrubs,
conifers and bamboo. The 'corridor enclosure' is a T-shaped space 4ft wide
x 8ft high (approx. 1.2m wide x 2.4m high), used originally as a service
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999691" page_id="56337112"  page_num="104" year="" vol="">
104
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.961099" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337112" page_num="104" year="" vol="">
KARSTEN - EUROPEAN ROBIN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998510272727273" page_id="56337112"  page_num="104" year="" vol="">
corridor for the connecting aviaries. It has been planted since with conifers
and become a habitat-type space. A 6ft x 18ft x 8ft high (approx. 1.8m x
5.4m x 2.4m high) raspberry cage is on the other side of the corridor. The
aviaries are mostly covered with glass or plastic (polyethylene sheeting) to
control heavy rainfall and contamination by wild bird droppings.
The raspberry cage protects our fruit from being raided by wild birds.
The European Robins had access to this cage most of the time. A small
flight (for holding the male) is connected by an overhead passage to an
indoor aviary not shown on the diagram. The space is used to hold the male
during the non-breeding season. All of the spaces connect with the corridor
by way of walk-through doors and overhead slides. There is a shift passage
from the male's holding enclosure to aviary No.l to cross over the corridor
space. A breeding aviary for Pekin Robins abuts part of one other side of
the corridor. I do not suggest building a breeding facility with this layout for
softbills. It simply evolved as more enclosures were added to accommodate
the growing colony of Pekin Robins; however, the complex layout provides
good flexibility for managing breeding activities. The service corridor
(shown on the diagram) connects to a building with other aviary systems
and this covered and secure space is often used to lure birds out of their
planted aviaries in order to be captured or moved away to allow for a nest
to be inspected, chicks to be banded (ringed) or to permit wire-to-wire visits
by other birds to the occupants of the above enclosures.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.83312" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337113" page_num="105" year="" vol="">
KARSTEN - EUROPEAN ROBIN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998848" page_id="56337113"  page_num="105" year="" vol="">
105
</page>
<author confidence="0.577138">
Peter Karsten
</author>
<bodyText confidence="0.983192" page_id="56337113"  page_num="105" year="" vol="">
Male singing.
Pairing and the first nesting attempt
The male was kept in the holding enclosure and the raspberry cage and
the female was kept in the corridor enclosure. The male soon demonstrated
aggressive behaviour by flying at the female, who sometimes stood her
ground and flashed her raised chest feathers at him in the same way that
he tried to intimidate her. I interpreted this as territorial behaviour and
not courtship. Both did some low-volume singing at first, some of which
was barely audible. I observed the birds through binoculars from a nearby
building and noted their singing by observing the movement of their ruffled
throat feathers and, at times, by observing their open beaks. Within two
week of their arrival the male sang louder and more frequently than the
female. He continued to fly towards the female who was on the other side
of the wire mesh, but following his initial threat display, sat by the wire
which separated them, with the female close to him on the other side. The
female came more frequently to the wire mesh that was separating them
and, on March 10th, two slides between the enclosures were opened. The
male chased the female as she entered his enclosure and pursued her in her
aviary as well, but did not make body contact with her. The female would
fly towards him, but always retreated when he flew in her direction. This
pattern of behaviour remained constant. He continued to show discomfort
due to the gout and often sat near a heat lamp, which was provided to
improve his blood circulation and reduce the accumulation of uric acid in
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998601" page_id="56337114"  page_num="106" year="" vol="">
106
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.646557" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337114" page_num="106" year="" vol="">
KAR8TEN - EUROPEAN ROBIN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996024780487805" page_id="56337114"  page_num="106" year="" vol="">
his right leg. He frequently sat with his chest resting on a perch or a flat
surface. His health improved by the third week of April and he began to
show more aggression towards the female. No courtship feeding was seen
and the compatibility of the two birds was called into question. Three more
attempts were made to pair the male with the female, but on each occasion
resulted in him chasing her more vigorously and intimidating her to a point
where she hid beneath vegetation in her enclosure. Further attempts were
made off and on between May-August. I saw the female twice during that
time showing fledgling-like begging behaviour by crouching low on a perch
and quivering her wings, but the male did not respond by feeding her. As
the breeding season was coming to a close and my hopes of them breeding
had vanished, he was moved to a distant aviary measuring 30ft x 16ft x 12ft
high (approx.9.1m x 4.8m x 3.6m high).
Early in November I was able to exchange a Pekin Robin for a European
Robin. It was believed to be a male and had been kept by a Chinese bird
fancier in a small, traditional Chinese songbird cage. The bird appeared to
be in good health, but due to the limited amount of exercise it had been able
to take in the small cage, I was suspicious of its overall physical condition.
The playing of taped European Robin song triggered vigorous singing and
encouraged me to hope that 1 had indeed acquired a male. As I had misjudged
the sexes before, I followed up with a DNA test using a drop of blood from
a toenail clipped just short enough so as not to cause undue bleeding. The
test confirmed the bird was a male.
I made no attempt to introduce the new male to the female, as it was
much too early in the season to expect courtship behaviour. He and the
female were housed in the same enclosures that were used before. The
males were in aviaries some 20m (65ft) apart and the singing of one male
clearly spurred the other on. There was some vocalisation from the female
as well during that time.
In the wild the female European Robin will seek out a male during
the winter months by entering his territory. Pairing does not happen
spontaneously, some familiarisation occurs while the gradual, seasonal
development of the reproductive organs and, in particular, the production
of sex hormones suppresses aggression and makes both birds receptive to
mating. I tried the female in the large habitat enclosure with male No. 1 on
November 27th. They met on a branch and displayed intense territorial
behaviour. The male immediately raised his fluffed-up chest and throat and
stood as tall as he could, while the female came closer and presented her chest
in a similar fashion and also fluffed-up her whitish under tail-coverts and
raised her tail high. Both did some typical curtsying before the female flew
off. They were kept together under close observation for a few days in this
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.833296" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337115" page_num="107" year="" vol="">
KARSTEN - EUROPEAN ROBIN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999561" page_id="56337115"  page_num="107" year="" vol="">
107
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.994779390243902" page_id="56337115"  page_num="107" year="" vol="">
large and densely planted aviary, with the male only occasionally chasing
the female, I then moved the female back to her own smaller enclosure.
During December the temperature often dipped to -4*C to "6*C (approx.
25*F-22*F), which clearly aggravated the male's gout. He stopped using
his right leg and was brought in to spend the winter in a heated enclosure in
which he often sat near a heat lamp. In March he was released again into
the large habitat aviary, and shortly afterwards was found one morning with
no tail feathers. I had noticed a pair of Coal Tits Pams ater becoming very
aggressive and pestering Mm at feeding time. The male Coal Tit had killed
another male Coal Tit a few days before while taking over a nest box. The
Coal Tits also harassed a pair of Blue Tits P . caeruleus, which led to the pair
of Blue Tits being removed from the enclosure. The Blue Tits thanked me
later by raising six chicks. The European Robin was returned to the indoor
enclosure and began to undergo an out of season partial moult of facial and
body feathers, which I assumed was due to his gout problem affecting his
metabolism. The prospect of him successfully breeding with the female
seemed very slim.
Meanwhile, from November Fehi nary male No.2 was housed in a large
planted aviary with two pairs of Pekin Robins, a Silver-eared Mesia L.
argentauris and some European finches. By February he was developing
territorial behaviour and would systematically drive the Pekin Robins away
from the food dish. Even after two dishes were set up 1 Oft (approx. 3m) apart,
he successfully patrolled these so that the Pekin Robins were potentially at
risk of starvation. Presumably the drive to establish a breeding territory
elevated his aggression. I have observed the reverse occur, whereby Pekin
Robins were systemically interfering with the feeding of juvenile European
Robins and tits. The aggressors simply flew to the dish the moment other
birds approached it and, though they did not actually chase or attack them,
effectively prevented them from feeding. This easily overlooked problem
can lead to the loss of birds, especially during cold weather. The culprits
were caught in a self-triggering trap baited with waxworms. Male No.2
was placed in the aviary next to the female and, as expected, there were
immediate confrontations at the wire mesh which separated them. On
March 10th the male was given access to the female. He was, however,
kept under strict observation and was seen chasing the female, but made
no contact with her. Although these short pursuits are part of courtship
behaviour, there is a fine line between persistent and dangerous attacks and
these short courtship chases. The two birds were left together, but after a few
days the male became increasingly aggressive and the two were separated
again. By April 21st they had been reunited and there were no further
confrontations. The female was often hiding in the dense vegetation while
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999501" page_id="56337116"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
108
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.816524" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337116" page_num="108" year="" vol="">
KARSTEN - EUROPEAN ROBIN
</sectionHeader>
<author confidence="0.402123">
Peter Karsten
</author>
<bodyText confidence="0.987486739130435" page_id="56337116"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
Male feeding female.
the male sang intensely. On May 5th I observed the female sitting on a perch
within 2ft (0.6m) of the male and holding a waxworm in her beak, but not
eating it. On May 7th the female was flashing her under tail-coverts at the
male. The male sang much less that day. There was a sudden change in the
daily routine, with the female failing to show up for insects at the evening
feed. On May 8th the female began to busily gather nesting material. She
pulled on a patch of moss and picked up strands of it and also other plant
fibres, old leaves and some grasses, followed by horsehair, which I had
quickly laid out. I took several photos of this activity, during which she
ignored me, so preoccupied was she picking up the horsehair. She chose
light coloured hair in preference to dark coloured hair. The male stayed
close by, picking up horsehair occasionally, but then dropping it. He did
not participate in building the nest, but kept a watch and sang quietly. The
female never flew directly to the nest but slipped through the undergrowth
and was soon out of sight. I had placed five nest boxes in the aviary and
it was some time before I was able to confirm which box she had chosen.
They were made of lOin (25.5cm) long sections of hollow cedar log, with
an outer diameter of approximately 8in (20.5cm) and an inner diameter of
5in (12.7cm). A piece of plywood was screwed to the back and a piece of
offcut was screwed onto the front of the box, leaving a slot-shaped opening
about lin-2in (25mm-50mm) high (see photo p. 112). The female filled the
cavity with the aforementioned nest materials and completed the nest with
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.833168" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337117" page_num="109" year="" vol="">
KARSTEN - EUROPEAN ROBIN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998898" page_id="56337117"  page_num="109" year="" vol="">
109
</page>
<author confidence="0.532964">
Peter Karsten
</author>
<bodyText confidence="0.988581826086957" page_id="56337117"  page_num="109" year="" vol="">
Nest and eggs.
a perfect lining of horsehair. She had apparently completed the nest that
evening, as no further nest material was picked up the following day. I had
mounted a video camera at the nest site while the pair was searching for
insects in the service corridor. I let them do this earlier to condition them
to being locked away from the nest site so that I could inspect it.
First dutch
Two eggs were discovered on May 10th, the female evidently having
laid her first egg immediately after completing the nest. The male was seen
on the TV monitor flying to the rim of the nest and looking in. Both birds
became secretive and did not come to pick up insects when they were called.
Also, the male's singing was considerably quieter and shorter in duration.
Food consumption increased. They were fed waxworms, waxmoths and
crickets, plus some white-skinned mealworms, egg cake and home-made
softbill mix. A dish containing finely crushed eggshell and a mineral
supplement is always present in the aviary. The female began incubation
on May 14th. The male was observed feeding her on the nest on May 24th.
The following day I had to travel to Germany and was to be away until June
3rd. The eggs were expected to hatch on May 28th-May 29th. Some male
European Robins have been accused of throwing out their newly-hatched
chicks and a judgement call had to be made on whether or not to leave him
in the aviary. As he showed normal behaviour by feeding the female on the
nest, I decided to leave him in the aviary with the female. My understanding
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997441" page_id="56337118"  page_num="110" year="" vol="">
110
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.952393" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337118" page_num="110" year="" vol="">
KAKSTEN - EUROPEAN ROBIN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995927317073171" page_id="56337118"  page_num="110" year="" vol="">
wife was left to look after the 20 aviaries housing some 50 birds - a task
she took on with considerable trepidation. After all, these were the first
European Robins to have nested in my aviaries and, as far as I was aware,
there were no others in Canada.
Although my wife provided them with ample supplies of waxworms and
crickets, on my return I found one dead chick in the nest and two carcasses
on the aviary floor. The chick in the nest appeared to have been abandoned
and the two dead chicks on the aviary floor appeared to have been damaged,
but it was not clear whether the damage had been caused by the parents or
possibly a mouse. The chicks looked as so they may have lived for about
two days. What, I asked myself, had gone wrong? The disappointment was
undeniable but short-lived thanks to the fact that the pair quickly re-nested.
I discovered the probable answer to my question when the second clutch
hatched and the size of the insect food, proved to be critical.
Second clutch
June 3rd. I made another enticing nest box for the adjoining flight and the
next morning the female was carrying nesting material into it. She worked
on the nest for part of each of the following three days.
June 7th. I could see one egg in the nest. During the day the male sang
louder and more often. Watching the birds on the TV monitor, I saw the
female sit on the nest at times prior to incubation beginning and twice saw
the male bring food to her.
June 13th. Incubation began. Four eggs were seen in the nest the previous
day and, on June 17th, I saw six eggs in the nest. She likely began incubation
after she had laid the fifth egg.
June 25th. On the TV monitor I watched the female spend a long period
of time looking into the bottom of the nest and later take waxworms to the
nest and appear to offer them to a chick or chicks. I took the precaution
of locking away the male in case he had been responsible for evicting the
chicks from the previous nest.
June 26th. The temperature was 31*C (87.8*F) in the shade and the
female did practically no brooding. Leafy branches were placed on the roof
to shade the nest. I set up a camera about 2ft (0,6m) from the nest and while
I was doing this the female flew repeatedly at my hand and emitted a hissing
sound. Of the food offered, the female selected only small waxworms, small
crickets and buffalo worms. I believe it is critical to provide small-sized
insect food during the first few days and that the lack of sufficiently small
insect food probably led to the death of the first brood of chicks. The female
did not feed the chicks adult crickets or mealworms, not even soft-bodied
larvae. On the second day she fed them waxmoths - wings and all Then,
as the chicks grew, she became less selective about the size of the insects,
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.313229" page_id="56337119"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
KAR8TEN - EUROPEAN ROBIN
</equation>
<page confidence="0.998527" page_id="56337119"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
111
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998291048780488" page_id="56337119"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
though she continued to show a bias towards small insects. Most of the
faecal sacs were consumed but a few were carried away and stuck on a far
perch. Later, most faecal sacs were deposited on one spot on that particular
perch (see photo p, 114) and only a few were consumed.
June 30th. On the TV monitor I watched the female constantly picking
at the chicks and standing over them in the nest without feeding them. The
chicks were gaping, which may have been to regulate their body temperature
and/or may have been because they were hungry. They shifted about a lot
in the nest and stretched and shook their necks as if irritated by the female&apos;s
grooming. This went on from 4.00pm-6.30pm and I became concerned that
the female might have lost her feeding response and that the chicks were
starving or sick. Twice the female dived deep down into the nest with her
wings beating and shook the nest, but I could not see what she was picking
at or trying to remove. At 8.00 pm, in desperation, I released the male back
into the aviary in an attempt to break the stalemate. He flew towards the
nest and perched about 2ft (0.6m) from it. As he watched the nest intently,
I tossed in more waxworms so that they were clearly in view and placed
more crickets in the self-feeder (described earlier). The female suddenly
left the nest and began to feed, watched by the male; who joined her feeding
the chicks at 9.00pm.
July 1st. Everything was perfect, with both parents caring for the
chicks. Did the female, I wondered, need the support of the male or had the
temperature been too high for the comfort of the chicks. The food offered
in 12 feedings amounted to: 95 waxworms, 16 waxmoths, 145 crickets and
350 buffalo worms, a total of 606 insects.
July 2nd. The temperature climbed to 33 *C (91.4*F) and in the afternoon
both parents sat motionless near the nest, holding waxworms in their beaks
but not feeding them to the chicks for several hours. When the parents did
move, the chicks gaped and became active. I suspected that the male was
guarding the nest and preventing the female from feeding them. (I have
often seen competition over parental duties between the male and female
Pekin Robin.) During the past three days, a problem had developed with the
male's right eye and, as a result, he kept it closed most of the time and the
discomfort from this may have affected his behaviour. After I had removed
him from the aviary in order to treat his eye, the female resumed feeding
the chicks and I watched her removing the faecal sacs, indicating that the
chicks were feeding normally.
July 3rd &amp; July 4th. The female fed the chicks regularly and sat near
the nest guarding it.
July 5th. The male was returned to the aviary. The chicks were
apprehensive to start with and ducked their heads when he made his first
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998979" page_id="56337120"  page_num="112" year="" vol="">
112
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.835465" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337120" page_num="112" year="" vol="">
KARSTEN - EUROPEAN ROBIN
</sectionHeader>
<author confidence="0.366197">
Peter Karsten
</author>
<bodyText confidence="0.997630818181818" page_id="56337120"  page_num="112" year="" vol="">
Sitting guarding the nest box.
three or four approaches, but soon gaped and eagerly took food from him.
To my surprise, the female had, by noon, started to build a new nest in
another box. She did though continue to participate in the feeding of the
chicks and the pair continued to work together harmoniously throughout
the following day.
July 7th. The new nest was completed and the chicks, who were now
defecating over the rim of the nest and doing a lot of preening, were being
fed mostly by the male.
July 8th. Two of the chicks fledged at 5.00pm.
July 9th. The remaining chicks had fledged by 7.30am and were hiding
in various parts of the aviary, near or on the ground. Food offered in eight
feedings amounted to: 100 waxworms, 10 waxmoths, 105 crickets and 350
buffalo worms, a total of 565 insects. The first egg was seen in the new
nest.
July 11th. The young were widely dispersed throughout the aviary. For
the first time the male was seen feeding mealworms to them. There were
three eggs in the new nest.
July 13th. The female had begun to incubate the latest clutch of eggs.
Food offered to the young and parents during eight feedings amounted to:
86 waxworms, 180 crickets and 150 buffalo worms, a total of 416 insects.
July 14th. The female was continuing to incubate the latest clutch of eggs
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.833296" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337121" page_num="113" year="" vol="">
KARSTEN - EUROPEAN ROBIN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999517" page_id="56337121"  page_num="113" year="" vol="">
113
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.960040365853658" page_id="56337121"  page_num="113" year="" vol="">
and was also occasionally feeding the young. The male had stopped feeding
them regularly and I became concerned that they might starve. I caught two
of the young and attempted to feed them by hand using a thin stick, but they
refused to take food from me. One youngster weighed 15. lg.
July 15th. The young were 20 days old and were seen picking up
waxworms from the ground. The female came off the nest for three to five
minutes and, together with the male, fed the young. Food offered to the
family during that day amounted to: 90-100 crickets (of %in (7mm) abdomen
length) in three feedings; 100-120 waxworms in four feedings; and 200-250
buffalo worms in a single feeding.
July 18th. The young were flying down to the ground to pick up
waxworms.
July 21st. The young were active and flying about. Their tail feathers
measured about %in (7mm) long. They appeared to be interested in listening
to the taped songs of European Robins.
July 24th. The young were independent of their parents and were moved
to an adjoining aviary. I found a mummified chick in the second nest, which
was presumably the missing sixth chick.
Third clutch
July 26th. The latest clutch of eggs hatched. The male fed the fledged
young at times and sang more today, but did not go near the nest.
July 27th. The female was feeding busily or standing over the nest
watching the chicks intently and from time to time shaking the nest and
removing foreign matter. The male was still not seen near the nest and by
the end of the day looked tired and listless. His eye problem persisted and
he was resting on his abdomen. His tail feathers were rough and untidy.
July 30th. As the juveniles had begun squabbling, I caught them and
moved them to separate enclosures. The male looked exhausted: his head
was slumped forward and resting on the ground. The female flew down and
sat near him for a moment, but then resumed feeding the latest brood.
July 31 st. The male was unable to fly up and had coordination problems,
also his eye was worse and he could no longer open it. He was moved to a
hospital cage and died on August 14th. He weighed 22.5g, which is above
the normal range. The post mortem examination gave no clue to the cause
of death and there was no obvious infection at the site of the right eye. His
age was unknown. The female continued to feed the chicks.
August 1 st. The young of the previous clutch were separated from each
other. Some of them, presumed to be males, began to sing very softly.
August 2nd-August 7th. The female continued to care for the chicks
herself. One jumped out of the nest, probably because of the amount of
noise I made placing boards on the aviary roof above the nest to provide
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999686" page_id="56337122"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
114
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.832593" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337122" page_num="114" year="" vol="">
KARSTEN - EUROPEAN ROBIN
</sectionHeader>
<author confidence="0.370722">
Peter Karsten
</author>
<bodyText confidence="0.956387833333333" page_id="56337122"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
Female depositing faecal sacs on perch.
extra shade. This chick - which weighed 10.5g - was unable to stand up
straight and fell over if it attempted to run. It developed diarrhoea and died
three days later.
August 8th &amp; August 9th. The four remaining chicks of clutch No.3
fledged. They looked healthy and dispersed around the aviary, scurrying
about like mice.
August 18th. The juveniles of clutch No.2 - now seven weeks old - were
showing the first orange feathers at the lower margin of the chest patch.
August 24th. They were all feeding themselves and rapidly acquiring
adult plumage. The adult female began to moult and lost all her tail
feathers.
September 1 st. The young of clutch No.2 - now almost nine weeks old
- had nearly completed their moult into adult plumage.
September 22nd. Found a dead young female from clutch No.2, that had
managed to slip through into the large enclosure occupied by male No. 1 with
the gout problem. She was wedged into a comer next to a rock and showed
severe trauma to the head. The injury was typical of the scalping attacks by
rival European Robins and noted among Pekin Robins as well.
October 7th. The birds of clutch No.3 - now 10 weeks old - had completed
their moult into adult plumage. The bodyweights of the 2006-hatched birds
of clutches Nos.2 &amp; 3 ranged from 14.5g-19.lg.
October 15th &amp; October 31st. Shipped two pairs of juveniles to
Winnipeg and Toronto.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.831991" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337123" page_num="115" year="" vol="">
KARSTEN - EUROPEAN ROBIN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99651" page_id="56337123"  page_num="115" year="" vol="">
115
</page>
<author confidence="0.571154">
Peter Karsten
</author>
<bodyText confidence="0.923526611111111" page_id="56337123"  page_num="115" year="" vol="">
Juvenile European Robin.
Summary
The author began 2006 with 2.1 European Robins. One pair was formed
that had three nests and produced three clutches of eggs. The first chicks
died, but the two following nests produced five and four young that were
reared to independence. The housing, feeding and step-by-step breeding
events are described and illustrated. The author has been breeding Pekin
Robins since 1999 and, to date, 80 offspring have been raised, some to
the third generation. Key contributors to success have been housing one
breeding pair per aviary, with dense cover, minimal disturbance, targeted
nest support, customized diet, on-site propagation of live insects for feeding
chick-rearing birds, and remote camera monitoring. European Robins are
highly spirited birds that are a delight to care for. They quickly find their
way into the heart of their keeper and clever ways to obtain food. However,
they tenaciously defend their territory and special attention needs to be paid
to this aspect of their management.
Detailed analysis of the softbill diet, relevant management practises and
the propagation and care of live insect cultures can be found in my book
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.7302745">
Pekin Robins and Small Softbills - Management and Breeding , reviewed in
the Avicultural Magazine Vol.l 13, No.4, pp. 182-183 (2007).
</reference>
<page confidence="0.997971" page_id="56337124"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
116
</page>
<figure confidence="0.380055666666667" page_id="56337124"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
KARST Erl * EUROPEAN ROBIN
Appendix
Diet
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.980744833333333" page_id="56337124"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
It has three components (besides a supply of live insects, a vitamin/
mineral supplement and clean drinking water): 1) dry mix; 2) egg cake;
3) moistening agents. The dry mix is prepared in batches for freezing or
refrigeration, by mixing it with finely chopped egg cake (see recipes below),
grated carrot, apple, cottage cheese and hard-boiled egg, to obtain a moist,
crumbly texture.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.977285428571429" page_id="56337124"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
Dry mix
20 parts Proprietary so fib ill pellets (18% protein)
20 &amp;quot; Kitten chow or puppy chow (28% - 32% protein)
5 &amp;quot; Oatmeal
4 &amp;quot; Mueseli grapenut breakfast cereal
4 &amp;quot; Poultry layer pellets (18% protein)
2 &amp;quot; Sunflower seeds
2 &amp;quot; Powdered whey
1 part Powdered yeast
1 &amp;quot; Hazel nuts
1 &amp;quot; Flax seed
1 &amp;quot; Bee pollen
1 &amp;quot; Wheat bran
1 &amp;quot; Wheat germ
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.963644666666667" page_id="56337124"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
The coarse ingredients should be finely ground (e.g. in a coffee grinder).
The egg cake is finely diced and dusted with a vitamin/mineral supplement
and mixed with the dry mix in equal proportions.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.992468230769231" page_id="56337124"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
Egg cake
1 % cups
Margarine
11 |
Sugar
m &amp;quot;
Wholewheat flour
3 A cup
Soya proteie/flour (from health food store)
% &amp;quot;
Gluten
1 Vz teaspoons baking powder
1 tablespoon lemon juice
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.602642" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337124" page_num="116" year="" vol="">
6 Eggs
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.481797" page_id="56337124"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
Cream margarine and add sugar. Beat together until very fluffy and light
(this is important). Then add eggs one at a time, beating well after each egg
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.833303" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337125" page_num="117" year="" vol="">
KARSTEN - EUROPEAN ROBIN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999128" page_id="56337125"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
117
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.7253645625" page_id="56337125"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
is added. Add dry ingredients, mix and divide batter between four loaf pans
(about 3!4in x Tin x 214in high (8.5cm x 18cm x 6cm high)) or two larger
ones, lined with wax paper. Bake for 50 minutes (or until done) in an oven
preheated to 350*F (141*C). Remove from oven and leave in pans for about
10 minutes. Then remove from pans and place on racks to cool. Do not
remove wax paper. Once cool they can be used to feed the birds or placed
in a freezer for future use. The loaf currently in use is kept in a refrigerator
in a plastic bag to help retain moisture.
Finely crushed eggshell is always available in a separate dish.
Bibliography
Giebig, M. Das Rotkehlchen. Verband Deutscher Waldvogelpfleger und Vogelzuechter.
Friedrich, U. and Volland, W. 1990. Futtertierzucht: Lebendfutter fiir Vivarientiere. Verlag
Eugen Ulmer, Stuttgart.
Heinzel, H., Fitter, R., Parslow, J. 1972. Birds of Britain and Europe with North Africa and
the Middle East. Harper Collins Publishers, London.
Karsten, P. 2002. Pekin Robins: Information on Care and Breeding. AFA Watchbird 29,2:56-
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.628069" page_id="56337125"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
68 .
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.46786" page_id="56337125"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
Karsten, P. 2007. Pekin Robins and Small Softbills - Management and Breeding. Hancock
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.894963846153846" page_id="56337125"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
House Publishers Ltd., Surrey, B.C., Canada.
Peter Karsten was born in Germany and, following the completion of his
formal education in Germany and Sweden, emigrated to Canada in 1962.
After a 30 year career at Calgary Zoo, for 20 years of which he held the
position of Zoo Director and Executive Director, he retired in 1994 to the
Gulf Islands of British Columbia, where he breeds Pekin Robins, European
Robins and other small softbills. He can be contacted at: 5741 Stanehill
Place, Denman Island, B.C., VOR ITO. E-mail:silvpine@island.net
* *
*
ST VINCENT PARROT CHICK
Houston Zoo in Texas, which has a long history of keeping and breeding
the St Vincent Parrot Amazona guildingii (I saw them there in the early
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.9777776" page_id="56337125"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
1970s), has this year raised a female chick. It hatched earlier in the year,
after an incubation period of 25 days, and was hand-reared by Chris Holmes,
the zoo's Bird Department Supervisor. For the first 28 days the chick was
fed every two hours from 5.00am to midnight. It was taken home by Chris
each evening in a specially made climate-controlled carrier and returned to
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999211" page_id="56337126"  page_num="118" year="" vol="">
118
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.987668" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337126" page_num="118" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE BROWN-BREASTED BARBET
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.94285" page_id="56337126"  page_num="118" year="" vol="">
Lyhius melanopterus AT WADDESDON MANOR
by Ian Edmans and Andrew Owen
The Brown-breasted Barbet is a distinctive African barbet found in
Somalia, Kenya, Tanzania, Malawi and Mozambique. It is found in forest
edges, remnant forest patches, tree cultivation and in tall trees in towns and
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.8897045" page_id="56337126"  page_num="118" year="" vol="">
Ian Edmans
Adult male Brown-breasted Barbet feeding female.
Andrew Owen
Adult female with one recently fledged youngster (right).
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.445215" page_id="56337127"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
EDMANS &amp; OWENS - BROWN-BREASTED BARBET
</equation>
<page confidence="0.993625" page_id="56337127"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
119
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.30043">
Andrew Owen
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.977127125" page_id="56337127"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
Recently fledged young Brown-breasted Barbet.
villages, occurring regularly up to an altitude of 600m (approx. 1,968ft) and
unusually up to 1,700m (approx. 5,576ft) in Tanzania and Malawi. It is
usually uncommon and local (Short &amp; Home, 2001).
It is a medium-sized barbet, approximately 16cm (6V4\n) in length.
Adults have a bright red head, cheeks and throat. From the rear of the crown
and behind the eyes to the nape and shoulders, the red is flecked with dark
brown. The chest and back are brown diffused with grey or white feathers
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.834549" page_id="56337128"  page_num="120" year="" vol="">
120
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.286479" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337128" page_num="120" year="" vol="">
EDMANS &amp; OWENS - BROWN-BREASTED BARBET
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.589182">
Ian Edmans
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985444866666667" page_id="56337128"  page_num="120" year="" vol="">
Adult Brown-breasted Barbet emerging from nest hole.
and the wings, tail, thighs and lower flanks are dark brown. The belly and
vent are white and there is brown and white feathering on the lower back.
The bill is coloured greyish-horn, the eyes are reddish-brown and the legs
and feet are dark grey.
In the wild it is primarily a fmgivorous species, feeding on figs, berries
and other fruits, that also hawks for insects such as bees and wasps. It is
a social species, breeding and foraging in extended family groups of up to
six or seven birds.
A pair of Brown-breasted Barbets arrived at Waddesdon in September
2007 and following a 30-day quarantine period the pair was moved to one
of the on-show aviaries. This measures approximately 5m long x 5m wide
x 7m high (16ft long x 16ft wide x 23ft high), with the roof half covered and
the birds having access to a heated indoor shelter. The aviary is furnished
with natural perches and planted with several shrubs and bushes, including
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.44924" page_id="56337129"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
EDMANS &amp; OWENS - BROWN-BREASTED BARBET
</equation>
<page confidence="0.994648" page_id="56337129"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
121
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999501048780488" page_id="56337129"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
box and bamboo. The floor has a covering of wood chips, mulch and mix
and leaf litter and there is a small pool in the centre of the aviary; however,
the barbets have never been seen to drink from this or bathe in it. They
share the aviary and shelter with a pair of Snowy-crowned Robin Chats
Cossypha niveicapilla , Emerald Starlings Lamprotornis iris and Purple-
crested Turacos Tauraco porphyreolophus . They receive a diet of diced
fruit, an insectivorous mix, T16 low iron pellets and a variety of insects.
Fruit though appears to form the bulk of the barbet's diet.
Three large, dead Elm tree Ulmus sp. logs, that were found in nearby
woodland were placed at various heights to encourage natural nesting
behaviour. The barbets also had access to a nest box for roosting, but preferred
to spend the winter months in the heated shelter. Having made initial attempts
to excavate holes in two of the logs, the pair almost immediately turned its
attention to the third log. This measures 2m (approx.6ft 6in) high and 25cm
(approx. 1 Oin) in diameter. It leans at an angle of approximately 40 degrees
and is on top of a second log, which raises it to about 2.4m (8ft) above the
ground. The entrance to the nest cavity that the pair excavated is 5cm (2in)
in diameter and 2.1m (approx.7ft) above the ground. The depth of the nest
chamber is not known, nor the exact dates the eggs were laid or exactly when
the chicks hatched. Colin Scott, who also keeps this species and attempted
unsuccessfully to hand-rear a chick, recorded an incubation period of 16
days. We believe that our chicks hatched about May 12th and that only the
female carried out the incubation and brooding duties. About four weeks
before the chicks fledged, the female stopped brooding them and assisted the
male feeding them. At the time the chicks could be heard in the nest.
Throughout the period a variety of livefood was provided including at
first, small mealworms Tenebrio molitor and small 'home-grown' waxmoth
larvae Galleria mellonella , and later soft-bodied mealworms that had
recently shed their skins. Just prior to the chicks fledging regular-sized
mealworms and Black Crickets Gryllus bimaculatus were introduced. Both
parents were observed masticating fruit and carrying it to the nest in their
closed bills. In addition to fruit and insects, T16 low iron pellets were also
regularly fed to the chicks.
The two chicks were first seen looking out of the nest hole two days prior
to fledging. The first chick fledged on June 22nd, followed by the second
chick a day later. Both chicks continued to return to the nest for periods of
time during the day and, occasionally, returned to the nest for the entire day.
It is thought that all four barbets roosted together at night in the nest log.
The young barbets were slightly smaller than the adults and had shorter,
broader bills, and the face and head were pale orange, rather than bright red.
Both parents continued to feed them for some time after July 3rd, 12 days
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994828" page_id="56337130"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
122
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.483101" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337130" page_num="122" year="" vol="">
EDMANS &amp; OWENS - BROWN-BREASTED BARBET
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970789866666667" page_id="56337130"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
after fledging, when both juveniles were observed following their parents
to the food dish and were seen to feed themselves. Within a few days of the
juveniles having fledged, the adults began further work on the nest chamber.
A second clutch, consisting of a further two chicks, was reared and the young
of the first clutch was observed carrying food into the nest log and feeding
the young when they had fledged.
The management of this and our other species of African barbets
appears to be quite straightforward. We have also been successful breeding
the Bearded Barbet L. dubius and the Spot-flanked Barbet Tricholaema
lacrymosa using the same techniques. There are a few other aviculturists in
the UK keeping the Brown-breasted Barbet and we hope that they will also
be successful with this species, so that we can attempt to establish a viable
captive-breeding population.
Products mentioned in the text
Nutribird T16 low iron pellets: Versele-Laga NV, Kapellestraat 70, B-9800, Deinze,
Belgium.
Reference
Short, L. L. and Horne, J. F. M. 2001. Toucans, Barbets and Honey guides. Oxford University
Press, Oxford &amp; New York.
As described above, the Brown-breasted Barbet Lybius melanopterus,
has been bred at Waddesdon Manor aviaries. This is probably the first
successful breeding of this species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who
knows of a previous breeding is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
Waddesdon Manor (website:www. waddesdon. org. uk), near Aylesbury,
Buckinghamshire HP 18 OJH, was built (1874-1889) by Baron Ferdinand
de Rothschild. On a hilltop overlooking Aylesbury Vale, it has one of the
finest Victoria gardens in the UK, at the heart of which are the aviaries. Mr
James de Rothschild bequested Waddesdon to the National Trust in 1957
and, a family charitable trust, under the chairmanship of Lord Rothschild,
now manages it.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9605115" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337131" page_num="123" year="" vol="">
GOOSANDER X EIDER HYBRIDS AT
WWT MARTIN MERE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998972" page_id="56337131"  page_num="123" year="" vol="">
123
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.984459533333333" page_id="56337131"  page_num="123" year="" vol="">
by J. Meldrum and P. J. Wisniewski
The Eurasian Goosander Mergus m. merganser and European Eider
Somateria m. mollissima have been maintained in the same exhibit for a
period in excess of 23 years at WWT (Wildfowl &amp; Wetlands Trust) Martin
Mere, Burscough, Lancashire, and are commonly kept together at other
WWT centres. At WWT Martin Mere they have shared their exhibit with
a number of waterfowl species during this period but currently cohabit
with Greater Flamingos Phoenicopterus roseus and Canvasbacks Aythya
valisineria. The undesirable production of hybrids has never previously
been an issue with goosanders and eiders and has never previously been
recorded in WWT collections (Brown, M. pers. comm.). Neither Johnsgard
(1965) or Rutgers and Norris (1979) mentioned this hybrid though the former
noted hybrids between goosander and Hooded Merganser Lophodytes
cucullatus.
Goosander x Eider ducklings.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998874" page_id="56337132"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
124
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.875800333333333" page_id="56337132"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
MELDRUM &amp; WISNIEWSKI - GOOSANDER X EIDER HYBRIDS
Three older Goosander x Eider ducklings with two juvenile European Goldeneyes.
Male specimens observed in the wild in Europe, one of which appeared
to be a drake eider crossed with a female goosander, were documented
by Gillham and Gillham (1996) and Gillham and Gillham (2002). The
following hybrids were also noted:
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.96257725" page_id="56337132"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
Eurasian Goosander x Common Shelduck Tadorna tadorna
Eurasian Goosander x Smew Megellus alhellus
Eurasian Goosander x Redhead A. americana
European Eider x Shelduck
European Eider x Mallard Anas platyrhynchos
European Eider x King Eider S. spectabilis
European Eider x Steller's Eider Polysticta stelleri
During 2005 two clutches of Eurasian Goosander drake x European
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.959600222222222" page_id="56337132"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
Eider duck hybrids were produced. The first clutch was laid next to a ditch,
under conifers and comprised three eggs of which two proved fertile. The
second clutch was laid in a clump of Pampas Grass Cortaderia selloana and
comprised four fertile eggs. Subsequently one of these became addled and
a second chick was dead in the shell.
The first clutch, which hatched on June 2nd 2005, consisted of 1.1 and
the second clutch, which hatched on June 24th 2005, consisted of 0.2. The
clutches were laid three weeks apart so there is a possiblity that both clutches
were laid by the same European Eider duck.
</bodyText>
<copyright confidence="0.270111">
MELDRUM &amp; WISNIEWSKI - GOOSANDER X EIDER HYBRIDS
</copyright>
<page confidence="0.994308" page_id="56337133"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
125
</page>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.268889">
Appearance
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985952055555555" page_id="56337133"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
The ducklings, not surprisingly, had characteristics of both the Eurasian
Goosander and European Eider, The newly-hatched 'gooders' were of
similar size and shape to eiders. The down was dark brown on the back and
sides, though not quite as dark as that of an eider duckling but with white
down on the belly and with a white mark on the left- and right-hand side of
the back (characteristic of a goosander). The bill resembled the sawbill of
a goosander duckling.
As fully-grown juveniles the 'gooders' developed the bulk of an eider
combined with the length of a goosander, the overall appearance being more
sawbill-like. The male was factionally larger and heavier than the female
but due to its coloration gave the appearance of being noticeably bigger (see
Table 1). Both sexes were predominantly brown with darker wing-tips, a
white speculum divided by a black line, a brownish head and a mottled
grey, brown and white chest and belly. The bill was blue-grey and the legs
and feet were yellowish. Prior to moulting into adult plumage, the drake
developed a white chest band, faint black and white vermiculations to the
flanks and a mottled brown and white belly.
Juvenile Goosander x Eider hybrids.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998061" page_id="56337134"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
126
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.556849">
MELDRUM &amp; WISNIEWSKI - GOOSANDER X EIDER HYBRIDS
Drake and three females in adult plumage.
Table 1. Biometrics of 2005 (adult) hybrids.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.971816041666667" page_id="56337134"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
Weight
Wing
Skull
Tarsus
Male
1.60kg
295mm
124.9mm
54.0mm
Female 1
1.45kg
290mm
116.5mm
54.1mm
Female 2
1.55kg
286mm
118.9mm
50.2mm
Female 3
1.55kg
302mm
122.0mm
54.0mm
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.998726666666667" page_id="56337134"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
As adults the females remained similar in coloration but developed a
paler, mottled chest and neck and more chestnut coloured head with a paler
wash between the eye and base of the bill, while the leg coloration intensified
to a brighter orange and the bill to flesh pink. The white speculum divided
by a broad black band became more obvious.
In contrast, the drake had a white head, neck and chest with the white
continuing onto the back and wings. Above the eye was a kidney-shaped
black smudge and a diffuse yellow-brown patch was present between the
eye and the base of the bill and behind the cheek. A thin black collar was
present. The flanks had black and white vermiculations, the tertials were
white edged with black, the wing-tips were black and the vent and tail were
grey. The bill turned to a horn-colour and then grey near the tip. The legs
</bodyText>
<copyright confidence="0.231107">
MELDRUM &amp; WISNIEWSKI - GOOSANDER X EIDER HYBRIDS
</copyright>
<page confidence="0.841733" page_id="56337135"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
127
</page>
<equation confidence="0.669177" page_id="56337135"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
&apos; \0x25A0 &apos; \0x25A0 - \0x25A0
1
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.996102" page_id="56337135"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
A closer view of the drake.
and feet were orange.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.407431">
Vocalisations
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9769188" page_id="56337135"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
As juveniles they produced mostly eider-like calls similar to the "po-po-
po" calls of the eider duck.
Behaviour
This was considerably more eider-like. Ducklings huddled together
like eider ducklings as opposed to frantically running about in different
directions, behaviour more characteristic of goosander ducklings. The
ducklings of clutch No.l were reared with two European Goldeneye
Bucephala clangula and one Hooded Merganser duckling, whilst those
of clutch No.2 were reared with three European Eider ducklings. All
mixed together well with no obvious dominance heirarchy or aggression.
Interestingly, when the two clutches were put together (at seven weeks and
four weeks respectively) with juvenile European Goldeneyes, European
Eiders, Smew and Hooded Mergansers, the four 'gooders' immediately
grouped together and continued to keep themselves to themselves, never
bullying or being bullied by any other species.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997377" page_id="56337136"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
128
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9602088" page_id="56337136"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
MELDRUM &amp; WISNIEWSKI - GOOSANDER X EIDER HYBRIDS
A final twist
Despite the fact that no goosander x eider hybrids had previously been
reported at WWT centres, 2005 for reasons which will remain a mystery,
proved a bumper year for such hybrids. At WWT Slimbridge and WWT
Llanelli similar hybrid pairings occurred. In 2006 another clutch of eggs
was laid in Pampas Grass at WWT Martin Mere. Of the five eggs one was
addled and the others were fertile and hatched on June 13th. In 2007 two
clutches were laid, the first, of three fertile eggs, in a nest under conifers
of which 2.0 ducklings hatched on May 24th and 0.1 on May 26th and the
second, of four eggs, of which two were clear and one was dead in the
shell. 0.1 hatched on June 18th. The first nest also contained a dumped
eider egg which hatched on May 24th. It is possible that all of the Martin
Mere hybrids originated from the same parents. Whether these birds will
themselves prove to be fertile remains to be seen.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.86946" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337136" page_num="128" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.901783888888889" page_id="56337136"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
Gillham, E. H. and Gillham, B. L. 1996. Hybrid ducks. A contribution towards an inventory.
Gillham, E. H. and Gillham, B. L. 2002. Hybrid ducks. The 5th contribution towards an
inventory.
Johnsgard, R A. 1965. Handbook of Waterfowl Behaviour. Constable &amp; Co. Ltd, London.
Rutgers, A. and Norris, K. A. Encyclopaedia of Aviculture. Vol.l. Blandford Press, Dorset.
Pat Wisniewski joined the WWT in 1983 and later became centre
manager at Martin Mere, a position he heldfor 16 years. Described as "one
of the greatest of the all-round naturalists ", he died in May 2008, just a few
weeks after submitting the above article co-authored with J. Meldrum.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.613879" page_id="56337136"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.972177" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56337136" page_num="128" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.901895" page_id="56337136"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
The society has a large stock of back issues mostly from 1935 onwards
but there are also some earlier issues still available. They are priced #3.00
each (including p&amp;p). Please check availability before placing an order.
Overseas members may be able to pay by credit card through a PayPal
invoice, but this service is not available in all countries. All enquiries
should be addressed to Paul Boulden, Hon. Secretary/Treasurer, Avicultural
Society, Arcadia, The Mounts, East Allington, Totnes, Devon TQ9 7JQ, UK
or E-mail:admin@avisoc.co.uk
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996467" page_id="56337137"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
129
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.801919" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337137" page_num="129" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE JAVAN MUNIA
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.399098545454545" page_id="56337137"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
Lonchura leucogastroides
by Neville Brickell
Introduction
There was confusion as to the correct identification of this species by
authors of avicultural works during the early years. It has been known by
a number of alternative names, such as Black-rumped Munia, Javanese
Mannikin and Javanese White-bellied Munia, all of which were acceptable.
Neville Brickell
Javan Munia.
Names such as Black-headed or Black-beaked Bronze Mannikin and Javan
Magpie Mannikin, however, were only likely to lead to confusion and were
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.9881815" page_id="56337137"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
best avoided. Kingston (1998) was of the opinion that confusion over the
identification of this munia in Australia, stems from the fact that there is
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994149" page_id="56337138"  page_num="130" year="" vol="">
130
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.785163" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337138" page_num="130" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - JAVAN MUNIA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.954199825" page_id="56337138"  page_num="130" year="" vol="">
variation in birds kept in Australian aviculture, probably attributable to
fertile hybrids having been produced by crossing it with other small south
Asian munias.
Description
Length 11 cm-11.5cm (dAin-d/Gn). Head, face and upper breast black
with a purplish sheen on adult birds in fresh plumage. Lower breast, belly
and flanks white, under tail-coverts dark brown to black. The upperparts are
medium brown and unstreaked, the rump is dark and the tail is dark brown to
blackish, with the central tail feathers graduated and slightly elongated at the
tip. The upper mandible is dark grey to blackish and the lower mandible is
pale greyish blue. The irises are dark brown and the legs and feet are grey.
Juveniles have paler brown upperparts and the belly and flanks are buff to
cream with some streaking.
The sexes look alike, however, Restall (1987) felt that the ridge of the
culmen where it meets the forehead was, on his adult birds, more pronounced
on the males than on the females. He also noticed a difference between the
markings on the flank feathers of first year males and females and provided
sketches illustrating these differences.
Voice
The male has a soft, pleasing purring or rattling song, whilst the contact
call consists of a " peteet " or " pee-ee-eet ." The call notes of the male and
female differ.
Distribution
Southern Sumatra, Java, Bali and Lombok (Indonesia). Strange (2002)
stated that it is a common resident on the islands of Java, Bali and Lombok,
that has expanded its range into southern Sumatra, either naturally or
possibly has been introduced there. Restall (1987) stated that it was
introduced to Singapore in 1922 and was considered the most abundant
munia in the region. Gibson-Hill (1949) was of the opinion that imported
birds occasionally escaped and formed small colonies, but these found it
difficult to maintain their numbers for any length of time. Ward (1968) stated
that it was an occasional visitor to Singapore and was unable to determine
whether these were escaped caged birds or had spread naturally.
Status
Common and widespread on southern Sumatra, Java, Bali and Lombok.
Strange (2002) described it as one of the most numerous birds in its range.
Habitat
Found in all kinds of open country, grasslands, cultivated fields and
gardens, from the beach up to 1,800m (approx. 5,900ft). It can be seen
in hotel gardens, parks and on golf courses, etc. Restall (1987) described
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.49544" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337139" page_num="131" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - JAVAN MUNIA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998591" page_id="56337139"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
131
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.972933675" page_id="56337139"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
watching one feeding among the plants growing in the window boxes at the
edge of the balcony of his first floor hotel room in Singapore.
Feeding
During the morning they spread out in loose flocks to feed on seeds
and insects and congregate in larger flocks at evening roosts in large trees,
according to Strange (2002) in his guide to the birds of Indonesia. In
Singapore they are said to feed in trees and shrubs in parkland and on the
seeding heads of both indigenous and exotic grasses, notably Bermuda Grass
Cynodon dactylon (which is found in most warmer regions of the world) and
Buffalo Grass Stenotaphrum secundatum. Restall observed them feeding in
a clump of Saccharum arundinaceum , a member of the sugar cane family.
They also visit paddy fields and are known as "rice ravagers" and local
children are encouraged to destroy their nests.
In captivity I feed them a good quality finch mixture consisting of red and
yellow panicum, Japanese millet and mixed canary seed. From waste ground
I gather Jungle Rice Echinochloa colona and the grasses, Rescue Bromus
unioloides, Guinea Panicum maximum and Johnson Sorghum halepense ,
the seeding heads of the last named needing to be crushed before they are
fed to the birds. Kingston (1998) in Australia suggested also Casuarina
Casuarina sp., lettuce and niger seed, and the seeding heads of grasses such
as Carpet Axonopus sp.. Purple Pigeon Setaria sp., Phalaris Phalaris sp. and
Rye Lodium sp. They generally show little or no interest in greenfood but
have shown a liking for Chickweed Stellaria media. Whilst Kingston was
in agreement that the Javan Munia does not generally accept supplementary
foods, Hargreaves (1999) in the UK regularly gave his birds a moist eggfood,
but reported that they showed little or no interest in livefood. In the southern
hemisphere, if livefood is offered, it is most likely to be termites.
Housing
My birds (each of which has a coded ring (band) on one leg) are housed
in a small colony in a bank of six cages, each section measuring 1m long x
0.7m wide x 0.8m high (approx. 3ft 3in long x 2ft 3in x 2ft 6in high) and
interlinked so that immature birds can, if required, be separated. Calvin
(1991) kept his birds in the basement of his home in the USA, housing
six pairs in a communal flight measuring 1.2m long x 0.6m wide x 0.9m
high (approx. 4ft long x 2ft wide x 3ft high), with greenery such as a small
banana plant, a weeping fig and miniature ornamental palms. Clumps of
dried grasses were provided as nesting sites. Johnson (2004) provided tins,
cane baskets, gourds and wire cylinders, whilst Kingston and I prefer half-
open-fronted finch nest boxes. The former also planted bamboos and tall
indigenous grasses.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998334" page_id="56337140"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
132
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.792168" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337140" page_num="132" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - JAVAN MUNIA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.984488695652174" page_id="56337140"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
Two adults and three juveniles.
Breeding
Sexing munias prior to pairing them can be a difficult undertaking, as
both sexes appear to look identical. In the past, determining which were
males and which were females, usually meant placing individual birds in
a cage on their own in which, with luck, a lone male would begin to sing.
If after a reasonable length of time, the bird did not sing, it was presumed
to be a female. This procedure often had to be repeated in order obtain
a satisfactory result. Today, surgical and DNA sexing, if one has access
to these procedures, can solve the uncertainty of the past, otherwise most
aviculturists have to continue to rely on the old methods. I have been
fortunate in having a slight advantage over most local aviculturists, as I have
been aware beforehand of the number of males and females I am likely to
have by the end of the breeding season. This became possibly by studying
the egg collection of the late Jack Scheepers (the man who discovered the
Lemon-breasted Canary Serinus citrinipectus in 1960) over many years and
learning to distinguish the differences between eggs from which male and
female chicks would hatch.
In the wild the Javan Munia nests in trees, bushes and shrubs. On Bali it
is said to prefer mostly ornamental varieties. It nests on epiphytes and palm
trees, either on the outer fronds, between the fronds or in the crown. The
nest is a large ball of grasses, fibres and other vegetation, with an entrance
at the side measuring about 7cm-8cm (2%in-3 %in) across. Goodwin (1982)
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.495455" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337141" page_num="133" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - JAVAN MUNIA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999367" page_id="56337141"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
133
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9985045" page_id="56337141"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
cited Hoogerwerf s observation that it breeds at all times of the year in west
Java, and those of Immelmann et al. that in the drier parts of east Java it
breeds only in the wet season. In Singapore it breeds from May-October.
It usually lays a clutch of five, or sometimes six or more, white eggs. These
measure 14mm x 10mm (Restall, 1987). The incubation period is 13 days
and the nestling period 18-21 days.
In the UK and Germany
Writing in 1987, Robin Restall observed that up until a few years before,
this species had been virtually unknown in UK aviculture. His birds came
from Indonesia in 1985 and the following year, when he visited the dealer
from whom he had obtained them, the dealer had a cage with seven or eight
from a customer who had bought two pairs that had produced 18 young. The
anonymous customer was very likely the first person in the UK to have bred
this species, followed shortly afterwards by Robin Restall. According to
Robin, finch shipments from Jakarta (Indonesia) went mostly to Germany,
where this munia was a free breeder.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.487241">
Hybrids
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9623535" page_id="56337141"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
In captivity hybrids have been recorded between the Javan Munia
and closely related species, such as the Bengalese L. striata dom., Indian
Silverbill L. ( Euodice) malabarica, Bib Finch or Madagascar Munia L.
nana and Red-backed Mannikin L. (Spermestes) bicolor ( nigriceps ).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.925074" genericHeader="references" page_id="56337141" page_num="133" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.947150941176471">
Brickell, N. 2005. Avicultural Guide - Finches &amp; Sparrows - Feeding &amp; Breeding in the
field. IBBRG, RSA.
Calvin, C. A. 1991. Breeding the Java Mannikin Lonchura leucogastroides. AFA Watchbird
18,1:4.
Gibson-Hill, C. A. 1949. Annotated checklist of the birds of Malayasia. Bull. Raffles mus.
No.20, pp. 1-299.
Goodwin, D. 1982. Estrildid finches of the world. British Museum (Natural History) &amp; Oxford
University Press, London &amp; Oxford.
Hargreaves, P. 1999. Breeding the Java Munia. The Estrildian 7,1:22-23.
Johnson, G. 2004. The Javan Munia. Australian Birdkeeper Issue 1, Vol.7, pp. 11-13.
Kingston, R. 1998. Keeping &amp; breeding Finches and seed-eaters. Indress Productions,
Queensland, Australia.
Restall. R. 1987. The Javan or Black-rumped Munia. Avicultural Magazine 93, 3, 130-135 .
Strange, M. 2002. A Photographic Guide to the Birds of Indonesia. Helm, London.
Ward, P. 1968. The origin of the avifauna of urban and suburban Singapore. Ibis 110,3:239-
254.
Neville Brickell, who lives in Durban, South Africa, has been keeping
</reference>
<bodyText confidence="0.77352525" page_id="56337141"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
birds for 56 years. He has kept a flock of Javan Munias for about eight
years and in 2004 won a best breeder awardfor having raised 38 fledglings.
Neville says, that because of restrictions, it is becoming increasingly difficult
to obtain new, unrelated birds, in South Africa.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999518" page_id="56337142"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
134
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9303725" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337142" page_num="134" year="" vol="">
HERBERT WHITLEY -
THE FOUNDER OF PAIGNTON ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.979197108108108" page_id="56337142"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
by Jo Gregson
Herbert Whitley moved to Devon in 1904. His father had died suddenly
at the age of 67 and left a small fortune from his brewery business, which
enabled Whitley's mother, Eleanor, to buy the Primley Estate in Paignton,
to which she moved from their home town of Liverpool with her daughter
and three sons.
Herbert and his brother William ran the estate and soon built up a
reputation for breeding quality livestock. Their South Devon cattle were
sold all over the world and their Devon Longwool sheep were sought after by
local farmers. There was also a fine stable of Shire horses, which worked in
the fields and were to be seen in the show ring under the Primley prefix.
Herbert had a passion for all living things, but above all he loved his
pigeons. He bred many varieties for the show bench, as well as for racing.
During wartime, his birds were used by the military to carry messages from
our troops overseas. He loved the colour blue and would always strive to
breed this colour into all of his livestock. For the Coronation in 1935, he bred
the first blue Light Sussex poultry. Herbert even cultivated a blue mallow
flower and named it the Primley Blue. The name Primley is derived from
the Anglo-Saxon words prim and ley meaning morning meadow.
After a few years, William moved up onto Dartmoor and left the running
of Primley solely to Herbert. In 1910, he bought his first exotic birds, a
pair of Sulphur-crested Cockatoos Cacatua galerita and from there the
collection grew until, in 1923, he opened Paignton Zoo. At the time a pair
of Black Swans Cygnus atratus cost #6 6s Od (approx.US$10 at the present
exchange rate). The zoo was to open and close twice during the following
14 years. Whitley had refused to pay entertainment tax on the grounds that
his collection was educational and not for entertainment purposes. He was
always keen for young people to learn and chose to close the zoo rather
than back down.
Whitley was very much in touch with other collectors of that time. Both
Delacour and Rothschild were great friends to him and he often sent material
to (Rothschild's) Tring Museum. During the 1930s, Seth-Smith, Curator
at London Zoo was charged #400 (approx. US$640 at the present exchange
rate) for a pair of Pigmy Hippopotamus Hexaprotodon liberiensis . A pair
of manakins (Pipridae) from Cleres cost a surprising #8 0s Od (approx.
US$12.80), while bird dealers were charging as little as #1 10s Od (approx.
US$1.75) for a pair of Red-billed Hombills Tockus erythrorhynchus.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.845659" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337143" page_num="135" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - HERBERT WHITLEY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998769" page_id="56337143"  page_num="135" year="" vol="">
135
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.990793195121951" page_id="56337143"  page_num="135" year="" vol="">
UK first breedings claimed by Whitley included: the Arabian Partridge
Alectoris melanocephala (1927), Pheasant Pigeon Otidiphaps nohilis
(1935), Black-naped Fruit Dove Ptilinopus melanospila (1932), Red Lory
Eos h. bornea (c.1939), Dusky Lory Pseudeos fuscata (c.1939), Fischer's
Lovebird Agapornis fischeri (1927), Blue throated Conure Pyrrhura
cruentata (1937) and Lilac-breasted Roller Coracias caudatus (1919).
When the Second World War broke out, Whitley was approached by Mr
Goddard, the owner of Chessington Zoo (just south of London), who feared
not only for the safety of his animals during bombing raids, but was also
afraid that the more dangerous animals might escape. He asked if Paignton
would take them until better times? Whitley agreed and took some of the
staff as well, one of whom was the famous elephant keeper, Alex Smith.
Alex gained notoriety later in life following his appearance with a young
elephant named Comet on the popular childrens' TV programme Blue
Peter. The elephant relieved herself in front of the TV cameras and then
pulled over Alex and left him lying in the rather large, steamy, pool on the
studio floor. To his embarrassment the event was captured on film and has
become one of live television's funniest moments and years later continues
to be shown on television.
Poor eyesight prevented Whitley from going to war and as a result he was
able to remain behind and care for his collection of animals, though sadly,
many of them had to be culled due to wartime food shortages.
There had always been kennels at Primley containing a few terriers,
setters, spaniels and collies, all of which were working dogs and were also
shown. Whitley's early show success was with Great Danes, in particular
Primley Prodigal, who became a champion in 1912. Many of his Great Danes
lived in the house - presumably to frighten off visiting salesmen. They were
also used to control the feral cat population. In 1928, Theo Marples judged
the greyhound Primley Sceptre the best of all breeds of the 9,466 entries
at that year's Crufts Dog Show. Oddly, Primley Sceptre was never shown
again and there appears to be no record of what happened to her. She may
have died from one of the many canine curses, for Whitley did not have the
luxury of our modem prophylactic measures and, as a result, many of his
dogs died of distemper.
He devised some home-made remedies for treating livestock, including
a mix of two thirds lard and one third gunpowder applied twice a day to re-
grow hair on broken knees. For ringworm he recommended one measure of
creosote mixed with seven measures of linseed oil applied daily. When he
became ill during 1909 the doctor treated him with strychnine. He was not
at all well the following day but went on to make a full recovery and repaid
the doctor's kindness by giving him a Great Dane puppy.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999381" page_id="56337144"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
136
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.961512" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337144" page_num="136" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - HERBERT WHITLEY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997825780487805" page_id="56337144"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
Herbert Whitley died on September 19th 1955 at the age of 69 and
was buried in the family grave at St Peters Church, Buckland in the Moor,
Dartmoor. (In place of the numerals, the churchyard clock face bears the
words, "My Dear Mother" which William Whitley had done as a memorial
to his mother). Herbert had never married and had no heirs, so following his
death, the Herbert Whitley Trust was formed to carry on many of his aims.
Over the years, he had built up the reputation of being a chain-smoking
recluse, who rarely slept. All of his buildings were designed with several
doors so that as someone came in through one door he could slip away quietly
through another. He used a rather colourful version of the English language
and never missed the opportunity to play a practical joke on someone. He
was though well respected by the local community and has certainly left an
impressive legacy for future generations.
In 1921, he bought the Slapton Ley and surrounding area in the South
Hamms of Devon to prevent its likely development. Slapton Ley is unusual
in comprising of two freshwater lakes not a stone's throw from the sea,
thus creating a very diverse habitat. The land is leased to the Field Studies
Council for a peppercorn rent of #1 (under US$2) per annum, but with
certain conditions, one of which is that no deck chairs or amusement arcades
are allowed on the beach. It has a Field Studies Centre where up to 3,000
students are taught each year.
Paignton Zoo was the first UK zoo to introduce its own education unit
whereby school groups can come and learn about animals first-hand. Today
it can boost of having the largest centre in any zoo in the UK. A student
scholarship is awarded annually by the Herbert Whitley Trust.
Whitley gifted two plots of land to local people. A playing field in the
St Michaels area of Paignton and a 14 acre (approx. 6 hectares) site nearby
for development as a sports centre. He was a passionate sportsman and, in
particular, a lover of rugby football.
The Primley woodland and meadow adjacent to his home, he bequeathed
to the people of Paignton. His house is now a home for the elderly and
the small country park is much used by local people as a place to exercise
their dogs. All in all he seems to have been rather a lonely man who cared
very much for others. Herbert Whitley will be remembered as an unusual
character and a great stockman.
Since the above article was written, Jo Gregson (e-mail: jo.gregson@
paigntonzoo.org.uk) has been promotedfrom Senior Head Keeper of Birds
to Curator of Birds at Paignton Zoo Environmental Park, Totnes Road,
Paignton, Devon TQ4 7EU ' UK. It is owned by The Whitley Wildlife
Conservation Trust, which also owns and runs the Living Coasts at Torquay
and Newquay Zoo in Cornwall.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.6460775" page_id="56337145"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
THE BLACK-AND-WHITE LAUGHINGTHRUSH
Garrulax bicolor
</figure>
<page confidence="0.99911" page_id="56337145"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
137
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.986852921052632" page_id="56337145"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
In the previous issue of the magazine Vol.l 14, No.2, pp.70-78 (2008),
Andrew Owen described the breeding of the Black-and-white Laughing-
thrush Garrulax bicolor at Waddesdon Manor aviaries. It is thought to be
the first breeding in the UK of this recently recognised species. Furthermore,
Andrew can find no record of it ever having been bred anywhere else in the
world, so thinks that it might even be a 'world first'!
A further three chicks were hand-reared at Waddesdon during the 2008
breeding season, during which a more successful and trouble free hand-
rearing diet was introduced. Papaya was no longer included in the diet,
instead it consisted solely of pinkie mice, pureed to a runny consistency
and first fed to the chicks 10 hours after they had hatched. Prior to this
they received only a small amount of electrolyte fluid every 1 Vi hours to
keep them hydrated.
The food was made courser as the chicks grew bigger and later they were
given pieces of pinkie mice. At seven to eight days, waxmoth larvae, crickets
and mealworms were added to the diet. The multivitamin supplement was
also omitted from the 2008 hand-rearing process.
As far as I can recall, I first saw the Black-and-white Laughingthrush
when the Avicultural Society visited Paultons Park in Hampshire in 2006,
when it was known as the Sumatran Laughingthrush and continued to
be treated as a subspecies of the White-crested species, i.e. Garrulax
leucolophus bicolor. However, Andrew said, our President Raymond
Sawyer, had told him that he had some 15-20 years ago. If anyone
remembered them, I thought it would be Nigel Hewston or perhaps Philip
Schofield or Dave Coles. Nigel said, he could certainly remember a pair
that lived for some time in an aviary in the walled garden as you come out
of the courtyard behind the Chestnut Lodge. The pair was the only ones he
had seen prior to seeing them at Waddesdon and Paultons Park in the last
couple of years. Nigel thought it had probably been in the 1980s, but could
not be more specific.
A few weeks ago I had out Vol.93, No.3 (1987) of the magazine and,
before putting it away, was flicking through the pages when I came upon
Philip Schofield's report of the President's Garden Party - 1987 (pp.177-
179) and there in the final paragraph was mention of the "White-crested Jay
Thrushes from Sumatra." It would seem to have been the first reference to
"/7/co/or" in the Avicultural Magazine and perhaps in UK aviculture. If you
have any knowledge of this laughingthrush having been kept or bred in the
past (or present), we would like to hear from you. -Ed.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998753" page_id="56337146"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
138
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.982892" genericHeader="method" page_id="56337146" page_num="138" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
BRED FOR THE FIRST TIME IN THE UK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99388915" page_id="56337146"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
Geoff Masson of Paultons Park in Hampshire is keen to trace anyone
who keeps the Grey Laughingthrush Garrulax maesi and, in particular, is
keen to find anyone with a spare male. The bird bred at Paultons Park a few
months ago is now feeding itself and at the time he wrote (October 8th) was
just beginning to moult. It is the first time this species from China, Vietnam
and Laos has been bred in the UK. Geoff had the bird DNA sexed and it is
a female. Paulton Park's three Grey Laughingthrushes appear to be the only
examples of this species in the UK. Geoff has made contact with a breeder
in Europe who has a single bird and hopes it will prove to be a male and the
breeder will be prepared to exchange it for some other species he requires.
He thinks he knows of another pair in a private collection in Europe and an
attempt is being made to contact this other owner with the view to planning
for the future of this laughingthrush in Europe.
The pair at Paultons Park laid a second clutch and hatched, it is believed,
at least one chick. Unfortunately this occurred on the weekend that Geoff
was on the society's visit to Berlin and he returned to find that it had been
lost - probably due to the weather. If, as hoped, the pair nest again next year,
Geoff plans to remove the eggs or perhaps remove the chicks and attempt
to hand-rear them. If you know of any other Grey Laughingthrushes, Geoff
can be contacted by telephone:023 8081 4442 or e-mail:Geoff@paultons.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.8890245" page_id="56337146"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
co.uk
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.948317" genericHeader="method" page_id="56337146" page_num="138" year="" vol="">
SUCCESS FOR VICE PRESIDENT
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.557603">
Avicultural Society Vice President Robin Restall, who lives in Caracas,
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995122692307692" page_id="56337146"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
Venezuela, is very happy that this year he has finally succeeded in breeding
the Sooty Grassquit Tiaris fuliginosa. The successful pair, housed this time
in Robin's aviary, built a fine, covered nest with a half-open front. (Robin
described his earlier frustrating and unsuccessful attempts to breed this
grassquit in the Avicultural Magazine Vol. Ill, No.2, pp.64-74 (2005).) At
the time Robin wrote (October) a pair of Blue-black Grassquits Volatinia
jacarina was raising its fourth brood in the same nest. A pair of Lesser or
Chestnut-bellied Seed-Finches Oryzohorus angolensis had finally bred, only
for the chicks to be thrown out and dumped in the mealworm bowl. This
had left the female looking unhappy, while the male - who Robin suspected
of having done the 'dirty deed' - was bouncing around and singing all the
time. Unfortunately, Robin found the chicks too late to attempt to hand-
rear them.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700169" genericHeader="method" page_id="56337147" page_num="139" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999101" page_id="56337147"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
139
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997946555555555" page_id="56337147"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
A pair of Saffron Finches Sicalis flaveola in interim or intermediate
plumage caught by a neighbour in his garden, who really wanted an old male
for its song, was given to Robin and within a week had two eggs in one of
his spare breeding cages. Two Spectacled or Bare-eyed Thrush nestlings
Turdus nudigenis were brought to Robin by the gardener at the end of June
and later two fledglings were brought to him. The smaller of the nestlings
had a broken leg and died, but the other three birds were reared and are the
subject of some notes by Robin, which will be published in a future issue
of the magazine.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.9221425" page_id="56337147"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
* *
*
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.884336" genericHeader="method" page_id="56337147" page_num="139" year="" vol="">
AFTER A POOR START
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.914269117647059" page_id="56337147"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Society Vice President, Mike Curzon MBE, reports that
after a poor start to the breeding season, results began to improve later in the
year. By early September he had bred a Chestnut-backed Thrush Zoothera
dohertyi , had three more Spot-flanked Barbets Tricholaema lacrymosa
in the nest and had bred two Black-throated Barbets T. melanocephala -
though sadly these were killed after they fledged. Mike has two breeding
pairs of Emerald Doves Chalcophaps indica which, by early September,
had produced 14 young and there were a further two aged one week old on
the nest, plus another two eggs. He had bred two Common Bronzewings
Phaps chalcoptera and had another one on the nest, had bred a Sulawesi
Ground Dove Gallicolumba tristigmata and a Superb Fruit Dove Ptilinopus
superbus , with another one on the nest. Following an earlier loss, the pair
of Rose-crowned Fruit Doves P. regina was sitting on another egg. Two
Black-naped Fruit Doves P. melanospila had been raised and there was
another on the nest. Mike has, so far, had no luck with his Beautiful Fruit
Doves P. pulchellus or his Coroneted Fruit Doves P. coronulatus , but hopes
they will breed next year.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.6959625" page_id="56337147"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
* *
*
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.783001" genericHeader="method" page_id="56337147" page_num="139" year="" vol="">
CHOICE SPECIES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.976568714285714" page_id="56337147"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
Earlier this year, Josef and Natalie Lindholm - who work at The Dallas
World Aquarium, where Josef is Senior Aviculturist - spent 13 days in
Germany, during which time they visited nine zoological collections.
They began at Frankfurt. The zoo does not have an especially large bird
collection (101 species at the time of their visit), but boasts some choice
species. At the top of the list I would place the Grey-necked Picathartes
Picathartes oreas. Hatched at the zoo in 1984, it is the last remaining
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995166" page_id="56337148"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
140
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.926077" genericHeader="method" page_id="56337148" page_num="140" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.851116066666667" page_id="56337148"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
picathartes in captivity (Chris Brack's 1994 colour photo of this bird was
reproduced in Vol.l 10, No.2, p.94 (2004)). Having previously bred the
White-necked species P. gymnocephalus, Frankfurt first bred the Grey-
necked Picathartes in 1971 and is the only zoo ever to have bred this species.
Another remarkable achievement by Frankfurt is to have kept and bred the
Brown-throated Wattle-eye Platysteira cyanea for a number of years.
Among other species in the Bird House that caught their eye were a
Shoebill Balaeniceps rex , a breeding group of Australasian Pied Herons
Egretta picata , Little Pied Cormorants Phalacrocorax melanoleucus,
(wild) Budgerigars Melopsittacus undulatus. Blue-winged Kookaburras
Dacelo leachii , African Pygmy Kingfishers Ispidina picta , Polillo Tarictic
Hombills Penelopides pcmini subnigra, Kikuyu White-eyes Zosterops
poliogaster kikuyuensis, Painted Finches Emblema pictum and Cuban
Finches (Grassquits) Tiaris canora. They saw a number of species which
are managed as part of European zoo breeding programmes, including the
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.94203875" page_id="56337148"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
Bali Starling Leucopsar rothschildi , Montserrat Oriole Icterus oberi and
Socorro Dove Zenaida graysoni , the dove a species for which the European
Association of Zoos and Aquaria (EAZA) studbook is maintained by
Frankfurt's Curator of Birds, Stefan Stadler.
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.988661" page_id="56337148"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
Frankfurt has been breeding Red-whiskered Bulbuls Pycnonotus jocosus
almost continually since 1964, and they saw a flock of 40 or so in the free-
flight hall. Most of the 100 or more that have been bred there have been
distributed among European zoos. Apparently the Red-whiskered Bulbul,
which was once common in US zoos, is currently exhibited only at Honolulu
Zoo - this species lives in the wild on the island of Oahu, having been
introduced onto Hawaii in the mid-1960s.
In Frankfurt's Grzimekhaus, they saw a colony of Social Weavers
Philetairus socius , whose enormous compound nest dominates the exhibit
the colony share with ground squirrels Xenus sp. Several generations of
Social Weavers have been bred there since 1980 and, it is, as Josef said,
like Frankfurt's breeding of the Red-whiskered Bulbul, another remarkable
example of the long-term captive breeding of a species of passerine.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.61976" page_id="56337148"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990699" genericHeader="method" page_id="56337148" page_num="140" year="" vol="">
SPREADING ALONG THE RHINE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9982866" page_id="56337148"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
Josef and Natalie were surprised to see feral Ring-necked Parakeets
Psittacula krameri flying free in Cologne Zoo and felt that they enhanced
the generally park-like atmosphere of the zoo. It seems that this introduced-
cum-escaped parakeet is now breeding in parts of Germany (as it is in parts of
the UK) and is spreading steadily in increasing numbers along the Rhine.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990848" genericHeader="method" page_id="56337148" page_num="140" year="" vol="">
HELP FOR THE PARROTS OF HALMAHERA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999274" page_id="56337149"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
141
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.956827875" page_id="56337149"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
David Waugh of Loro Parque Fundacion reports that Burung (BirdLife)
Indonesia has initiated a project to protect the 167,300 hectares (approx.
413,398 acres) Aketajawe-Lolobata National Park, and thereby protect
several species of parrot found on the Indonesian island of Halmahera, North
Maluku (the Northern Moluccas). Funding for the project is being provided
by Loro Parque Fundacion (LPF) of Spain, the Zoological Society for the
Conservation of Species and Populations (ZGAP) and the Association for
the Conservation of Threatened Parrots (ACTP), both of Germany, and the
Global Environment Facility (GEF).
Halmahera is home to nine species of parrot, two of which - the White (or
Umbrella) Cockatoo Cacatua alba and Chattering Lory Lorius g. garrulus
- are of most concern. These two species are endemic to North Maluku,
with the largest populations occurring on Halmahera. The other species
are the Red-flanked Lorikeet Charmosyna placentis , Violet-necked Lory
Eos squamata, Moluccan Hanging Parrot Loriculus amabilis, Moluccan
(or Amboina) King Parrot Alisterus amboinensis , Red-cheeked Parrot
Geoffroyus geoffroyi , Eclectus Parrot Eclectus roratus and Great-billed
Parrot Tanygnathus megalorhynchos .
The clearance and fragmentation of the island's forests have accelerated
rapidly since the early 1990s and, as well as being threatened by habitat loss,
Halmahera's parrots continue to be under severe pressure from trapping
to supply both the domestic and international cage bird trade. It was as a
result of this that, from 1994-1999, the then BirdLife International Indonesia
Programme collaborated with the Indonesian Directorate General of Nature
Protection and Conservation on a project, also financially supported by the
LPF, to identify priority areas for parrot and biodiversity conservation on
Halmahera. This led to the declaration of Aketajawe-Lolobata National
Park in 2004.
However, the park had very weak management and few resources and
illegal logging and bird trapping continued. The current project aims to
set up an effectively managed protected area that will secure the long-term
future of the White Cockatoo, Chattering Lory and other threatened species
and their habitat. During the first period of this project it is important for
Burung Indonesia to establish a good working relationship with officials
of Aketajawe-Lolobata National Park and the Temate Natural Resources
Conservation Division. It is also important that it monitors the current
wildlife trade in North Maluku. Despite the fact that there have been no
domestic or export quotas for parrot species since 1999, trade has continued
and parrot trapping and trading locations, along with exit points, have been
identified.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998811" page_id="56337150"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
142
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996804" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337150" page_num="142" year="" vol="">
MEMORIES OF DEREK GOODWIN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993420052631579" page_id="56337150"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
by John F. Burton
I was first introduced to Derek by the late Dr Denis F. Owen in the Bird
Room of the Natural History Museum in South Kensington in August 1948
when I began work as a Scientific Assistant in the museum's Department of
Entomology. I found Derek very friendly and eager to convey his immense
enthusiasm for bird behaviour, especially that of corvids, pigeons and
Phasianidae, of which he was most knowledgable. We sometimes lunched
together in the museum's restaurant or that of the Victoria and Albert
Museum or in a local pub called The Hoop and Toy. On these occasions
Derek talked almost nonstop about birds, particularly their behaviour, and
was often so preoccupied that I feared for his life and limb when we crossed
such busy thoroughfares as Cromwell Road.
In the early 1950s Derek was living at Virginia Water and occasionally
invited me to his home to see the Lanceolated and European Jays and other
corvids, Barbary Doves and gamebirds housed in his aviaries. The late Dr
K. E. L. (Ken) Simmons was sometimes present and then our conversation
usually concentrated on the Great Crested Grebe. A particular memory of
Derek's home-cooked lunches was that the dessert invariably consisted of
a Lyon's fruit pie beside which nestled two Yeast-vite tablets. Derek had
a great fondness for salt and I noticed that he usually sprinkled it liberally
on his food. Once when he visited my home, my mother was astonished
when he sprinkled salt over slices of bread and jam. In a letter written in
2002, answering a letter in which I had mentioned that I had read that a low
salt diet is believed by some experts to lessen the incidence of Meniere's
disease, from which Derek had suffered, he scoffed at the idea and said he
was continuing to eat salt, as he had done since the age of four, with "bread
and butter, ice cream, cakes, bananas, etc., as well as with meat and potatoes,
etc." Fortunately in his case, the disease had become less and less severe
from the early 1990s and was hardly troubling him, apart from the fear that
it might return. When it started it caused 60% hearing loss in his left ear,
but had not affected his right ear and at the age of 83 he could still hear the
high-pitched contact calls of Goldcrests and Long-tailed Tits. Although in
his latter years he suffered from bouts of depression and often slept badly,
awaking from nightmares, he obtained much consolation from his continuing
interest in birds and, latterly, in butterflies and moths. In June 2002, he
wrote, "I am not very well and rather depressed at the moment, but birds
and butterflies still please me." He often dealt with his correspondence in
the very early hours of the morning and from 2004 I found his handwriting
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.816067" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337151" page_num="143" year="" vol="">
BURTON - DEREK GOODWIN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999429" page_id="56337151"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
143
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999465804878049" page_id="56337151"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
increasingly difficult to read. In a letter sent in January 2005 he mentioned
that his arthritic hands prevented him from typing.
On a visit to Virginia Water on June 1st 1952, I recall spending much
of the day watching with him from a hide he had constructed a pair of Jays
feeding a single nestling. This was in a wood near his home where we also
discovered a pair of Lesser Spotted Woodpeckers feeding well advanced
nestlings in a hole low down in an alder adjacent to a stream. A few days
later we visited Dartford Marshes in north-west Kent and heard two Quail
calling from the wheatfields. We also found two Turtle Dove nests in a
hawthorn thicket, one with eggs and the other with two nestlings - an unlikely
find on these Thames-side marshes nowadays.
The following weekend we decided to stay overnight on the marshes.
As it started to get dark on the Saturday evening, I asked Derek where he
thought we should stay for the night? He replied, "Right here" and laid down
in the marsh pasture where we had earlier been watching Com Buntings.
I was somewhat taken aback as we had no tent and I had assumed that we
would find bed and breakfast accommodation. I laid down beside him and
eventually dozed off until sometime after midnight when I awoke feeling
cold and covered with a light dew. I woke Derek and suggested that we
would find more shelter and warmth in a nearby hawthorn thicket. We found
that the drawback there was that it was home to a large number of rats, so
took turns to keep them at bay by shining our torches. After a rather restless
and chilly night, we finally awoke at 4.00am to a choms of a hundred or so
Linnets that had roosted in the thicket. Soon after we left there we came upon
a small stackyard around which six Red-legged Partridges were feeding.
We watched them for a time, then climbed onto a half built haystack to get
a better view. The increasing warmth from the rising sun led to us falling
asleep after our restless night and when we eventually pulled ourselves
together at about 7.00am, the partridges were nowhere to be seen. Later we
found a pair accompanied by two chicks. Derek was searching for the chicks
in thick vegetation in order to ring (band) them when he disturbed another
adult Red-legged Partridge. He then saw that a Stoat had been crouching very
close to this bird. Derek took out a Lapwing call-pipe and began blowing
frequent shrill blasts on it, which had a startling effect on the Stoat. It was
clearly puzzled and fascinated by the sound and run round and round in the
vegetation close to us. On one occasion it jumped right beside Derek's feet.
After a few minutes, however, it lost interest and rapidly departed.
Derek told the story of a summer visit he made to the former Perry Oaks
Sewage Farm near where Heathrow Airport stands today. The surface of
the sludge beds had become dry, cracked and solid-looking. Walking along
the edge of one of them, Derek came upon a pair of Pied Wagtails, I believe,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999605" page_id="56337152"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
144
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.969334" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337152" page_num="144" year="" vol="">
BURTON - DEREK GOODWIN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.978591225806452" page_id="56337152"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
and became so intent on obtaining a closer look at some interesting aspect of
their behaviour, that he forgot that the surface was not as solid as it looked
and impulsively stepped upon it and immediately sank up to his armpits in
the sludge. Fortunately other birdwatchers hastened to haul him out, which
they managed with a sound, so Derek said, like that of a cork coming out of
a champagne bottle but without the same pleasing odour. He managed to
remove much of the sewage sludge by rolling about on a grassy bank and
returned home via the London Underground with fellow passengers sitting
as far away from him as possible.
Another example of his implusiveness can be found in his article about
wild Rock Doves published in the Avicultural Magazine Vol.87, Nod, pp. 19-
33 (1981), in which Derek described his searches for nests of this species
in the dangerous sea caves of South Uist, where he had permission from
the laird to obtain a few squabs for study in captivity. Having managed to
secure one on the other side of a chasm in a sea cave, using a landing net at
the end of two long sticks lashed together, the lashings suddenly gave way
and the young Rock Dove, a female, was thrown into the sea below. Derek
instantly jumped into the ice cold water and at some considerable peril to
himself succeeded in rescuing it. However, it was the only one he was able
to return home with, though soon afterwards he was sent another squab from
Shetland which, happily, proved to be a male.
When I first got to know Derek in the late 1940s, I was impressed by
his determination to teach himself German so that he could read the books
and papers by German-speaking ethologists and ornithologists whose works
he admired. In our recent correspondence he often sent me German poems
and remarked that he was able to read and hear German without having to
translate it in his head.
Derek&apos;s first job was in 1937 working for his father, a bespoke tailor, in
London. Following wartime service in the Army from 1941-1946, he joined
the Bird Room staff of the British Museum (Natural History) in October
1946 and retired in February 1982.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.397896" page_id="56337152"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.820071" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56337152" page_num="144" year="" vol="">
2009 SUBSCRIPTION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999297142857143" page_id="56337152"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
The time has come around again to remind members and other subscribers
that the 2009 subscription will become due on January 1 st. Those who would
prefer to make the payment in US dollars will again be able to send checks
or money orders (US$38 for receiving magazines by regular mail or US$50
by air mail) to: The Avicultural Society, c/o Jane Cooper, 12650 Hearst
Road, Willits, California 95490-9231, USA. All checks and money orders
should be made payable to The Avicultural Society.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99927" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337153" page_num="" year="" vol="">
IN THE PINK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994750263157895" page_id="56337153"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
During the 2008 breeding season, some 30 different species bred and
raised more than 100 young at the Cotswold Wildlife Park and Gardens,
Burford, Oxfordshire. Species bred included the Pink Pigeon Nesoenas
mayeri, Ross's Turaco Musophaga rossae , Citron-crested Cockatoo Cacatua
sulphurea citrinocristata , Madagascar Teal Anas bernieri and Omei Shan
Liocichla Liocichla omeiensis.
A record six Pink Pigeons were raised, using Barbary Doves as foster
parents. The park has been working with the Pink Pigeon since 1997 as part
of a European Endangered Species Programme (EEP) run by the Durrell
Wildlife Conservation Trust on behalf of the Government of Mauritius.
Thanks to the release of captive-bred birds and improved habitat protection
the wild population has increased to some 330 or so birds.
As so few collections are succeeding in breeding the Citron-crested
Cockatoo, the European Endangered Species Programme (EEP) Co-ordinator
recommended that hand-rearing be considered and it proved successful.
Keepers succeeded in hand-rearing a chick and left the pair with a second
clutch, from which the pair also raised a chick.
The park also succeeded for the first time in breeding the Omei Shan
Liocichla, a species for which it holds the European studbook.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.84157" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56337153" page_num="" year="" vol="">
GOOD NEWS FROM LORO PARQUE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.980928" page_id="56337153"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
A further three Lear's Macaws Anodorhynchus leari have been raised
at Loro Parque, two by their parents and one by a pair of Green-winged
Macaws Ara chloropterus . It brings the total number bred there in 2008 to
four. In 2006, Loro Parque Fundaqion started with two pairs, received from
Sao Paulo Zoo, and now has 11 Lear's Macaws.
It has kept the Yellow-tailed Black Cockatoo Calyptorhynchus funereus
for many years, but has only just succeeded in hatching its first ever chick.
In 2002, it managed to exchange one of its two males for a two-year old
female, which having laid infertile eggs in 2006 and 2007, this year sat
for 18 days before abandoning the two eggs, which were transferred to an
incubator, where one hatched. The chick weighed 19.8g and had intensive
yellow down. Curator Dr Matthias Reinschmidt described the chick, which
is being hand-reared, as "very lively and active."
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.7918292">
Two Pesquet's Parrots Psittrichas fulgidus were hand-reared and four
pairs of Purple-bellied Parrots Triclaria malachitacea bred successfully.
Greater Vasa Parrots Coracopsis vasa also bred successfully, so did the
Pileated Parrots Pionopsitta pileata and the parque's Red-spectacled
Amazons Amazona pretrei , after failing to breed last year.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.800821" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56337154" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.44901175" page_id="56337154"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
A visit to Cikananga Wild Animal Rescue Centre, Java, Indonesia
by Andrew Owen.97
The European Robin Erithacus rubecula -
its care and breeding in aviculture
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.9338895625" page_id="56337154"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Peter Karsten.101
Breeding the Brown-breasted Barbet Lybius melanopterus
at Waddesdon Manor
by Ian Edmans and Andrew Owen.118
Goosander x Eider hybrids at WWT Martin Mere
by J. Meldrum and P. J. Wisniewski.123
Breeding the Javan Munia Lonchura leucogastroides
by Neville Brickell.129
Herbert Whitley - the founder of Paignton Zoo
by Jo Gregson.134
The Black-and-white Laughingthrush Garrulax bicolor .137
News &amp; Views .138
Memories of Derek Goodwin
by John F. Burton.142
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</table>
</algorithms>
