<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.952028333333333" page_id="56293239"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
OIL.
SILVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 108
No. 2
2002
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293240" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991785428571428" page_id="56293240"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2002 as for 2001: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.614431" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293240" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.928391444444444" page_id="56293240"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, P.O. BOX 47, EDENBRIDGE, KENT TN8 7WP, ENGLAND.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TNI3 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail:lee.palm@ virgin.net
Enquiries regarding membership should be sent to:
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.78133" page_id="56293240"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE MEMBERSHIP SECRETARY, Stewart Pyper, 21, Primrose Hill,
Nunney, Frome, Somerset BA11 4NP.
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.99671375" page_id="56293240"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998437" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293240" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.9972025">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7386625" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293241" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<category confidence="0.359638">
VoL 108 - No. 2 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2002
</category>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8024925" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293241" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THREATS TO PARROTS IN AVICULTURE
by Rosemary Low
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999784678571428" page_id="56293241"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
In recent years we have all heard much about factors which are
endangering the existence of parrots in the wild but we also need to give
some thought to another aspect. Many of the species which we know in
aviculture could die out in our aviaries without more careful planning and a
greater sense of responsibility on the part of those who hold them.
Today is the most important period in the history of parrot aviculture.
This is because aviculturists currently have in their care many wild-caught
birds of species which will never again be imported from the wild. All such
birds are potential founders of the stock with which future generations must
work. That is, they, and they alone, can pass on genes which are not already
present in captive stocks. To ensure that their breeding will be successful
for an unlimited number of generations, the gene pool must be as wide as
possible. Most aviculturists know about the effects of inbreeding, that is,
pairing together closely related birds which genetically are very similar.
The result after two or three generations is small and often degenerate
specimens, and decreasing fertility.
The greatest threats to parrots in aviculture will result from breeders
who hold the rarer species but who do not manage them in a responsible
way. By this I mean that they give little or no consideration to the future of
the species and that they are mainly motivated by financial gain. As the wild
status of so many parrots is not yet well known, and as one out of three of
parrot species is known to be endangered in the wild, it is surely prudent to
consider almost every one currently known in aviculture to be worth
preserving for future generations. Therefore, when I refer to the rarer species,
I mean rare in aviculture and/or in the wild.
Some of the threats
Let me illustrate some ways in which irresponsible owners can endanger
the captive survival of the rarer parrots.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.989597" page_id="56293242"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
50
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.660864" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293242" page_num="50" year="" vol="">
LOW - THREATS TO PARROTS IN AVICULTURE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997310658536585" page_id="56293242"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
Failure to cooperate with other breeders or studbook coordinators
One of the biggest dangers is that rare species are obtained by breeders
who have only one pair of the species - and usually a collection consisting
of one pair only of many different species. If they breed, a couple of
youngsters might be sold to someone else - usually the first person who
offers to buy them. Ideally, the buyer should already keep the species and is
therefore able to offer unrelated partners. Or, he or she will obtain at least
one other pair from another source. There are two reasons for this: one is to
prevent inbreeding and the other is that selling young which are destined to
be the only pair of their species in a collection is the quickest way to ensure
its extinction in captivity. So often, when one bird of a rare species dies, the
owner either cannot find another to replace it, or cannot afford to do so. Yet
he or she does not make the effort to enquire who might need the survivor.
Studbooks are of vital importance in ensuring the survival of rare species
in aviculture. The studbook keeper can quickly locate surplus males or
females, if they exist, and can place young birds where they will be used to
their best advantage. Some studbooks are already operating and I would
urge everyone who keeps the relevant species to participate - even if they
are not breeders. Just knowing the location of rare species may be important
at some stage.
Producing rare species which are unsuitable for breeding
Another threat to parrots is producing young of rare species which are
unsuitable for breeding. Young of Moluccan Cockatoos Cacatua
moluccensis , Hyacinth Macaws Anodorhynchus hyacinthinus and Golden
or Queen of Bavaria's Conures Guarouba guarouba are hand-reared from
the egg because they are considered to be desirable pets. Although a few of
these birds might find their way back into breeding situations, many of them
will not breed. This is because if they have been without contact with their
own species from the time of independence until one or two or more years
of age, they have not had the opportunity to learn the behaviour of their own
species. Some present greater problems in this respect than others. Male
cockatoos and Eclectus Eclectus roratus kept in this way are more likely to
be useless for breeding than Amazons Amazona spp., for example.
For this reason, when I hand-reared Moluccan Cockatoos, I isolated them
from the age of five or six weeks and kept them in a quarantine room. Their
only companion was an adult male Moluccan. As soon as the young ones
could fly, they were released from their cage to fly with the adult. I have
found that Moluccan Cockatoos which are not reared in this manner cry
continually and make food soliciting calls whenever they see a person. This
goes on for many months, whereas those reared in an adult's company show
normal behaviour and vocalisations.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.445284" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293243" page_num="51" year="" vol="">
LOW - THREATS TO PARROTS IN AVICULTURE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998034" page_id="56293243"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
51
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.985958027027027" page_id="56293243"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
It is the duty of all responsible aviculturists to ensure that a percentage
of the young reared are suitable for breeding and placed in a breeding
situation. If this does not happen, when the breeding pairs which currently
consist of wild-caught birds die, there will be no suitable birds to replace
them.
Legislation and its interpretation
Over 120 countries are members of CITES, the treaty which was designed
to protect threatened species from excessive trade. Unfortunately, not only
has CITES failed to do that in many instances, but in some cases it has
obstructed the work of genuine breeders. Much of the wording of the treaty
is vague and has been interpreted differently in various countries. Some of
.those responsible for implementing CITES seem to have lost sight of the
purpose of the treaty.
Some breeders have ceased to keep Appendix 1 species, such as the
Moluccan Cockatoo, because of the paperwork involved in selling the young.
Breeders of Appendix 1 species must now have the parents and young
microchipped and give proof of the origin of the parents before they can sell
the young. This seems reasonable in theory but sometimes it can be very
difficult. It can be impossible to prove the origin of pairs of Appendix I
species which were imported perhaps 20 years ago. Two cases of which I
know related to Goffin's Cockatoo C. gojfini and Golden or Queen of
Bavaria's Conures - and the birds had been known to me over this long
period. Nevertheless, we must accept that the identification of individual
birds in essential to prevent the system being abused.
Lack of exchange of information
Many breeders have accumulated information which would be of great
value to others rearing the same species. Unfortunately, much of this
information never becomes accessible to others. If aviculture is to realise its
full potential, it is absolutely vital that breeders share such knowledge,
preferably in the form of the printed word. I do not refer only to rare species.
If you study avicultural literature you will find that successes with rare species
are well documented. However, detailed and factual accounts of successes
with common species are much rarer. Therefore, everyone should carefully
record and publish, in words and pictures, accounts of the species with which
they have most experience. I believe that we should consider it our duty, in
return for the privilege of keeping these wonderful birds.
Rosemary Low, P.O. Box 100, Mansfield, Notts. NG20 9NZ, UK.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994574" page_id="56293244"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
52
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.716585" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293244" page_num="52" year="" vol="">
THE MANDARIN DUCK
by Philip Schofield
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99575852631579" page_id="56293244"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
Johnson and Payn (1957), writing of ornamental ducks, stated that the
Mandarin Aixgalericulata "......by common consent, heads the list both for
beauty of colouring and charm of habits." This still holds true nearly half a
century later with a much wider range of species commonly available,
although the Mandarin's colourful, but less extravagantly plumaged congener
the Carolina Wood Duck A. sponsa, must run it close. The dainty prettiness
of some of the teal is balanced by their smaller size which makes them more
vulnerable to predators.
The Mandarin Duck has been in UK aviculture since at least the 1740s
(Lever, 1977). London Zoo paid the then enormous sum of #70 (almost
US$100 at the present exchange rate) for two pairs in 1830, two years after
opening, and achieved the first UK breeding in 1843. Even though increasing
numbers were being bred in captivity, Delacour (1954) referred to large
numbers being exported from the Far East to Europe and the USA between
1910 and 1940. In the early part of this period they were cheaper than
(presumably English-bred) Carolinas. A display advertisement by the dealer
Willson's in the 1910 Avicultural Magazine offered pairs of Mandarins for
45 shillings (#2.25 or roughly US$3.20 in today's currency) compared with
50shillings (#2.50 or roughly U$3.50) for Carolinas.
A pair of Mandarins became my first exotic ducks in the autumn of
1971. The pair had the run of my parents' Ipswich back garden where they
were soon joined by a pair of Bahama Pintail Anas bahamensis. The area
was roughly triangular in shape, each side measuring about 70ft (approx.
21m), with the conventional lawn, shrubs and flower beds. Two blocks of
aviaries took up some of the ground space, and the ducks had an irregular
shaped concrete pond some 10ft x 4ft x 2ft deep in the middle (approx. 3m x
1.2m x 0.6m deep in the middle). The following winter brought prolonged
snow and ice, and the female Bahama Pintail had her feet badly frost-bitten.
The Mandarins remained noticeably unaffected by the weather, and in
subsequent years have always appeared indifferent to cold, although like
most animals they dislike strong winds. Part of the attraction of Johnson
and Payn's book is their assessment of each species for its potential adverse
effect on garden plants. They recommend Mandarins as being completely
harmless, and indeed mine caused no complaints from the two keen gardeners
in the family. Although they grazed the lawn to some extent, the Mandarins
did not even appear to sample flowering plants, even alpines. Although
they often perched on the rockery, their tiny feet did no damage. This would
not apply to aquatic plants, which are quickly eaten. The garden was
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.779421" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293245" page_num="53" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - MANDARIN DUCK
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99841" page_id="56293245"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
53
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998751627906976" page_id="56293245"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
surrounded partly by 6ft (approx. 1.8m) high wooden fence panels, and partly
by chainlink wire a little more than half that height. With hindsight, my
ducks were not sufficiently protected from predators. However, the local
cats did not bother them, and although the garden was bordered by open
country, there did not seem to be any Foxes Vulpes vulpes. This contrasts
with my situation 30 years later here in Dorset, in a town setting, where
Foxes are a continual menace, and anything smaller than Shelduck Tadorna
tadorna need the protection of an aviary to survive. A fox-proof fence is no
barrier to our predatory local cats, which have killed ducks up to the size of
Pintail A. acuta.
For a variety of reasons I did not manage to breed Mandarins until 1974,
but have bred them in small numbers most years since then. Nesting naturally
in hollow trees, they readily accept nest-boxes, while I find 25 litre (5.4 UK
gallon) plastic barrels as good as anything, although not as pleasing to look
at as some of the elaborate wooden 'duck cotes' that one can buy. Most of
those used by my Mandarins have been placed directly on the ground,
although one that was some 3ft (almost lm) up a sloping tree trunk was
especially popular. Over the years, in addition to species of perching ducks,
this attracted such conventionally ground nesting species as Common Teal
A. crecca and Chiloe Wigeon A. sibilatrix. At one time I had a pair of
Mandarins housed in a large aviary at a children's home where I worked,
and they nested in a shed alongside bantams and call ducks. Boxes and
other nesting places should be furnished with leaf mould or wood shavings
with perhaps a little chopped straw. Hay should not be used, as it tends to
attract fungal spores and become a health hazard. Laidlay (1929) referred
to a Mandarin nest in long grass, but this must be regarded as exceptional. I
have had up to 14 eggs laid in a clutch, of which the 13 hatched were hatched
by the duck. I would be reluctant to put this many under a bantam, but a
duck in a natural nest site is a very different proposition from artificial
incubation. I never leave a broody hen off eggs for longer than 15 minutes,
yet incubating ducks seem able to leave their eggs for much longer with
excellent hatchability. Seth-Smith (1940) described the descent from a high
nest site by Mandarin ducklings at Foxwarren Park, the ducklings being so
light that they can fall considerable distances without harm. In the early
days, all my Mandarins were hatched and reared by bantams, until I found
that with suitable protection from the elements and other birds, the ducks
make efficient mothers of their own broods. I usually remove the mother
and ducklings to an enclosed shed for the first few weeks, with a floor
covering of wood shavings which are changed daily. With a galvanised
chicken drinker and a pan of poultry chick crumbs, with greenfood
occasionally, rearing is usually uneventful. No bathing facilities are provided
until the ducklings' breast feathers are through, at which stage the birds are
moved outside.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996499" page_id="56293246"  page_num="54" year="" vol="">
54
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.938957" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293246" page_num="54" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - MANDARIN DUCK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999527761904761" page_id="56293246"  page_num="54" year="" vol="">
As with an increasing number of waterfowl the Mandarin is available
now in colour mutations. The first to emerge was the silver, which I met
with first in the mid-1980s, and which I believe originated in the Netherlands.
It is quite striking, with a bright red bill. Basically a white bird, it has all the
markings indicated in pale fawn. These birds are probably seen at their best
when kept with the normal form, when the contrast is quite pleasing. I have
kept silvers since 1992, and bred a few. The ducklings are a little harder to
rear perhaps, having red eyes and therefore relatively poor vision and white
down that therefore provides less efficient insulation. My normal females
usually start laying in April, while the silvers usually wait until May. More
recently a blonde variety has appeared. I have not seen it yet, but am prepared
to find that like the blonde Carolina, it is something of a disappointment. I
have already described (Schofield, 1997) the way in which the silver mutation
appears to be inherited, but cannot at this stage do the same for the blonde.
With a view to keeping a breeding stock, I tend to retain younger birds,
so have scant data on longevity. However, I suspect that few Mandarins
reach their tenth birthday. A male of known age on a friend's pond failed to
regain full plumage after its twelfth summer, and died that winter.
There are effectively three ways to keep Mandarins. The conventional
way is to surround a piece of land, provided with a pond and appropriate
planting, with a fox-proof fence. In this situation the birds should be wing-
clipped or pinioned. Allowing them to fly free in the UK could invite
prosecution under the Wildlife and Countryside Act, although this has
happened only once, and I am not aware of the exact circumstances. It must
be debatable whether free-flying exotic waterfowl on one's own land could
be regarded as having been "released to the wild"; there is little if any
difference between this and that of exotic birds of prey being flown free by
falconers. Animal welfare organisations seem able to release into the wild,
with impunity, hand-reared orphaned Rabbits Oryctolagus cuniculus, another
introduced, if long-established exotic.
There are advantages to keeping Mandarins in aviaries. They can be
allowed their powers of flight and to exhibit their natural perching behaviour,
and will be seen to be surprisingly agile both on the wing and when perching.
Under these conditions, so long as Am (12mm) mesh netting is used, they
can be kept completely safe from predators. A minimum size aviary for a
pair would be about 200sq ft (approx. 18.5 sq m), that is 10ft x 20ft (approx.
3m x 6m). Anything smaller might result in overcrowding if a brood of
grown ducklings is present. The size of the pond is less important that its
design. For a mixed aviary, it needs to be saucer-shaped. Shallow edges all
round will enable small birds to drink and bathe without risk of drowning.
If young passerines are due to fledge, a temporary cover can be placed over
the pond and the ducks restricted to a poultry drinker for a week or so until
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.779631" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293247" page_num="55" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - MANDARIN DUCK
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994919" page_id="56293247"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
55
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999395380952381" page_id="56293247"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
the newcomers are flying confidently.
Mandarins in my aviaries have caught and eaten frogs that found their
way through the wire mesh, and might not therefore be entirely safe with
small fledglings. My suggested precaution for preventing this (Schofield,
2000) is to catch fledglings and cage them within the aviary until they can
fly well. I use a small all-wire, Spanish call-bird cage, a little bigger than
the nest, and the parents feed the fledglings through the wire until it is safe
to let them out. While harmless to most other birds, except perhaps small
fledglings, Mandarin drakes can be unpleasantly aggressive to other ducks
in such a small enclosure. Species they would not bother in a large area
may be subjected to unacceptable bullying. This can even extend to a second
Mandarin female, if one is attempting to breed from a trio consisting of a
drake and two ducks. While such an arrangement has worked well for me
in a large area, under aviary conditions one of the females was persecuted
and had to be removed. One season I had three drakes and two ducks living
as a group in a collection of a dozen (12) species. The Mandarin drakes
used to display as a group, and the two ducks reared their 17 ducklings in a
group creche. While the male Mandarin will guard his mate's nest-box
throughout the 30 day incubation period, he loses interest when the young
hatch, and usually commences his eclipse moult.
A third way to keep Mandarins is to have a low fence around the
enclosure, and gently walk the birds into a shed or aviary at night. This can
be done only if cats are not a problem, and the local foxes operate only at
night. The ducks adapt well to this regime and will breed satisfactorily.
The same remarks about aggressive behaviour apply to night confined birds
as to those in aviaries. A completely unacceptable practice is to release
pinioned Mandarins onto an unfenced area of water, and expect them to
stay. Something will eat them, or they will wander off and come to a bad
end.
The Mandarin is one of the few ducks that indulges in mutal preening.
Any two birds that are on friendly terms may preen each other, usually about
the head and neck. It tends to be initiated by a female and is as likely to
occur between casual associates as it is between a mated pair. Further aspects
of Mandarin social behaviour, some open to alternative interpretation, were
described by Wicks (1955). Lorenz (1953) described display functions and
postures in some detail.
One winter I had only a single Mandarin, a juvenile female, living in a
mixed collection. Ignoring other ducks, she persistently courted a male
Golden Pheasant Chrysolophus pictus, whose colour scheme might
superficially recall that of a Mandarin drake. When a male Mandarin was
introduced, the female went to him immediately. Mandarin drakes will pair
readily with Carolina females, especially in the absence of a female Mandarin
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.992063" page_id="56293248"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
56
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.935675" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293248" page_num="56" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - MANDARIN DUCK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999449333333333" page_id="56293248"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
(males of both species will also on occasion form strong homosexual pair
bonds, either intra- or interspecific). However, due to the Mandarin having
a different arrangement of chromosomes, hybrids rarely or never result. I
can recall a detailed article by A. A. Prestwich in the Avicultural Magazine ,
describing a number of reported cases pf Mandarin hybrids, and concluding
that none of them was conclusively proven (I do not have the relevant issue,
so am unable to quote from it more fully, but have to rely on my memory).
Whether the Mandarin has ever produced a hybrid remains debatable.
However, while I have seen hybrids produced by Carolinas with a wide
range of species from diving ducks such as the Rosybill Netta peposaca to
such surface feeders as the Chestnut-breasted Teal A. castanea , I have never
seen a hybrid which had any suggestion of Mandarin parentage.
When I first became involved with Mandarins, they customarily sold for
#10 (approx. US$14.20) a pair, twice the asking price for Carolinas. The
general opinion in those days was that Carolinas were easier to breed, were
almost certain to do so at one year old, and laid more eggs. The more
extravagantly plumaged Mandarin also seemed to be more in demand, hence
the difference in price. The normal coloured form of both species is currently
priced from #35-#40 (approx.US$50-US$57), so what has happened? It
would appear that we are seeing the sort of 'artificial evolution' that occurs
with domestically bred populations of animals. In this case, there has been
selection for Mandarins that lay more eggs in their lifetimes, which could
involve laying at a younger age. Allied with a greater effort to breed them,
they have effectively caught up with Carolinas in the population stakes. I
find that modern Mandarins usually lay at one year old, and still find more
budding waterfowl enthusiasts want to start with this species than with its
congener. Hence the current pricing situation.
Mandarin eggs tend to be slightly larger than those of the Carolina, and
seem to produce slightly larger and more viable ducklings. While ducklings
of both species are susceptible to cold and wet in their early days, the more
robust Mandarin ducklings seem to start feeding more readily, and a higher
percentage survive the critical first week, at least in my small collection. It
may be that wild Mandarins in their native Asia breed at higher altitudes
than do Carolinas in North America, and need to be that much larger at birth
to survive. It is likely that the original gene pool of the captive Mandarin
population was much greater than that of the Carolina, with wild-caught
Mandarins imported up to the Second World War, long after the declining
North American wild population of Carolinas had to be reinforced by captive-
bred birds from Europe. The western avicultural/feral population of A.
galericulata may therefore be genetically more viable than that of A. sponsa.
The differences in duckling size and genetic diversity may help to explain
why the Mandarin has become well established as a wild species in the UK,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.779514" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293249" page_num="57" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - MANDARIN DUCK
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997195" page_id="56293249"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
57
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998855119047619" page_id="56293249"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
while the Carolina has not, despite breeding in a feral state on many occasions.
Another factor suggested by Lever (1977) is that Carolina ducklings may
be more vulnerable to predation, taking as they do 10 weeks to reach the
flying stage, while Mandarins are airborne two weeks earlier.
The Mandarin's history as a feral species in the UK was described by
Lever (1977), who mentioned (p.290) free-flying birds at Woburn at the
beginning of the twentieth century. The Avicultural Society's role in further
introductions may be less well known. In the magazine in June 1929, David
Seth-Smith suggested releasing some 50 pairs in the London parks, initially
wing-clipped to prevent them from straying, but with the view to eventual
naturalisation. He appears to have invited donation of either birds or funds
for their purchase. Fitter (1959) described how Alfred Ezra, John Spedan
Lewis and W. H. St Quintin jointly financed the project the following year.
Ninety-nine wild-caught Chinese Mandarins were released in the parks, some
of which were fully-winged and departed immediately, one to Hungary and
another to Sweden. The remainder seem to have left as soon as they could.
It will never be known to what extent this massive release contributed to the
species becoming firmly established as a British bird. Ezra's own full-winged
colony at Foxwarren Park in Surrey was just becoming established at that
stage, and Fitter went on to summarise the Mandarin's establishment in
nearby Windsor Great Park during the 1930s, probably from several sources,
including Foxwarren and the London parks.
Certain birds by their beauty and ease of management are particularly
suitable for aviculture. Except in so far as many species are likely to depend
on captive propagation for their continued existence, rarity holds little
relevance. The Mandarin owes its popularity to its hardy constitution
combined with attractive colours and elegance of form. As such it is likely
to remain numerous as long as there are aviculturists to keep it. Goodwin
(1965) suggested, I think rightly, that to become domesticated, a species has
to be capable of being bred with the minimum of effort. Anything that
requires dedication will always remain in the hands of a few dedicated
keepers.
Given that the Mandarin Duck is apparently threatened by deforestation
in parts of its range, its establishment as a wild-living British bird must help
ensure its continued existence. It appears that the Mandarin may have been
part of our fauna some 600,000 years ago; Goodwin (1988) hinted that it
could be an analogous case to the Azure-winged Magpie Cyanopica cyanea
which occurs in the Far East and on the Iberian Peninsula, and nowhere in
between. How long does a species need to have become extinct in a given
country before releasing it there becomes an introduction rather than a
reintroduction? The Wildlife and Countryside Act does not enlighten us
here. Certainly the environmental purists would probably prefer that we
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996441" page_id="56293250"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
58
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.929745" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293250" page_num="58" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - MANDARIN DUCK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994964" page_id="56293250"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
had no Mandarins in the UK. Such political correctness fails to consider
that (1) the Mandarin's requirements are so specific that it is unlikely to
compete with any current native species and (2) our countryside and wildlife
are so much products of human intervention (even such an everyday animal
as the Rabbit being exotic in origin) that one non-predatory, non-destructive,
non-hybridizing species can do little damage to this less than pristine
ecosystem, while (3) wild-living Mandarins give a lot of pleasure to (open-
minded) birdwatchers and lay people alike.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909932" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293250" page_num="58" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97553716" page_id="56293250"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
Delacour, J. 1954. The Waterfowl of the World. Country Life, London.
Fitter, R. S. R. 1959. The Ark in Our Midst. Collins, London.
Goodwin, D. 1965. Instructions to Young Ornithlogists VI -Domestic Birds. Museum Press
Ltd, London.
Goodwin, D. 1987. Introduced and Re-Introduced Birds in Britain. Avicultural Magazine
93,4:226-237.
Goodwin, D. 1988. &amp;apos;The History of the Birds of Britain' (Review). Avicultural Magazine
94,4:228-229.
Lever, C. 1977. The Naturalised Animals of the British Isles. Hutchinson &amp; Co., London.
Johnson, A. A. and Payn, W. H. 1957. Ornamental Waterfowl. H. F. &amp; G. Witherby, London.
Laidlay, J. C. 1929. Carolina and Mandarin Ducks. Avicultural Magazine Fifth Series VII,7:172.
Lorenz, K. 1953. Comparative Studies on the Behaviour of Anatidae. Avicultural Magazine
59,3:80-91.
Savage, C. 1952. The Mandarin Duck. A. &amp; C. Black.
Seth-Smith, D. 1929. Avicultural Notes. Avicultural Magazine Fifth Series VII,6:152-153.
Seth-Smith, D. 1940. The Foxwarren Collection. Avicultural Magazine Fifth Series 5,1:3-7.
Schofield,?. 1997. Waterfowl Mutations, Hybrids and the Colour Purple. Avicultural Magazine
103,4:147-148.
Wicks, E. 1955. Dispositions of Mandarin and Carolina Ducks of Interest to Bird-Lovers
Rather than to Bird-Scientists. Avicultural Magazine 61,3:114-117.
Willson's. 1910. (Trade Advertisement). Avicultural Magazine Third Series, Vol.l.
Philip Schofield, who is an Avicultural Society Council Member, is by
profession a social worker and lives in Dorset in south-west England. He
specialises in waterfowl and seed-eating pigeons, and also keeps a few other
species.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.520077" page_id="56293250"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8822555" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293250" page_num="58" year="" vol="">
INTERNATIONAL WILD WATERFOWL ASSOCIATION'S
ANNUAL CONVENTION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8998495" page_id="56293250"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
The International Wild Waterfowl Association's Annual Convention will
take place in San Diego, California, starting on October 16th 2002. Visits to
the famous San Diego Zoo and San Diego Wild Animal Park will be on the
agenda and visits to other collections are being planned. Members of the
Avicultural Society are most welcome to join the association. Further details
are available from Christopher Marler (Tel/Fax: 01234 711451).
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996922" page_id="56293251"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
59
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.985385" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293251" page_num="59" year="" vol="">
SCARLET IBIS INCUBATE SACRED IBIS EGGS AND
PARTLY REAR A SACRED IBIS CHICK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.701649" page_id="56293251"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
by Brett K. Banner
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.94322" genericHeader="introduction" page_id="56293251" page_num="59" year="" vol="">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.956364457142857" page_id="56293251"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
The nests of two pairs of Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber were parasitized
by a Sacred Ibis Threskiornis aethiopicus at Metrozoo, Miami, Florida, USA.
The Scarlet Ibis incubated the Sacred Ibis eggs despite the dissimilarity
between these eggs and their own. One Sacred Ibis chick was partly reared
by Scarlet Ibis parents. The significance of this behaviour is discussed.
In the wild, ibis (family Threskiornithidae) are known to occasionally
engage in intraspecific brood parasitism. For example, in a population of
White Ibis E. albus in South Carolina, USA, 2.7% of all eggs laid were laid
by intraspecific brood parasites (Kushlan and Bildstein, 1992). Conversely,
interspecific brood parasitism involving wild ibis has apparently not been
reported. A number of studies of wild colonies have not reported ibises
laying their eggs in the nests of other wading birds or vice versa even where
mixed species breeding assemblanges made such activity possible (ffrench
and Haverschmidt, 1970; Urban, 1974; Bildstein, 1993).
In captivity, birds that are not sympatric in the wild are housed together
sometimes, providing opportunities for brood parasitism that would otherwise
not be possible. This paper describes the unusual series of incidents in
which a captive Sacred Ibis laid eggs in the nests of two pairs of Scarlet Ibis
at Metrozoo, Miami. These eggs were accepted by the Scarlet Ibis and one
Sacred Ibis chick was partly raised by a pair of Scarlet Ibis.
Five Sacred Ibis were among the birds housed in a 0.6 hectare (approx.
1 x h acre) open air, walk-through aviary at the zoo, prior to August 24th
1992. On that date, Hurricane Andrew struck the zoo, destroying the aviary
and liberating over 200 birds. Over the next several weeks, traps were set
and many of the escaped birds were recaptured. One of the Sacred Ibis flew
out of the zoo grounds and was never recaptured, but the other four remained
on site, roosting usually in an open exhibit housing a species of African
antelope, the Gerenuk Litocranius walleri, and a group of pinioned Abdim's
Storks Ciconia abdminii.
The three male Sacred Ibis were eventually caught and pinioned, but the
fourth, a female, was not recaptured. The three males were subsequently
placed back in the Gerenuk display and the full-winged female spent most
of her time with the pinioned birds. She did, however, occasionally fly
some 730m (approx. 800yds) across the zoo to an open exhibit containing
seven pinioned Scarlet Ibis, along with over 50 Caribbean Flamingos
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.987934" page_id="56293252"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
60
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.880353" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293252" page_num="60" year="" vol="">
BANNOR - IBIS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998554928571429" page_id="56293252"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
Phoenicopterus ruber ruber , two Roseate Spoonbills Ajaia ajaja and
numerous waterfowl. In 1995 and 1996, the female Sacred Ibis paired with
one of the pinioned males, nested, and raised chicks in the Gerenuk exhibit.
In 1997 she laid again, beginning on April 20th. When checking on May
5th, the two eggs were missing and had apparently been predated.
On May 15th I searched the Scarlet Ibis exhibit for a nest and found one
on the ground tucked beneath a large-leaved Philodendron selloum. This
nest (nest A) contained four eggs. Three of them had been laid by a Scarlet
Ibis, but the fourth obviously had not its size and appearance suggested that
It had been laid by the Sacred Ibis. This was confirmed on June 1st, when a
Sacred Ibis chick hatched in the nest. The Scarlet Ibis fed and cared for the
Sacred Ibis chick. However, on June 3rd it was removed from the nest for
hand-rearing because it was approximately twice as large as the Scarlet Ibis
hatched on June 2nd, leading to concern that the younger chick would be
unable to compete successfully for parental care. A second Scarlet Ibis
chick hatched on June 6th; both these chicks were successfully raised to
maturity by their parents.
When removed from the nest, the Sacred Ibis chick weighed 108g. Two
Sacred Ibis chicks hand-reared at the zoo in 1987 weighed 38.5g and 3L8g,
respectively, at hatching. If the chick hatched under the Scarlet Ibis parents
was of a similar weight at hatching, It must have approximately tripled its
initial weight in only two days, demonstrating the high level of attention it
must have received.
Another pair of Scarlet Ibis nested simultaneously approximately 2m
(6ft 6m) from the first pair and laid a single egg on May 17th. When checking
on June 8th, I discovered that a Sacred Ibis egg had been laid in this nest
(nest B). When the nest was checked on June 14th, it contained a second
Sacred Ibis egg and the Scarlet Ibis egg was missing. A third Sacred Ibis
egg was laid in the nest on June 16th. There was now a clutch composed
entirely of three Sacred Ibis eggs, which the pair of Scarlet Ibis continued to
incubate.
One of the eggs was cracked and found to contain a dead embryo when
the nest was inspected on June 27th. Sacred Ibis eggs have an incubation
period of about 28 days (Urban, 1974), therefore, the remaining two eggs
were expected to hatch by mid-July. On July 11th, however, it was noticed
that neither bird was on the nest and an inspection revealed that both eggs
were gone. They may have been predated, or may have been knocked out
of the nest and fallen into the lake adjacent to the nest. The pair of Scarlet
Ibis had been sitting for a total of 55 days, the final 27 days having been
spent incubating a clutch composed entirely of Sacred Ibis eggs.
The above incidents are noteworthy for three reasons. Firstly, it shows
that in captivity at least, the same female Sacred Ibis may incubate her own
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.551913" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293253" page_num="61" year="" vol="">
BANNOR - IBIS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997966" page_id="56293253"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
61
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997178921052632" page_id="56293253"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
eggs one breeding season and become a brood parasite in another breeding
season. Secondly, since in this case the female Sacred Ibis was able to fly
and her mate was not, it was evident that the female essentially abandoned
her mate at the present nesting site to lay at another location some 730m
(approx. 800yds) away. That she would do so is surprising, in light of the
statement by Hancock et al. (1992) that: "(A strong) pair-bond is the key to
successful nesting..in ibis and related wading birds. In this case the pair
bond between the male and female Sacred Ibis in 1997 would seem to have
been quite loose, leading to her departure from his enclosure and to her
laying her eggs in the nests of two pairs of Scarlet Ibis and leaving them to
incubate her eggs. In the first instance (nest A), this could still be considered
to have been successful, as a healthy chick resulted from this unusual
behaviour.
The third reason that the incidents described were noteworthy is that the
Scarlet Ibis accepted the Sacred Ibis eggs despite the differences in size and
colour between the eggs of the two species. Urban (1974) reported that
Sacred Ibis eggs average 63.4mm x 43.9mm, while ffrench and Haverschmidt
(1970) listed mean measurements for Scarlet Ibis eggs of 56.0mm x 37.1mm.
Coloration of the two species' eggs is also different. Sacred Ibis eggs are
dull white with a faint bluish tinge and occasionally a few dark reddish
spots, whereas Scarlet Ibis eggs are dull olive green to buff with dark brown
markings (ffrench and Haverschmidt, 1970; Urban, 1974; pers. obs.). These
differences in size and coloration, while readily discernible to me in the
cases noted above, did not dissuade the two pairs of Scarlet Ibis from
incubating the Sacred Ibis eggs.
As nest B was clearly visible from across the lake, I was able to check
whether the Scarlet Ibis were sitting on the eggs in the nest without disturbing
them; this I did at least twice a day on my working days throughout the
incubation period. Never did I observe the nest without one parent being in
attendance. This suggests that in order to lay three eggs in nest B over the
eight day period, which it did, the female Sacred Ibis was probably not able
to sneak up to the Scarlet Ibis nest without the owner's knowledge. I did not
observe nest site interactions between the Sacred Ibis and the pair of Scarlet
Ibis, but it seems probable that the female Sacred Ibis could have used her
size advantage to force the sitting Scarlet Ibis off the nest. As both nesting
pairs of Scarlet Ibis returned rapidly to their eggs after I had made an
inspection, it is similarly unlikely that disturbance by another ibis kept them
from their nest for long.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.96176" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56293253" page_num="61" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.955441" page_id="56293253"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
I would like to thank S. Connors and J. Mellen for their helpful comments
on my manuscript.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996581" page_id="56293254"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
62
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.956067" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293254" page_num="62" year="" vol="">
BANNOR - IBIS
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.354767266666667" page_id="56293254"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
Bildstein, K. L. 1993. White Ibis: wetland wanderer. Smithsonian Institution Press, Washington
DC.
ffrench, R. P. and Haverschmidt, F. 1970. The Scarlet Ibis in Surinam and Trinidad. Living Bird
9: 147-166.
Hancock, J. A., Kushlan, J. A. and Kahl, M. P. 1992. Storks, ibises, and spoonbills of the world.
Academic Press, London.
Kushlan, J. A. and Bildstein, K. L. 1992. White Ibis. In: The Birds of North America, No.9
(Poole, A., Stettenheim, P., and Gill, F., eds.). The Academy of Natural Sciences, Philadelphia
and The American Ornithologists' Union, Washington, DC.
Urban, E. K. 1974. Breeding of Sacred Ibis ( Threskiornis aethiopica ) at Lake Shala, Ethiopia.
Ibis 116: 263-277.
Brett K. Bannor made the above observations when he worked at
Metrozoo, 12400 Southwest 152 Street, Miami, Florida 33177, USA. His
present address is: 13427 Fairway Glen Drive #102, Orlando, Florida 32824,
USA.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.307703" page_id="56293254"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.826749" genericHeader="introduction" page_id="56293254" page_num="62" year="" vol="">
CONURES NEST IN KENT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998415421052631" page_id="56293254"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
In April 2001, a fifth species of parrot, the Blue-crowned Conure Aratinga
acuticaudata, was discovered nesting in the wild in the UK. A nest with
four eggs was found in a park in Lewisham, Kent, but by May 6th, the nest
had been abandoned and the eggs were missing, possibly taken by a Grey
Squirrel Sciurus carolinensis. This species of conure was first reported in
Bromley in 1997, when two were observed visiting a bird feeder. In 1999 a
flock of 15 was observed. An account of this nesting attempt, observations
on this species in the wild in the UK and a summary of three of the four
parrot species - the Rose-ringed or Ring-necked Parrakeet Psittacula krameri ,
Alexandrine P. eupatria. Monk or Quaker Parrakeet Myiopsitta monachus
and Budgerigar Melopsittacus undulatus - that have or continue to nest in
the UK, are given by Chris Butler, Grant Hazelhurst and Kristie Butler in
First nesting by Blue-crowned Parakeet in Britain, British Birds 95,1:17-20
(January 2002).
Last Christmas, long-time member Derek Goodwin, who lives near
Bromley, Kent, wrote saying that from at least November 10th - December
5th 2001, there were two Senegal Parrots Poicephalus senegalus flying about
where he lives. By Christmas they had disappeared and he feared they might
have died in the cold weather at that time.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.991472" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293255" page_num="63" year="" vol="">
NOTES ON THE FEEDING AND NESTING
OF OLIVE PIGEONS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998182" page_id="56293255"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
63
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.890521952380952" page_id="56293255"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
by Neville Brickell
The African Olive Pigeon Columba arquatrix is also known as the
Rameron Pigeon, Yellow-eyed Pigeon or Speckled Olive Pigeon.
In the wild it feeds predominately on fruits and berries, as well as eating
seeds and insect life, most notably caterpillars. It feeds in the forest canopy
on both indigenous and introduced trees, also on bushes and has been
recorded at lower elevations raiding cultivated fruits such as olives, grapes
and mulberries. Apparently it never descends to the ground to drink, but
has been observed descending to the ground to feed on the hard seeds of
Croton macrostachys in the central African country of the Congo. In Cape
Province, South Africa, it has been seen consuming seeds of the Stone Pine
Pinus pinea, which contain an oily endosperm, and also those of a black
wattle Acacia sp., an exotic grown for commercial purposes. A single bird
was observed eating seeds from a tree known locally here in South Africa as
the Rooikrans A. cyclops , which despite its South African sounding name is
native to Australia. Bugweed Solanum mauritianum, red when mature, is a
favourite of this species, as is the Ink-berry bush Phytolacca dodecandra,
as reported from Zimbabwe. Back in 1927 an extensive study of the feeding
habits of the African Olive Pigeon was undertaken in the Knysna Forest, in
which the fruits or berries of close to 30 trees were found to be consumed by
this species. These included:
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.98114935483871" page_id="56293255"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
Bush Gwarri
Euclea crispa
Cape Plane
Ochna arborea
Common Saffron wood
Cassine papillosa
Red Saffron wood
Cassine crocea
Cape Ash
Ekebergia capensis
Hard Pear
Olinia ventosa
4 mm-5 mm long
black when mature
orange-red to red
pale lemon yellow
when mature
white to pale yellow
dark red, streaked
yellow sometimes,
pink to bright red
when mature
pink or red
October-February
August-November
August-March
March-September
December-April,
or even as late
as June
December-June
</figure>
<page confidence="0.923867" page_id="56293256"  page_num="64" year="" vol="">
64
</page>
<figure confidence="0.986548848484848" page_id="56293256"  page_num="64" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - OLIVE PIGEONS
White Pear black with bright December-June
Apodytes dimidiata red succulent heel
Thorn Pear
Scolopia zeyheri
Ironwood
Olea capensis
Large-flowered Ochna
Ochna atropurpurea
Notsung
Halleria lucida
Poison-peach
Diospyros dichrophylla
Stinkwood
Ocotea bullata
Wild Grape
Rhoicissus tomentosa
red to pink
when mature
purple when mature
bright red
black when mature
golden velvety
purple
purplish-black
when mature
July-September
February-September
September-November
May-December
April-October
March- June
January-April
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.973686" page_id="56293256"  page_num="64" year="" vol="">
Observations have also been made on the feeding habits of captive
pigeons living in bird gardens and zoos in South Africa. Fruits provided
have included guavas, apples, grapes, apricots, pawpaw (papaya) and
tomatoes, when necessary cut into 10mm (slightly less than Ain) cubes.
Banana is extremely popular, immersed first in diluted milk, to reduce the
stickiness. Dried and soaked raisins, sultanas and currants were always
available, and they were offered steamed diced carrots, shelled garden peas
and com, mostly of the red varieties that had been stripped from the cob.
Lettuce and watercress were the preferred greenfoods. A mixture of various
grains was also offered, including whole maize which apparently they have
no difficulty swallowing. I was unable to identify all the ingredients of the
softfood mixtures, but believe these included nectar, bread and milk, pound
cake, cmshed dog biscuits, sponge msks, boiled rice and egg food. A popular
brand of South African softfood contains wheat flour, whole fresh eggs,
salt, soya flour, niger and maw seeds, plus vitamins, minerals and trace
elements. As this species is partly insectivorous, mealworms were also
supplied, though sparingly. Food was placed on trays well off the ground,
each covered by a canopy to protect the food from rain. Water should
preferably be provided in glazed ceramic dishes or pots, as in a controlled
experiment in Australia these and glass dishes showed considerably lower
bacterial growth (Brown, 1995).
Despite being a common species over much of its range, relatively few
nests have been found. Of the 15 recorded in South Africa, six were at
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.541469" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293257" page_num="65" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - OLIVE PIGEONS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.880347" page_id="56293257"  page_num="65" year="" vol="">
65
</page>
<table confidence="0.3956885" page_id="56293257"  page_num="65" year="" vol="">
N. Brickell
African Olive Pigeon
</table>
<page confidence="0.979387" page_id="56293258"  page_num="66" year="" vol="">
66
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.738454" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293258" page_num="66" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - OLIVE PIGEONS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970006857142857" page_id="56293258"  page_num="66" year="" vol="">
heights of 6m 14m (approx. 20ft-46ft), a further seven were between 2m-
6m (approx.6ft 7in-20ft) above the ground and the remaining two were only
lm-1.5m (approx.3ft 3in-5ft) from the ground. Nests were located in gardens,
open rolling country, near the coast in a grove of milkwoods Sideroxylon
sp., and at the foot of a waterfall. A nest in Zimbabwe was in a wooden
gully. Both indigenous and exotic trees and bushes are utilised for nesting.
The nest is a fairly substantial platform of loosely arranged twigs, coarser
ones forming the base and finer ones the saucer-shaped central depression,
which is lined with a few green leaves. A nest under observation in the
Chimanimani Mountains of Zimbabwe had been built of heather instead of
twigs and was lined with just three green leaves. One nest in South Africa
measured 13cm (approx.5in) across and another 19cm (approx. 7 Van).
Breeding has been recorded in all months, but in southern African countries
probably occurs most frequently during the cooler months of April-June.
There is usually just a single egg but clutches of two eggs, attributed to the
African Olive Pigeon, have been recorded in the Congo. The eggs are white
with a glossy surface and measure about 39mm x 29mm. The incubation
period is 17-20 days (16-20 days in captivity), with both birds being involved.
The nestling period is 19-22 days (19-20 days in captivity). Melkkamer in
western Cape Province, South Africa, and Engel (in Uys) observed nesting
behaviour which constituted a nestling period of 20 days, with young
becoming independent shortly thereafter.
Both in captivity and in the wild this species has been observed to have
little fear of human beings. While photographing it, Uys noted that he could
walk up to the base of the tree in which this pigeon was nesting, without
disturbing the sitting bird. If the bird was disturbed, it would return within
15 minutes and continue incubation. While he was erecting and dismantling
his hide it tolerated any amount of movement and was not easily displaced.
My knowledge of this species in captivity has been limited over the
years to those I have seen when visiting bird gardens and zoos in southern
Africa, and the private collection of John Muller, for many years a breeder
of the African Olive Pigeon, who kindly allowed me to photograph his birds.
My observations have revealed that nests may be built among growing
foliage, as well as in artificial receptacles such as wire baskets (fixed in
forks of trees) and wooden trays with sides varying from 6cm-10cm (approx.
2V4in-4in) high, that prevent the egg from rolling off and the nestling from
making an early exit from the nest. An example can be seen in my photograph
(p.68) showing a nestling in one of John Muller's aviaries. Nesting materials
have consisted of teff grass, lucerne stalks, small twigs, notably the dried
midribs of Flamboyant trees (much favoured for providing a splash of colour
along pavements in KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa), pine needles and, in
Zimbabwe, tobacco plant stalks. The only lining, if it has been recorded,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.593221" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293259" page_num="67" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - OLIVE PIGEONS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998641" page_id="56293259"  page_num="67" year="" vol="">
67
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.977573547619048" page_id="56293259"  page_num="67" year="" vol="">
has been dried moss and weeds. By questioning aviculturists employed by
bird gardens and zoos, I have learnt that one to three day old young are
scantly covered with pale golden yellow hair-like down. The eyes open at
five to seven days. At seven to eight days the amount of crop milk fed to the
young is usually reduced and they are fed softened grain and fruit from the
parents' crop.
The Cameroon Olive Pigeon C. sjostedti, more commonly known as the
Cameroon Rameron Pigeon or Sjostedti's Pigeon, feeds on seeds and fruits
of various trees, especially yellowwoods Podocarpus spp. and figs Ficus
spp. The single breeding record is of a nest in the month of May, 8m (approx.
26ft) above the ground in the horizontal fork of a forest tree. The loosely
constructed nest was made of criss-crossed sticks and contained a single
white egg with a smooth, glossy surface. The egg measured 37.9mm x
27.2mm. In captivity a clutch contained two eggs. The incubation period
was 16 days and the nestling period 19 days. Besides the usual commercially
cultivated fruits the birds were offered Wild Plums Harpephyllum caffrum,
cultivated White Mulberries Morus alba and Natal White Figs Ficus
natalensis Syn. F. burkei (Beckx pers. comm.).
The Comoro Olive Pigeon C. pollenii has also been called the Comoro
Pigeon and Comoro Wood Pigeon. It feeds on berries and seeds and probably
also takes insect life, including caterpillars. All of the stomachs that have
been examined have contained fruits; those of birds from Mayotte mostly
the fruits of the stinkwood Octotea sp., which produces acorn-like oval fruits
about 2cm (PAin) long that are in season from February-June or later. Grit
was also present in the stomachs of seven specimens.
This species breeds in dense evergreen forests, with a record of a nest
5m (approx. 16ft) above the ground near the topmost branches of a tree that
had been pollarded and had a close rounded head of young branches. The
male was incubating a fresh egg, which was white with a smooth, glossed
surface. The egg measured 39.7mm x 30.5mm. Occasionally, two eggs
have been recorded. Females examined during August and November have
been found to be holding small yolking oocytes (individual cells, each of
which can produce an ovum or egg). A bird collected in November was no
more than three months old. However, this species probably breeds
throughout the year. There appear to be no records of the Comoro Olive
Pigeon having been bred in captivity.
The Sao Tome Olive Pigeon C. thomensis is also known as the Sao Tome
Maroon Pigeon or Maroon Pigeon. In the wild it has been observed feeding
on the dark red berries of the Montane Tree Schefflera mannii. The only
other type of food recorded being seeds of an unidentified origin. Nothing
appears to be known of its breeding habits in the wild and I have no
knowledge of any being held in captivity.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.984123" page_id="56293260"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
68
</page>
<table confidence="0.2983965" page_id="56293260"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - OLIVE PIGEONS
N. Brickell
African Olive Pigeon nestling
References and bibliography
</table>
<reference confidence="0.993399642857143">
Beeson, C. W. 1960. Birds of the Comoro Islands. Ibis 103b,1:5-106.
Brickell, N. and Konigkramer, T. (eds.). 1997. African Birds in Field &amp; Aviary. African Bird
Book Publishing, Durban, South Africa.
Brown, D. 1995. A Guide to ... Pigeons, Doves and Quail. ABK Publications, Tweed Heads
South, NSW, Australia.
Palgrave, K. C. 1988. Trees of Southern Africa. Strnik Publishers, Cape Town, South Africa.
Rowan, M. K. 1983. The Doves, Parrots, Louries &amp; Cuckoos of Southern Africa. David Phillip
Publishers, Cape Town, South Africa.
Tarboton, W. 2001. A Guide to the Nests and Eggs of Southern African Birds. Struik Publishers,
Cape Town, South Africa.
Uys, C. J. 1967. Breeding of Rameron Pigeon Columba arquatrix. Ostrich 38,3:201-202.
Neville Brickell, 100 Innes Road, Durban 4001, KwaZulu - Natal,
South Africa. Tel/Fax: 031-3129701 (from outside South Africa replace 031
with 27-31)/E-mail: aimests@global.co.za
</reference>
<page confidence="0.997661" page_id="56293261"  page_num="69" year="" vol="">
69
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.764128333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293261" page_num="69" year="" vol="">
VON DER DECKEN'S HORNBILL Tockus deckeni AT THE
OKLAHOMA CITY ZOOLOGICAL PARK
by Chris Smith
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997970756756757" page_id="56293261"  page_num="69" year="" vol="">
Hornbills are a family of birds aptly named for their large distinctively
shaped beaks that curve slightly downward. Those of some species are
adorned by a casque and this and the beak of some species are brightly
coloured and may have vivid patterns. Hornbills are found in a variety of
habitats, ranging from semi-arid savannah to dense tropical rainforests. Most
of the large forest-dwelling species tend to be predominantly frugivorous,
while the smaller brush-dwelling hornbills tend to be generally predominantly
insectivorous or carnivorous. Hornbills are exclusively Old World
inhabitants.
Although hornbills are distinctive in their outward appearance, it is their
breeding behaviour that sets them apart from all other birds. As most if not
all members know, what makes hornbills unique is that the females (with
the exception of the ground hornbills Bucorvus spp.) seal themselves inside
the nest cavity, behind a wall of mud, excreta and items of uneaten food.
Once egg-laying has begun the females moult their flight and tail feathers
and are flightless until new feathers grow. While incubating the eggs and
brooding the chicks, the female is dependent on the male to bring food for
her and the chicks, which is passed in through a narrow slit left in the plaster.
With many of the smaller species, such as Von der Decken's, the female
may spend approximately two months in the nest, after which she breaks
out through the plaster that is then repaired from within by the chicks (using
food and/or excreta), which remain in the nest for several more weeks.
Having left the nest, the female assists the male bringing food for the chicks.
In the case of some of the larger species, the female may remain sealed in
the nest cavity for in excess of 100 days.
The family of hornbills, Bucerotidae, comprises 54 species and is divided
into two subfamilies. Most species belong to the subfamily Bucerotinae,
the typical hornbills. The two species of ground hornbill, which constitute
the subfamily Bucorvinae, differ from the others in that the females do not
seal themselves in the nest cavity.
Von der Decken's Hornbill
Von der Decken's Hornbill Tockus deckeni is one of the smaller species
of hornbill, measuring roughly 47cm (18 72in) long and weighing up to 212g.
Females are generally smaller and weigh slightly less than males. This
hornbill has black upperparts and white underparts, with some white on the
wings and white outer tail feathers. The male's bill is mainly red at the base
and pale orange to yellow or ivory at the tip (see photo p.72). That of the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.990987" page_id="56293262"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
70
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.808686" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293262" page_num="70" year="" vol="">
SMITH - VON DER DECKEN'S HORNBILL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991214547619048" page_id="56293262"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
female is wholly black and is proportionally smaller.
Von der Decken's Hornbill is found in semi-arid savannah and open
woodland from central Ethiopia and southern Somalia, southwards through
eastern Kenya to central Tanzania (considered a subspecies by some, but a
full species by others, Jackson's Hornbill T d. jacksoni or T. jacksoni is
found from central Ethiopia to south-east Sudan, north-east Uganda and
north-west Kenya). Von der Decken's Hornbill is sedentary, with pairs
establishing territories.
The diet of Von der Decken's Hornbill consists mainly of insects, but it
also consumes small vertebrates, fruits, berries, seeds and buds. It forages
mostly on the ground. Von der Decken's Hornbill has developed a rather
unusual symbiotic relationship with the Dwarf Mongoose Helogale undulata.
The hornbills forage alongside the mongooses, preying upon insects flushed
out by their activities. The mongooses benefit from the presence of the
hornbills in that the birds warn of potential predators, allowing the mongooses
to spend less time on sentry duty. This relationship has evolved to a point
where each species will wait for the other to begin foraging. Von der Decken's
Hornbills will even go as far as waking their partners by vocalizing loudly
at the entrance to the mongooses' den should they remain inside too long in
the morning.
Von der Decken's Hornbill is considered to be common throughout its
range, that overlaps several national parks and reserves, which should help
ensure the survival of this species.
In captivity
The captive population of Von der Decken's Hornbills in North American
institutions is quite modest, with at June 2001, according to the International
Species Information System, 56 (26.22.8) specimens. This number does
not include birds that are in private collections.
Oklahoma City Zoological Park has exhibited Von der Decken's Hornbills
since 1989, when a wild caught pair was added to the zoo's animal collection.
The birds were housed in an enclosure that measured roughly 4m wide x 3m
deep x 4m high (13ft wide x 9ft 9in deep x 13ft high).
The diet offered by the zoo consists of a blended predominately fruit
mix (chopped apples, grapes, carrots, oranges, raisins, corn kernels and
celery), soaked Wayne Bite dog food, ZuPreem Marmoset Diet, Nebraska
Bird of Prey Diet, chopped hard-boiled egg, Apple Paradise pellets, soaked
Mazuri Monkey Crunch 20 biscuits, live crickets, mealworms and
waxworms. Two vitamin supplements, Vionate and Osteo-form, are added
to the diet on a daily basis.
The hornbills hatched their first chicks within a year of their arrival. For
the next several years, the pair continued reproducing, until the male died in
1995. Fortunately, a new male was acquired from Denver Zoo later that
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.441899" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293263" page_num="71" year="" vol="">
SMITH - VON DER DECKEN'S HORNBILL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998563" page_id="56293263"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
71
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998895880952381" page_id="56293263"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
year. The new male was introduced to the female without any difficulties
and the pair has since become quite prolific, producing 17 offspring to date.
In December 1998, the zoo's hornbill programme nearly took a turn for
the worse when the female suffered a broken left leg. Despite the efforts of
the veterinary staff, the female's leg would not heal properly and the hornbill
did not help matters by frequently picking at the bandages and cast. After
six months of unsuccessful treatments, the hornbill's foot was amputated.
The female recovered and adapted to a continued productive life despite
having only one foot.
The exhibit
Although the enclosure the hornbills resided in was suitable for their
needs, the birds were removed from the exhibit while it was remodelled in
the spring of 2001. The new exhibit has been designed to better feature the
breeding biology of hornbills. Therefore it is centred on the nest site, which
is a large semi-circular section of a cottonwood tree Populus sp.,
approximately 1.7m (6ft 3in) in height and 70cm (2ft 4in) in diameter.
Although the tree had been dead for several months, the exterior was solid
and it appeared to have rotted from the inside. A nest-box was built into the
tree from behind, with the top and bottom cut to fit the interior perimeter of
the tree and with the back of the box flush with the back of the tree. An
opening approximately 10cm (4in) in diameter was cut in the tree as the
entrance to the box, in which was placed pine bark mulch before it was
attached to the tree.
To showcase this aspect of the hornbill's life cycle, two small Achiever
Security System surveillance cameras were installed in the nest-box. One
was placed on the top of the box to provide an overview of the nest and the
other was mounted at the side of the nest, with holes drilled through which
the cameras could film activity in the nest. The camera cables were run
through a PVC pipe, which led from the tree and along the ceiling of the
exhibit, to monitors mounted outside the exhibit where zoo staff and visitors
could observe activities in the nest. A VCR was also wired into the system,
allowing zoo staff to record activities in the nest and review them at more
convenient hours.
A dead cedar tree Cedrus sp. provides most of the perching for the
hornbills in the exhibit, which is landscaped to resemble arid grassland.
Several varieties of grasses are used including Miscanthus, Andropogon and
Calamagrostis spp. The substrate is topsoil and sand.
On March 29th 2001, the pair of hornbills was introduced into the newly
remodelled exhibit. The birds began investigating the nest-box literally
within a few minutes of their release into the exhibit. The two were frequently
seen performing courtship displays in which each bird would spread its wings
and lower its head while uttering a series of continuous clucks. The male
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.95108" page_id="56293264"  page_num="72" year="" vol="">
72
</page>
<figure confidence="0.466723" page_id="56293264"  page_num="72" year="" vol="">
SMITH - VON DER DECKEN'S HORNBILL
Male Von der Decken's Hornbill
Chris Smith
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.99035819047619" page_id="56293264"  page_num="72" year="" vol="">
was also observed carrying food items to the nest, even though the female
was not inside yet. By April 3rd, construction of the nest entrance had
begun. Both birds were seen working on it, but it appeared that the female
did the majority of the work.
On April 9th, the female had sealed herself in the nest. At this point,
both cameras were providing footage of the bird in the nest. Unfortunately
though, the female noticed the small gap through which the side-mounted
camera was pointed, and began to plaster this opening. For a brief period,
zoo staff and visitors were given the opportunity to view close-up footage
of the hornbill's plastering techniques. Luckily, the camera was undamaged.
The female appeared to be unaware of the opening in the roof of the nest-
box, thus allowing zoo staff and visitors an overhead view of the nesting
behaviour of the hornbill.
The male was observed gathering blades of grasses and delivering them
to the female after she had sealed herself in the nest. The female spent
many hours lining the nest with the grasses to her specifications. The
preferred type appeared to be Miscanthus. On April 15th, the female laid
her first egg. Three days later, a second egg was laid. After yet another three
days, a third egg was laid. A fourth egg was laid, but was seen only when
reviewing the video recordings. The female was very attentive to the eggs.
Only on one occasion was she off the eggs long enough for all four to be
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.435145" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293265" page_num="73" year="" vol="">
SMITH - VON DER DECKEN'S HORNBILL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.980632" page_id="56293265"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
73
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.429194">
Chris Smith
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.983163833333333" page_id="56293265"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
One-footed female
seen. The first chick hatched on May 9th, after a 24 day incubation period.
A second chick was seen three days later, and a third three days after the
second. The fourth chick was not seen in the nest, as the female constantly
covered at least one or two of the chicks. After the first chick hatched, live
insects were offered several times throughout the day. More than enough
insects were offered each day, as there were consistently insects left over
from the previous day.
On May 27th, one of the younger chicks was found dead outside of the
nest-box. Two days later, another dead chick was found ejected from the
nest. One of these was the fourth chick that had not been seen on the monitor.
The two oldest chicks, which were considerably larger than the two younger
chicks, were clearly visible on the monitor. The causes of death of the two
chicks were never determined, but it is reasonable to suspect that they were
out-competed for food, even though there were plenty of insects offered.
The loss of the two chicks was unusual, as the pair had previously reared as
many as five chicks without any losses. The remaining two chicks appeared
to be in good health and were growing rapidly. At about four weeks of age,
they had grown most of their contour feathers and looked like miniature
versions of the adults.
On June 4th, the female exited the nest, 56 days after she had sealed
herself in the nest cavity. The first chick left the nest on June 23rd aged 45
days. The second chick fledged the following day. The chicks continued to
be fed by the adults for the next couple of weeks.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997876" page_id="56293266"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
74
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.831845" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293266" page_num="74" year="" vol="">
SMITH - VON DER DECKEN'S HORNBILL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99722975" page_id="56293266"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
After the chicks left the nest, the video monitor was turned off. Although
the camera and monitor system was in use for less than three months, the
time and resources put into incorporating it into the exhibit was well worth
it. Not only did it provide a means of entertaining and educating zoo visitors,
it also allowed zoo staff to accurately document the nesting cycle of Von der
Decken's Hornbill. The time the female sealed herself in the nest to the time
the first egg was laid was recorded, as well as the precise incubation periods
and fledging dates. Most references list only estimated incubation periods,
often citing the time from when the female was sealed in the nest to when
chicks were first heard in the nest cavity . The surveillance system, which
includes two cameras, a monitor and all the necessary cables, was surprisingly
inexpensive, costing approximately US$90 (#60-#65).
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.478526666666667" page_id="56293266"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
To the Bird Department of Oklahoma City Zoological Park: Darcy
Henthorn, Neil Carter, Mary McFarland, Danny Lawrence and Andy
Middick, Jim Fish, Curator of Birds; Jack Grisham, Director/Animal
Management and Bert Castro, Executive Director/CEO.
Bibliography
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.99088064">
Fry, C.H., Keith, S. and Urban, E.K. 1988. The Birds of Africa. Volume III. Academic Press
Inc., San Diego, USA.
del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A. and Sargatal, J. 2001. Handbook of the Birds of the World Volume 6,
Mousebirds to Hornbills. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona.
Kemp, A. 1995. The Hornbills. Oxford University Press, Inc., New York.
Paterson, L. 1992. Breeding the Von der Decken' s Hornbill at Leeds Castle, Maidstone, Kent
in 1990. Avicultural Magazine 98,2:44-47.
Zimmerman, D., Turner, D.A. and Pearson, D. 1999. Birds of Kenya and Northern Tanzania.
Princeton University Press, Princeton, New Jersey, USA.
Products mentioned in the text
Achiever Security System &amp; Remington Achiever Security System. Manufactured by Achiever
Security, Miami, Florida, USA.
Apple Paradise Food. Manufactured by Marion Zoological, Plymouth, Minnesota, USA.
Mazuri Monkey Crunch 20. Manufactured by PMI Nutrition International Inc., Brentwood,
Missouri, USA.
Osteo-form. Manufactured by Vet-A-Mix, Shenandoah, Iowa, USA.
Vionate Vitamin and Mineral Powder. Manufactured by Gimbom-Rich Health, Atlanta, Georgia,
USA.
Wayne Bite Meat and Bone Meal Formula. Manufactured by Royal Canin USA, Inc., St.
Peters, Missouri, USA.
ZuPreem Marmoset Diet. Produced by Premium Nutritional Products Inc., Mission, Kansas,
USA.
Chris Smith, Bird Department, Oklahoma City Zoological Park, 2102
NE 50th, Oklahoma City, Oklahoma, USA 73111 Tel: (405) 424-3344/Fax:
(405) 425-0243.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.993924" page_id="56293267"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
75
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.794989666666667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293267" page_num="75" year="" vol="">
A SUMMARY OF PITTAS IN EUROPEAN ZOOLOGICAL
COLLECTIONS
by Malcolm Ellis
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996266567567568" page_id="56293267"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
"Pittas have long been popular avicultural subjects, which given the right
conditions do well, expect this is when it comes to breeding. Breeding
successes remain relatively uncommon ..." I wrote in my introduction, when
I reprinted the late Jean Delacour's account of breeding the Hooded Pitta
Pitta sordida (Avicultural Magazine Vol. 103, No.3, pp. 120-123 (1997)), first
published in the magazine in 1934, prior to which no species of pitta had
bred or even nested in captivity.
In the introduction I mentioned that a few years later Delacour succeeded
in breeding Elliot's Pitta P. ellioti. I also mentioned the breeding of the
Bengal or Indian Pitta P, brachyura in Edward Marshall Boehm's aviaries;
the Blue-winged Pitta P moluccensis at the Wildfowl Trust, Slimbridge; the
Hooded Pitta at Birdland, Bourton-on-the-Water and the Banded or Van der
Bosch's Pitta P guajana irena at Blackpool Zoo.
There have been other breedings, some since I wrote the introduction,
and some before 1997 which I was unaware of, or missed, such as the
breeding of the Giant Pitta P. caerulea at San Antonio Zoo, Texas, described
here in the Avicultural Magazine (McKelvey and Miller, 1979). Pittas of
the World - A Monograph on the Pitta Family by Erritzoe and Erritzoe (1998),
has for each species (it lists 30) a section headed - Captivity - from which I
have learnt that 24 Banded Pittas were reared at New York Zoological Park
(presumably in the mid-1970s). All it would seem were hand-reared, after
the earliest nestlings died after the first few days. For more than half of the
species there is no information under this heading, nothing having been
published about them in captivity, mostly because they have never been
kept. This is no longer true, however, of the Garnet Pitta P granatina which
was recently kept by Raymond Sawyer at Cobham; the Black-crowned or
Graceful Pitta P. venusta, of which single examples are currently kept at
Alphen a/d Rijn in the Netherlands and Vogelpark Walsrode, Germany; and
the Elegant Pitta P. elegans , which has recently been bred at Cologne Zoo,
Germany (Pagel, 2000).
Earlier this year, along with the photo of the Black-crowned or Graceful
Pitta (p. 77) taken at Vogelpark Walsrode in 1998, I was sent a copy of a
paper titled Pittas (Pitta spp.) in Europe , summarized as of 30 August 2001,
the work of Marc Damen, Burgers' Zoo, Arnhem, the Netherlands, which
has been very successful recently breeding the Hooded Pitta.
Marc Damen has kindly given me permission to make use of his work,
and what follows are 'edited highlights' of his summary of the seven species
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.985372" page_id="56293268"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
76
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.918811" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293268" page_num="76" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - PITTAS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.978635921052631" page_id="56293268"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
of pitta that are or have been exhibited recently in EAZA (European
Association of Zoos and Aquaria) institutions, plus a few added observations
of my own.
Indian Pitta P. brachyura
Antwerp Zoo, Belgium, had a male Fairy Pitta R b. nympha (treated as
a full species, P. nympha , by Erritzoe and Erritzoe, 1998) from May 1996-
March 2001, when it died . P. brachyura , once a familiar pitta in aviculture,
has with the death of this bird, now disappeared from EAZA collections.
Elegant Pitta R elegans
Cologne Zoo, Germany, received a pair of Elegant Pittas in 1999. In the
Avicultural Magazine , Theo Pagel (2000) described how this pair bred there
in 2000, and illustrated his account with colour photos of the nest, egg,
nestling and first fledged youngster. Marc Damen notes that according to
ISIS there were 1.1.1 at Cologne at the end of September 2001, "with one
birth in 2001."
Banded Pitta P. guajana
Nykpbing, Denmark, acquired a pair of Banded Pittas in 1990. The pair
produced four offspring in 1994, three in 1995 and two in 1998. As of
September 2001, according to ISIS, there were 1.0.3 in the collection.
Vogelpark Walsrode, Germany, acquired three pairs in 1999. Marc
Damen describes them as being of the nominate subspecies, but the Vogelpark
Walsrode Bird Inventory 2000 listed them as the Blue-tailed or Borneo
Banded Pitta P. g. schwaneri. Damen states that three young were raised in
2000, but has no data for 2001. Dr Dieter Rinke informed me in an e-mail
that he is currently preparing an article on the breeding of Banded Pittas at
Walsrode, so we may learn more shortly.
Blue-winged Pitta P. moluccensis
(Treated sometimes, particularly in the past, as a subspecies of P. brachyura )
Alphen a/d Rijn in the Netherlands acquired two pairs in 1990. One
female was exchanged for a male in 1992. Reproduction started in 1992,
when five young were hatched but failed to survive. In 1993 two young
were hatched but also failed to survive. In 1995 a male was acquired from
Chester Zoo and another male from Frankfurt Zoo, but there was no further
breeding. As of September 2001 the male from Chester was the only one
still alive. It was acquired by Chester Zoo in 1987, so is at least 14 years
old.
Frankfurt Zoo, Germany, acquired seven (5.2) Blue-winged Pittas in
1990. They started breeding in 1992, when six young were hatched, three
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.2353885" page_id="56293269"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - PITTAS
77
Copyright Christopher W. Brack
Black-crowned Pitta Pitta venustra photographed at Vogelpark Walsrode in 1998
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.997206142857143" page_id="56293269"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
of which failed to survive. The following year four were hatched but failed
to survive and in 1994, six were hatched, of which four failed to survive.
The surviving offspring were sent to Hong Kong, Alphen and Leipzig. In
1998 five were hatched, three of which were reared and one sent to Krefeld.
As of September 2001 a total of three (2.1) were living at Frankfurt Zoo,
consisting of a pair acquired in 1990 which was therefore at least 11 years
old, and one of the pair's 1998 male offspring.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995521" page_id="56293270"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
78
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.907006" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293270" page_num="78" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - PITTAS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97742687804878" page_id="56293270"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
Walsrode had several of these pittas in the 1990s but by the end of 2000
only one male remained.
Hooded Pitta P. sordida
Alphen a/d Rijn acquired five Hooded Pittas in 1999, three from a Dutch
dealer and two from Arnhem, where they were bred in 1998. As of September
2001 it still had four (0.2.2).
Burgers' Zoo, Arnhem, the Netherlands, acquired four pairs of Hooded
Pittas in 1997. They started breeding the following year when no less than
23 offspring were produced, of which about half had disappeared after some
six months. Others were caught and sent to Alphen a/d Rijn (2), Bristol Zoo
( 3) and Rotterdam Zoo ( 5). During 1999 a further 21 were bred, but again
most of them disappeared. The single youngster that could be caught was
sent to Rotterdam. In 2000 a total of 22 young were seen, of which two
pairs were caught and sent to Chester Zoo. As of September 2001, at least
19 had to date been bred that year, of which 5.3.4 had been caught and 4.2.2
were available to collections with a serious interest in breeding this species.
According to a later report ( Avicultural Magazine Vol.108, No. 11. p.43
(2002)) 26 was the eventual number of young bred, of which just three
failed to survive.
Bristol Zoo, UK, had as of September 2001 a pair of Hooded Pittas, both
birds having been bred at Burgers' Zoo, the male having been sent originally
to Chester Zoo. Hooded Pittas bred at Bristol Zoo in 1999, but only one
young one was reared successfully and in 2000 was sent to London Zoo in
exchange for an unrelated female.
Budapest Zoo, Hungary, had as of September 2001 one bird of which
the sex was unknown.
Chester Zoo, UK, has no Hooded Pittas currently, neither has London
Zoo or Hamburg Zoo, Germany.
Dvur Kralove in the Czech Republic had this species nest in 2000 and
2001, but the four young failed to survive. As of September 2001 it was left
with 1.0.1 Hooded Pittas.
Cologne Zoo, Germany, had as of September 2001, according to ISIS,
0.0.2 Hooded Pittas.
Leipzig Zoo, Germany, has one P. s . cucullata sex unknown, having lost
another at the end of 2000.
Rotterdam Zoo had at September 2001, a female Hooded Pitta from
Burgers' Zoo, the male having died shortly after arriving there.
Walsrode had according to the Vogelpark Walsrode Bird Inventory 2000,
2.5.1 P. s . muelleri, at the end of 2000. It also had a pair of P. s. cucullata ,
which it acquired in 1999 and that nested the same year, but the offspring
died.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.611567" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293271" page_num="79" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - PITTAS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99707" page_id="56293271"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
79
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.994241" page_id="56293271"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
Warsaw Zoo, Poland, has a pair of Hooded Pittas.
Wuppertal Zoo, Germany, acquired 2.1 P. s. muelleri in 1993 that made
several breeding attempts but never managed to raise any young. As of
September 2001 it continued to keep 2.1 P. s. muelleri.
Marc Damen believes that the Hooded Pitta is the only species of pitta
that, if managed carefully, may have a long term future in EAZA collections.
Blue-crowned Pitta P. soror
Alphen a/d Rijn acquired 1.2 Blue-crowned Pittas, the male of which
died in 1998, leaving it with, as of September 2001, according to ISIS, the
two females.
Black-crowned or Graceful Pitta P. venusta
Alphen a/d Rijn had as of September 2001, according to ISIS, one Black-
crowned Pitta, another having died in 1999, two years after arriving there.
Walsrode had according to the Vogelpark Walsrode Bird Inventory 2000,
one bird listed as a Graceful Pitta, at the end of 2000. It is presumably the
same bird as that in the photograph taken there in 1998.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.956993" genericHeader="references" page_id="56293271" page_num="79" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.8783246">
Erritzoe, J. and Erritzoe, H. 1998. Pittas of the World A Monograph on the Pitta Family. The
Lutterworth Press, Cambridge, UK.
McKelvey, S.D. amd Miller, B.W. 1979. Breeding the Giant Pitta at the San Antonio Zoo.
Avicultural Magazine 85,3:109-111.
Pagel, T. 2000. Notes on keeping and breeding the Elegant Pitta Pitta elegans. Avicultural
</reference>
<figure confidence="0.3821142" page_id="56293271"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
Magazine 106,4:165-169.
Acknowledgements
My thanks to Marc Damon for allowing me to freely make use of
information in Pittas (Pitta spp.) in Europe, summarized as of 30 August
2001. Marc Damen can be contacted at: Burgers' Zoo, B. V. - Schelmseweg
85, 6816 SH Arnhem, Netherlands. Tel: (026) 4 42 45 34/Fax: (026) 4 43
07 76/ E-mail: m.damen@burgerszoo.nl
Footnote
Daniel Shearing has drawn my attention to Breeding the Hooded Pitta
Pitta sordida by Bob Beeson, published in Foreign Birds 65,4:152 (Winter
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.950879285714286" page_id="56293271"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
1999). The first nest contained four eggs, three of which hatched only for the
chicks to be ejected. The second clutch also contained four eggs of which
only one hatched and the chick was found dead 14 days later. The third nest
contained five eggs all of which hatched. Three chicks died within the first
week. One of the remaining two left the nest on the 13th day and the other on
the 15th day. One died on the 18th day; the other was reared successfully and
could fly at 20 days and was seen feeding itself at 30 days.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.989851" page_id="56293272"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
80
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.744836" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293272" page_num="80" year="" vol="">
THE PRESIDENT'S GARDEN PARTY 2001
by Stewart Pyper
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987181368421052" page_id="56293272"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
The President's Garden Party 2001 was held on Sunday, July 15th, once
again by kind invitation of our President Miss Ruth Ezra and Vice President
Raymond Sawyer. Almost 80 members and their guests journeyed to
Cobham, including several who were there for the first time. The weather
in England last summer was variable, so we were fortunate that on the day
of our visit, except for a few spots of rain early in the afternoon which sent
members and their guests hurrying to get macs and umbrellas, the weather
was pleasant, though the temperature was below average.
One of the changes that had taken place since our last visit is that the
lakeside aviary has a new walkway (to do this a hedge has been removed)
and this makes viewing the birds much easier. The aviary houses Superb
Starlings, melanistic Stella's Lorikeets, Scarlet Ibis, Swainson's Jays and a
Collared Jay. Raymond was warned that Swainson' s Jays can be particularly
dangerous when approaching breeding condition and will attack even
pheasants.
The aviary which used to house the Red-billed Choughs now houses a
pair of Southern Ground Hornbills. We were surprised to see them as we do
not normally associate Raymond with keeping hornbills. When first acquired
the pair had damaged the wire netting but by the time of our visit had settled
in. The four aviaries in the paddock have been rebuilt and there are separate
pairs of Red-billed Choughs in three of them. All three pairs built nests but
went no farther, having been moved there only just before Easter. It is
hoped they will breed successfully this year.
At the time of our visit, Avocets, Black-necked Stilts, Green
Woodhoopoes, Red-billed Choughs and Pink-necked Fruit Doves had bred.
The latter is believed to be either the first or second UK breeding of the
Pink-necked Fruit Dove. After seeing those at Cobham, Rosemary Wiseman
expressed doubt about whether her birds, which bred earlier, are the same
species that Raymond has bred.
In the tropical house a pair of Spangled Cotingas built a 'nest' on one of
the girders. The use of inverted commas is because it was such an awful
attempt at nest building. The single egg failed to hatch. Some members
may recollect that for many years Raymond had two male Purple-throated
Fruit Crows. He now has a pair that has carried nesting material but has yet
to build a nest. The two have an aviary to themselves, that has a heated
shelter into which they are shut on all but the warmest summer nights. The
pair of Toco Toucans looked lovely and Raymond had found a mate for his
remaining Keel-billed Toucan.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.583051" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293273" page_num="81" year="" vol="">
PYPER - PRESIDENT'S GARDEN PARTY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99757" page_id="56293273"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
81
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997100037037037" page_id="56293273"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
The colony of eight Carmine Bee-eaters, that had been put outside in the
waterfall aviary in early June, was a magnificent sight. The birds respond
to Raymond's call to be fed mealworms, which he throws up into the air and
they catch. It is an incredible sight to see in a Surrey garden. As we were
about to leave they were swooping to catch insects over the pool. We also
saw Blue-bearded, Red-bearded and White-throated Bee-eaters. The
Chestnut-collared Kingfisher sat motionless the entire time I spent in the
six indoor flights in which I can recall seeing wood swallows, niltavas, Red-
headed Tits, Hooded Pittas, Purple Honeycreepers, various sunbirds and
tanagers, and a male Ruby-Topaz Hummingbird, that obliged us by flying
about so that we could admire its iridescent plumage.
Barbary Shrikes or Yellow-crowned Gonoleks were seen, as were several
pairs of Bartlett's or Mindanao Bleeding Hearts, the old pair of African
Pygmy Geese, Roulroul Partridges, numerous starlings including the Golden-
breasted or Royal, Fairy Bluebirds and at least three Blue-winged Mountain
Tanagers. In 2001 the Blue-bellied Rollers failed to rear their young.
During tea Prof. J. R. (Bob) Hodges, one of our Vice Presidents and a
former Hon. Editor of the magazine, thanked Ruth and Raymond for their
wonderful hospitality and great generosity in donating approx. #550
(US$800), the proceeds of ticket sales, to the society's funds.
As always there was so much to see and admire, including the tortoises,
some very impressive Koi, lots of bonsai and, of course, the beautiful gardens
and all the other plants. If you have not yet visited Cobham, or it was some
time since your last visit, may I suggest that you make an effort to join us
there this year on Sunday, July 14th.
Whilst looking through some back issues of the magazine for a member,
I came across the following notice attached to the July 1926 issue.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.59397" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56293273" page_num="81" year="" vol="">
GARDEN PARTY AT FOXWARREN PARK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990510909090909" page_id="56293273"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
"This was to have been held on 15th May, but was postponed on account
of the strike. It is now to take place on Saturday, 24th July, and Mr. and Mrs.
Ezra have most kindly invited members of the Society to attend."
"A char-a-banc will leave no. 17 Knightsbridge (two doors west of Hyde
Park Tube Station) at 2.15pm, punctually, and all who intend to be present
are requested to notify the Hon. Secretary, Miss Knobel, 32 Tavistock Square,
W.C.l. Not later than 19th July."
The strike referred to was the General Strike of 1926 and a char-a-banc
(pronounced sharabang) was an old-fashioned motor coach. It was the first
year of Alfred Ezra's Presidency of the Avicultural Society and it is possible
that last year's visit to Cobham was the 75th Anniversary of the first visit.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994753" page_id="56293274"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
82
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.651985" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293274" page_num="82" year="" vol="">
THE SOCIETY'S VISIT TO CHESTER ZOO
by Stewart Pyper
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.988840789473684" page_id="56293274"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
The society's Spring Social Meeting at Chester Zoo was postponed
because of the outbreak of foot and mouth disease in the UK, and members
and their guests visited the zoo eventually on Sunday, September 2nd 2001.
The arrangements were made by council member Dr Roger Wilkinson,
General Curator: Higher Vertebrates and Research at Chester Zoo. Some
areas of the zoo continued to be off-limits, including the Asian Elephant
House in which a pair of Great Hombills is housed, otherwise all of the
birds were on view. As Bird Notes from Chester Zoo, 2001, written by
Roger, appeared in the previous issue (Avicultural Magazine Vol. 108, No. 1,
pp.24-31), I will limit my notes to certain birds.
The highlight perhaps was seeing the four young Blue-winged
Kookaburras with their proud parents. This species is smaller than the more
common Laughing Kookaburra and more colourful. A constant stream of
visitors was walking past the aviary but the birds remained unconcerned.
Roger said that this species has been bred at Dublin Zoo, but the success at
Chester is almost certainly a UK first breeding.
The Islands in Danger exhibit is an aviculturist's delight. We were able
to view the pair of Red Birds of Paradise that came from Bronx Zoo, New
York. Still not yet in adult plumage, the pair are the only birds of paradise
on show here in the UK. Occupying the floor of their flight is a pair of
Green-naped Pheasant Pigeons, that blended very well with the vegetation.
Another flight houses a pair of rare St Lucia Amazons, which would not
come forward to be viewed. A third flight houses a pair of Stella's Lorikeets
and a White-collared Kingfisher, as well as a pair of White-naped Pheasant
Pigeons. The aviaries extend right up to the roof and viewing was very
good. An enclosure away from the birds houses a Komodo Dragon.
It is always an interesting experience to visit the Tropical Realm in which
a large number of birds inhabit the free-flight area and others are housed in
enclosures within it. Both Great and Rhinoceros Hombills have large flights
but have yet to reward their keepers by reproducing successfully. Tarictic
Hombills had reproduced and we were taken behind the scenes to view on a
television monitor young in the nest-box, filmed by a camera placed in the
top of it. It is hoped that this camera and those placed in other hornbill nest-
boxes will provide valuable information about their nesting behaviour from
which lessons can be learnt. A Vietnamese Pheasant chick had been raised
successfully for the first time at Chester Zoo.
The colony of Humboldt Penguins had been allowed to produce a large
number of young in order to provide birds for the new exhibit at Emmen
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.256689" page_id="56293275"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
PYPER - CHESTER ZOO
</equation>
<page confidence="0.998154" page_id="56293275"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
83
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.992759142857143" page_id="56293275"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
Zoo in the Netherlands. Some years the number has been limited to just one
or two because Chester birds are already well represented in the EEP
population. We met Karen Davies, the zoo's most experienced penguin
keeper, who in 2000 went to South Africa to help care for the many thousands
of penguins rescued following the oil spill disaster there.
Chester Zoo's record with flamingos is excellent and it was a joy to
view the wonderful colony of perhaps a 100 or so Caribbean and Chilean
Flamingos. Europe on the Edge houses a vast collection of birds, including
White Storks which had reared two young. I also saw Condor Cliffs, the
Andean Condor exhibit, which Roger wrote about in the Avicultural
Magazine Vol. 103, No.l, pp.1-3 (1997). It is just one of a number of new
exhibits that had been built since our previous visit in July 1996.
Roger was especially pleased that the zoo had bred two Red-tailed
Amazons and had again been successful with the Mount Apo Lorikeets. He
explained that some of the older parrot aviaries are due to be replaced soon,
showed us the Bat House and the latest addition at Chester - the Jaguar
Exhibit - sponsored by Jaguar Cars now part of the Ford Motor Company.
It was due to be officially opened a few days after our visit. Our thanks go
to Roger, General Curator: Operations, Mark Pilgrim, Team Leader, Wayne
McCloud and other members of the staff who showed us around and answered
the many and varied questions asked of them.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8742705" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293275" page_num="83" year="" vol="">
THE SOCIETY'S SECOND VISIT TO THE NATURAL
HISTORY MUSEUM
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.477">
by Stewart Pyper
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.969735928571429" page_id="56293275"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
On Tuesday, October 30th 2001, the society visited the Ornithology
Department of the Natural History Museum at Tring. It was our second
visit. A report on the first visit appeared in Vol. 104, No.3, p. 133 (1998). Dr
Prys-Jones made the arrangements for our visit and welcomed us. Only
when one visits the museum does one appreciate the size of the collection,
which was moved to Tring from South Kensington, London, in the 1960s.
It has over one million specimens of about 95% of the known bird species,
and is the third largest skin collection in the world. It also has about one
million eggs, 17,000 specimens preserved in spirit, over 14,000 skeletons
and 2,000 nests. There is a wealth of historical material collected by
naturalists including Audubon and Darwin.
The library is fantastic and we were privileged to be able to view volumes
by Gould and Lear, and the original plates painted by Commander A. N.
Hughes for a special edition of Smythies' Birds of Borneo. Viewing some
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.9941" page_id="56293276"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
84
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.699502" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293276" page_num="84" year="" vol="">
PYPER - NATURAL HISTORY MUSEUM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.971031071428571" page_id="56293276"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
of the magnificent hand-coloured plates in Gould's Monograph of the
Trochilidae (Hummingbirds), we could only marvel at the way the wonderful
iridescent plumage was portrayed. We thought the Purple-throated Carib
especially outstanding.
Mark Adams is in charge of the bird skins and showed us a tray containing
Darwin's finches, whose differences played such a vital role in the
formulation of Darwin's theory of evolution. We were also shown a selection
of blue macaws, including Lear's and Spix's. All skins are tagged with a
label stating when, where and who collected them. It would have been
wonderful to have spent more time examining the skins and noting the great
names from the past, who played such an important part in the assembling
of this great collection. It could be said that every label tells a story.
The planned two hour tour turned out to be two and three-quarter hours
long, as various questions were asked of Robert Prys-Jones and his colleagues
Mark Adams, Jo Cooper, Michael Walters (who has worked there with eggs
and nests for over 30 years) and Alison Harding the librarian.
The Bird Group has offered to help members whenever possible, and
any enquiries should be addressed to: The Bird Group, Dept, of Zoology,
The Natural History Museum, Akeman Street, Tring, Herts. HP23 6AP.
Tel:0207 9426158/Fax:0207 9426150/Email:rpp@nhm.ac.uk The same
means should be used to contact the museum should any member have
material such as dead birds or eggs, which he or she think may be of interest
to the museum.
Visits are normally restricted to those whether amateur or professional,
engaged in original research or the production of artwork intended for
publication. The society hopes to arrange another visit in three or four years'
time. If you missed this and the previous visit, I suggest that if we are
fortunate enough to be invited back again, you make sure that you attend.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.631091" page_id="56293276"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99072" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56293276" page_num="84" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINES BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.966749333333333" page_id="56293276"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
A large stock is available including some early issues. Further details
are available from: Hon. Secretary/Treasurer, The Avicultural Society,
P.O. Box 47, Edenbridge, KentTN8 7WP, UK or e-mail:lee.palm@ virgin.net
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995823" page_id="56293277"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
85
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998874" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293277" page_num="85" year="" vol="">
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998668125" page_id="56293277"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
Nigel Hewston writes: In his interesting article on laughingthrushes in
Vol.107, No.4, pp. 152-156 (2001), Philip Schofield touched on their
interactions with other species in aviaries. When I first encountered this
group the only species regularly available was the White-crested, which
was, like the Greater Necklaced, recognised as an unsuitable companion for
smaller birds. A number of the smaller species available more recently have
often been housed, and in some cases bred, with smaller species with few
problems (though they can sometimes be aggressive to larger birds such as
turacos), but recent experiences with a pair of Black-faced Garrulax affinis
will lead me to be very cautious about mixing laughingthrushes in the future.
I received five of these birds last May among a number of birds I had
agreed to house for another member while he rebuilt his aviaries. One pair
was housed in a small aviary with no other birds in it, a second pair went
into a large aviary with a range of smaller birds, and a single female was put
into another mixed flight. Neither pair bred, and in the autumn the pair that
had been housed alone was moved into an aviary containing pairs of Omei
Shan Liocichlas Liocichla omeiensis and Rufous-winged Fulvettas Alcippe
castaneiceps and a male White-tailed Robin Cine l id turn leucumm . Following
the moult this pair seemed to appreciate the larger aviary and really came
into condition, by December behaving as I would expect birds to behave in
March or April, but with no obvious aggression shown towards the other
birds. You have no doubt guessed what comes next and may be thinking
that housing laughingthrushes with fulvettas is pretty silly anyway, but these
birds had been housed with fuvettas and other small birds in a much smaller
aviary over a long period before they came to me, with no problems.
During a period of cold weather in January I found a fulvetta dead and
partially eaten. With no aggression observed and not having seen both
fulvettas for a few days in the well-planted aviary I assumed the bird had
succumbed to weather or disease and then been partially eaten by mice or
by the laughingthrushes, which spent a lot of time foraging on the aviary
floor. However, a week or so later I found the robin dead. I knew that this
bird had been alive and well the day before, and on checking thoroughly (as
I had on the first occasion) and failing to find any signs of mammal entry It
was obvious that the laughingthrushes were to blame. They had not just
killed but also eaten the bird very efficiently, leaving the skeleton completely
stripped but in one piece complete with tail and flight feathers, the only
damage being a large hole in the back of the skull. The laughingthrushes
were Isolated in another aviary and three months later there have been no
more losses.
The other three birds have caused no problems, even though the second
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994444" page_id="56293278"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
86
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998912" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293278" page_num="86" year="" vol="">
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996454" page_id="56293278"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
pair was carrying nesting material in February. I suspect that this species
will prove to be an early breeder, though I won't be finding out as I'm
relieved to say they are going home very soon, though they are lovely birds
which I would be very happy to keep had I room to house them alone. I
suppose this tale is just a reminder of how dramatically birds' behaviour can
change when they come into breeding condition. The fulvettas are amazingly
hardy for such tiny birds, this was their fifth or sixth winter outdoors (though
their first with me). They fledged chicks last year and the survivor is still
very fit.
News &amp; Views in the same magazine included mention of the breeding
of the Verditer Flycatcher Muscicapa (or Eumyiasl) thalassina at Paradise
Park. There is a useful website on this species set up by one of the Avian
Interest Groups of AAZPA (the American Association of Zoological Parks
and Aquaria) which includes a comparison of the husbandry techniques of
three successful breeders, and links to hand-rearing protocols for yuhinas
and niltavas. A husbandry review viewable as a download from the site
includes details of a successful breeding by Jim Collins in 1991, which is
the earliest published UK breeding I have come across. The site can be
visited at: www.csew.com/flycatcher, or if you go via the Riverbanks Zoo
site, at: www.riverbanks.org/aig you can also access sites on a number of
other bird groups.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.826233" page_id="56293278"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.93665" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56293278" page_num="86" year="" vol="">
INCREASE IN THE NUMBER OF MACAWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996805307692308" page_id="56293278"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
The number of Lear's Macaws Anodorhynchus lean is slowly increasing
in the small area of north-eastern Brazil to which this species in endemic,
thanks to the efforts of many individuals and organisations, including
BioBrasil, the IB AM A, local landowner Fundagao Garcia D'Avila and the
World Parrot Trust. A survey early last year recorded 246 birds, an increase
of more than 30% since the previous survey in the late 1990s when 170
were seen.
The Disney Conservation Initiative has recently made a substantial
donation towards the conservation of this splendid macaw. This money
will be used for ongoing habitat creation through growing more Licuri Palms,
the nuts of which are an essential food source for the macaws, the protection
of nest sites and for continuing work compiling a photographic record of
each individual bird.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998471" page_id="56293279"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
87
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9937665" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293279" page_num="87" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
PIONUS PARROTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99642396969697" page_id="56293279"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
When I was asked to review this new book, I was rather hesitant at first,
as I thought "another book on parrots" - but I was pleasantly surprised for
Rosemary Low's latest book as its title states is solely about the Piones
group of parrots. It gives details of all Pionus species and includes subspecies.
Over the years Rosemary has kept or had in her care all of the parrots in this
group. I can recall seeing her pair of Massena's that at the time was the only
pair I knew of in the UK and still have the slide that I took of the pair. She
also recalls Raymond Sawyer's mutation Pionus which he had at Cobham
that often caused auguments as to which species it was!
The chapter titled Care and Housing has good advice on building aviaries,
floor coverings, etc. Diet and nutrition covers seed mixtures, pulses, fruits,
vegetables and greenfoods suitable for these birds. Rosemary also gives a
good rearing diet and, finally in this section, mention is made of vitamin A
which is a must to help avoid E. coli and aspergillosis infections. In the
early days a number of Pionus were sadly lost to aspergillosis because of
the lack of information available then.
The chapter on breeding for a change hardly mentions incubation and
hand~rearing, but does give egg weights and lengths of incubation, as well
as chicks' growth rates. The one thing that I always avoid regarding nest-
boxes is screwing pieces of wood on the inside to act as a ladder for the
female to climb up and down. I always glue my pieces of wood (using
wood glue) to avoid, as happened many years ago, a youngster loosing an
eye on a screw that was protruding, after the female has chewed the wood
away.
The chapters titled Pets and Health Care are very informative, and suggest
ways to occupy birds with things they can chew and play with. In the Wild
gives details of habitat, food and the status of each species. Finally all the
species are dealt with separately, with a description of each species and
subspecies, as well as a distribution map for each species.
Pionus Parrots by Rosemary Low, published by Dona, has a soft cover,
78 pages and 24 colour photographs and is a book I can fully recommend.
It is priced #11.95 including postage and is well worth it. It is available
from leading avicultural booksellers and from Rosemary Low, P.O. Box
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.46715">
100, Mansfield, Notts. NG20 9NZ, UK.
Cliff Wright
</reference>
<page confidence="0.997093" page_id="56293280"  page_num="88" year="" vol="">
88
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.885891" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293280" page_num="88" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
PHEASANTS, PARTRIDGES &amp; GROUSE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.966888947368421" page_id="56293280"  page_num="88" year="" vol="">
Sub-titled A Guide to the Pheasants, Partridges, Quails, Grouse,
Guineafowl, Buttonquails and Sandgrouse of the World , this the latest of the
Helm Identification Guides covers 253 species including the Australian
Plains-wanderer. The main authors are Steve Madge, author of two earlier
Helm Identification Guides, Waterfowl and Crows and Jays, and Phil
McGowan Conservation Director for the World Pheasant Association (WPA).
There are 72 colour plates which appear to illustrate all 253 species and
show the male (an exception is Hoogerwerf's Pheasant (which may prove
to be a subspecies of Salvadori's Pheasant) of which only the female has
been formally described), female, juvenile and subspecies when appropriate.
The plates are the work of Norman Arlott, Robin Budden, Daniel Cole,
John Cox, Carl D'Silva, Kim Franklin and Daniel Mead. There is variation
in their styles, with the work of some of them being more pleasing than that
of others.
The 253 species accounts include most of the information one expects
to find in such an identification guide. There are alternative names, features
that help distinguish the species from similar looking birds, a description of
the adult male, adult female and juvenile, followed by a description or
descriptions of any subspecies (under the heading Geographical Variation);
measurements and weights are also given. There is a description of each
species' habitat, its voice, habits, breeding behaviour, distribution, status,
and the reference sources are cited at the end of each species account.
Of most interest to aviculturists are likely to be the species descriptions
and those of subspecies along with the breeding data, which include the
clutch size, description of the eggs and length of incubation of each species.
When this is unknown in the wild, information from captive breeding is
given, if known. References sources include the Avicultural Magazine.
The birds covered in this guide belong to some of the most threatened of
all avian groups. The authors note that a recent assessment of the status of
the pheasants considered no fewer than 50% to be at risk of extinction. The
part dealing with the status of each species is often quite extensive and
based on recent information. It makes interesting reading and is the part I
am sure I will refer back to most frequently.
Pheasants, Partridges and Grouse by Steve Madge and Phil McGowan
with Guy M. Kirwan (488 pages), published by Christopher Helm, London,
has a recommended retail price of #45. The fact that it covers such a wide
range of species will undoubtedly make this guide especially attractive to
aviculturists interested in such birds.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.477041">
Malcolm Ellis
</subsectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996947" page_id="56293281"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
89
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.844668" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293281" page_num="89" year="" vol="">
THE SOCIETY ADOPTS A PAIR OF HORNBILLS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9938755625" page_id="56293281"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society has adopted a pair of Bushy-crested Hornbills
Anorrhinus galeritus living in the wild in Thailand. It has done so through
the Hornbill Research Foundation (HRF) in Bangkok, which administers
this very successful project in and around Budo-Sangai Padi National Park
in the south of the country.
Local villagers, some of whom may have been poachers who sold hornbill
chicks in the past, receive payment for protecting the nests and collecting
valuable data for HRF researchers. Following the breeding season, the
nesting results are sent to each individual donor. They also receive photos
of their hornbill or hornbills at the nest, a photo of the villager who observed
their particular family and photos of some of the types of food that the male
hornbill brought to the nest. The nesting results and photos of our pair of
hornbills will be available later in the year and it is hoped to publish these in
the magazine. Further information about the HRF and its nest adoption
programme can be found by visiting the Coraciiformes TAG website:
www.coraciiformestag.com/ and clicking on to the link to the HRF.
The decision to adopt a pair of hornbills, and to also look into making a
donation towards helping to fund research on the Yellow-throated
Laughingthrush in China, was taken by the council at its recent meeting. It
followed the earlier decision to donate money, from time to time, towards
conservation and research and other worthy causes. As an example of the
latter, a donation was made to the NCA (National Council for Aviculture),
towards funding its representation to government on the proposed Animal
Welfare Bill.
The amount of money available for such donations is quite small, so any
donations will of necessity be fairly small and the projects will be chosen
with great care, and preferably be aviculture related. We hope these plans
have the support of the majority of members and those making donations to
the society will in future indicate whether they wish all or part of their
donation to go towards funding conservation and research. Any person or
organisation wishing to be considered for help with funding should in the
first instance send details to the Hon. Editor.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.362598" page_id="56293281"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<reference confidence="0.795496">
IS IT A FIRST?
Martin Vince, Assistant Curator of Birds, Riverbanks Zoo and Garden,
South Carolina, USA, has e-mailed to say that the zoo has bred a Blue-
winged Leafbird Chloropsis cochinchinensis, and wonders if anyone has
bred this species before?
</reference>
<page confidence="0.990648" page_id="56293282"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
90
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9791445" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293282" page_num="90" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
GREATER SUCCESS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986556142857143" page_id="56293282"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
Greater Bird of Pardise Paradisaea apoda , Red Bird of Paradise P. rubra,
Kagu Rhynochetos jubatus and Madagascar Crested Ibis Lophotibis cristata
were bred during 2001 for the first time at Vogelpark Walsrode, Germany.
Great Blue Turaco Corythaeola cristata hatched chicks, one of which was
found dead after approximately 24 days, but it was not reported if the others
were reared to independence. It was also reported that Andean Cock-of-
the-Rock Rupicola peruviana had laid an egg.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.840446" page_id="56293282"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.842542" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293282" page_num="90" year="" vol="">
SPIX'S MACAW UPDATE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.982102777777778" page_id="56293282"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
It was reported ( Cyanopsitta No. 63, p.8, December 2001) that the
Brazilian environmental authority, the IBAMA, has requested that the Loro
Parque Fundacion transfer one of its two female Spix's Macaws Cyanopsitta
spixii (held with a single male at the LPF parrot breeding centre) to Mauricio
dos Santos' collection at Criadero Chaparral, Recife, Brazil. It has also
requested the transfer of a female from Roland Messer's collection in
Switzerland to Sao Paulo Zoo in Brazil, and that of a male from Sao Paulo
Zoo to Roland Messer's collection. This will establish three new pairs. The
above would seem to suggest that Sao Paulo Zoo presently has at least two
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.648449666666667" page_id="56293282"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
Spix's Macaws, rather than the one reported in the previous issue ( Avicultural
Magazine Vol. 108, No.l, p.45).
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.955465" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293282" page_num="90" year="" vol="">
SOUTH OF THE BORDER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998891666666667" page_id="56293282"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
More than 300 species, over 80% of North American migrant bird
species, winter in Mexico. To help assess the status of some of these and
some resident Mexican species, Cornell Laboratory of Ornithology has
appointed Dr Eduardo Inigo, a prominent and respected Mexican
ornithologist and conservationist, to compile statistics on the number of
wild birds captured there for the cage bird trade. Concern centres mainly
around parrots and finches, such as the Painted or Nonpariel Bunting
Passerina ciris - a favourite with Mexican trappers - which has declined by
60% in the USA during the past 35 years. He will attempt to document the
extent of this trade and its potential effect on the species' overall decline
and help determine how this trade should be regulated both nationally and
internationally.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.699384" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293283" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.984221" page_id="56293283"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
91
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.987808" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293283" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
SECOND GENERATION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9939478" page_id="56293283"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
Ian Hinze has phoned to say that despite having moved house and had
builders working in his new home for months, he has succeeded in breeding
his Mali or Kulikoro Firefinches Lagonosticta virata through to the second
generation, and as so to confirm the breeding, in the background the young
could be heard being fed by their parents.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.854151" page_id="56293283"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.722788" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293283" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
PLANTAIN-EATER PREFERS WILLOW-HERB
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9274787" page_id="56293283"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
To date 14 Western Grey Plantain-eaters Crinifer piscator have been
raised at the Cots wold Wildlife Park, Oxon. The first nine chicks failed to
survive past 12 days and others have also been lost. It has been noticed that
it is only when the parents have access to Rose-bay Willow-herb Epilobium
angustifolium growing in the aviary on which to feed (along with a variety
of other plants and whole lettuce spiked on branches), that they succeed in
rearing their young successfully. The Cotswold Wildlife Park achieved the
second breeding of this West African species in the UK, the first breeding
being credited to F. Tamms in 1989. One kept at London Zoo in the late
1950s was very fond of the leaves of hawthorn Crataegus sp.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.408597" page_id="56293283"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.573651789473684" page_id="56293283"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
A LONG LIST OF SUCCESSES
Species bred at San Diego Zoo and San Diego Wild Animal Park during
2001 included a Cardinal Lory Chalcopsitta cardinalis , nine Blue-crowned
Lory Vini australis , three Pesquet's Parrot Psittrichasfulgidus, two Double-
eyed Fig Parrot Cyclopsittta diophthalma , three Horned Parrakeet
Eunymphicus cornutus, three Great Blue Turaco Corythaeola cristata, nine
White-fronted Bee-eater Merops bullockoides, two Purple or Rufous-
crowned Roller Coracias naevia, three Racquet-tailed C. spatulata, seven
Blue-bellied C. cyanogaster , six Bearded Barbet Lybius dubius, five Boehm's
Barbet Trachyphonus darnaudii boehmi, three Malaysian Long-tailed
Broadbill Psarisomus dalhousiae psittacinus, four Guianan White-bearded
Manakin Manacus manacus, one Spangled Cotinga Cotinga cayana, two
Collared Finchbill Spizixos semitorques , four Ruby-throated Bulbul
Pycnonotus melanicterus dispar , two Orange-bellied Euphonia Euphonia
xanthogaster, two Turquoise Tanager Tangara mexicana, seven Metallic
Starling Aplonis metallica, two Golden-breasted Starling Cosmopsarus regius
magnificus , two White-breasted Wood Swallow Artamus leucorhychus
amydrus, three Superb Bird of Paradise Lophorina superba feminina and a
Magnificent Bird of Paradise Diphyllodes magnificus hunsteini.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995172" page_id="56293284"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
92
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9815115" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293284" page_num="92" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
RECORD NUMBER OF YOUNG REARED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985547527777778" page_id="56293284"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
A grand total of 1,104 young were raised in 2001 at Loro Parque, Tenerife,
a 30% increase on the previous record of 853 young reared there in 2000.
Twenty-six species and subspecies of lory produced 90 chicks. These
included five rarely bred Cardinal Lories Chalcopsitta cardinalis. Musk
Lorikeets Glossopsitta concinna hatched eight chicks and the number of
Yellow-bibbed Lories Lorius chlorocerus increased by four. The Emerald
Lories Neopsittacus pullicauda hatched two chicks. Six Rosenberg's
Lorikeets Trichoglossus haematodus rosenbergi were bred and three
Johnstone's or Mt Apo Lorikeets T. johnstoniae, for which the Loro Parque
Fundacion holds the European Studbook. The fundacion now has 16 of the
latter. Two pairs of Blue-crowned Lory Vini australis hatched five young.
Fifteen species and subspecies of cockatoo produced 93 chicks. Most
productive were the six breeding pairs of Major Mitchell's or Leadbeater's
Cockatoos Cacatua leadbeateri. Moluccan Cockatoos C. moluccensis
hatched 14 young and two pairs of Blue-eyed Cockatoos C. ophthalmica
produced seven chicks, some of which were hatched in the hand-rearing
station. Three Keas Nestor notablis were reared, bringing the Loro Parque
population to 13. A group of nine young are currently exhibited in an aviary
with some Galahs or Roseate Cockatoos Eolophus roseicapilla, and are a
great attraction because of their hilarious behaviour.
All three species of fig parrot at Loro Parque nested successfully, with
Edward's Psittaculirostris edwardsii raising five chicks. Great-billed Parrots
Tanygnathus megalorhynchos hatched four young. With the ever increasing
popularity of colour mutations of Australian parrakeets, Loro Parque is to
be commended on its plan to build up normal or natural coloured populations
of species such as the Scarlet-chested Parrot or Parrakeet Neophema
splendida.
Fifteen Timneh Grey Parrots Psittacus erithacus timneh were raised and
four pairs of Cape Parrots Poicephalus robustus fuscicollis produced a total
of nine young. The breeding colony of Nyasa Lovebirds Agapornis lilianae
produced 22 young. The Long-tailed Parrakeet Psittacula longicauda was
bred for the first time at Loro Parque, with one youngster being reared to
independence.
There was a considerable improvement in the number of macaws bred
in 2001. One hundred and forty-eight young of 13 species were reared,
including five Hyacinth Macaw Anodorhynchus hyacinthinus , Blue-headed
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.7735518">
Macaw Ara couloni and 11 Blue-throated Macaw A. glaucogularis. The
five pairs of Blue-throated produced more young than ever before.
Forty-four Sun Conure Aratinga solstitialis were among the 113 young
Aratinga conures of 12 species which were reared. Six Golden or Queen of
Bavaria's Conures Guarouba guarouba were parent-reared. Two Thick-
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.699439" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293285" page_num="93" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996012" page_id="56293285"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
93
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.966238176470588" page_id="56293285"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
billed Parrots Rhynchopsitta pachyrhyncha were parent-reared and an egg
laid by a second pair was hatched in an incubator.
Following radical changes in nutrition, developed in collaboration with
the veterinary department, five species and subspecies of Bolhorhynchus
parrakeets bred successfully. This included the first breeding at Loro Parque
of the Andean Parrakeet B. orbygnesius. Two pairs produced a total of six
young. Altogether 15 young caiques Pionites spp. were hatched and Loro
Parque's first Short-tailed Parrot Graydidascalus brachyurus. Six Plum-
crowned Pionus P. tumultuosus and 10 Coral-billed P sordidus crallinus
were among 29 Pionus reared.
Twenty species and subspecies of Amazon produced a total of 90 young.
It included the first captive breeding worldwide of the Scaly-naped Amazon
Amazona mercenaris. In a huge flocking aviary housing two pairs, one pair
had a clutch of three eggs, two of which were fertile and from which two
chicks were reared. Other species and subspecies bred included Yellow-
shouldered Amazon A. barbadensis , Red-topped A. rhodocorytha , Festive
A. festiva bodini, Red-spectacled A. petrei , Yellow-lored A. xantholora and
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.640831153846154" page_id="56293285"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
Yellow-faced Amazon A. xanthops.
Purple-bellied Parrots Triclaria malachitacea produced seven chicks and
Loro Parque now has probably the largest number of this species in captivity.
The overall number of parrot species and subspecies in the collection has
increased to 322.
Prof. David Waugh, who was the Loro Parque Fundacion's first Scientific
Director from 1995-1998, has left his post as Director of the Royal Zoological
Society of Scotland to return as Environmental Advisor to Loro Parque and
the LPF.
* * *
FALKLAND ISLANDS HAVE NEW OWNER
Frank Woolham reports that the Bronx Zoo-based Wildlife Conservation
Society (WCS) has acquired ownership of the spectacular islands of Steeple
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.91468525" page_id="56293285"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
Jason and Grand Jason, two of the western-most islands in the Falklands
chain in the south Atlantic.
The islands were a gift from New York philanthropist Michael Steinhardt,
a member of the WCS Board of Trustees. They support large populations of
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.9097885">
Rockhopper Eudyptes crestatus, Gentoo Pygoscelis papua and Magellanic
Penguins Spheniscus magellanicus, Black-browed Albatross Diomedea
melanophrys, Southern Giant Petrel Macronectes giganteus, Falklands Skua
Catharacta antarctica and the rare Striated Caracara or 'Johnny Rook'
Phalcoboenus australis.
Steeple Jason is more than five miles (approx. 8km) long and nearly one
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998229" page_id="56293286"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
94
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.926943" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293286" page_num="94" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9826495" page_id="56293286"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
mile (approx. 1.6km) wide, Grand Jason is almost seven miles (approx.
11km) long and approximately two miles across (approx. 3.2km). Steeple
Jason's nesting population of more than 150,000 pairs of Black-browed
Albatross is considered the largest in the world.
According to WCS Senior Conservationist, Dr William Conway, who
has undertaken wildlife surveys of the islands, their vast bird colonies
represent one of the remaining great wildlife spectacles left on earth -
comparable to the wildebeest migration of the Serengeti and that of caribou
in the Arctic region.
These two islands were once owned by the late Len Hill who established
one of the first, if not the very first bird garden, the wonderful Birdland in
the Cotswold village of Bourton-on-the-Water, Glos., here in the UK. The
story of Birdland and the acquisition of the Steeple Jason and Grand Jason
were described in his book, Penguin Millionaire. In News &amp; Views
(.Avicultural Magazine Vol.77, No.2, p.77 (1971)), A. A. P. (Arthur Prestwich)
reported that Len Hill had produced stamps for these two islands bearing
his portrait and remarked that it was surely the first time a member of the
society had been depicted on a stamp. Adding, that as the islands have no
human inhabitants the stamps were useless for postal puiposes, but were of
considerable philatelic interest.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.568532" page_id="56293286"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
* * *
IS THIS A RECORD?
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.984058" page_id="56293286"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
I have been sent a cutting about a Blue &amp; Gold Macaw Ara ararauna
reputed to be 103 years old and to have been once owned by Winston
Churchill, who is said to have taught it a few swear words, which the macaw
still uses occasionally.
Believed to have been born in 1899, the macaw is said to have been
acquired by a Mrs Stribling in 1900. Following her death in the 1930s, the
macaw which is named 'Charlie', was sold to a Percy Dabner and the
following year was bought by Churchill and took up residence at his country
retreat at Chartwell, Kent, where he also kept his famous Black Swans Cygnus
atratus.
Churchill is said to have had the macaw for 28 years, including when he
was war-time Prime Minister, until his death in 1965, after which it was
given to Percy Dabner's son-in-law Peter Orum, who had a pet shop. The
past three years, the macaw which is badly plucked on the underparts, has
lived at Peter Drum's Reigate, Surrey, garden nursery, which has enjoyed a
large increase in visitors following the national and international media
coverage the story has received.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.692554" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293287" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.968823" page_id="56293287"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
95
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.943709" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293287" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
NEW ARRIVALS AT MARWELL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994573125" page_id="56293287"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
Several new species have been added to the collection at Marwell
Zoological Park in Hampshire. A group of 16 Black-cheeked Lovebirds
Agapornis nigrigenis and a pair of Sun Conures Aratinga solstitialis have
been received from Shaldon Wildlife Trust and four pairs of Sacred Ibis
Threskiornis aethiopicus from the Cotswold Wildlife Park have joined
Waldrapp Geronticus eremita , Black-crowned Night Heron Nycticorax
nycticorax , Marabou Leptoptilus crumeniferus and spoonbill Platalea spp.
in the park's Marabou Mansions aviary.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.847283" page_id="56293287"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.717852" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293287" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
LOOKING FOR A MATE?
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.892505" page_id="56293287"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
If you are looking for a mate to pair-up any un paired birds you may
have, why not post your requirements on the bulletin board of the society's
website; www.avisoc.co.uk. Present requirements posted on the site, include
two female Yellow-bellied Tits Pams venustulus , a female Red-billed Buffalo
Weaver Bubalornis niger , a female Chopi Blackbird Gnorimopsar chopi
and female Cinereous Finches Piezorhina cinerea and Mongolian Larks
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.587108" page_id="56293287"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
Melanocorypha mongolica.
* * *
GRAHAM TULK
Members and their guests attending the Spring Social Meeting at the
Cotswold Wildlife Park were saddened to leam of the death of Graham
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.967383133333333" page_id="56293287"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
Tulk and before lunch stood for a minute's silence. Graham had died
suddenly of a heart attack earlier in the week. He was aged 60. Graham
often attended social meetings and I remember following the visit to Michel
Klat's wonderful collection at Hare Hatch, sitting opposite Graham and Ms
wife during the sumptuous tea prepared for members and their guests by
Diane Klat in the village hall, and Graham joking about having to forego
the many cakes and other sweet things because he had been persuaded
recently of the need to go on a strict diet.
A popular figure, Graham had, according to accounts, been an avid
bud keeper from a very early age and had in his time kept a wide and varied
collection. Lately though he had specialised in breeding Australian finches,
most notably some of the best Gouldian Finches in the UK, and had become
increasingly interested in developing new colour varieties.
Gur deepest sympathy is extended to his widow Sylvia and sons Robert
and Stephen.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.988395" page_id="56293288"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
96
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.4920705">
Softfood With Fruit
Universal Food
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.956400153846154" page_id="56293288"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
WITTE MOLEN Softfood with fruit is a
complete food for insectivorous and fruit
eating birds such as thrushes, blackbirds,
starlings, turacos, toucans, green magpies,
birds of paradise and jays. This ideal,
balanced diet has a uniquely low iron
content of less than 70ppm. It contains
the right proportion of proteins, vitamins,
minerals and all the essential amino acids
and fatty acids. This food is enriched
with berries and pieces of papaya,
pineapple, figs and apricots. It also
contains honey, brewers yeast and vitamin C.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.39272" page_id="56293288"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
5kg Tub #19.95 2 Tubs 10 kg #34.95
25kg Sack #53.95 Prices include Delivery
WITTE MOLEN Universal food is a
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.926898916666667" page_id="56293288"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
complete food for insectivorous and fruit
eating birds. This ideal nutritional blend
contains the right proportion of proteins,
vitamins, minerals and all the essential
amino and fatty acids. This food is
enriched with juniper berries and fresh
water shrimps and also contains honey
and brewers yeast and the correct
amount of vitamin C. With Witte Molen
Universal food you can keep your birds
as healthy and as active as they are in the
wild.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.929293956521739" page_id="56293288"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
5kg Tub #17.95 2 Tubs 10 kg #29.95
25kg Sack #42.95 Prices include Delivery
Vitamins &amp; Minerals
Sunbird Nectars
Livefoods
Soak Mixes
Nuts
Eggfoods
Softbill Diets
Straights
Seed Mixtures
Parrot Mixes
Frozen Foods
Lorikeet Nectars
Supplements
Handrearing
Formulas
Mynah Pellets
Dried Fruits
Berries
Egg Rearing Food With
Hedgerow Plants
WITTE MOLEN Egg Rearingfood is a
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.984297818181818" page_id="56293288"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
complimentary food fit for all seed eating
birds. This rearing food has a unique low
iron content and contains all vitamins,
minerals and amino acids in the right
proportions. A mixture of a selected
number of natural herbs is added, which
has a positive influence on the taste and
acceptance by the birds. Witte Molen Egg
Rearingfood is also gladly eaten by
budgerigars and parrots. Mix with seed to
produce a delicious meal for your parrots.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.61380575" page_id="56293288"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
5kg Tub #17.95 2 Tubs 10 kg #29.95
25kg Sack #47.95 Prices include Delivery
Moist Egg food
WITTE MOLEN Eggfood is a
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.971483363636364" page_id="56293288"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
complimentary food enjoyed by all seed-
eating birds. This food contains the
correct amount of vitamins, minerals and
the essential amino and fatty acids to
keep your birds in good health. Witte
Molen Eggfood is composed of light
digestable egg products, bakery products
and various seeds. This food is made
from the highest quality products to
ensure your birds are maintained at their
optimal standard.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.538853888888889" page_id="56293288"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
5kg Tub #16.95 2 Tubs 10kg #28.50
25kg Sack #39.95 Prices include Delivery
Wimo Eggfood Red
5kg Tub #17.95 2 Tubs 10kg #29.95
Prices include Delivery
P&amp;P only #4.95 up to 45kg unless included in price (for most postcodes). Rob Harvey Specialist
Feeds, Kookaburra House, Gravel Hill Road, Holt Pound, Famham, Surrey, GU10 4LG.
Tel: 01420 23986 Fax: 01420 23078 E-mail: rob@robharvey.com Website: www:robharvey.com
Sole UK agent for Witte Molen &amp; Avi-Plus All major CC taken
</table>
<figure confidence="0.817136428571429" page_id="56293289"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The proven supplements
system to Improve breeding
performance.
Daily EssentialsS
(or Bird Park Essentials)
Calcivet
(CalciBoost outside Europe)
Feast or Flourish
ProBoost SuperMax
Potent Brew
BIRDCARE
COMPANY
Leading the way - naturally
Contact us for details:
</figure>
<table confidence="0.923165333333333" page_id="56293289"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Birdcare Company, Unit 21/22, Spring Mill Ind. Est.,
Avening Road, Nailsworth, Glos, GL6 OBU, England.
Tel: 0845 130 8600 (local call charge only)(UK only) or
Int + 44 1453 835330 Fax: Int + 44 1453 834302
E-mail: sales@BirdcareCo.com or advice@BirdcareCo.com
Website: www.BirdcareCo.com
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.781861" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293290" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.920566137931034" page_id="56293290"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
3 9088 01769 6469
Threats to parrots in aviculture
by Rosemary Low.49
The Mandarin Duck
by Philip Schofield..52
Scarlet Ibis incubate Sacred Ibis eggs and partly rear
a Sacred Ibis chick
by Brett K. Bannor.59
Notes on the feeding and nesting of Olive Pigeons
by Neville Brickell. 63
Von der Decken's Hombill Tockus deckeni at the Oklahoma
City Zoological Park
by Chris Smith.69
A summary of pittas in European zoological collections
by Malcolm Ellis.75
The President's Garden Party 2001
by Stewart Pyper.80
The Society's visit to Chester Zoo
by Stewart Pyper.82
The Society's second visit to the Natural History Museum
by Stewart Pyper.83
Letters to the Editor.85
Book Reviews
Pionus Parrots. 87
Pheasants, Partridges &amp; Grouse. 88
The Society adopts a pair of hombills.89
News &amp; Views.90
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</table>
</algorithms>
