<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.7017708" page_id="56256212"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 115
No. 4
2009
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256213" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.984815548387097" page_id="56256213"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2009 as for 2008: British
Isles #18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please).
The subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the
Society later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of
the AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, ARCADIA, THE MOUNTS, TOTNES, DEVON TQ9 7QJ,
UK.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TNI 3 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail: Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have not
been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of a
particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history. Articles
should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the scientific
names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given. References
cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line drawings,
black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular point in
the article will be used where possible and should be clearly captioned. If
authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when submitting the
article and write their name on the back of each photograph. Tables and
graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be aware of
the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of the page
which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997594" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56256213" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982475333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.879014" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256214" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.92404" page_id="56256214"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 115-No. 4 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2009
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995356" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256214" page_num="" year="" vol="">
NOTES ON THE NESTING ACTIVITY, VOCALIZATIONS
AND EGG-LAYING OF THE CHINESE PAINTED QUAIL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9679843" page_id="56256214"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Coturnix chinemis
by Janice L. Pappas
Introduction
Over the past 23 years I have, as a large part of my avicultural activity,
kept Chinese Painted Quail. During this time I have taken the opportunity
to make observations and report on their varied behaviours (Pappas, 1996).
One of the most fascinating behaviours involves the vocalizations made by
both the male and female quail when they are engaged in nesting activities.
My purpose in this paper is to describe and show how the Chinese Painted
Quail's calls, nest building and egg-laying activities are related.
The Chinese Painted Quail Coturnix chinensis (Sibley &amp; Moore, 1993;
synonymous with Excaifactoria chinensis ) is an Old World quail found
in counties such as China, the Philippines, Indonesia and other areas of
south-east Asia, south to parts of northern and eastern Australia, where
it is known as the King Quail; Clements (2007) calls it the Blue-breasted
Quail. It is small enough to fit in the palm of a hand. As well as the natural
or normal-coloured form, as an avicultural subject, it is propagated in a
variety of colours such as silver, cinnamon and white, with the males having
different bib colourings. Among this quail's more charming behaviours is
the delightful tidbitting call between pairs. However, other vocalizations are
important because of their association with particular behaviours, including
nesting activities.
The male is the more vociferous of a male-female pair, although the
female Chinese Painted Quail will, at times, call. During an impending
reproductive cycle, the female will find a suitable, inconspicuous place, to
make a nest in which to lay her eggs. As the clutch increases in size, it is
noticeable that the male and female pay attention to keeping a lookout for
any possible disruption to their nesting activity. A wide variety of calls are
made by the male and female with respect to various activities they share,
such as tending to the nest and the clutch of eggs.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997978" page_id="56256215"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
162
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.711358" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256215" page_num="162" year="" vol="">
PAPPAS - CHINESE PAINTED QUAIL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987508857142857" page_id="56256215"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
In my study, I was interested in determining the connection between
nesting activity, vocalization and egg-laying. As it happens over a period
of a few days, I noticed that I could anticipate when the next egg would be
laid - which was approximately 25 hours after the previous egg had been
laid - by the increase in calling by both the male and female. From this, I
decided to try to ascertain more precisely the relationship between nesting
activity, vocalization and egg-laying.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.819206">
Methods
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998038578947368" page_id="56256215"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
The Chinese Painted Quail I chose for my study was my first pair of
quail. According to the place where I purchased them, the pair had been
together all along and the female had not laid eggs in the past year. The birds
were silver in colour, with the male having red eyes. Both birds weighed
approximately 45g each.
During the period in which my observations were made, my quail used
two different nest sites within their large cage. The first nest site was not
bolstered by other structures I might have added for them, while the second
nest site consisted of a small, square, woven basket in which the female felt
secure and therefore accepted the site for laying her eggs (see photo p. 163).
My quail were kept in their cage in a relatively quiet spot where they would
not be disturbed but could be readily observed.
The observation period was from January-July 1987, which amounted to
just over six months. During this period, the date, the time of male crowing,
the time of female crowing and the time of egg-laying were all recorded.
These data were recorded at all hours of each day. The data were analysed to
determine the relationship between vocalization and egg-laying. In addition,
detailed observations were made of their nesting behaviour with regard to
vocalization and egg-laying.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.965449">
Results
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.969040909090909" page_id="56256215"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
A total of 1,143 calls were heard from the male and 720 calls were heard
from the female. A total of 65 eggs were laid. During the six month period,
the data were compiled and plotted at one hour intervals (see Fig.l). From
midnight to 5.00am, crowing by both the male and female was at a minimum.
Peak calling by the male occurred at two different time intervals, one between
7.00am-8.00am and the other between 7.00pm-8.00pm (19.00hrs-20.00hrs).
Peak calling time for the female was between 9.00am-10.00am and then
diminished from 10.00am to noon, followed by a level of relative stability,
albeit with some oscillation in the amount of calling from approximately
1.00pm-10.00pm (13.00hrs-22.00hrs), with peak egg production occurring
at4.00pm-5.00pm (16.00hrs-17.00hrs). Calling by both the male and female
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.400705" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256216" page_num="163" year="" vol="">
PAPPAS - CHINESE PAINTED QUAIL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998857" page_id="56256216"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
163
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.984530238095238" page_id="56256216"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
My Chinese Painted Quail at their second nest site in a basket.
diminished at peak egg-laying time, after which calling by the male increased
sharply, but calling by the female did not increase as much (see Fig.l).
The male's peak calling occurred approximately six hours prior to the
start of egg-laying and the female's peak calling time occurred approximately
four hours prior to the start of egg-laying (see Fig.l). When egg-laying was
in progress, the male's calling rose to a second peak from late afternoon to
night. Calling by the female was below its peak during the entire laying
period. There was a higher number of calls by both the male and female
at the start of the egg-laying period, these then dipped at the maximum
egg-laying time, then increased in the time interval just after the maximum
egg-laying time (again see Fig.l).
Nest building activities and nesting behaviour
On November 23rd 1986,1 bought a pair of silver Chinese Painted Quail.
Three days after I brought them home, the male began to call. It was not
until January 14th 1987, that the female began to call. It was evident from
the beginning that the two quail were very devoted to each other.
From January-March 1987, both the male and female engaged in nest
building activities, much of which consisted of scraping or digging a nest
by kicking and fluttering materials to make a depression on the floor of the
cage. At one point, when the male was standing next to her and was facing
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999438" page_id="56256217"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
164
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.621339" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256217" page_num="164" year="" vol="">
PAPPAS - CHINESE PAINTED QUAIL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986340833333333" page_id="56256217"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
Fig.l. Comparison of time of number of eggs laid to number of crows by
the male and female Chinese Painted Quail.
her, the female pecked his left leg. He moved away from the nest and the
female carried on nest building and continued to keep the male away from
the nest. Even after feeding not far from the nest, the female returned to
the nest site to prevent the male from approaching it. When feeding, the
female took pieces of vegetables and threw them over her shoulder into
the nest area around her. She continued with her nest building activities,
feeding in the same way and pecking the male's back or legs to send him
away from the nest.
Not long after this, the female settled down in the nest and laid her first
egg on January 20th 1987. Both the male and female called out. The male
stood at the left front of the nest. The female continued her nesting behaviour
and tried to roll an egg under her breast. She also continued to peck the
male when he was near the nest. However, the male walked around the
female in the nest a number of times and had done so even when she was
in the process of laying an egg. At times, the female left the nest and paced
about with the male. She then returned to the nest and continued with her
nesting behaviours. Both the male and female continued now and then to
dig at the nest site.
I have witnessed the male engaged in egg rolling behaviour and throwing
food over his shoulder to the nesting site. The male was active at the nesting
site, engaged in tidbitting and making a variety of calls, including a preening
call, a rapid, high-pitched " whit-whit " call, a cricket call and a crow call.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.400845" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256218" page_num="165" year="" vol="">
PAPPAS - CHINESE PAINTED QUAIL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998996" page_id="56256218"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
165
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999346678571429" page_id="56256218"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
In and around the nest, the male made a nesting call, that was a bubbling
sound or a series of&amp;apos; "whoooos" while scraping out the nest. The female also
called and usually made a two-note high-low call or soft "peeping" single
notes. The male was very attentive towards the female despite her sometimes
pecking him. He stood near the nest keeping a lookout while the female ate
seeds. Even when the female was away from the nest, the male would go
over to the nest site and stand near it keeping a lookout.
From April-July 1987, the pair had a square basket which I had placed
in the cage for the pair to use as a new nest site. Almost Immediately after
I had placed it in the cage, the female began to throw pieces of vegetable
over her shoulder into the basket. However, the first egg was laid between
the old nest site and the basket. When the female slept in the basket, the
male was exceptionally quiet and moved very slowly. Finally, the female
laid an egg in the basket. At that point, the male stood very still near the
basket, turning his head from side to side scanning the area.
Shortly afterwards, the male went to the old nest site and did some
calling. The female subsequently proceeded to lay an egg at the old nest site.
Eventually, the female returned to the nest basket. She continued to frequent
the nest basket and lay her eggs in it. The male positioned himself in front
of the nest basket or walked around with his body stretched tall and kept
a lookout, but sometimes went to the old nest site and called. After a few
hours, the female and the male returned to the old nest site and commenced
to engage in nest building activities and feeding. Egg-laying then proceeded
at the old nest site.
Towards the end of April, the female returned to the nest basket to lay
her eggs. The male would be positioned to the left or right of the front of
the basket and would remain very still. The nest basket continued to be the
place for egg-laying and nesting behaviour through until early July 1987.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.792635">
Discussion
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.979580454545455" page_id="56256218"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
Studies such as this one are important as little recent information has
been published in ornithological research journals on the behaviour of this
particular Old World quail Some of what is known about the natural history
of the Chinese Painted Quail and related Coturnix species was obtained by
late nineteenth century and early twentieth century aviculturists (e.g, Butler,
1897; Meade-Waldo, 1898; McGregor, 1909; Finn, 1911; Hopkinson, 1926;
Hachisuki, 1931), because it was difficult to find and observe these small
quail in the wild. As the Chinese Painted Quail became more popular
with aviculturists, more observations and information on its behaviour
was published in the mid-late twentieth century (e.g. Delacour &amp; Mayr,
1946; Johnsgard, 1988; Alderton, 1992), especially in journals such as the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999219" page_id="56256219"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
166
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.646404" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256219" page_num="166" year="" vol="">
PAPPAS - CHINESE PAINTED QUAIL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.976859048780488" page_id="56256219"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine (e.g. Seth-Smith, 1957; Yealland, 1962; Harrison et
al. 1965; Harrison, 1965, 1968, 1973a &amp; 1973b; Robbins, 1979; Pappas,
1996).
Chinese Painted Quail produce many kinds of calls for particular
purposes. During heightened interest in reproductive activity, a variety of
calls are uttered, some of which may be interpreted specifically with respect
to nest building, egg-laying and incubation. In my study, both the male and
female called when engaged in nest building and egg clutch activities.
The crowing call is usually uttered in the morning and evening and when
the male and female are not within sight of each other. However, in my
study, when the female was incubating eggs, the male uttered the crow call,
which may have been his announcement about his status with the female.
The male called to announce to all that he was not only with his female
companion engaged in the reproductive cycle, but also that other males
should stay away. The female called at times, seemingly to announce that
soon another egg would be added to the clutch. The male also uttered the
low volume call just prior to the crow call, especially when the female was
sitting on eggs. He would travel to the farthest extent of the cage and utter
the low, hoarse call. I have observed this a number of times with various
pairs of quail (Pappas, 2001).
During nest building, Chinese Painted Quail act in a similar way to
Bobwhite Colinus virginianus (Stokes, 1967), Gambel's Quail Callipepla
gambelii (Ellis &amp; Stokes, 1966) and the Chukar Partridge Alectoris chukar
(Stokes, 1961). As with other quail, my quails' behaviour of taking food and
throwing it over the shoulder was their means of bringing materials to the
nest, rather than carrying such materials via the beak. Scraping the ground
and lobbing materials to the nest site are part of the display performed by
the Chinese Painted Quail.
Just as with other quail, such as the Bobwhite (Stokes, 1967), nest
scraping or digging by my Chinese Painted Quail, was accompanied by a
nesting call. Although the call varies from species to species, there is no
mistaking the particular call and its association with nesting activities. It is
usually a series of short, soft or low notes. The nesting call and associated
nesting behaviours leading to egg-laying are among the most important
activities in the life of the Chinese Painted Quail.
From data recorded on vocalizations, the peak calling time between
7.00am-8.00am represents the morning calls that can be expected from
the Chinese Painted Quail. The evening vocalization period represents
the usual time for this to occur. Most importantly, during maximum egg-
laying, vocalizations by both the male and female diminish. This indicates
a potential predictor for egg-laying, whereby there is an increase by the male
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.400827" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256220" page_num="167" year="" vol="">
PAPPAS - CHINESE PAINTED QUAIL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998761" page_id="56256220"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
167
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.951363375" page_id="56256220"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
in vocalization one hour prior to maximum egg-laying and two hours prior
to maximum egg-laying by the female (see Fig.l).
Conclusion
Careful observations along with noting the times of the Chinese Painted
Quail vocalizations provided a way to anticipate and, potentially predict, the
time of egg-laying. The same seems to be true with Bobwhite, GambePs
Quail and the Chukar Partridge, and it would be interesting to learn if this
is the case with other species of Galliformes.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9419" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56256220" page_num="167" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999073" page_id="56256220"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
I would like to thank my mother, father and my husband for their
contributions in recording data for my study. Without their help, I would
not have been able to conduct this study.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.949039" genericHeader="references" page_id="56256220" page_num="167" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.9064989">
Alderton, D. 1992. The Atlas of Quails. T.F.H. Publications, Neptune City, New Jersey.
Butler, A. 1897. The ^wnese Quail (Excalfactoria chinensis). Avicultural Magazine 4,37:1-3.
Clements, J. F. 2007. The Clements Checklist of the Birds of the World. Sixth Edition.
Christopher Helm, London and Cornell University Press, USA.
Delacour, I., Mayr, E. 1946. Birds of the Philippines . The Macmillan Co., New York.
Ellis, Jr., C. R,, Stokes, A.W. 1966. Vocalizations and behavior in Gambel's Quail. The
Condor 68:72-80.
Finn, F. 1911. Game Birds of India and Asia. Thacker, Spink &amp; Co., Calcutta.
Hachisuka, M. 1931. The Birds of the Philippine Islands. H. F. &amp; G. Witherby, London.
Harrison, C. J. O. 1965. Plumage pattern and behaviour in the Painted Quail. Avicultural
Magazine 71,6:176-184.
Harrison, C. J. O. 1968. Some notes on the behaviour of nesting Painted Quail, and some
further notes on their calls. Avicultural Magazine 74,1:7-10.
Harrison, C. J. O. 1973a. Plumage pattern in the buff varieties of the House Sparrow and the
Painted Quail. Avicultural Magazine 79,3:73-74.
Harrison, C. J. O. 1973b. Further notes on the behaviour of Painted Quail (. Excalfactoria
chinensis), Avicultural Magazine 79,4:136-139.
Harrison, C. J. O., Restall, R., Trollope, J. 1965. The egg-rolling behaviour of the Painted
Quail Avicultural Magazine 71,4:127-130.
Hopkinson, E. 1926. Records of Birds Bred in Captivity. H.F. &amp; G. Witherby, London.
Johnsgard, P. 1988. The Quail, Partridges and Francolins of the World, Oxford University
Press, Oxford.
McGregor, R. 1909. A Manual of Philippine Birds, Part 1: Galliformes to Eurylaemiformes.
Bureau of Science, Department of the Interior, Manila.
Meade-Waldo, E. 1898. Breeding the Chinese Painted Quail (. Excalfactoria chinensis).
Avicultural Magazine 5,49:1-2.
Pappas, J. 1996. Some observations on the behaviour and care of the Chinese Painted Quail.
Avicultural Magazine 102,3:103-105.
Pappas, I. 2001. " Coturnix chinensis " (on line), Animal Diversity Web: http://animaldiversity.
ummz.umich.edu/site/accounts/pictures/Cotumix_chinensis.html
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998638" page_id="56256221"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
168
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.627185" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256221" page_num="168" year="" vol="">
PAPPAS - CHINESE PAINTED QUAIL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.716190625" page_id="56256221"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
Robbins, G. 1979. Quail in captivity. Avicultural Magazine 85,4:216-223.
Seth-Smith, D. 1957. Breeding the Painted Quail. Avicultural Magazine 63,1:21-22.
Sibley, C. G. and Monroe, B. L. 1993. A World Checklist of Birds. The Distribution and
Taxonomy and its Supplement. Yale University Press, New Haven, Connecticut.
Stokes, A. W. 1961. Voice and social behavior of the Chukar Partridge. The Condor 63:111-
127.
Stokes, A. W. 1967. Behavior of the Bobwhite, Colinus virginianus. The Auk 84:1-33.
Yealland, J. J. 1962. The Painted Quail. Avicultural Magazine 68,1: 24-26.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.775509928571429" page_id="56256221"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
Janice L. Pappas, Museum of Paleontology, The University of Michigan,
1109 Geddes Road, Ann Arbor, Michigan 48109-1079, USA.
Note:
As a Research Scientist associated with the University of Michigan
Museums of Zoology and Paleontology, I have access to a complete set of
Avicultural Magazines. If at any time one of our members needs a copy
of an article published in one of the earliest issues that may not be readily
available, I will be happy to obtain a photocopy of the article.
Janice L. Pappas
* * *
SOCIAL MEETINGS 2010
The Avicultural Society's Spring Meeting will be held at the Cotswold
Wildlife Park, Burford, Oxfordshire, on Saturday, March 27th. The 2010
AGM will take place immediately prior to lunch, provided that a large
</table>
<reference confidence="0.6502264">
enough room is available.
The President's Garden Party will be held on the afternoon of Saturday,
July 17th, at Chestnut Lodge, Cobham, Surrey.
On Saturday, September 11th, there will be a visit to the bird collection
at Leeds Castle, Maidstone, Kent.
</reference>
<figure confidence="0.259327" page_id="56256222"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
THE TROPICAL SCREECH OWL Megascops choliba
by Peter Stocks
</figure>
<page confidence="0.998729" page_id="56256222"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
169
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.987992783783784" page_id="56256222"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
The Clements Checklist of the Birds of the World Sixth Edition (Clements,
2007) lists 24 species of screech owl Megascops spp. and numerous
subspecies. The screech owls are to the New World what the scops owls
are to the Old World and until very recently both were grouped together in
the genus Otus ; indeed in many publications the screech owls can still be
found listed in the genus Otus.
The screech owls inhabit a diverse range of habitats, being found not
only in forest, but also in deserts, dry savannah, woodland, parkland and
gardens. They seem to fall within the size range 7 Vain-11 to (approx. 19cm-
28cm). Some are more stocky than others and appear somewhat larger. The
Western Screech Owl M kennicotti is a good example of this.
The Tropical Screech Owl M choliba , which is found from Costa
Rica southwards through northern South America, reaching as far south as
northern Argentina and Uruguay, is about mid-range in size. Clements (2007)
lists nine subspecies. In addition, the Tropical Screech Owl is polymorphic,
with the three most easily distinguishable morphs (colour phases) being the
greyish brown, brown and rufous (there are also intermediates). Restall et
al. (2006) illustrate three subspecies and deep rufous, rufous, light brown,
dark grey-brown and a very dark so-called black example of the plumages
of this owl and note that there is considerable variation within morphs,
subspecies and local populations.
The facial disc of the greyish brown morph is lightish grey with a
broad black border and the crown of the head and upperparts have heavy
dark streaking. The plumage of the underparts is finely vermiculated with
brownish buff and has vertical black streaks, each with four or five finer
lines running horizontally through them and creating a fishbone-like pattern.
The tail feathers are mottled and have fairly indistinct barring. The eyes are
a dirty yellowish colour and both the bill and cere are greyish green. The
talons are horn-coloured with a blackish tip, though not necessarily all of
them (I have had specimens with one or more lacking this coloration).
The brownish morph has predominantly brown plumage, with dark brown
streaking and the other dark coloration also this colour. The rufous morph
is a most striking looking bird with rust-coloured plumage.
As far as habitat goes, the Tropical Screech Owl seems to prefer open
forest, savannah and woodland. Indeed, although it pains me to say so, this is
a species which may have benefited from, dare I say It, deforestation, which
has opened up new clearings and promoted secondary growth. In towns and
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99524" page_id="56256223"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
170
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.839744" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256223" page_num="170" year="" vol="">
STOCK - TROPICAL SCREECH OWL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986555268292683" page_id="56256223"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
cities across its range, it is often found in parkland, where it may be seen
perched in trees and bushes. During the breeding season birds will often
roost together (I have observed with my own pairs that one will often lean
up against the other) but at other times roost singularly. Although observing
its behaviour in the wild must be fraught with difficulties as it seems to be
strictly nocturnal.
The Tropical Screech Owl was first imported into the UK in the early
1970s and Twycross Zoo is known to have had two in 1972. They later
proved to be a pair, that was initially housed in a cage approximately 4ft x
2ft x 4ft high (1.2m x 0.6m x 1.2m high), along with a Spotted Little Owl or
Spotted Owlet Athene hrama , in what I believe at the time was the children's
section of the zoo.
Apparently no serious attempt was made to breed the Tropical Screech
Owls prior to 1976. In April that year a broken egg was found on the floor,
after which consideration was given to providing them with more adequate
accommodation. An aviary was constructed for them which measured
approximately 8ft x 5ft x 6ft high (2.4m x 1.5m x 1.8m high) and had a 8ft
x 3ft (2.4m x 0.9m) wire mesh viewing panel the width of the aviary, but
was otherwise completely boarded, including the roof. For some unknown
reason, not only was the pair of Tropical Screech Owls transferred to the
new aviary, but also the Spotted Little Owl or Spotted Owlet, and all three
birds shared a nest log. In May 1977 an egg was laid, but despite this, all
three owls were left together in the aviary. A few days later disaster struck
when the bottom of the nest log gave way and a smashed egg was found on
the floor. The log was repaired and put back in place and soon afterwards a
second egg was laid. Yet again, however, catastrophe reared its ugly head
and the bottom of the nest log fell out again (how could this have been
allowed to happen?). Following this a more conventional wooden nest box
was provided and was readily accepted. The next time two eggs were laid
and it was noted that the Spotted Little Owl or Spotted Owlet remained in the
nest box throughout the incubation period, though it is not known if it played
an active part. A policy of non-interference seems to have been adopted
and although the first egg was scheduled to hatch on June 13th, it was not
known for certain whether the eggs were fertile and whether or not they had
hatched. A belt and braces feeding regime was adopted and the amount of
food was duly increased. It should be noted though that this species tends
to be a somewhat voracious eater and an increase in food consumption is
not necessarily an indication that there are chicks in the nest.
However, on July 16th a chick finally appeared at the nest hole and later
fledged successfully. Dave Coles (1986) listed it as the first successful
breeding of this species in the UK.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.52344" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256224" page_num="171" year="" vol="">
STOCK - TROPICAL SCREECH OWL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998724" page_id="56256224"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
171
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.988171242424243" page_id="56256224"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
Following this successful breeding, the Tropical Screech Owl seemed
to disappear from the avicultural scene and nothing more was heard of it
until a farther importation in 1991, of birds that were direct descendents of
founder populations in Canada and Germany. The birds were said to have
originated from Paraguay. If this was true (and it is not a hundred percent
certain that it was) then they likely belonged to the nominate subspecies
M c. choliba.
In my own collection I used to keep the grey and brown morphs of this
delightful owl and always paired grey to grey and brown to brown, but I
now keep only the brown morph. I am given to understand that there are
some examples of the rufous morph in Germany, but I am currently unable
to verify this.
Where I live in East Anglia, here in the UK, we are often prone to
quite bitter easterly winds coming in from the North Sea, but at no time
do my birds - despite their name - show any signs of discomfort. They are
housed in aviaries measuring some 4ft 6in wide x 9ft long x 6ft high (1.4m
wide x 2.8m long x 1.8m high). The rear third of the roof is covered with
corrugated perpex sheeting and the back and one third on each side of the
aviaries is, on the top third only, boarded, but the remainder is open to the
elements. However, dependent on the position of the aviary or aviaries, it
may in some circumstances be prudent to use polythene sheeting or some
similar material to provide extra protection, especially if particularly severe
weather is anticipated.
I provide a nest box Sin x Sin (20cm x 20cm) square and approximately
1ft (30cm) high at the front and 1ft 4in (40cm) high at the back, with an
offset hole approximately 3 in (7.5 cm) in diameter. In the bottom of the box
I place a substrate of wood shavings on which the female lays a clutch of
three to four rounded eggs which measure approximately 33mm x 30mm.
Incubation commences after the second egg has been laid and lasts for
approximately 28 days. The young fledge at approximately four weeks of
age and are independent a farther four weeks after that. Once they have
acquired adult plumage, at about three to four months of age, they can be
surgically or DNA sexed.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.978041" genericHeader="references" page_id="56256224" page_num="171" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.997726">
Clements, J. F. 2007. The Clements Checklist of the Birds of the World Sixth Edition.
Christopher Helm, London &amp; Cornel! University Press, USA.
Coles, D. 1986. First Breeding Records for Birds Reared to Independence under Controlled
Conditions in the United Kingdom. Published by the author. Website:www.dcbooksxo.uk
Restall, R., Rodner, C. and Leetieo, M. 2006. Birds of Northern South America: An
Identification Guide. Vol.2: Plates and Maps. Christopher Helm, London.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998656" page_id="56256225"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
172
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.866751" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256225" page_num="172" year="" vol="">
A LONG-TERM STUDY SUGGESTS THAT THE
SLATE-COLOURED SEEDEATER Sporophila schistacea
IS BOTH MONOTYPIC AND POLYMORPHIC
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.971037611111111" page_id="56256225"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
by Robin Restall
The Slate-coloured Seedeater Sporophila schistacea is a medimum-
sized finch which ranges from Belize and Guatemala (immediately south of
Mexico) southwards through Central America to northern South America,
reaching as far south as north-western Bolivia. It is poorly known and
generally regarded as probably being rare. It was first described in 1862,
but for nearly a century scientists and ornithologists alike confused it with
the Grey Seedeater S. intermedia. Both taxa had the name Grey Seedeater
Spermestes grisea. It was not until 1923 that they were finally recognised
as distinct and separate species. The specific characteristics that separate
the Slate-coloured Seedeater from other grey seedeaters are its orange bill,
the white marks on the sides of the throat, the white half-wing-bar and its
greenish olive legs and feet, with pale coloured nails.
It is apparently normadic, flying in flocks high over forests and wooded
foothills, looking for flowering or seeding bamboo. It flies all along the
Northern Cordillera of Venezuela and we have twice seen it in our garden
in Santa Paula, in Caracas. On one occasion a bird flew into the house in
an attempt to join the birds singing in the laboratory. Like all birds that are
associated with seeding bamboo, it can be common for a few months, but then
disappear. Most birds that are seen in bamboo-free locations are in transit, i.e.
passing through. Its exact relationship with bamboo is unclear. Unlike most
Sporophila seedeaters it has a peculiarly-shaped bill with a sickle-shaped
upper mandible only one third as deep as the larger, lower mandible; it also
has rictal bristles (see Fig. 1). The construction of the bill suggests it is
adapted for dealing with hard bamboo seeds Chusquea sp., while the rictal
bristles suggest it catches and consumes insects - presumably those found
on its preferred species of bamboo. I have seen it hawking insects in my
aviary and searching the leaves of the Ficus , apparently looking for insects.
Most individuals will readily take mealworm larvae and pupae, but ignore
the beetles. They will also nip out the emerging buds of Chusquea bamboo
growing in the aviary - to such an extent that three Chusquea bamboos I
was attempting to grow, were all killed by these seedeaters.
Over a period of more than 10 years, I studied specimens in museums in
Europe, North America and here in Venezuela. I gathered information from
birders, bird keepers, trappers and bird sellers, but considering the depth and
breath of my investigation, I came up with very little information of real
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.578687" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256226" page_num="173" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SLATE-COLOURED SEEDEATER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999404" page_id="56256226"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
173
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.986083675" page_id="56256226"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
value. By far the most rewarding part of the project was obtaining live birds
and keeping them in the laboratory and aviary. Many birds were kept for
varying periods during the six years of the study, some for only a few months
and a few for as long as five years. The total numbers of individuals studied
was more than 70. As the study progressed, I carefully made measured
drawings of most of the birds - some of different birds together and others
of particular birds - and, as time passed, repainted them again and again.
Summary
Both sexes of the Slate-coloured Seedeater have three distinct and
separate plumage phases. These are juvenile, intermediate and adult. The
progress of the female's plumage is predictable and variations are slight,
probably within the allowance of individual variation. However, the male's
plumage becomes increasingly variable with age and that of adult males
can range from the common grey and white bird illustrated in field guides,
to morphs that can only be identified as S. schistacea by the shape of their
bill and their song. The illustrations on pp. 174-175 show the development
of the plumages of some individuals and give an indication of the range of
variation. The chart on p. 178 shows at a glance how the plumages develop
from juvenile to intermediate to adult.
Juvenile
Six different juvenile plumages are shown at the top of p 174 Most
juveniles have either warm brown or warm grey upperparts. The bill is dusky
coloured, as are the legs, feet and nails. These two forms are sufficiently
distinct and frequently occurring to be recognised as two separate morphs.
The third has citron-olive plumage very similar to the first intermediate
plumage and, unless the bird has a yellow fleshy gape flange, it is not possible
to tell whether it is a juvenile or an immature bird. Alas, I have no certain
evidence that the citron-olive morph has a juvenile female plumage. Some
of the individuals I painted were clearly recently fledged, as shown by the
flange of yellowish skin at the comers of the gape.
Intermediate female
The next group of birds (below) shows the progression of two different
females. The bird on the left goes from juvenile to a yellow-bellied citron-
olive intermediate plumage (centre) and then into its first adult plumage
(on the right). The bill of the young juvenile female is entirely dark brown,
but after a few months shows a characteristic orange to hom-coloured
spot under the bill The dark, usually uniform coloured undertail-coverts,
appear to be a characteristic of female plumage, although 1 have not had
sufficient specimens, that were subsequently confirmed to be females, to be
positive about this. Most males in intermediate plumage have pale, ticked
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999328" page_id="56256227"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
174
</page>
<table confidence="0.343287" page_id="56256227"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SLATE-COLOURED SEEDEATER
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.577814" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256228" page_num="175" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SLATE-COLOURED SEEDEATER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997809" page_id="56256228"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
175
</page>
<page confidence="0.999364" page_id="56256229"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
176
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.884061" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256229" page_num="176" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SLATE-COLOURED SEEDEATER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995930195121951" page_id="56256229"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
or cinnamon undertail-coverts; the cinnamon is a lighter and warmer colour
than the dull brown of the female's undertaibcoverts.
Intermediate male
Males enter the intermediate plumage phase alongside females of the
same age. The intermediate plumage though usually extends through several
moults and several distinct phases of development. Many birds showed at
least two distinct intermediate phases and most showed three, some others
showed four or more. The third group of illustrations (at the foot of p. 174)
show part of a series of studies over several years of a male, that follow
it from juvenile (upper left) through the first dull citron-olive phase to the
bright middle intermediate phase, when the amount of orange on the bill is
increasing from the base towards the tip. By the time the bird has acquired
the third intermediate plumage, the orange on the bill is brighter or richer in
colour, but the plumage is paler and less greenish above. The yellow below
has some white mixed in with it, and the amount of white increases in the
next plumage. By the sixth plumage in this sequence (lower right) the bird
is clearly showing emergent basic adult plumage; the bill is now entirely
orange and touches of black and white are showing on the face and throat.
If one of the wings is spread and the primary coverts are pushed to one side,
a small amount of white may often be seen at the base of the primaries, as
was the case with this particular bird.
The progress of the 'butterfly' male
The fourth group of illustrations (at the top of p. 175) show how the
plumage of an individual male goes through a continuing development - that
continues after it acquires its first basic adult plumage and on through the life
of the bird. Note how all the characteristics of the basic adult plumage are
apparent in the case of the first bird in the middle row (bird No. 4). It is only
when the bird is almost three years old that the small patch of white becomes
apparent at the base of the primaries. In the following two plumages, the
basic plumage becomes increasingly clear and definitive. The first bird on
the bottom row (bird No.7) has begun to show a plumage pattern that goes
beyond the basic definitve plumage - with the white marks on the sides of
the throat now extending from the chin to the sides of the neck and with
more white appearing on the wings; this bird had three wing-bars - it was
the only time I have seen this. The fully adult male usually shows only a
partial wing-bar, formed by the terminal white edges of the innermost four,
or more rarely five, median wing-coverts. The following year (the bird was
now five years old) the white had begun to encroach upwards onto the sides
of the breast. By the time the final drawing on the right-hand side of the
bottom row was made, not only had the small patch of white at the base of
the primaries disappeared, but the amount of white on the sides of the throat
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.578724" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256230" page_num="177" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SLATE-COLOURED SEEDEATER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998918" page_id="56256230"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
177
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.98736435" page_id="56256230"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
and on the sides of the breast had dramatically increased. Bird keepers in
Venezuela who specialise in keeping this species, say that this is a very rare
variety and is known amongst them as El macho Mariposa (the butterfly
male) and is highly prized. A photograph of a bird sent to me a few years
ago by Hennning Pust in Denmark was an example of this morph.
Adult male polymorphism
The final group shows eight adult male plumages, painted from live, wild
birds. These are birds that were brought to me when they were already adult
or moulted into these plumages while in my aviary or laboratory. They are
not one-off plumages, as I have seen each one a few times, or many times,
on different occasions. Nonetheless, the grey male, the first bird on the
top row (bird No.l) and the bird on the right in the middle row (bird No.6)
are the common ones that are usually seen (the solid olive cast to the grey
plumage is not noticeable in the field). Note also that the two birds on the
bottom row (birds Nos. 7 &amp; 8) are extremely unusual and very unlike the
typical grey bird. But this is not the definitive set of morphs or variants
- according to bird keepers here in South America there are up to no fewer
than 20 different varieties recognised within the bird keeping fraternity. They
include birds with long, forked tails and birds with short, square-cut tails,
'dwarfs and giants&amp;apos; 10cm (approx. 4in) and 13cm (approx. 5in) in length
from the tip of the bill to the tip of the tail, for example. All are morphs I
have found occurring along the northern part of Venezuela.
Plumages chart
It is easy to see in the first box (on the following page) the three basic
juvenile plumages that occur. There is never any white at the base of the
primaries in any of the juvenile plumages. The colour of the undertail-coverts
is variable (inconsistent). The bill is typically Sporophila in profile, but is
1 Q%~ 15% smaller than that of the adult; the shallow, scimitar or scythe-shape
of the upper mandible is apparent and identifies the species, should there be
any doubt. The legs, feet and nails are dull to greyish brown to dusky.
Listed in the next two boxes are the intermediate plumages. In her
first intermediate plumage, the female moults into the same citron-olive
colour as the male, but is distinguished from him by having all-dull brown
undertail-coverts. The legs and feet may lighten and become more greyish
to olivaceous grey and the nails may lighten to a kind of horn colour. The
bill is dusky with a small area of horn colour under the base.
The male usually has an extended intermediate stage, passing through
three morphs, or, if the entire intermediate stage is regarded as being citron-
olive, then there are usually three phases to this morph. In the second of
these phases, the plumage is surprisingly bright. The belly is bright citron
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.983829" page_id="56256231"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
178
</page>
<figure confidence="0.902668071428571" page_id="56256231"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SLATE-COLOURED SEEDEATER
Plumages chart
Juvenile
Three morphs
h Warm brown 2. Warm grey 3, Citron-olive
Small, all dusky coloured bill
Legs, feet and nails dusky
Intermediate
Female monomorphic
Bill dusky with small pale spot under base
Undertail-coverts uniform brown
Male progresses through three morphs
1. Dullest
Bill dusky with emergent pale spot under base
Olive above, sulphur-yellow below
2. Brightest
Bill gradually becoming orange from the base
Bright olive above, citron-yellow below
3. Palest
Bill all orange
Greyish olive above, white emerging into yellow on underparts
Undertail-coverts of all three variable - often cinnamon
Adult
Female monomorphic
Bill uniform dusky
Brown above and on sides of body, belly white to buffy
Undertail-coverts brown
Male has multiple morphs
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.7989522">
1. Soft grey 2. Typical grey 3. Dark grey
4. Citron-olive 5. Black above 6. Olive-grey above
All have an orange bill and white at the base of the primaries
7. Charcoal 8. Fuscous
Bill partly orange, no white at base of primaries
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.578709" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256232" page_num="179" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SLATE-COLOURED SEEDEATER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999199" page_id="56256232"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
179
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.971750413793103" page_id="56256232"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
and the back is bright olive green. The soft parts do not change with each
moult, but change gradually from dusky with a pale horn coloured patch
under the base, becoming increasingly horn-orange around the base of both
mandibles, through nearly all-orange with a dusky tip to finally all-orange.
The colour of the legs, feet and nails also change gradually, the legs and feet
becoming olive-grey and the nails becoming increasingly pale to pale horn
colour with some older birds. There are though also individuals with dull
coloured legs, feet and nails, that continue through into adult plumage.
In the final two boxes, it can be seen that the female returns to a cryptic
brown colour, with a whitish to buffy belly and an all-dusky coloured bill.
The legs, feet and nails are variable in colour. In contrast, the male may moult
into the plumage of one of several morphs. At one extreme is a medium
grey morph, with a white belly and yellowish bill and looking for all the
world like the Grey Seedeater S. intermedia. I have even had birds in this
plumage with brown legs, feet and nails, and it was only the characteristic
bill shape that confirmed their identification. At the other extreme is the
dark charcoal coloured bird, with a very clearly defined white belly and
with white markings on the throat and wings, a rich orange coloured bill and
green-olive legs and feet and pale yellow nails. The only characteristic of
adult plumage which is constant in the male is that the coloration and pattern
markings invariably intensify with each year that passes.
Fig.l. Bill colour of Slate-coloured Seedeater.
1. Juvenile: bill entirely dusky; 2. &amp; 3. Intermediate: bill initially dusky
but with increasing amounts of yellow-orange; 4. &amp; 5. Adult male: bill
clearly showing line of the cutting edge. Note also the rictal bristles.
Conclusion
It seems undeniable that the Slate-coloured Seedeater is polymorphic. I
have not been able to examine the types of the various subspecies described,
but from photographs, descriptions and measurements, all fall within the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994827" page_id="56256233"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
180
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.883873" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256233" page_num="180" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SLATE-COLOURED SEEDEATER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98578971875" page_id="56256233"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
range of taxa found in Venezuela and, therefore, it seems to me equally
undeniable that the species is monotypic. This study and the findings would
have been impossible without the use of avicultural skills and experience.
Every effort was made during the six years of the study to maintain the
birds in as natural conditions as possible, with exposure year-round to local
hours of daylight, sunlight and rain. As feeding was of great concern, fresh
growing grasses that were in seed were offered regularly, including green
rice on the stem, collected fresh from the rice fields, and a wide variety of
seeds. Insects were also offered, as was a brand of softfood imported from
the USA.
Aviculture
This species is well-known but is uncommon in aviculture outside of
South America. It is popular amongst specialist birdkeepers in some South
American countries. It is apparently bred regularly in Brazil, where it is said
to do best in an upright cage. Birds from northern South America (mostly
from Venezuela) are (illegally) taken across the border into Brazil, from
where they are exported to continental Europe, where this species is favoured
by Sporophila specialists. The male has a strong and persistent song and is
a showy and active bird in an aviary. When in breeding condition, he will
chase all other yellow- and orange-billed birds and, at times, almost any
other bird he perceives to be invading his territory. The female builds a very
small, neat, cup-shaped nest and, in my experience, will readily use coconut
fibre to make the cup of the nest, subsequently surrounding it with fine grass
rootlets and odd strands of grassy vegetation. She lays two, or more rarely
three, pale, slightly bluish eggs, speckled with browns, including umber,
slightly more densely at the broad end. Incubation begins after the second
egg is laid. The female can become very nervous and I have lost clutches of
eggs and young nestlings, which I have found on the floor beneath the nest,
or at the far end of the laboratory or aviary, presumably as a result of minor
disturbances. As with other Neotropical grassfinches, the young fledge early
(after 12-13 days) and the precocious fledglings hide low down in cover for
the first few days and continue to be fed by their parents.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.8648755">
Avicultural Society Vice President Robin Restall lives in Caracas,
Venezuela. E-mail:robinrestall@gmail. com
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.958273" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256234" page_num="181" year="" vol="">
EXPERIENCES BREEDING THE WHITE-THROATED
MAGPIE-JAY Caiocitta formosa IN SOUTH AFRICA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998513" page_id="56256234"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
181
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997705891891892" page_id="56256234"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
by F. C. Barm coa t
A noteworthy collection of soft-billed (i.e. non-seed-eating birds) and
an excellent facility for breeding them have fairly recently been built-up by
Graeme Hoffman on his 12 acre (approx.5 hectare) property on the north-
western side of Johannesburg. About l,200sq m (approx. 13,0Q0sq ft) are
now under aviaries and there are 80 enclosures of varying sizes, as well
as a well equipped kitchen for food preparation, a hospital room in which
birds that fall ill can receive instant attention, breeding rooms for mice and
mealworms and rooms for food storage.
Graeme has bred birds since he was eight years of age, beginning with
finches and progressing to quail, pheasants and waterfowl, and then onto
the African Grey Parrot Psittacus erithacus and South American parrots.
About 12 years ago he began to become interested in breeding softbills,
spurred on by the advent of the commercial availability in South Africa of
excellent proprietary foods, which greatly simplify the feeding of such birds.
Expertise in breeding these types of birds has increased astronomically and
with their great variety of forms and behavioural patterns, they provide a
challenge and are a never ending source of interest. Furthermore, these
groups of birds seldom destroy aviary vegetation and can, therefore, be
housed in aesthetically pleasing aviaries. This fits in well with Graeme's
professional expertise as a nurseryman and his business, a home-based
landscaping service, that specialises in indoor plants.
Wisely in this softbill breeding facility there is now a focus on certain
groups of birds, namely jays, toucans, barbets, rollers and hombills. With
the jays the greatest breeding success to date has been achieved with the
beautiful and incessantly active White-throated Magpie-Jay from Central
America. There were some very interesting aspects to the breeding of this
species.
Two pairs became available four years ago. Because the White-throated
Magpie-Jay is known to live in flocks and to be a social nester, with several
members of the flock feeding the young in the nest and after they leave it,
all four were initially house together in a fully planted aviary measuring
7m x 1.2m x 2.4m high (approx. 22ft 9m x 4ft x 5ft high). The roof of the
aviary was partly covered and partly open to the weather, there were trees
in the aviary and for feeding the aviary was accessed from a passageway
at the back, where fibre cement heating panels for each aviary, reduce the
chill on cold winter's nights.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998537" page_id="56256235"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
182
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.944749" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256235" page_num="182" year="" vol="">
BARNICOAT - WHITE-THROATED MAGPIE-JAY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999814615384615" page_id="56256235"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
The first year the pairs seemed to be trying to dominate each other and no
nesting took place. So, for the following summer the two pairs were split up
and housed in separate, but similar aviaries, in which both pairs built nests
of sticks in shallow wicker baskets 20cm (approx. 8in) in diameter. They
only chose baskets fixed up in the uncovered parts of the aviary flights and
avoided those placed under cover.
The first pair produced four eggs, but the female seemed restless and the
incubation was unsatisfactory and none of the eggs hatched. The second pair
had a clutch of five eggs, incubated well and hatched five chicks. A sudden
cold snap one night led to the death of four them, leaving only one alive,
which had been in the middle of the cluster of young and had, therefore, to
some extent been insulated by the others. The surviving chick eventually
grew into a fine young female, that was left with the parents.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.717644">
Eelco Meyjes
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9955075" page_id="56256235"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
The White-throated Magpie-Jay is found from central Mexico to
northern Costa Rica.
There were more fortunate breeding results the following year. Five
eggs were laid and all hatched. However, for some reason or other two of
the chicks died and were carried from the nest and placed in the food bowl
on the third and fifth days respectively. The remaining three survived with
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.768341" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256236" page_num="183" year="" vol="">
BARNICOAT - WHITE-THROATED MAGPIE-JAY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999297" page_id="56256236"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
183
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998831727272727" page_id="56256236"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
help from their older sister from the previous breeding season, who helped
feed them and also helped guard the nest. Within a month of fledging, the
nest was relined and a second clutch of four eggs was laid, from which three
chicks hatched successfully. One of these was carried dead to the feeding
bowl on the eighth day, but the other two fledged. This means there is now
a colony of eight birds - the original pair and six of their offspring. They
are a picture of health and are incessantly active, with graceful movements,
and obviously enjoy life together in a single aviary. It would seem that
the parents enjoy having their offspring close to them and educating them
about the rearing process. Possibly flocks seen in the wild are built-up in
this way.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.537492">
Eelco Meyjes
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999562615384615" page_id="56256236"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
The female has a slightly shorter tail, more extensive black by the ear-coverts, a
narrower breast band and slightly duller upperparts.
Perhaps to a great extent responsible for this significant breeding success
is the feeding regimen. Available at all times is a bowl ofNutribird T16 (little
orange pellets, which the magpie-jays carry all over the aviary and hide in
odd places, and which they retrieve later when they fancy eating them); also
a bowl of the proprietary insect pate made by the Belgian company Orlux.
Twice a day fresh meat is provided, usually skinned and gutted day-old
chicks, cut into 1cm (approx. Ain) cubes, bone and all, or newborn mice. It
is felt that the former provide the best results. When the magpie-jays have
a growing brood of young, the supply of meat is increased and is virtually
available on demand. Also given every two hours is a supply of mealworms
(the giant type as well as regular-sized ones) and 6mm-1 Omm long imported
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999524" page_id="56256237"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
184
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.945084" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256237" page_num="184" year="" vol="">
BARNICOAT - WHITE-THROATED MAGPIE-JAY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.966781193548387" page_id="56256237"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
crickets. During the winter months the magpie-jays receive an austerity diet,
from which the protein is cut-out on alternative days.
Very apparent to me was the delightful rapport that has developed between
the magpie-jays and their owner, who visits them regularly twice a day - for
the morning feed and towards evening - so as to spot any problems as soon
as possible. They obviously recognise him and respond to his presence in
a confiding manner. The first sign of their decision to commence nesting is
when they start placing an odd stick or two on the feeding-table, as though
to communicate their intention, and most chicks that have died have been
carefully placed in the food bowl, as though to make the fact known. In
general most softbills soon develop a close relationship with their attendant
and show trust and confidence.
Avicultural Society Vice President Fred Barnicoat is a retired
schoolmaster who taught Latin. He lives in Johannesburg, South Africa
and is of Cornish descent. He joined the Avicultural Society in 1958 and
continues to keep, breed and show aviary birds.
The White-throated Magpie-Jay was first bred in the UK a few years ago
at Paultons Park in Hampshire. Geoff Masson told me that the pair hatched
one youngster this year and they always planned to leave it with its parents,
having read that these birds live in family groups. If they are successful
again next year, they have the opportunity to enlarge the aviary by opening
it up and combining it with the adjoining aviary and allowing the group to
grow. They have also hand-reared two chicks which they hope to pair-up
with birds bred by a friend on the Isle of Wight. Geoff has been in contact
with a number of breeders of this species in the USA, who seem to hand-rear
all their young because, they say, the parents kill them. If they tried harder
they could prevent this, Geoff believes, by providing the birds with forms of
stimulation, such as, for example, throwing a lot oflivefood into the aviary
to make the birds, particularly the male, hunt for it. Another idea is to give
them sunflower seeds, which they have to hold in the foot on a perch and
hammer open with their beak to extract the kernel. -Ed.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998655" page_id="56256238"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
185
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.96881" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256238" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
MANAGEMENT OF THE CRESTED PIGEON
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.885717714285714" page_id="56256238"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
Ocyphaps lophotes AT EXMOOR ZOO
by Derek Gibson
Identification
The Crested Pigeon, which has long been a familiar bird in aviculture - it
was first bred in the UK at London Zoo in 1849 (Coles, 1986) - is readily
identifiable (see photos of female on pp. 186-187).
Sexing
Visually sexing adults is not an easy undertaking, the key may be the
orbital ring, with that of the male being more pronounced than that of the
female; the metallic wing speculum is not a reliable guide, as it seems to
vary from individual to individual. DNA sexing is obviously a more reliable
method and puts an end to wasted breeding seasons, during which supposed
'pairs' fail to breed. Juveniles are also difficult to sex visually.
Alternative names
The Crested Pigeon seems to have a few alternative names. These
include: Crested Bronzewing, Crested Dove and Whistle-winged Pigeon,
the last name because its rapid wing-beats produce a distinctive whistling
sound which is produced by air passing over a modified primary feather in
each wing, when it takes to the sky; and, Topknot Pigeon, which is the name
more correctly used for Lopholaimus antarcticus, a very different looking
Australian species.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.58646">
Subspecies
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9767366" page_id="56256238"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
Two subspecies are recognised: G. I lophotes of central and eastern
Australia; and G. /. whitlocki found in central and northern Western Australia.
The latter is said to have narrower black wing-bars and less white on the
tip of the tail.
Distribution and habitat
Found over most of Australia, avoiding only the more moist habitats in
the far north and the south-east comer of New South Wales. Inhabits lightly
wooded grassland, usually in the vicinity of water, be it in a suburban park
with a pond or in flocks and pairs at water troughs on the numerous inland
ranches.
Feeding
In the wild it forages almost exclusively on the ground, eating a wide
variety of seeds and even feeding on noxious weed such as Salvation Jane
or Paterson's Curse Echiumplantagineum , a species native to Europe, which
has become an invasive species in Australia. It is also known to take insects,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999376" page_id="56256239"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
186
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9206645" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256239" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - CRESTED PIGEON
Female Crested Pigeon,
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994934" page_id="56256239"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
such as an Australian Psyllid Glycaspis brimble combei , more commonly
known as the Red Gum Lerp Psyllid.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.715201">
Status
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9329928" page_id="56256239"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
The IUCN considers the Crested Pigeon to be of lower risk/least
concern.
Breeding
Breeding in the wild seems to take place at any time of the year. The
nest consists of the usual flimsy platform of twigs hidden in a dense, thorny
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700636" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256240" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - CRESTED PIGEON
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998767" page_id="56256240"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
187
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9704122" page_id="56256240"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
Silting female.
bush, ! m 5m (approx. 3ft-16ft) above the ground (Gibbs et ah 2001). Two
white eggs are laid and are incubated for 18-20 days. Newly-hatched squabs
weigh on average 9.5g and are cared for by both sexes until they fledge at
16-24 days (Brown, 1995).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.748455">
Exmoor Zoo
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9885255" page_id="56256240"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
Here at Exmoor Zoo we had Crested Pigeons on display in mixed exhibits
with other species in various aviaries of varying dimensions for five years,
during which time we never succeeded in breeding a single Crested Pigeon.
At that point, the decision was taken to get all six Crested Pigeons DNA
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998794" page_id="56256241"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
188
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.938647" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256241" page_num="188" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - CRESTED PIGEON
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999445268292683" page_id="56256241"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
sexed, as a result of which we discovered that all six were males. We were
able to exchange two for DNA sexed females at the beginning of 2008.
At present we have on exhibition to the public two DNA sexed males
living in an aviary measuring approximately 4.9m long x 2.9m wide x 3m
high (roughly 16ft long x 9ft 3in wide x 9ft 9in high). The floor is covered
to varying depths with sand. The aviary is heavily planted with Eucalyptus
cinerea , Zebra Grass Miscanthus sinensis 'Zebrinus' and Elephant Grass
Pennisetum purpureum , a Cabbage Tree Cordyline australis and various
species of bamboo. The eucalyptus provides most of the perching, but we
also use Beech Fagus sylvatica branches about 2cm-4cm (%in-1 Yzin) in
diameter. Other birds in this mixed exhibit include Red-billed Quelea Quelea
quelea , Snowy-crowned Robin-Chat Cossypha niveicapilla and Crowned
Plover Vanellus coronatus, which seems to be a good mix of species both
for the public and for the birds.
The other Crested Pigeons, two males and two females, all DNA sexed,
are housed off-display. At first each pair was housed in an aviary measuring
3.7m long, x 1.2mwide x 3m high (approx. 12ft long x 4ft wide x 9ft 9in
high). Each aviary had perches placed at opposite ends of the flight and
28cm long x 21cm wide x 12cm deep (approx. 1 lin long x 8!4in wide x 5in
deep) nest baskets placed 30cm (approx. 1ft) below the roof at the back of
each aviary. When the males came into breeding condition both continually
drove their respective mates literally all day. Wing-clipping the males failed
to produce a satisfactory outcome and eventually they had to be separated
to prevent any further problems.
In April 2008 we changed our management and housed both pairs together
in an aviary 3.7m long x 2.7m wide x 3m high (approx. 12ft long x 9ft wide
x 9ft 9in high), which they shared with a pair of Crested Guineafowl Guttera
pucherani. The floor of the aviary is covered with pea gravel. Both species
were fed a diet which we make-up ourselves (see Table 1) and receive two
supplements, Avi-Mix and Abidec. The guineafowl got livefood, such as
mealworms, once a day, and it was customary to see the Crested Pigeons on
the ground trying to eat as many as they could before the less agile guineafowl
came along and quickly ate what remained. Once again the aviary had
perches at opposite ends to provide them with the maximum flying space.
They were though placed 0.3m (about 1ft) below the roof in an attempt to
stop the guineafowl using them. The guineafowl had their own perching
arrangement in the centre of the aviary. This was only 0.5m (approx. 1 ft 8in)
rising to 0.65m (just over 2ft) above the ground in the shape of a triangle
made from Beech branches 10cm (4in) in diameter. The nest baskets from
the pigeons' previous aviaries were used again. Dried grass and leaves,
thrown onto the aviary floor, were provided as nesting material.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.836086" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256242" page_num="189" year="" vol="">
GIBSON * CRESTED PIGEON
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99909" page_id="56256242"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
189
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999578475" page_id="56256242"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
The male Crested Pigeons began displaying to the females at the
beginning of May. The male really puts a lot into his courtship display:
his wonderful tail is fanned and raised in the air, his head is directed down
towards the ground and, with his entire body swaying up and down, he emits
a rhythmic whoop, whoop, whoop We were interested to observe that
the behaviour of the most driven male seemed to be defused as a result of it
sharing the aviary with a larger species, especially one as large and relatively
clumsy as the Crested Guineafowl.
The first egg was laid on July 19th, followed by the second egg on July
20th. Everything went well in the aviary while the female was incubating
the eggs. The only slight concern was that the other female was occasionally
spotted sitting in the nest basket, near the eggs though not actually on them,
while the female whose eggs they were, was at the feeding station (all four
birds have different coloured leg bands for ease of identification). The
first squab hatched on August 18th quickly followed on August 19th by its
sibling. During the rearing it was noted that three birds seemed to be actively
involved, although only the mother was observed feeding the squabs. The
other male continued to display to any bird which was on the same perch
as him, for as long as it remained there. The two young Crested Pigeons
grew very quickly and almost before we knew it they looked like miniature
versions of their parents. By the time the young were 14 days old, the femal e
was spending more time off the nest, seemingly to encourage the young to
fledge, which they did. The first fledged on September 3rd, followed by the
second the next day, although both returned to the nest most evenings.
Straight away the males began in earnest to drive the females again and
it was not long before the first female had laid again. Once more two eggs
were laid. The first was laid on September 11th and the second on September
12th. At no time was aggression shown towards the two young pigeons by
the adults, but the guineafowl were inquisitive and, on arriving at the zoo one
morning, one of the young pigeons was found on the ground. Thankfully,
no serious harm had come to it. It had though lost its crest, so we were left
with a crestless Crested Pigeon! As a result, the guineafowl were removed
and housed in another aviary.
The two young were seen feeding themselves on September 29th.
One of the second clutch of eggs began to hatch on September 30th but,
unfortunately, the second egg failed to hatch and was found to contain a
partially developed embryo.
As soon as they were a little bit larger and able to withstand the rigours of
aviary life, the two older squabs were moved to the on-display exhibit, so that
visitors to the zoo could appreciate that they are rather beautiful birds.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994183" page_id="56256243"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
190
</page>
<table confidence="0.9749588" page_id="56256243"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - CRESTED PIGEON
Derek Gibson
Day one.
Derek Gibson
Aviary housing Crested Pigeons.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.70026" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256244" page_num="191" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - CRESTED PIGEON
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997827" page_id="56256244"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
191
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.990272">
Table 1. Diet fed to all seed-eating pigeons at Exmoor Zoo.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.7954972" page_id="56256244"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
60g Pigeon mix
20g Waterfowl maintenance pellets
60g Parakeet mix
60g Insectivorous mix
30g Chick crumbs
V 2 Carrot cut into 5mm cubes
Vi Apple cut into 5mm cubes
Greenfood, e.g. shelled peas, broccoli, etc
1 Og Mineralised grit
Supplements mentioned in the text
Avi-Mix: Vetark Animal Health, PO Box 60, Winchester, Hants S023 9XN, UK. Website:
www.vetark.co.uk
Abidec: Cheraro UK Limited, 1 Tower Close, Huntingdon, Cambridge PE29 7DH, UK.
Website:www.abidec.com
References
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.983858777777778">
Brown, D. 1995. A Guide to... Pigeons, Doves and Quail. Australian Birdkeeper, Tweed
Heads South, NSW, Australia.
Coles, D. 1986. First Breeding Records for Birds Reared to Independence Under Controlled
Conditions in the United Kingdom. Dave Coles, Reading, Berks. Website:debooks.co.uk
Gibbs, D., Eustace, B. and Cox, J. 2001. Pigeons and Doves: A Guide to Pigeons and Doves
of the World. Pica Press, East Sussex, UK.
Derek Gibson is Head Keeper at Exmoor Zoo, South Stowford, Bratton
Fleming, Barnstaple, North Devon EX31 4SG, UK. E-mail:Exmoorzoo@
btconnect. com/Derek. r.gibson@btinternet. com
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998591" page_id="56256245"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
192
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.5857545" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256245" page_num="192" year="" vol="">
THE SOCIETY'S VISIT TO COLCHESTER ZOO
by Philip Schofield
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987485324324324" page_id="56256245"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
I visited Colchester Zoo frequently as a child in the 1960s. Like most
zoos of the time, it functioned as more of a consumer than a producer of
wildlife, with a preponderance of imported, wild-caught stock. From those
days, I remember particularly Tayra, Grison and Malabar Squirrels among
the mammals, and that the birds included wing-clipped crowned pigeons
sharing an open enclosure with cranes and waterfowl. The impression was
that Lions, Leopards and Cheetahs (the zoo had relatively 'handleable'
examples of all three) were the most valued exhibits. There were, however,
lots of animals, many of them in comparatively small functional enclosures
with little in the way of stimulation.
How Colchester Zoo has changed since then! It still gives the impression
of being very full of animals, with comparatively little visitor space between
the enclosures. However, the latter are invariably spacious, imaginatively
designed and beautifully planted, with the animals presented in as natural
and attractive settings as possible.
We visited the zoo on March 28th, before the summer season had really
got under way and, although I did not see any of the arena presentations,
I understand that in addition to the more conventional owls and raptors,
crowned cranes and guineafowl also take part.
I hope I will be forgiven for writing in a bird journal about the mammals
of Colchester Zoo. They are so varied, well-kept and interesting, that I
cannot omit them. Large areas are devoted to African species, including
an area with zebras, ostriches, White Rhinoceroses, antelopes and crowned
cranes, with a bachelor group of three male giraffes. The youngest of these is
a pure-bred Rothschild's Giraffe, and it is hoped to work with this subspecies
in the future. In their own large and well laid out area is the zoo's group of
African Bush Elephants, the repeated breeding of which (some by artificial
insemination) must me one of the zoo's crowning achievements. Five were
in evidence at the time of our visit, and we saw some of the training that is
carried out daily. As with all the animals at Colchester, the aim of training
is to facilitate handling and health checks without the need for chemical
restraint. Training also provides behavioural enrichment for the animals.
Most of the mammals seem to be clicker trained, as are some of the reptiles,
such as Slender-snouted Crocodiles and the two female Komodo Dragons
(a species that until recently was either a legend or a distant memory in UK
zoos, depending on whether one was old enough to remember the pre-war
ones at London Zoo). We saw two female elephants interacting with their
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.345521" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256246" page_num="193" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - COLCHESTER ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999522" page_id="56256246"  page_num="193" year="" vol="">
193
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.996997609756098" page_id="56256246"  page_num="193" year="" vol="">
keepers in free contact. Protected contact, in which the trained animal
responds to cues and is handled through a safety barrier, is employed with
the third, a less even-tempered cow elephant and also with the magnificent
breeding bull and the juvenile home-bred bull.
Amongst the group of zebras is an elderly female zebra x donkey hybrid,
with a sign on the enclosure suggesting that the breeding of hybrids is not
appropriate in the modem conservation zoo and that this animal is a relic
of past attitudes. When I visited the zoo, perhaps 10 years earlier, three
4 Zedonks' were on show with their donkey mother. They had been bred
in the early days of Colchester Zoo, when the impression was that the zoo
could afford only one zebra. They received star billing in the local press
and were a considerable attraction. Zebra hybrids, with a horse or donkey,
are more commonly known as zebroids; 'Zedonk' appears to be Colchester
Zoo&amp;apos;s unique contribution to the English language.
Another relic of the same era is a magnificent male orang-utan named
Rajang, now in late middle age but still an impressive animal, with the deep
intelligent eyes of his kind. He too is a hybrid, from the days when Bornean
and Sumatran orangs were not always correctly identified and even the most
reputable zoos inadvertently produced such hybrids. Rajang is vasectomised
to prevent a second hybrid generation and it is hoped that an appropriate
female companion can be found for him. Meanwhile, he reigns in a solitary
state in an enormous new building purpose-built for orangs.
Other primates include groups of Gelada Baboons, Squirrel Monkeys
and Mandrills. Chimpanzees, including the chocolate mutation (originating
perhaps from Twycross Zoo!), occupy their own large and well-appointed
complex.
Other hoofstock housed elsewhere in the zoo, include the tiny Malayan
Chevrotain and the Philippine Spotted Deer. A captive population of the
latter, which is becoming increasingly rare in the wild, is fast becoming
established in the UK. For those interested in zoo history, there is a good
photograph of this deer (the type specimen photographed in 1870), in John
Edwards's London Zoo from Old Photographs (1996). Young were reared at
the zoo in succeeding years, but the species does not appear to have become
established there.
Spotted Hyenas used to be a feature of the collection at Colchester and,
after the rest of the group had gone, I was introduced (through 2m (5cm)
weldmesh) to the surviving elderly female named Mbembe, a charming
and friendly animal. The collection also includes a young pair of Striped
Hyenas. A young pair of Fennec Foxes have reared young and are likely to
make further contributions to the UK population of this enchanting creature.
Sand Cats were also on view at the time of my previous visit, but are no
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999619" page_id="56256247"  page_num="194" year="" vol="">
194
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.680656" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256247" page_num="194" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - COLCHESTER ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998063951219512" page_id="56256247"  page_num="194" year="" vol="">
longer represented in the Colchester collection. These two species, both
very small and sandy coloured and with large ears, always seem to me to be
canine and feline versions of the same model. Other cat species represented
in the collection include Amur Leopard, Tiger and Margay.
Turning to the birds: apart from a handsome pair of Egyptian Geese,
waterfowl are conspicuous by their absence. The only other geese are what
are apparently feral Canada Geese. I initially assumed that the Egyptian
Geese were also free-flying birds, but they turned out to be pinioned.
Although at large on the zoo lakes when we saw them, I wonder if they
were fugitives from the nearby mixed African area. This area is overlooked
by a tall aviary housing African vultures, some of which, such as Ruppell's
Griffon Vulture, have bred. Inside the African Pavilion, a breeding colony of
Rufous-necked or Village Weavers was very active, with the birds displaying,
quarrelling and working on their nests, above a group of Leopard Tortoises
with whom they share the enclosure. Three male and one female Dalmatian
Pelicans living at liberty on a lake and looking in good condition have not
so far bred. This could change if the dietary adjustments suggested by a
pelican-keeping member of our party are adopted. Most pelicans inhabit
freshwater, but in UK zoos are fed on sea fish. Whereas in European zoos,
situated further from the sea, they are more likely to be fed freshwater fish as
a matter of convenience and, as a result, European zoos are more successful
at breeding pelicans than UK zoos. We did not see the flock of 15 Chilean
Flamingos, as the birds were still in their winter quarters. Consistent success
is achieved at Colchester Zoo breeding Cattle Egrets, Humboldt Penguins
and Hammerkops; five of the last named were reared in 2008.
When the zoo opened in 1963, among the first birds were Andean Condors
and this species continues to be represented in the collection, at present by two
females. An old male, perhaps one of the original birds, had died recently,
apparently from lead poisoning. The collection also includes a pair of King
Vultures. Also on view are Painted Storks (the Asian version of the African
Yellow-billed Stork), which I do not recall seeing elsewhere. Among other
birds on view are a fine pair of Red-billed Blue Magpies, surely one of the
finest birds for public as well as private collections, that one can only hope
will receive the attention needed to firmly establish a self-sustaining captive
population. Colchester also has Stanley (Blue or Paradise) Cranes and East
African Crowned Cranes. The latter have bred repeatedly and some of the
young have been retained and trained as demonstration birds. We also saw
Southern Ground Hombills and Asian Black Hombills, both viewed through
glass, that is a feature of many of the zoo's enclosures.
It was an enjoyable day out to this major conservation-oriented zoo for
the 55 members and their guests who travelled to Colchester in Essex. The
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.345504" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256248" page_num="195" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - COLCHESTER ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999081" page_id="56256248"  page_num="195" year="" vol="">
195
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.96918925" page_id="56256248"  page_num="195" year="" vol="">
President's Garden Parties apart, it was the best attended social meeting for
many years and many, myself included, were left with the impression that
we could have profitably spent two or three days there, to have done justice
to all there was to see. I will certainly be going back again.
Our Chairman Christopher Marler thanked Managing Director Dominic
Tropeano for allowing us to hold our meeting at the zoo and for the wonderful
hospitality we received and, in appreciation, made him an Honorary Member
of the Avicultural Society.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.865601" page_id="56256248"  page_num="195" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.633715" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56256248" page_num="195" year="" vol="">
PREFERRED NESTING MATERIALS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.94621675" page_id="56256248"  page_num="195" year="" vol="">
One of our members is currently studying for a degree in zoo management
and as part of the third year of his study is investigating whether Zebra
Finches Taeniopygia guttata prefer natural or synthetic nesting materials. If
you have any information which may be relevant, you are asked to contact
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.582838" page_id="56256248"  page_num="195" year="" vol="">
Luke Forster by e-mail:lukeforster@hotmail.com
* * *
LAUGHINGTHRUSH CENSUS
On behalf of the Avicultural Society's Special Interest Groups, Andrew
Owen, Curator of Birds at Chester Zoo, and Ian Edmans, Assistant Curator
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.952213" page_id="56256248"  page_num="195" year="" vol="">
of Birds at Waddesdon Manor, are undertaking a census of captive-bred
laughingthrash.es in the UK.
There are currently 459 laughingthrushes known to be kept in the UK.
Several of the 23 species being kept appear to be increasing in numbers, but
others are represented by only one or &amp;apos;two individuals.
All keepers of laughingthrushes are asked to complete a questionaire,
copies of which are available from Ian (see address below) or can be
downloaded at: www.waddesdon.org.uk/aviary/aviary_publications.html
Completed forms should be returned to Ian at: Waddesdon Manor
Aviary, Waddesdon, Nr. Aylesbury, Buckinghamshire HP! 8 OJH. For more
information about the laughingthrash census you can contact Ian at: Ian.
Edmans@nationaltrast.org.uk
The results of the census will be published in the Avicultural
Magazine.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999486" page_id="56256249"  page_num="196" year="" vol="">
196
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9855605" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256249" page_num="196" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
A SOUTH AMERICAN ODYSSEY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999087083333334" page_id="56256249"  page_num="196" year="" vol="">
For those of you who think that Rosemary Low only writes books about
parrots - think again. Although weighted towards parrots, Rosemary's latest
book - Go Westfor Parrots! - is a fascinating insight into Rosemary's travels
over the past 30 years and the vast array of species and people that she has
encountered. It is as much a travel log as it is a bird book and as such will
be equally treasured by the traveller as it will be by the naturalist.
With its stunning cover shot of Hyacinth Macaws flying over the Pantanal
to its charming hand-drawn maps, this book is one which you will find
difficult to put down. Rosemary has surpassed herself with the simple but
highly effective layout of the book; each chapter covers a particular South
American country or island group, and each country has an insert panel
within the chapter, with details of interesting and sometimes little known facts
about the area. Each chapter concludes with a list of species mentioned in
the text, together with their scientific names, and a list of the threatened bird
species in each threat category. Even though many of Rosemary's acounts
are of trips taken several years ago, each chapter is neatly rounded off with
an update, providing details of the latest conservation measures being taken
in the area, the current status of the birds, if it has changed, and, even in
some cases, updates on the characters that she met.
The book is illustrated with numerous photographs which really bring
the text to life; these vary from images of the swamp men in Trinidad to
Bolivian market scenes and the tranquillity of the Argentinian lakes; and, of
course, a wealth of images of birds and other animals. If I had one criticism
of the book, and it is a minor one, it would be that all the photographs are in
black and white - it is such a shame that some of these stunning shots could
not be reproduced in colour.
In typical Rosemary style, this book is packed with well-written
descriptions of wildlife, habitat and the amazing and often humbling
characters that she has encountered on her travels. Whether you read it
from cover to cover or just dip in to find out more about your next holiday
destination, you will not be disappointed. This book deserves a much wider
audience than just the avicultural and natural history market. When you
buy a copy, why not buy a second copy and give it to a friend who knows
nothing about birds, I guarantee that they will enjoy it and, if it does not
awaken the dormant naturalist and conservationist within them, I will be
truly surprised.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909695" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256250" page_num="197" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99893" page_id="56256250"  page_num="197" year="" vol="">
197
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.98920775" page_id="56256250"  page_num="197" year="" vol="">
Go West for Parrots! (ISBN 978-0-9531337-6-5), 320 pages, 120 mono
illustrations, 18 maps, is available from Insignis Publications, PO Box 100,
Mansfield, Notts NG20 9PR, UK. Price #10.95 plus #3 postage. Cheques
should be made payable to Rosemary Low.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.456337">
David Woolcock
</subsectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.964125" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56256250" page_num="197" year="" vol="">
DISCOVERING NATURE IN BRITAIN AND NORTHERN
IRELAND
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.922844434782609" page_id="56256250"  page_num="197" year="" vol="">
RSPB Where to Discover Nature in Britain and Northern Ireland is a
new guide to RSPB (Royal Society for the Protection of Birds) reserves,
with two to four pages on each. It is full of excellent colour photos, giving
a good impression of the different habitats as well as examples of the birds,
invertebrates and mammals which may be present on each reserve. Details
include seasonal variations, facilities, what to look out for and occasional
snippets of additional information about species present. The maps of the
reserves are clear and informative, although an indication of scale would
be helpful. The main problem I found with this book is the layout, which
is by country and region, with no mention of counties and only one map
on the inside front cover. It would be more useful if a map of each area
was included, or if the reserve details included the county and nearest large
town. Postcodes and grid references are given but these are useful only if
you have maps/the internet immediately to hand. The title of the book is
slightly misleading due to the clustering of RSPB reserves in certain areas.
Thus the book does not describe many of the best places to discover nature
in areas such as 'the midlands 5 (covering numerous counties) which has
only five RSPB reserves. Conversely Scotland has 43 reserves and almost
100 pages describing them. Overall this is an attractive book that gives a
comprehensive overview of RSPB reserves.
RSPB Where to Discover Nature in Britain and Northern Ireland (ISBN
9781408108642) by Marianne Taylor, paperback, 352 pages, 250 colour
photos, 120 colour maps, Is published by A&amp;C Black, London W1D 3HB.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.40893" page_id="56256250"  page_num="197" year="" vol="">
Website;www.acblack.com Price #12.99.
Shirley Ellis
</figure>
<page confidence="0.999" page_id="56256251"  page_num="198" year="" vol="">
198
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996731" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256251" page_num="198" year="" vol="">
LATEST FBF BREEDING REGISTER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994776923076923" page_id="56256251"  page_num="198" year="" vol="">
The latest Foreign Bird Federation (FBF) Breeding Register, which
covers the period 2005-2008, reveals that a total of 16,679 birds of 522
species were recorded as having been bred in the UK in 2008. Although
the total was higher than those for any of the preceding three years, there
are no 2008 breeding records for a significant number of species and some
others were bred in fewer numbers than one might expect - or at least that
is what the records show.
On the plus side, the number of Crested Wood Partridges Rollulus rouloul
being bred each year seems to be rising, with an all-time high of 79 being bred
in 2008. Twenty-six Chinese Bamboo Partridges Bambusicola thoracicus
were bred, 14 Madagascar Partridges Margaroperdix madagascarensis and
15 Black Francolins Francolinus francolinus . One suspects that many more
pheasants were bred than the records show. The Congo Peafowl Afropavo
congensis , having last been bred in the UK in 2004, seems in danger of
disappearing from the register.
Here again, as always, a long list of waterfowl were bred, but not in
the numbers one might expect, at least not according to the records; and,
it appears, that neither the Caribbean Flamingo Phoenicopterus ruber or
Greater Flamingo P. roseus were bred in 2008. Pleasingly, five Boat-billed
Herons Cochlearius cochlearius are listed as having been bred. There are
no records of the Corncrake Crex crex having been bred since 2004 or of
the Socorro Dove Zenaida graysoni having been bred in 2008. This led me
to suspect that some collections had not submitted their results and, upon
checking, I was disappointed to discover that London and Whipsnade Zoos,
Paignton, Edinburgh and the Wildfowl &amp; Wetlands Trust are all missing
from the list of contributors.
Amongst the many pigeons and doves recorded as have been bred
in 2008, were 10 Eared Doves Z. auriculata, 18 Luzon Bleeding-Hearts
Gallicolumba luzonica , four Nicobar Pigeons Caloenas nicobarica and
five Bruce's Green Pigeons Treron waalia; three crowned pigeons Goura
spp. were bred. Two hundred and twenty-one Grey Parrots Psittacus e.
erithacus are listed as having been bred in 2008, plus 11 P e. timneh . Just
two Blue-throated Macaws Ara glaueogularis are listed and four Military
Macaws A militaris , as well as four Blue-headed Primolius couloni and five
Yellow-collared P. auricollis. It is noticeable that several species of parrot
have not been recorded as having been bred since 2004 or earlier.
Turacos generally continued to do well: 19 White-cheeked Turacos
Taurco leucotis were bred, 17 Fischer's Turacos T. fischeri , 14 Red-crested
T. erythrolophus and 11 Violet Turacos Musophaga violacea ; others bred
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.962498" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256252" page_num="199" year="" vol="">
FBF BREEDING REGISTER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999117" page_id="56256252"  page_num="199" year="" vol="">
199
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.983802384615384" page_id="56256252"  page_num="199" year="" vol="">
included two Ross's M. rossae, two White-crested I leucolophus and four
Purple-crested 7 porphyreo lopkus . I am pleased to see that the Guira
Cuckoo Guira guira was bred again in 2008. The Laughing Kookaburra
Dacelo novaeguineae and White-collared Kingfisher Todiramphus chloris
were bred, but not the Blue-winged Kookaburra D. leachii. Five Red-billed
Hombills Tockus erythrorhynchus and five Von der Decken's T. deckeni were
bred, plus a Wrinkled Hombill Aceros corrugatus and a Writhed Hombill A.
leucocephalus. A total of 45 Spot-flanked Barbets Tricholaema lacrymosa
were bred between 2006-2008 and seven Spangled Cotingas Cotinga cayana
were reared - one in 2008 and two in each of the preceding three years.
Eleven Blue-crowned Laughingthrushes Dryonastes courtoisi were bred
in 2008 and six Sumatran Black-and-white Laughingthrushes G. bicolor . A
remarkable 71 Pekin Robins Leiothrix lutea were bred, 64 Chestnut-backed
Thrushes Zoothera dohertyi and 17 Snowy-crowned Robin-Chats Cossypha
niveicapilla (three fewer than the previous year) but, disappointingly, only
six White-rumped Shamas Copsychus malabaricus were recorded as having
been bred in 2008 and no Magpie Robins C. saularis.
Probably more small seedeaters (waxbills, grassfinches and munias) than
ever before are now being bred. The 2008 figures, for example, include 631
Cut-throat Finches Amadina fasciata , 231 Blue-capped Waxbills Uraeginthus
cyanocephala , 122 Red-cheeked Cordon Bleus U. bengalus, 138 Golden-
breasted Waxbills Amandava subflava (Sporaeginthus subflavus ) and a
large number of Australian species, with the Gouldian Erythrura gouldiae ,
of which 1,472 are listed as having been bred in 2008, way out in front of
all of the others.
Ninety-four Red Siskins Carduelis cucullata are listed as having been
bred and 91 Mexican House Finches Carpodacus mexicanus. Eighty-four
Cuban Finches or Grassquits Tiaris canorus were bred, an increase on the
number bred in each of the preceding three years. One further breeding
I cannot resist commenting on, is the breeding of seven Scarlet Tanagers
Piranga olivacea - it is a species I cannot recall ever having encountered in
aviculture - and I would like to know more about this breeding.
The register provides a fascinating snapshot of the state of UK aviculture.
It is interesting to see which species are thriving (i.e. breeding well) and which
are not and are likely, therefore, as a result of the EU ban on bird imports, to
eventually die out - perhaps never again to be seen in this country.
Copies of the register for 2005-2008 are now available price #5 (post
free). Cheques should be made payable to the Foreign Bird Federation and
sent to the FBF Breeding Registrar: Reuben B. Girling, 11 Deramore Drive,
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.5225215" page_id="56256252"  page_num="199" year="" vol="">
Badger Hill, York YO10 5HW.
Malcolm Ellis
</figure>
<page confidence="0.971696" page_id="56256253"  page_num="200" year="" vol="">
200
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.977501" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256253" page_num="200" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
DEVELOPMENTS AT LORO PARQUE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.973862869565218" page_id="56256253"  page_num="200" year="" vol="">
Loro Parque announced in September that a further two Pesquet's Parrots
Psittrichas fulgidus had hatched and were growing up alongside their two
earlier siblings. A Thick-billed Parrot Rhynchopsitta pachyrhyncha had
also hatched, after the pair had broken the first egg. The second egg was
removed from the nest and artificially incubated and a third egg was left
with the female to incubate.
As part of the international breeding programme, two adult female Lear's
Macaws Anodorhynchus leari arrived from Busch Gardens, Tampa, Florida.
The two females were hatched there in the 1980s, but because it had not
been possible to find mates for them, it was decided to transfer them to the
Loro Parque Fundacion (LPF) and at the same time transfer their ownership
to the Brazilian Government. They were brought from the USA to Tenerife
by the LPF President Wolfgang Kiessling. It is planned to pair them with
two young males bred by the Loro Parque Fundacion, which now holds 17
Lear's Macaws.
An enormous, new, free-flight aviary, named Katandra Treetops - katandra
in the Australian aboriginal language meaning "song of the birds" - has
recently been opened in the parque. It houses various species of lories and
lorikeets, cockatoos, kookaburras, crowned pigeons, fruit doves, Golden
Pheasants Chrysolophuspictus, Mandarin Ducks Aixgalericulata, egrets and
many other birds. Waterfalls flow into a lake, surrounded by lush tropical
vegetation, and there is a suspension bridge and walkways from which
visitors can watch the birds.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.461173" page_id="56256253"  page_num="200" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.519491" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256253" page_num="200" year="" vol="">
CHANGES AT TWYCROSS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.79514925" page_id="56256253"  page_num="200" year="" vol="">
Ben Potterton, Zoo Operations Manager at Twycross Zoo in Warwickshire,
here in the UK, reports that the bird department has had an interesting past
nine months, following a dramatic change in the department's management,
which resulted in an immediate improvement in breeding results.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.44482225" page_id="56256253"  page_num="200" year="" vol="">
Macaroni Penguin Eudyptes chrysolophus , Humboldt Penguin
Spheniscus humboldti, Cattle Egret Bubulcus ibis , Striated Caracara
Phalcoboenus australis , Blue-winged Goose Cyanochen cyanoptera , Crested
Wood Partridge Rollulus rouloul , Black-winged Ground Dove Metriopelia
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.466285333333333" page_id="56256253"  page_num="200" year="" vol="">
melanoptera and Boobook Owl Ninox b. boobook all bred and some of the
parrots and Chilean Flamingos Phoenicopterus chilensis showed encouraging
signs that they may breed in the near future.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700357" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256254" page_num="201" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994966" page_id="56256254"  page_num="201" year="" vol="">
201
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.993123" page_id="56256254"  page_num="201" year="" vol="">
A new collection plan was implemented early in 2009 and as a result
several new species were added to the collection, these include Red Turtle
Dove Streptopelia tranquebarica, Madagascar Turtle Dove S. picturata ,
Bar-shouldered Dove Geopelia humeral is, Temminck's Tragopan Tragopan
temminckii , Mountain Bamboo Partridge Bambusicola fytchii , Boat-billed
Heron Cochlearius cochlearius and African Grey Hombill Tockus nasutus.
These have been introduced into the old block of aviaries at the back of the
Tropical House. Green Imperial Pigeon Ducula aenea , Little Pied Cormorant
Phalacmcorax melanoleucos, Purple Heron Ardeapurpurea , Black-crowned
Night Heron Nycticorax nycticorax and Striated Heron Buteroides striata
have been added to the birds in the Long-House Aviary and, Nyasa Lovebird
Agapornis lilianae and European Roller Coracias gar ruins, are housed in
off-show breeding aviaries. Southern Cassowary Casuarius casuarius are
back in the collection after a short break and Raven Corvus corax , African
Pied Crow C. albus and Silvery-cheeked Hombill Ceratogymna (. Bycanistes )
brevis have also been added to the collection.
There have been a number of other new developments at the zoo during
2009. These include a new pet area which has an Australian walk-through
aviary, that includes a prolific flock of Gouldian Finches Erythrura gouldiae.
A new Himalaya building is due to open in spring 2010, one of the main
attractions of which will be a large exhibit housing waterbirds. Some of these,
including Little Grebe Tachybaptus ruficollis , Ringed Plover Charadrius
hiaticula and Little Bittern Ixobrychus minutus , have already arrived and
waterfowl, terns and other waders are due to arrive in the coming months.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.673862" page_id="56256254"  page_num="201" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.749943" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56256254" page_num="201" year="" vol="">
BIRDLIFE APPEAL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.976307857142857" page_id="56256254"  page_num="201" year="" vol="">
In Its latest letter appealing for donations to help fund its work trying to
save threatened species, BirdLife IntemationaTs Chief Executive Dr Marco
Lambertini writes that 1,227 species are on the 2009IUCN Red List of birds
under threat of extinction - that is over 12% of all bird species.
With its partners it is working hard to control the use of the veterinary
drag diclofenac which is such a potent threat to vulture populations in Asia
and Africa. It is also working to protect remnant forests on Sao Tome,
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.589567166666667">
the Comoro Islands, Sangihe, Indonesia (home of the Red and-blue Lory
Eos his trio and Sangihe Hanging Parrot Loriculus catamene ) and Brazil's
remaining Atlantic forest. Other measures include protecting and managing
tropical forest in important bird areas in Indonesia, Colombia, Ecuador,
Peru and Mexico. An Action Plan is being implemented to save the Spoon-
billed Sandpiper Eurynorhynchus pygmeus , the population of which has
</reference>
<page confidence="0.996309" page_id="56256255"  page_num="202" year="" vol="">
202
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.926374" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256255" page_num="202" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.958660333333333" page_id="56256255"  page_num="202" year="" vol="">
declined by more than 80% in the past 30 years, leaving just 400 remaining
breeding pairs.
Among its recent successes is the downlisting of Gurney's Pitta Pitta
gurneyi from Critically Endangered to a lower threat category. This 'jewel
of the forest' has benefited from improved protection and forest management,
resulting in fewer chicks being lost to predators such as the Dog-nosed Cat
Snake Boiga cynodon, as well as an increase in the number of earthworms,
which account for three-quarters of the pitta's diet. Other species similarly
downlisted include the Gorgeted Wood-Quail Odontophorus strophium,
Marquesas Imperial Pigeon Ducula galeata and Somali Thrush Turdus
lidoviciae.
To learn more about BirdLife International and its work you can visit its
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.524866" page_id="56256255"  page_num="202" year="" vol="">
Website:www.birdlife.org or E-mail: birdlife@birdlife.org
* * *
FIRST SUCCESS FOR CAPTIVE BREEDING PROGRAMME
The Institute for Research and Nature Conservation (Instituto de
Pesquisa e Conservaqao da Natureza - Ideia Ambiental) of Curitiba, Brazil
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.989332" page_id="56256255"  page_num="202" year="" vol="">
is working to conserve the Red-browed Amazon Amazona rhodocorytha in
the wild, where as few as 845 birds are estimated to survive in the Atlantic
forest of eastern Brazil; and, as an insurance policy, in 2006 initiated a
parallel project to establish a captive breeding programme in Brazil. With
financial support from the Loro Parque Fundacion (LPF) and the American
Federation of Aviculture (AFA), a breeding centre was built on land owned
by another of its partners, Curitiba City Zoo (Zoologico Municipal de
Curitiba). The breeding centre will, it is hoped, establish a genetically viable
captive breeding population of this species in Brazil, exchange information
with other breeders, and may eventually be used to release captive-bred
birds into the wild to boost the declining population. The project is run by
Louri Klernann Jr of Ideia Ambiental and benefits from the advice of Pedro
Scherer-Neto of the Curitiba Natural History Museum (Museu de Historia
Natural Capao da Imbuia).
The captive breeding programme began with 21 birds, confiscated by
the Brazilian authorities and deposited with the centre by IBAMA (Brazilian
Institute of Environment and Natural Resources). Following quarantine
the birds were sexed and placed together in a large aviary to enable them to
choose their own mates. At least seven pairs were established, which were
transferred to breeding aviaries. It took two breeding seasons for all of the
birds to reach maturity and feel comfortable in their new surroundings. Now,
the first pair has nested and was recently rearing three healthy chicks. The
other pairs were being closely observed in the hope that they too might be
about to breed.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700393" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256256" page_num="203" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995641" page_id="56256256"  page_num="203" year="" vol="">
203
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.988794" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256256" page_num="203" year="" vol="">
END OF SEASON REPORT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989886115384615" page_id="56256256"  page_num="203" year="" vol="">
Birds bred at Chester Zoo during the 2009 breeding season included two
Socorro Doves Zenalda graysoni and two Montserrat Orioles Icterus oberi.
It was the first time either of these species have bred there. Five Ecuadorian
or Lilacine Amazons Arnazona autumnalis lilacina were bred, three of which
were hand-reared. Currently it is the only collection in the UK breeding
the Fairy Bluebird Irena puella, the chicks of which are hand-reared. Two
pairs of Tawny Frogmouths Podargus strigoides produced five young (this
species also bred at London Zoo). Caribbean Flamingos Phoenicopterus
ruber and Chilean Flamingos P chilensis also had a good breeding season.
Breeding programmes are being planned for the Sumatran Black-and-white
Laughingthrash Garrulax bicolor and Red Bird-of-Paradise Paradisaea
rubra, the zoo having recently acquired three females of the latter, which it
hopes to pair with its three existing males.
The zoo's new walk-through aviary, called the Tsavo National Park Bird
Safari, was officially opened recently. It houses birds living in Kenya's Tsavo
National Park, where Chester Zoo supports a number of key conservation
projects. It is hoped the aviary will eventually house up to 15 different
species, these include Hamerkop Scopus umbretta, Hottentot Teal Anas
hottentota, Von der Decken's Hombill Tockus deckeni , Lilac-breasted Roller
Coracias caudatus , Superb Starling Lamprotornis superbus and weavers
Ploceus spp. Bird staff continue to work on conservation projects abroad,
notably with the Mauritius Fody Foudia rubra and Mauritius Olive White-
eye Zosterops chloronothos on the Indian Ocean island of Mauritius and
the nearby He aux Aigrettes. The zoo also continues to support Prof. He
Fen-qi's work with the Blue-crowned Laughingthrash Dryonastes courtoisi
in China.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.557429" page_id="56256256"  page_num="203" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.816173" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256256" page_num="203" year="" vol="">
WINTER WEAVERS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993056545454545" page_id="56256256"  page_num="203" year="" vol="">
Here in Cornwall, down in the far south-west, we had a relatively mild
(but very wet) late autumn (fall) and early winter, nevertheless it came
as a surprise to learn that Village Weavers Ploceus cucullatus were still
nesting outdoors at Paradise Park, Hayle, at the beginning of December. On
December 3rd, Curator David Woolcock told me that in their entrance aviary,
protected only by a piece of clear plastic sheeting to prevent the rain causing
a problem, Village Weavers had four nests, three of which contained chicks
and, fresh eggshell on the floor that morning, suggested that the fourth nest
might also contain chicks. Already, more than 20 young had been bred in
2009. David added, that in December the biggest problem is keeping up a
supply of long grass for nest building.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998867" page_id="56256257"  page_num="204" year="" vol="">
204
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9824005" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256257" page_num="204" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
ASTONISHING SUCCESS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986937117647059" page_id="56256257"  page_num="204" year="" vol="">
In their Christmas card featuring "Birds of Texas: Big Bend Country",
Josef and Natalie Lindholm confirmed that since 2007,19 Andean Cocks-of-
the-Rock Rupicolaperuvianas have been hatched at Dallas World Aquarium,
of which 14 are still alive.
Josef and Natalie went on to reveal that over 200 toucans, toucanets and
araqaris of 14 taxa were hatched at Dallas World Aquarium during 2009, of
which at least 170 survived. Another probable first captive breeding, to go
with the breeding of the Many-banded Ara^ari Pteroglossus pluricinctus
and Fiery-billed Araqari P. frantzii (mentioned in the previous issue), was
the breeding of the (Panamanian) Blue-throated Toucanet Aulacorhynchus
caeruleogularis (formerly the Blue-throated Emerald Toucanet A prasinus
caeruleogularis). There are now 29 taxa of toucans, toucanets and ara^aris
represented in the aquarium's bird collection. New species and subspecies
added during the year included Blue-banded Toucanets A. coeruleicinctus
and its first Lettered Ara 9 aris P inscriptus and Black-throated Toucanets
A. atrogularis (formerly the Black-throated Emerald Toucanet (A. p.
atrogularis).
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.7413096" page_id="56256257"  page_num="204" year="" vol="">
Homed Guans Oreophasis derbianus , Wattled Guans Aburria aburri ,
Helmeted Curassows Pauxi pauxi and Homed Curassows P unicornis ,
as well as Nocturnal Curassows Nothocrax urumutum and Blue-billed
Curassows Crax alberti , have arrived from Dr Estudillo.
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.915127" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256257" page_num="204" year="" vol="">
NEWLY DISCOVERED POPULATION OF RARE PARROTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999320941176471" page_id="56256257"  page_num="204" year="" vol="">
A new population of the Critically Endangered Yellow-eared Parrot
Ognorhynchus icterotis , consisting of a breeding colony of some 100-120
birds, has been discovered on the eastern slopes of the Andes in Colombia.
The birds nest and feed not in Wax Palms Ceroxylon quindiverse, but instead
nest in the smaller Andean Royal Palms Dictyocaryum lamarckianum , which
grow below 2,000m (approx. 6,500ft) above sea level.
A team of field workers belonging to Fundacion ProAves has evaluated
the new location and believe the birds may be a relict Eastern Cordillera
population that has managed to survive by adapting to different habitat.
Because so few Wax Palms survive in the highlands (where they are cut down
for Palm Sunday celebrations), the Yellow-eared Parrots are coming down to
1,200m-1,500m (approx. 4,000ft-5,000ft) to nest in the Andean Royal Palms.
The area is very steep and relatively heavily forested, although gradually
being cleared and, therefore, at some risk. Each day the parrots fly up to
less accessible higher elevations. ProAves has a good working relationship
with local landowners and will continue to monitor the population and plan
the best way to conserve the site.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998026" page_id="56256258"  page_num="205" year="" vol="">
205
</page>
<table confidence="0.773919766666667" page_id="56256258"  page_num="205" year="" vol="">
Contributors to Volume 115 - 2009
Ackroyd, Nicholas
The parent-rearing of Hooded Pitta chicks Pitta sordida mulleri
in a mixed species walk-through exhibit at ZSL London Zoo.................27
Bamicoat, F. C.
Experiences breeding the White-throated Magpie-Jay
Calocitta formosa in South Africa.........................................................181
Borghesio, Luca, Kumsa, Toler a, Remould, Jean-Marc
and Bekele, Afework
Is Prince Ruspoii's Turaco threatened by hybridization with
the White-cheeked Turaco?..........................................,......................... 138
Bralsford, Gary
Keeping and breeding the Lesser Kiskadee Philohydor lictor. ............. 113
The challenge of keeping kingfishers......................................................41
Brickell, Neville
Further notes on an African bunting........................................................37
Gibson, Derek
Management of the Crested Pigeon Ocyphaps lophotes
at Exmoor Zoo....................................................................................... 185
The unusual nesting behaviour of a pair of White-browed Coucals
Centropus superciliosus at Exmoor Zoo..................................................17
Hal lager, Sara
The distraction behaviour of a female Kori Bustard Ardeotis kori. ....... 116
Hewston, Nigel
The society&amp;apos;s visit to Berlin.....................................................................20
Low, Rosemary
Iron storage disease (haemochromatosis) in lories................................ 119
Pappas, Janice, L.
Notes on the nesting activity, vocalizations and egg-laying
of the Chinese Painted Quail Coturnix chinensis ..................................161
</table>
<page confidence="0.993549" page_id="56256259"  page_num="206" year="" vol="">
206
</page>
<figure confidence="0.930457875" page_id="56256259"  page_num="206" year="" vol="">
Contributors to Volume 115 - 2009 (cont'd)
Peat, Louise
Hand-rearing White-browed Coucals Centropus superciliosus . .1
Quinque, Dr Henry
My life with the Kagu Rhynochetos jubatus.. .........49
Restall, Robin
A long-tern study suggests that the Slate-coloured Seedeater
Sporophila schistacea is both monotypic and polymorphic.....172
The comparative behaviour of hand-reared
Spectacled Thrushes Turdus nudigensis ...2
Schofield, Philip
The society&amp;apos;s visit to Colchester Zoo...192
The society's visit to Exmoor Zoo.........149
Simpson, Nigel
Hand-rearing pigeons and doves at Bristol Zoo Gardens.......121
Stocks, Peter
The Tropical Screech Owl Megascops choliba ..........169
Thurlow, Graham
Birdwatching in the Philippines........126
Waugh, David
Further news of the Blue-throated Macaw..........35
Wuest, Rene
Searching for the Black-collared Lovebird
Agapornis swindernianus in Uganda.........
</figure>
<page confidence="0.992155" page_id="56256259"  page_num="206" year="" vol="">
143
</page>
<page confidence="0.995753" page_id="56256260"  page_num="207" year="" vol="">
207
</page>
<table confidence="0.94092525" page_id="56256260"  page_num="207" year="" vol="">
Index to Volume 115 - 2009
Agapornis swindernianus , a search for, in Uganda ....143
Ara glaucogularis, further news of.............35
Ardeotis kori , the distraction behaviour of a female.............. 116
Birdwatching, in the Philippines.................................................126
Book Reviews
Go West for Parrots! ......196
International Zoo Yearbook, Volume 43.......153
RSPB Where to Discover Nature in Britain and N. Ireland.197
The Wisdom of Birds.....46
Why Does my Parrot?.........152
Bunting, Cabanis's, notes on...........37
Bustard, Kori, the distraction behaviour of a female................ 116
Calocitta formosa , breeding in South Africa...... 181
Centropus superciliosus, hand-rearing..........7
Centropus superciliosus , unusual nesting behaviour..........17
Coturnix chinensis, nesting, vocalizations and egg-laying....161
Coucal, White-browed, hand-rearing.....7
Coucal, White-browed, unusual nesting behaviour.....17
Emberiza cabanisi , notes on................37
FBF Breeding Register ..... 198
Haemochromatosis (see Iron storage disease)
Hombills, Family Adoption Report, from Thailand......134
Iron storage disease (haemochromatosis) in lories...119
</table>
<reference confidence="0.981964666666666">
Kagu, my life with. ...........49
Kingfishers, the challenge of keeping........41
Kiskadee, Lesser, keeping and breeding..........113
Lories, susceptible to iron storage disease (haemochromatosis)...119
Lovebird, Black-collared, a search for, in Uganda ....143
Macaw, Blue-throated, further news of................................35
</reference>
<page confidence="0.997572" page_id="56256261"  page_num="208" year="" vol="">
208
</page>
<table confidence="0.840150733333333" page_id="56256261"  page_num="208" year="" vol="">
Index to Volume 115 - 2009 (cont'd)
Magpie-Jay, White-throated, breeding in South Africa ...181
Megascops choliba , notes on, including breeding..........169
News &amp; Views....... 156,200
Ocyphaps lophotes , management at Exmoor Zoo..........185
Officers &amp; Council Members, as from March 28th 2009.......1
Philohydor lie tor, keeping and breeding.... 113
Pigeon, Crested, management at Exmoor Zoo..... 185
Pigeons and doves, hand-rearing at Bristol Zoo Gardens.. 121
Pitta, Hooded, parent-rearing of chicks at London Zoo........27
Pitta sordida mulleri , parent-rearing of chicks at London Zoo... 27
Quail, Chinese Painted, nesting, vocalizations and egg-laying............. 161
Rhynochetos jubatus , my life with...........49
Screech Owl, Tropical, notes on, including breeding...169
Seedeater, Slate-coloured, may be monotypic and polymorphic.172
</table>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.939612">
Social Meetings
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9878801" page_id="56256261"  page_num="208" year="" vol="">
The society's visit to Berlin and its two zoos... 20
The society's visit to Colchester Zoo. 192
The society's visit to Exmoor Zoo.. .149
Sporophila schistacea , may be monotypic and polymorphic.172
Tauraco leucotis , hybridizing with T. ruspolii. ... 138
Tauraco ruspolii, may be threatened by hybridization.....138
Thrush, Spectacled, comparative behaviour of hand-reared chicks..2
Turaco, Prince Ruspoli's, may be threatened by hybridization...138
Turaco, White-cheeked, hybridizing with I ruspolii. ........................... 138
Turdus nudigenis, comparative behaviour of hand-reared chicks...2
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.992023" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256262" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONSERVING CASSOWARIES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995131538461539" page_id="56256262"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Jo Gregson, Curator of Birds at Paignton Zoo Environment Park,
here in the UK, is leading the International Cassowary Recovery Team,
set up recently to coordinate efforts to conserve cassowaries in European
collections.
Jo wants to find out where the cassowaries in Europe originated from
and what is their genetic make-up. The team plans to approach all the zoos
in Europe and ask them to provide DNA samples, so that an attempt can be
made to trace the origin of their birds. It is suggested that there could be
up to eight distinct forms of the Southern Cassowary Casuarius casuarius.
These may be subspecies or could even be distinct species - nobody is quite
sure. In their 1980 checklist, Howard and Moore recognised three species
of cassowary, the Double-wattled C. casuarius , Dwarf C. bennetti and
One-wattled C. unappendiculatus, with several subspecies listed for each
of them. In his 2007 checklist, Clements (citing as his reference source
Handbook of the Birds of the World Vol.l) recognised the same three
species, known now as the Southern, Dwarf and Northern Cassowaries, but
listed no subspecies.
For more than 30 years cassowaries have been kept at Paignton Zoo,
during which time a total of 17 have been bred. Currently it has five Southern
Cassowaries.
Found in New Guinea, the Aru Islands and Queensland, north-eastern
Australia, the Southern Cassowary is threatened by human encroachment,
especially in Queensland, where as few as 1,500 may remain. Continuing
loss of habitat for residential, agricultural and industrial development is
contributing to the decline of this species in Queensland. Birds are injured
or killed in collisions with vehicles and in dog attacks.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.5988" page_id="56256262"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.985694" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56256262" page_num="" year="" vol="">
BIRD PARK FOR SALE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.977813333333333" page_id="56256262"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Come and enjoy the clean green lifestyle New Zealand has to offer.
This is a growing business/lifestyle in tourism with huge potential for
further development. With over 300 birds this is one of New Zealand's
largest collections.
To view video tour of this property go to: www.propertylink.co.nz and
type in PL4401 or e-mail: garym@propertylink.co.nz
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.980040166666667" page_id="56256263"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
si nil .* ** *
3 908 0097702 ^
III
CONTENTS
Notes on the nesting activity, vocalizations and egg-laying of the
Chinese Painted Quail Coturnix chinensis
by Janice L. Pappas.161
The Tropical Screech Owl Megascops choliba
by Peter Stocks.169
A long-term study suggests that the Slate-coloured Seedeater
Sporophila schistacea is both monotypic and polymorphic
by Robin Restall.172
</figure>
<table confidence="0.695392777777778" page_id="56256263"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Experiences breeding the White-throated Magpie-Jay
Calocitta formosa in South Africa
by F. C. Bamicoat.181
Management of the Crested Pigeon Ocyphaps lophotes
at Exmoor Zoo
by Derek Gibson.185
The society's visit to Colchester Zoo
by Philip Schofield.192
Book Reviews
Go West for Parrots!.196
RSPB Where to Discover Nature in Britain
and Northern Ireland.197
Latest FBF Breeding Register.198
News &amp; Views.200
Contributors to Volume 115 - 2009.205
Index to Volume 115 - 2009.207
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</table>
</algorithms>
