<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.769982428571429" page_id="56312741"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
0 . 1 --
&amp; -y i
3J /WIC ULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 118
No. 4
2012
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990762" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312740" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.96460475" page_id="56312740"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2012: British Isles #21.00:
Overseas #24.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the
Society later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of
the AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.687655" page_id="56312740"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, SHERATON LODGE, STATION ROAD, SOUTHMINSTER,
ESSEX CM0 7EW, UK.
</construct>
<bodyText confidence="0.94756275" page_id="56312740"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Barclays Bank, Bumham-on-Crouch Branch. Please
quote Account No. 13296954, Sort Code 20 54 30, and ensure you send your
name as the account reference, or else we cannot match payments. In case
of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and Treasurer at the address
above, or e-mail: otusscops@talktalk.net
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have not
been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of a
particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history. Articles
should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the scientific
names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given. References
cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line drawings,
black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular point in
the article will be used where possible and should be clearly captioned. If
authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when submitting the
article and write their name on the back of each photograph. Tables and
graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be aware of
the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of the page
which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997594" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56312740" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982475333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.812745" genericHeader="method" page_id="56312739" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.312335" page_id="56312739"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 118 - No. 4 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2012
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.994407666666667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56312739" page_num="" year="" vol="">
FURTHER THOUGHTS ON THE DIETARY
REQUIREMENTS OF QUAIL AND THEIR
KEEPING AND BREEDING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.974336111111111" page_id="56312739"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Carl Gamham
I was interested by Jack Eitniear and Terry Becherer's article on dietary
considerations when breeding Montezuma Quail Cyrtonyx montezumae
(Vol. 118, No. 1, pp.6-11 (2012)). I began keeping quail in the early 1980s,
when a friend passed onto me a handful of Bobwhite Colinus virginianus
eggs he could not get to hatch. I managed to hatch them without difficulty
and was hooked - though I was yet to master rearing the chicks.
Quail, Their Breeding and Management by Gary Robbins (1983) was at
the time the only source of information about keeping and breeding quail,
so the following year I set up pretty much as the author advised and bought
my first quail - a pair of California Callipepla californica. Over the next
few years my collection increased to include three to five pairs each of
10 species and one subspecies, including Mountain Quail Oreortyx picta ,
Meam's Quail C. montezumae mearnsi and Gambel's Quail C. gambelii ,
which I imported privately from the USA.
All of the stock was kept, as it is here today, along with Stone Partridge
Ptilopachus petrosus and See-see Partridge Ammoperdix griseogularis, in
outdoor, unheated, unlit, raised pens, on a 2in-3in (approx. 5cm-7.5cm)
deep litter of peat, chopped straw and wood shavings/chips. The pens for
the California Quail-sized species are 4ft (approx. 1.22m) square and those
for the Jungle-bush Quail Perdicula asiatica and similar sized species are
two-thirds this size. A branch is provided for perching on, as well as a
block/stump. Kept dry, these pens need cleaning only every two to three
years and, even then, any build-up of droppings is not obvious due to the
birds scratching in the litter.
The birds were fed a 50:50 mix of poultry chick crumbs and a seed mix
based loosely on the mix credited to T. R. Warwick in the above mentioned
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999442" page_id="56312738"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
146
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.910159" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312738" page_num="146" year="" vol="">
GARNHAM - QUAIL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996588414634146" page_id="56312738"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
book, but with one-eighth of the mix consisting of oilseeds - linseed, rape,
safflower, hemp and niger. It had a protein content of 14% and was of
high quality due to the oilseed content. Prior to BSE (bovine spongiform
encephalopathy), the chick crumbs contained fish meal and meat and bone
meal. The coccidiostat was usually amprolium. The protein content was
18%. The birds were fed this all year round, with some fine oystershell added
during the laying period. They were fed each day and waste was minimal.
They were also provided with water treated with a multi vitamin/mineral mix
Duphasol, sold as a pick-me-up for intensively farmed poultry, which became
unavailable following the takeover/merger of Duphar b.v. by Solvay b.v.
Apart from a single experiment in the early days with a trio of Gambel's
Quail, all were and continue to be kept in pairs. Here on the Essex-Suffolk
border, the commoner Callipepla species began laying in the second week
of April. The Mountain Quail began to lay approximately 10 days earlier
- usually on April 1 st, give or take no more than a day and, therefore, easily
remembered. The birds kept by a good friend under very similar conditions
further north not far from Merseyside in north-west England, laid their first
eggs of the season approximately one week later. The end of laying, which
happened sometime in September or early October, was definitely influenced
by the weather.
Crested Bobwhite C. cristatus laid on and off throughout most of the
year. I never kept count but a pair probably laid over 150 eggs. Some were
laying when the temperature was around -20*C (-4*F) and the wind chill
-40*C (-40*F) during the freak winter sometime in the late 1980s. Drifting
snow was something like 6ft (approx. 1.8m) deep in my garden and the eggs
froze in the nest box. Masked Bobwhite C. v. ridgwayi , Jungle-bush Quail,
Elegant (Benson's /Douglas) C. douglasii and Meam's, in particular, started
later than the commoner Callipepla species and laid fewer eggs.
Pairs of the commoner Callipepla species produced 60-80 eggs per
year. Mountain Quail produced even more, with some pairs producing over
100 eggs per year. A friend with no previous experience of keeping quail,
imported some Mountain Quail from the USA a few years after I did and set
them up as I instructed him. He produced a huge number of young which
took two to three years to sell - he even gave some away. He had flooded
the UK market at the time when quarantine restrictions still existed between
the UK and mainland Europe and links between the two barely existed.
I never kept a record of the fertility of my birds, but stock that was not
inbred certainly laid very few non-viable eggs. Meam's and Elegant, in
particular, were known to be hopelessly inbred even back then and although
each pair produced 30-40 eggs, very few chicks were produced. I never
got into double figures during the few breeding seasons I had them. The
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.622375" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312737" page_num="147" year="" vol="">
GARMHAM - QUAIL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999056" page_id="56312737"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
147
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999371756097561" page_id="56312737"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
only pair of Meam's which was from the Bob Tybie strain, which produced
viable eggs and a large surplus of females in the USA, was loaned to a
friend who succeeded in producing just a couple of female chicks before
the female died,
A second importation into the UK of Meam's a few years later produced
similar, possibly worse results, with a massive surplus of males. Weirdly,
the current European stock, origins unknown, but very unlikely to include
ancestors of the two UK importations, produces rather few eggs but of high
viability and resulting in a substantial surplus of females.
Over the 30 years that I have kept and bred small gamebirds, I have seen
many come into the hobby and many leave, but two common management
techniques, particularly in the USA, but also in mainland Europe and to a
lesser degree here in the UK, that always seem largely incompatible with
small gamebirds breeding well in captivity, are keeping them other than in
pairs and keeping them on wire-floored pens. I have very seldom seen or
heard of birds doing as well as the birds here and those of my good friend not
far from Merseyside, when subject to one or other or both of these regimes.
Smaller pens are often a problem too.
My single experimental trio of Gambel's Quail kept long ago produced
one very stressed female and 30 or so eggs. It is also a sobering thought that
the many millions of Red-legged Partridges Alectoris rufa that are reared for
sport shooting in Europe each year are almost exclusively produced from
paired breeders, albeit housed in wire-floored pens - the days of flock mating
of the species are long gone.
The choice of compounded feeds today, since the emergence of BSE
and the ban on the inclusion of animal proteins in ruminant feeds, is not as
simple as before. Animal proteins can be used for poultry and game feeds,
but many compounders cannot risk cross contamination in their mills, so only
large compounders use fish meal by dedicating a production line to its use
and not using the line for ruminant feed production. Based on experience
here and a published science-based study of commercial game flocks, the
inclusion of fish meal in the food fed to gamebirds (albeit probably only
l%-3%, the exact amount of fish meal being unknown due to commercial
secrecy) does improve egg production and viability. This being so, I now
have a limited choice of what I can feed my birds, so use 28% protein game
starter mini-pellets, with fish meal, as the compounded part of the ration fed
to my birds during the laying period.
Today, Stone Partridge in particular breed freely here, which is not the
case with very many other people who keep this species.
A second problem is the move to lasalocid as a coccidiostat in all but
breeder rations. Compounded feed being only 50% of the diet, the intake
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998892" page_id="56312736"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
148
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909029" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312736" page_num="148" year="" vol="">
GARNHAM - QUAIL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99965743902439" page_id="56312736"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
of any coccidiostat will be far below the minimum therapeutic amount, yet
many keepers continue to use chick crumbs as the adult diet. The problem
is that lasalocid is concentrated in eggs and causes developmental problems
in the embryo. The mini-pellets that I feed to my birds are not medicated.
As something of a postscript, it is worth noting that on the one hand,
quoting the basic nutritional analysis can be very misleading, while on the
other hand, birds can eat only what is available to them, but there is mounting
evidence that when they have a choice they choose to eat to obtain their
amino-acid requirements rather than, for instance, calories.
Research on poultry and a few non-domesticated species suggests that
fat intake, assuming that there are adequate amounts of essential fatty-acids
present, needs to be around 1% of dry matter, but that food becomes far
more palatable when it contains at least 3% fat. Similarly, protein quality
- how closely the essential amino-acid content of the protein matches the
requirements of the consumer - is equally as important as total protein intake.
Research into the diets of captive Japanese Quail Coturnix japonica and
Bobwhite (see, for instance, Dozier and Bramwell, University of Georgia)
indicate that a diet with 24%-28% protein, usually derived from soy (soya)
and a small proportion of corn (maize) is required for optimum laying
performance, while levels of substantially less than 10% are an adequate
maintenance level. There is also the issue of digestiblity and digestion
inhibitors that are present in all plant foods,
In the large scale commercial manufacture of stock feeds, amino-acid
content is carefully controlled, but in the case of Ultrakibble, the protein
content derives almost entirely from com (maize, in the form of gluten
meal), which is low in tryptophan and very low in lysine. Although lysine
hydrochloride is added (at a level below that of the preservatives in it, two
of which are typically used at no more than 0.1%), this is not enough to
make good the shortfall, which effectively reduces substantially the protein
content of Ultrakibble which is available for body repair and reproduction,
etc. (It should be noted there is more dicalcium phosphate in it than fish
meal and the calcium content is given as 0.21%-1.2% - a huge range for a
compounded feed.) There is also some evidence suggesting that arginine
from com gluten is poorly metabolised by poultry.
Also bear in mind that cooking (as with Ultrakibble), reduces protein
digestibility by anything up to 30% even in a well-controlled and analysed
process - this is one of the reasons why compounded farm stock feeds are
generally not cooked but, at most, very precisely and quickly heat-treated
to destroy pathogens and certain digestion inhibitors, such as those in
legumes, including soy (soya). Cooking temporarily increases carbohydrate
digestibility, but in commercial stock feeds this is not an attractive proposition
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.614162" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312735" page_num="149" year="" vol="">
GARNHAM - QUAIL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999354" page_id="56312735"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
149
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.975409411764706" page_id="56312735"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
when viewed against decreased protein digestibility, as protein is expensive
and carbohydrates are cheap. (This is in contrast to pet foods, which are
usually cooked, as cats and dogs digest raw carbohydrates rather poorly, so
cooking becomes financially very attractive.)
As for natural diets being a useful guide to captive diets of birds: a
common estimate amongst workers in avian science is that captive birds
require approximately 30% the calorie intake of what they would need in the
wild. However, their protein intake, in absolute terms, will be unchanged as
body regeneration/replacement etc. proceed at the same pace. This being so,
to imitate the protein intake of a bird living in its natural habitat in the wild,
the captive diet should have a substantially higher protein content than that
in the wild, though very much dependent in both situations upon factors such
as protein quality and digestibility. That said, the production of a clutch of
eggs in the wild makes very different demands on a bird compared to those
of producing numbers of eggs semi-continuously.
Also of note, perhaps, is that various sources quote acorn protein content
(from a variety of oaks) as being of high quality with a score in excess of
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.9344195" page_id="56312735"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
100 .
Useful further reading
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.789402526315789">
Clasing, K. C. 1998. Comparative Avian Nutrition. Cab International, Wallingford, UK.
Carey, C. (ed.). 1996. Avian Energetics and Nutritional Ecology. Springer, New York.
Robbins, G. E. S. 1983. Quail, Their Breeding and Management. World Pheasant Association,
UK.
Utrakibble ingredients
Corn Gluten Meal, Sorghum, Vegetable Oil, Rice Bran, Cane Molasses, Dicalcium
Phosphate, Fish Meal, Hydrated Sodium Calcium Aluminosilicate, Salmon Meal, Cinnamon,
Diatomaceous Earth, Dehydrated Watercress Pulp, Dehydrated Spinach Pulp, Dehydrated
Carrot Pulp, Dehydated Lettuce Pulp, Dehydrated Beet Pulp, Dehydrated Celery Pulp, Choline
Chloride, Turmeric, Propionic Acid (Preservative), Sorbic Acid (Preservative), Benzoic Acid
(Preservative), L-Lysine Monohydrochloride, Calcium Carbonate, Vitamin E Supplement,
Niacin Supplement, Calcium Pantothenate, Vitamin A Supplement, Vitamin B12 Supplement,
Riboflavin Supplement, Biotin, Vitamin D3 Supplement, Roughage Products, Mineral Oil,
Lactobacillus Acidophilus Fermentation Product Dehydrated, Lactobacillus Casei Fermentation
Product Dehydrated, Bifidobacterium Thermophilum Fermentation Product Dehydrated,
Enterococcus Faecium Fermentation Product Dehydrated, Silicon Dioxide, Citric Acid, Mixed
Tocopherois (Preservative), Rosemary Extract, Manganous Oxide, Copper Oxide, Calcium
lodate, Sodium Selenite.
E-mail: carl.garnhaml 00@googlemail. com
</reference>
<page confidence="0.974953" page_id="56312734"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
150
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.774517" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312734" page_num="150" year="" vol="">
HAVING BEEN AN AVXCXJLTURIST FOR FIFTY YEARS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.955359710526316" page_id="56312734"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
Part 2
by Bernard Sayers
In the 1960s or early 1970s Aubry Buxton, a director of Anglia Television
which produced Survival , one of the longest-running and most successful
wildlife TV series at the time, maintained a large private collection of birds
at Norman House, his home near Stansted Airport and, for a few years,
opened his collection to the public. The unspoilt rolling meadows, lakes and
woodland, had been fenced with what must have been miles (kilometres) of
fox-proof fencing, to form a network of adjoining large paddocks. These
were stocked with flocks of ducks, geese and swans, cranes, flamingos and
deer. A pathway wound round the paddocks and not only was the exotic
stock of great interest, but it was an excellent opportunity to do some
birdwatching, for the varied habitat attracted many finches, buntings, tits,
flycatchers and wagtails.
Near the entrance to the park were two aviaries, which had been modified
from pig pens. One housed a tame Bateleur Terathopius ecaudatus and the
other two European Eagle-Owls Bubo b. bubo , which were notable for their
enormous size. Of the hundreds of eagle-owls I must have seen during the
past 50 years, these were the biggest I have seen. When the collection was
dispersed, these owls were acquired by Malcolm Moy, who at the time had
a bird park at Smallburgh in Norfolk. A few years after Malcolm moved to
Inveraray to set up the Argyll Wildlife Park for the Duke of Argyll, I renewed
my acquaintance with these eagle-owls when I was asked to crate them.
They certainly felt extremely heavy when I handled them (Malcolm said
each of them weighed lOlbs (approx. 4.5 kg)). The two owls were obtained
as youngsters by Aubry Buxton, whose keeper told me that they were fed
on road kill and other wildlife casualties, along with chicken heads - and, I
think, the latter may have been the reason why the owls were so heavy. At
the time many of the chickens reared for meat production were caponized,
which involved injecting a pellet into the back of the neck, which chemically
castrated cockerels and acted as a growth booster. Were there still, I wonder,
traces af the pellet in the necks and, by feeding the heads of capons to the
owls, did this cause them to grow abnormally large? I cannot be sure, but
to my knowledge the owls never attempted to breed and were undoubtably
extremely large and, I think, this theory may have some credibility.
Behind the aviaries housing the eagle and eagle-owls was a large
enclosure in which Cliff and I saw for the first time a pair of yellow Golden
Pheasants Chrysolophus pictus and were absolutely awestruck by this
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.389604" page_id="56312733"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
SAYERS - 50 YEARS AN AVICULTURIST
</construct>
<page confidence="0.999409" page_id="56312733"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
151
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999378585365854" page_id="56312733"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
beautiful pair of birds. It was autumn and the pair had just completed its
moult. The male's crest retained the typical golden colour although it was
possibly a tad paler than normal and the cape was orange edged with black
like that of the normal male and likewise the back was glossy green. The
real differences were the fact it possessed a lovely primrose yellow breast,
soft brown wing-coverts and secondaries, white primaries and a buff/brown
tail dotted with yellowish white. The yellow of the breast fades a little as a
result of exposure to the sun, but in freshly moulted birds it positively glows.
The yellow Golden Pheasant is sometimes called Ghigi's Golden Pheasant
in honour of Professor Alessandro Ghigi of Bologna, Italy who played a
major role in establishing this mutation. It is said to have occurred in a
collection in Bavaria and Alexander Hampe from Coburg was instrumental
in transferring the birds to Professor Ghigi in 1952. (see A New Mutation
of the Golden Pheasant by Alessandro Ghigi in Vol.63, No.6, pp. 190-191
(1957).) I know little about mutations, but I have read that the original male
from Bavaria proved to be recessive. Whatever the ethical arguments about
breeding mutations, as Cliff and I stood spellbound admiring the pair of
yellow Golden Pheasants we resolved that we must obtain a pair without
delay and later I will relate where this led us.
While chatting to the keeper we learned that Mrs Pamela Johnston
maintained an extensive and varied collection nearby. Aware that we were
keenly interested in exotic livestock, he offered to telephone Mrs Johnston
and ask if we could see her collection. She was agreeable to this and so
we headed for Mole Hall at Widdington, near Saffron Walden. This part of
north-west Essex is particularly beautiful and much less densely populated
than most of the county. The rolling countryside is scattered with quaint,
picturesque villages, including the village of Ugly, which is home to the
insensitively named Ugly Women's Institute.
After a short drive along winding lanes we found Mole Hall and Cliff's
car bumped over a cattle grid into the grounds. As the car came to a halt we
were joined by a very large Aberdeen Angus bull. A quick vote was taken
to decide who should get out of the car first and it seemed I was the popular
choice. I was reasonably relaxed about this as bulls of beef breeds of cattle
are usually fairly docile and, surely, Mrs Johnston and her husband would
not have had a dangerous bull wandering free in their garden. As I got out
of the car the bull ambled up to me and I introduced myself and, in return,
the bull good naturedly coated the front of my pullover with dribble. I
stood taking in the beauty of the setting with the extensive rolling lawns and
innumerable Weeping Willows Salix babylonica. To one side was the lovely,
ancient house, with its pink-washed walls. It is on an island surrounded by
a moat which was stocked with ornamental ducks, Black Swans Cygnus
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999034" page_id="56312732"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
152
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.338014" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312732" page_num="152" year="" vol="">
SAYERS - 50 YEARS AN AVICULTURIST
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.964102682926829" page_id="56312732"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
atratus and a flock of Caribbean Flamingos Phoenicopteras ruber and the
grounds were dotted with various enclosures. It would have been difficult
to have conjured up a more idyllic setting and I was constantly reminded
of Wind in the Willows.
Many of the animals were tame and undoubtedly Mrs Johnston's pride
and joy was her magnificent troop of Humboldt's Woolly Monkeys Lagothrix
lagotricha. Even now these sensitive monkeys are considered to be difficult
by some zoo personnel, but 30-40 years ago only a few specialist collections
enjoyed any success with them. The troop at Mole Hall had a large, warm,
indoor enclosure which they could retire to when they wished and also had
the opportunity to roam free in the gardens. I was told the grounds were
planted with Weeping Willows, as these are the only trees which could survive
the depredations of the monkeys. When Mole Hall opened to the public in
1963, the Woolly Monkeys could no longer be allowed so much liberty and,
as nowadays, all owners are required to hold a Dangerous Wild Animals
Licence, I guess it would be illegal to allow them to roam free.
Dingos Can is dingo , Foxes Vulpes vulpes , Coypu Myocastor coypus ,
Ring-tailed Coatis Nasua nasua, Raccoons Procyon lotor, Humboldt
Penguins Spheniscus humboldti and some lovely otters occupied the
enclosures dotted around the gardens. Mole Hall made something of a
speciality of keeping otters and had considerable success breeding both the
Small-clawed species Amblonyx cinereus and the Canadian or Northern
River Otter Lontra canadensis.
The tennis court had been roofed over and divided into two. On one side
was an aviary housing a pair of Green-winged Macaws Ara chloropterus and
on the other side was a larger compartment housing Indian Blue Peafowl
Pavo cristatus and Demoiselle Cranes Anthropoides virgo. Later, these
two aviaries housed Red-billed Curassows Crax blumenbachii and Snowy
Owls B. scandiacus. The curassows certainly laid eggs, because I have
several of them in my collection, but to the best of my knowledge the pair
never reared any chicks. I have had a magnificent pair of tame Bare-faced
Curassows C. fasciolata in my collection for many years and have had
many eggs - usually clutches of two, but occasionally of just one and, on
two occasions, of three eggs - some of which have been fertile, but none of
which have hatched. The female never shows any inclination to incubate
the eggs, which have either been placed in an incubator or under a heavy
breed of broody hen but, to my great regret, the embryos have always died
mid-way through incubation,
I always feel that such a failure is usually the result of inadequate
husbandry and, therefore, feel responsible for this lack of success. Sadly, I
have no idea what I might do to try to remedy this problem. Snowy Owls,
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.389622" page_id="56312731"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
SAYERS - 50 YEARS AN AVICULTURIST
</construct>
<page confidence="0.999755" page_id="56312731"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
153
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.992536414634146" page_id="56312731"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
on the other hand, have proved to be far more of a success story at both Mole
Hall and here. The original pair at Mole Hall was imported from Canada
and bred very well. A later pair came from my collection, in which almost
60 have been parent-reared over the years. The Mole Hall collection also
included Mackinder's Eagle-Owls Bubo capensis mackinderi , Spotted Eagle-
Owls B. afrieanus , Tawny Owls Strix aluco and a magnificent Changeable
Hawk-Eagle Spizaetus cirrhatus.
Paddocks around the periphery of the garden housed deer, ponies and
a magnificent pair of Saras Cranes Grus antigone , which reared chicks
regularly. Varied though the collection was it was evident, however, that
monkeys were prominent in Pamela Johnston's affections. Later a trio of
Chimpanzees Pan troglodytes was added to the collection, but when I first
visited it the stock consisted mainly of small to medium-sized monkeys.
Prominent in my memory is a wonderful pair of Wanderoos or Lion-tailed
Macaques Macaca silenus from the monsoon forests of the Western Ghats
of India where this species has become very rare and there is now an
international studbook for the zoo population. There were also capuchin
monkeys Cebus spp., as well as several mangabies Ceropithecus spp. from
Africa. In those days it was macaques from Asia and North Africa and
African monkeys which predominated in zoological collections. Nowadays
there are very few macaques, Mona Monkeys C. mona, Patas Erythrocebus
patas , mangabies and Vervet Monkeys C. aethiops left in the UK and instead
South American species, lemurs and leaf monkeys predominate.
Over the years many interesting species were exhibited at Mole Hall
Servals Felis serval were added to the collection and a butterfly house was
opened and, of particular interest to me, was a lovely pair of Western or Blue
Crowned Pigeons Goura cristata which bred successfully several times. The
pair had a warm shelter, but chose to nest in a dense hedge in the outside
aviary. This species was first bred in the UK at London Zoo in 1914, since
when only a handful of collections have bred this impressive pigeon. When
it became necessary to reduce the size of the Mole Hall collection, I believe
the breeding pair went to Rode Tropical Bird Garden.
Some of Mrs Johnston's stock had, I was told, been bought from
"Palmers Pet Stores" in Camden Town. Palmers, Regent Pet Stores, was a
large double-fronted shop in Parkway, just a short distance from Camden
Town underground station on the way to and from London Zoo (in Regent's
Park). Palmers (always without an apostrophe) was a fascinating shop and I
always called in when visiting the zoo. It was stocked with a vast range of
foodstuffs, sundries and cages and an archway led into the second part of the
shop which was an absolute treasure trove of exotic livestock. There were
cages with parrots, parakeets and tame softbills such as mynahs, toucans and
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999675" page_id="56312730"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
154
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.335788" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312730" page_num="154" year="" vol="">
SAYERS - 50 YEARS AN AVICULTURIST
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998181731707317" page_id="56312730"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
hombills etc. and numerous vivariums containing pythons, boas and other
non-venomous snakes, baby caimans, lizards, terrapins and tortoises etc.
Towards the back of the shop were cages containing birds of prey, monkeys
and animals such as squirrels, kinkajous, civets, fruit bats, mongooses etc.
A few larger, more strongly constructed cages, occasionally housed baby
Chimpanzees, Sun Bear cubs Helarctos malayanus and baby cats of various
species and there were more enclosures in the small yard out the back.
When the animals were bought by knowledgeable customers such as
Pamela Johnston they undoubtedly enjoyed comfortable lives, but I shudder
to think what happened to some of the animals which were bought on
impulse by less knowledgeable customers. This was particularly true of
baby monkeys, which are enchanting when young, but become destructive,
wilful and frequently aggressive as they become mature. Of course, most
of the animals sold by Palmers would now be subject to a Dangerous Wild
Animals Licence, so could not be bought by impulse buyers. (Although
Palmers closed several years ago and now appears to be a cafe-cum-wine
bar, the owners have retained the famous old pet shop sign dating back to
at least the 1930s.)
For many years a pair of Bateleurs Terathopius ecaudatus , the male
of which I bought from Palmers, was among the stars of my collection.
Although the pair built bulky nests and the female laid several times this was
always in the depths of winter (and these were very severe in the 1960s and
1970s) and none of the eggs hatched. The Bateleur is, of course, one of the
few eagles with sexually dimorphic coloration. They take about five years
to assume full colour and get the brilliant red facial skin, by which time the
female's secondaries have a broad silver bar across them, whereas those of
the male are entirely glossy black.
Earlier I mentioned how acquiring a pair of yellow Golden Pheasants
became a top priority for Cliff and me. This quest took us to Stagsden
Bird Gardens on the outskirts of Bedford and resulted in me maintaining
close contact with this collection from its inception until its closure several
decades later. The bird garden was founded by Fred (invariably known as
F. E. B.) Johnson, a portly gentleman with trademark glasses and cigar and
an impish sense of humour. My first contact with Fred had been when he
worked, I believe, for the Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, and
lived at Newport Pagnell. There he maintained a collection of pheasants with
which he enjoyed considerable success. Fred had been bom into a farming
family near Bury St Edmunds in Suffolk and obviously inherited the farming
community's natural ability as stockmen, for he kept and bred species such
as Satyr Tragopan satyra and Temminck's Tragopan T. temminckii which
were regarded as tricky in those days.
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.389614" page_id="56312729"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
SAYERS - 50 YEARS AN AVICULTURIST
</construct>
<page confidence="0.999619" page_id="56312729"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
155
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999689390243902" page_id="56312729"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
Around about the early 1960s Fred received a family legacy which
enabled him to buy the Grove at Stagsden with the intention of realising a
long held ambition to establish a bird garden and open it to the public. In
theory Stagsden was in an unrivalled position for it was close to a number
of major road networks and seemingly within easy travelling distance of a
vast population of potential visitors. The only drawback was that, being in
a rural setting, it was only accessible by car and, in the early 1960s, by no
means the majority of families owned a car.
The Grove consisted of a large (and in my view) rather ugly house with
a small copse between it and the road. To either side there were meadows
totalling in all about 10 acres (4 hectares). Fred proceeded to develop these
into a network of paddocks for waterfowl and enclosures for his beloved
pheasants. It was here that a problem arose. Fred's rather unorthodox method
of aviary building, whilst enabling him to build a large enclosure before
breakfast, to the incognoscenti looked rather unattractive and somewhat
casually constructed. Fred's method of working was to erect a stout post at
each of the four comers of quite a large plot of land and then stretch heavy
wires between them. Wire netting was then thrown over the flimsy support
structure in a tent-like fashion and clipped together where appropriate. At
ground level the wire netting was bent outwards and weighed down with
large rocks. If the enclosed area contained small trees or bushes, so much
the better, as these provided additional support and prevented the roof
from sagging so much. Such enclosures had limited aesthetic appeal but,
aviculturally, proved perfectly satisfactory. Not only were they large, but the
scmb in the aviaries provided the pheasants with a near natural environment.
Many pheasants being nervous and skittish by nature, the abundance of cover
provided them with a sense of security. Also, if the occupants panicked
and flew into the wire, the structure's lack of rigidity meant they were less
likely to sustain serious injuries. The pheasants showed their approval by
thriving and breeding very well, but the visiting public did not appreciate
such benefits and were less impressed. They complained that many of the
pheasants and waterfowl hid amongst the undergrowth and could not be
seen and they wanted to see a greater variety of birds.
Somewhat reluctantly Fred decided to diversify and had some rather more
traditional aviaries constmcted. This was at a time when I was importing
wild-caught birds (a past I am not proud of, but in the 1960s, relatively few
birds were bred in captivity, as wild-caught birds were widely available and
relatively cheap to buy) and obtained for Fred toucans, macaws, lories, fruit
pigeons, owls and other birds. Other interesting species, including a superb
adult pair of King Vultures Sarcoramphus papa , Fred obtained from other
sources. This was more in accord with the public's expectations but, even
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99955" page_id="56312728"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
156
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.34903" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312728" page_num="156" year="" vol="">
SAYERS - 50 YEARS AN AVICULTURIST
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985639390243902" page_id="56312728"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
so, the gate receipts and revenue from the sale of young birds never really
covered the costs of running the bird gardens and, at best, he really only
succeeded in losing money slowly.
Fred had wide interests and was a great collector. I can recall him studying
and collecting lichens, species roses, exhibition Modena pigeons, pedigree
poultry, land snails, orchids and natural history books. The latter developed
into a business and for many years Fred dealt in new and antiquarian natural
history books. A substantial number of books in my library were acquired
from Fred, usually in exchange for birds.
Orchids of the Pleurothallis and Lepanthes genera were another of Fred's
particular interests. He amassed a huge collection of literally thousands of
these orchids, many of which are so small that the flowers had to be admired
under a magnifying glass. Some were bought from specialist nurseries and
many others imported from collectors in their countries of origin. Among
the latter was the somewhat extravagantly named "Bhumibol the Adventurer
of Peru"! Fred's orchid collection was housed in two large greenhouses
which had been erected behind the house. He delighted in taking visitors
into the greenhouses and discussing the origin of the orchids, their growing
requirements, horticultural history, the source of his plants, taxonomy and a
host of other subjects. Fred knew a great deal about orchids and such was his
enthusiasm that he lost track of time and being shown his orchid collection
could become a lengthy operation. It was somewhat irreverently alleged
that two visitors ushered into the orchid house as teenagers had reached
pensionable age by the time they finally emerged!
Fred was a wonderfully eccentric and idiosyncratic character, who as
he became more engrossed emitted clouds of cigar smoke, which must
have been a potent deterrent to insect pests, but left non-smokers like me
choking and finally staggering out into the fresh air smelling like a well-
smoked kipper, especially in the winter when the greenhouses were not so
well ventilated. During his occasional resolutions to economise he would
exchange his trademark cigar for a pipe and always left a couple of buttons
of his shirt front undone and, every so often when the need arose, would pull
out the end of his vest and thoroughly wipe the mouthpiece of his somewhat
juicy pipe on it.
Present day pheasant keepers owe Fred a great debt of gratitude for the
contributions he made to introducing new species and establishing stocks
of first class birds of species which had virtually disappeared during the
Second World War. In 1960 Fred was the first person in the UK to breed
the nominate subspecies of the Koklass Pheasant Pucrasia m. macrolopha
and imported from Nagaland in northern India seven Hume's Bar-tailed
Pheasants Syrmaticus humiae and bred them with great success - his initial
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.389607" page_id="56312727"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
SAYERS - 50 YEARS AN AVICULTURIST
</construct>
<page confidence="0.999518" page_id="56312727"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
157
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.991542829268293" page_id="56312727"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
success in 1962 is thought to have been the worldwide first captive breeding
of this species. I have vivid memories of him showing me my first Blood
Pheasant Ithaginis cruentus - although sadly he had only the one. Fred bred
many other species which although not first breedings were rare in aviculture,
including breeding the spectacular Cabot's Tragopan T. caboti. His young
stock was always of first class quality and vigour and so he did a great deal
to re-establish many pheasants in UK aviculture.
Another of Fred's interests were mutations and he bred several colour
forms of the game pheasant, leucistic Moorhens Gallinula chloropus and
yellow and dark-throated Golden Pheasants. By the selective breeding of
yellow and dark-throated specimens of the latter, he produced a new mutation,
the salmon Golden Pheasant. This mutation, with its dingy orange breast,
is not particularly attractive and never became popular and I doubt if many
exist today. Fred supplied Cliff and I with an excellent pair of yellow Golden
Pheasants which proved to be a first class pair from which we bred a great
many youngsters over the ensuing years.
I must mention a hybrid pheasant exhibited at Stagsden which, in theory,
should have been impossible to produce. Although not invariably the case,
it is generally believed that hybrids between two species in the same genus
will be fertile, whilst hybrids between species from different genera will be
infertile (i.e. mules). This trigeneric hybrid was between a Golden Pheasant
(Chrysolophus ) mated to a hybrid between a melanistic game pheasant
(.Phasianus ) x Reeves's Pheasant ( Symaticus ). The hybrid had been bred in
a tiny aviary on the balcony of a flat in Eastbourne. I think the breeder gave
Fred three youngsters. When the hybrid cock eventually died I was given
the body and still have the preserved skin, which clearly shows characteristic
colouring of all three - the Golden Pheasant, melanistic game pheasant and
Reeves's Pheasant.
Fred also liked waterfowl and always maintained a nice collection at
Stagsden. There were two large walk-through enclosures. One contained
a large flock of Barnacle Geese Branta leucopsis which bred prolifically
and the other, which contained a pond, was home to a mixed collection of
ducks and geese. There were also several smaller enclosures for swans and
aggressive and disruptive species. In the large mixed species paddock was
Fred's pride and joy, a good sized flock of Red-breasted Geese B. ruficollis.
Although this species was being bred in collections at that time, it was
regarded as difficult and this and the Red-breasted Goose's great beauty,
made these birds very expensive. At their peak, they reached #400-#500
(approx. US$650-US$800) per pair, at a time when this was worth a great deal
more than it is today. So imagine Fred's elation when one season his flock
of Red-breasted Geese produced some 40 goslings. This must have made
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99893" page_id="56312726"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
158
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.334357" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312726" page_num="158" year="" vol="">
SAYERS - 50 YEARS AN AVICULTURIST
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996332184210526" page_id="56312726"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
a major contribution towards balancing the books that year. Red-breasted
Geese, however, are not dependable, regular breeders. One year they might
be very productive whereas another year, when conditions appear virtually
identical, they will do little or nothing,
After 10 years of struggling with the endless problems and demands of
running a public collection and the difficulty of generating sufficient income
to pay the considerable running costs Fred decided that, at his age, it had
all become too much and decided to sell the collection. Fred sold Stagsden
Bird Gardens in May 1975 and he and his family moved to Glebe Farm,
near Dereham in Norfolk, where he continued his activities as a bookseller.
Fred kept his cherished flock of Red-breasted Geese in a paddock at the
rear of the house where he could watch them from his lounge. Later, I
think, he moved to Wells-next-the-sea. I learnt a great deal from Fred and
always enjoyed our long conversations which were invariably humorous and
informative. Sadly, these are treats of the past now that Fred and his wife
are no longer with us. Their son, Andrew, continued the family profession
of natural history bookseller and, for a time, had premises just off Piccadilly
in London, which were a "must visit destination."
The new owners of Stagsden Bird Gardens were Jane and Rodney
Rayment, a young couple who had run a post office/general stores in Hertford.
However, in their spare time they were keenly involved in aviculture and
falconry. There was also continuity from the Fred Johnson era in the person
of Peter Kaminski. For a number of years Fred had relied upon the help
of Peter Gatlin, a joiner by trade and a knowledgeable birdkeeper - who
subsequently left to take charge of the building and maintenance of aviaries
for Pat and Roy Harvey at Birdworld, near Famham, Surrey - and Peter
Kaminski who had worked for Fred part-time whilst still a schoolboy and
who joined Jane and Rod to form the small team that was to run Stagsden
for almost two decades.
In the third part of Bernard's reminiscences he will describe how under
Rod's dynamic ownership a vast expansion programme was launched and
many new aviaries and paddocks were constructed and a huge and varied
collection of birds assembled. Bernard usually combined a trip to Stagsden
with a visit to Christopher Marler s collection at Weston Underwood and
will also write about Christopher s eagles, vultures and owls (including
the incredibly rare Blakiston's Fish Owl Ketupa blakistoni, the only living
example Bernard has ever seen), flamingos, pelicans, cranes, storks and many
other birds (and mammals) Christopher has kept and bred over the years.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9609715" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312725" page_num="159" year="" vol="">
KEEPING AND BREEDING THE WHITE-FRONTED
WOODPECKER Melanerpes cactorum
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999129" page_id="56312725"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
159
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.979771324324324" page_id="56312725"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
by Richard Green
The White-fronted Woodpecker Melanerpes cactorum measures 16cm-
18cm (approx. 6!4in-7in) in length. It is similar in size and behaviour to the
Lesser Spotted Woodpecker Dendrocopos minor , the smallest of the three
UK woodpeckers. It has similar quick agitated movements and a similar
head-nodding action. It is small and agile, bouncing on both feet at the
same time as it moves around the trunk of a tree, appearing first at one side
and then the other, followed by short bursts of drumming as it attempts to
expose insect life, upon which it feeds.
The male has a white forehead and face and a yellow throat, along with
a red crown, but the latter can be observed only by catching the male and
parting the black feathers to expose the red feathers on the crown. Both sexes
have a grey nape and hind neck and a blue-black mantle and scapulars, with
a creamy white area between the wings, from the nape to the base of the tail.
The wings are barred and checkered black and white, as is the tail. The breast
is grey. The female is smaller with a shorter beak and a paler yellow throat
and lacks the male's red crown. The juvenile is browner and lacks a gloss
to the plumage which the adults have and also lacks the yellow throat. Like
most woodpeckers this species has a noisy call - a loud "weep weep."
It is a South American species found from arid south-east Peru to Bolivia,
Paraguay, south-west Brazil, northern Argentina and Uruguay, that inhabits
subtropical and tropical dry forests and shrubland. They move around in
small family groups of up to five or six birds. They drill holes in the trunks
and branches of trees and plants such as Prosopis flexuosa (which belongs
to a genus of flowering plants of the pea family) and feed on the extruded
sap, particularly during the months of June-September when water is scarce,
thus giving the bird its common name of "sapsucker." Sap forms a major
part of their diet and intruders which attempt to take advantage of their
efforts are driven off.
In South America it breeds from September-December. At this time loud
drumming can be heard as groups establish their territories. It is known to be
a cooperative breeder with several birds sharing many of the nesting duties.
The nest cavity is in the trunk of a palm tree or cactus. The information on
clutch size is not specific. The information I have found is general to the
Piciformes and describes clutches of between two to five eggs. However, I
have a feeling that Melanerpes cactorum may be a bird which generally lays
a clutch of just one or two eggs. The eggs are white and roundish in shape
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994981" page_id="56312724"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
160
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.817958" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312724" page_num="160" year="" vol="">
GREEN - WHITE-FRONTED WOODPECKER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999642243902439" page_id="56312724"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
and are incubated by both sexes for a period of 11-14 days.
I have kept and bred many softbills over a 30 year period and have always
had an interest in woodpeckers. After having successfully kept and bred the
White Woodpecker M. candidus , I felt that I would like to try to breed another
species of woodpecker. In 2009,1 bought four woodpeckers from a Belgian
dealer, I was unsure which species they were, as this information got lost in
translation, however, on arrival home they were identified as White-fronted
Woodpeckers. There was one male and three females. Initially, the birds were
housed in an indoor flight constructed of breeze blocks and tubular steel, of
the type used for keeping and breeding parrots. The flight was furnished with
upright, Silver Birch Betulapendula trunks, and provided with parakeet-type
nest boxes in which the birds could roost. They were offered an omnivorous
diet of grated dog biscuits, cheese, carrot, diced fruit, eggfood, softbill food
and T16 pellets, fortified with raw minced (ground) beef and livefood. They
remained in this building over the winter and although the building was
unheated the temperature remained well above freezing.
In April 2011, the group of four birds was released into a breeding flight
of similar construction to that described above. It measured 10ft x 5ft x
7ft high (approx. 3m x 1.5m x 2.1m high) and had the roof covered with
fibreglass sheeting. The flight was again furnished with Silver Birch trunks,
as these are softer and easier for them to excavate than some others. One of
the trunks was hollow for part of its length, so I bored a 50mm (2in) diameter
hole in it. I also placed a number of nest boxes in the flight, as well as some
hollow logs and parakeet-type nest boxes. The concrete floor of the flight
was covered with sand and leaves to encourage insects and mahonia bushes
were planted in large pots,
Unfortunately, one of the females showed signs of involuntary twitching
and quickly perished. Two of the three remaining birds seemed to have paired
up and one morning in mid-May when I was feeding the birds, I discovered
the remaining female dead on the floor, almost certainly having been attacked
and killed by one or both of the recently formed pair. So, my birds proved
not to be cooperative breeders showing, perhaps, that often birds in captivity
behave differently to those at liberty. (In instances of cooperative breeding,
such groups often consist of a breeding pair and its offspring/helpers from
an earlier brood or broods.)
By early June the pair was using the Silver Birch log and was also
excavating holes higher up the trunk. The birds were "hammering" regularly
and I noticed that the main stem of one of the mahonias had been stripped
of its bark. Believing that the birds were about to begin breeding, I began
to give them more livefood consisting of mealworms, crickets and waxmoth
larvae. The smaller White-fronted Woodpeckers showed a greater desire for
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.387124" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312723" page_num="161" year="" vol="">
GREEN - WHITE-FRONTED WOODPECKER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998789" page_id="56312723"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
161
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999283785714286" page_id="56312723"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
The adult pair of White-fronted Woodpeckers (above) has a yellow
throat whereas the duller, immature bird lacks a yellow throat.
livefood than the larger White Woodpeckers. It soon became obvious that the
White fronted Woodpeckers were incubating an egg or eggs, as one or other
of the birds was always missing. After some 14-15 days the pair was seen
carrying livefood into the nest and a few days later faint "chirping" could
be heard. Both parents took turns to brood the, as yet, unknown number of
young, but after some 18 days both parents were seen in the flight and the
nest chamber fell silent. As the pair was no longer seen entering the nest
chamber, I felt sure that the young must have perished. However, a few
days later I caught a glimpse of a young bird peering out of the nest hole
and a couple of days after that it emerged, not from the nest hole but from
another hole higher up the trank. An inspection showed that the birds had
excavated three escape holes higher up the trunk. The young bird (there was
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998543" page_id="56312722"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
162
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.81655" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312722" page_num="162" year="" vol="">
GREEN - WHITE-FRONTED WOODPECKER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999538" page_id="56312722"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
only one) spent the winter with its parents outdoors in the aviary constructed
from breeze blocks, with the covered roof. Although ice regularly formed
on the water the three birds seemed quite active and happy. In October I
noticed that both adults had lost their yellow throat, so in effect had gone
'out of colour' and resembled the young bird. A couple of months later the
latter was found to be getting a red cap and was, therefore, a young male.
It was exchanged for a female belonging to a Dutch breeder, who had two
females and was in need of a male.
As the birds rely on sap prior to the breeding season, I began giving them
nectar in an attempt to stimulate breeding and, hopefully, get a larger brood
of young. I give them a typical nectar mixture suitable for sunbirds, to which
I add biotin as a substitute for the cambium layer found beneath the bark of
trees and also add T16 fruit pellets and eggfood. I then put the whole lot
into a blender and mix them until they are the consistency of lorikeet food
and this is eagerly taken by the woodpeckers.
This year (2012) the birds appeared to show no interest in breeding and
I thought that due to the poor weather perhaps, they had failed to come into
breeding condition. However, when I was feeding the birds one day towards
the end of June, I saw there were three birds flying around the aviary. This
came as a great surprise to me as at no time had I noticed that either of the
pair was missing. They must have come out of the nest hole when the White
Woodpeckers in the adjacent flight uttered their alarm call. As luck would
have it, the young bird has proved to be a male, which I have paired with
the female I obtained last year from the Dutch breeder.
I hope the second pair will breed in 2013 and, with this in mind, I am
providing the pair with a rotten log some 7ft (2.1m) high and larger in
circumference than previous logs, in the hope that a larger log may lead to
the birds raising a larger brood of young. If I succeed in getting both pairs
to breed, I hope to try to get this South American woodpecker established
in a UK zoo or bird garden.
As described above, the White-fronted Woodpecker Melanerpes
cactorum has been bred by Richard Green. This is probably the first
successful breeding of this species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who
knows of a previous breeding is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999342" page_id="56312721"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
163
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9990515" genericHeader="method" page_id="56312721" page_num="163" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE
ORANGE-BREASTED FIG PARROT Cyclopsitta gulielmitertii
AND DOUBLE-EYED FIG PARROT Cyclopsitta diophthalma
AT WELTVOGELPARK WALSRODE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998278485714285" page_id="56312721"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
by Anne Hoppmann and Norbert Neumann
Weltvogelpark Walsrode houses four of the five species of fig parrots.
Two of these, the Orange-breasted Fig Parrot Cyclopsitta gulielmitertii and
the Double-eyed Fig Parrot C. diophthalma , which in Germany can be seen
only at Weltvogelpark Walsrode, successfully reared young during the 2012
breeding season.
The Orange-breasted Fig Parrot, which has seven recognised subspecies,
inhabits rainforest, monsoon and swamp forests in the lowlands and hilly
regions up to 1,100m (approx. 3,600ft) on the island of New Guinea, Salawati
in the western Papuan Islands and on the Aru Islands. In the wild the main
breeding season is between December-June. This species nests in a hole
which the birds excavate themselves in an arboreal termitarium (termites'
nest). In contrast, the Double-eyed Fig Parrot nests in an existing cavity
in a rotten tree trunk or limb of a tall tree. This species, which has eight
recognised subspecies, is found on New Guinea, the western Papuan Islands
and some offshore islands, the Aru Islands and on the north-east coast of
Australia. It inhabits lowland and montane forests and more open woodland
up to 2,000m (approx. 6,560ft). The main breeding season occurs between
March-June on New Guinea, while in Australia this species breeds mainly
between August-November.
A special feature, alluded to in their name, is the diet of these small
parrots, which in the wild feed mainly on the fruits of various fig trees - they
prefer though to eat the seeds rather than the flesh of the figs. In addition,
they take a variety of other fruits and berries, nectar and also insects and
their larvae.
Experience of keeping fig parrots in captivity has shown that they are very
sensitive to disturbance, especially during the breeding season. Changes to
their surroundings, especially in and around the nest box, can unsettle them.
It is very important, therefore, to be particularly careful when dealing with
these birds, if they are to be bred successfully.
To encourage our Orange-breasted Fig Parrots to begin breeding, we
provide them with nest boxes measuring 30cm long x 20cm wide x 20cm
high (approx. 12in long x 8in wide x 8in high), placed in the enclosure behind
the scenes. The nest boxes, which are made of waterproof particle board,
have a 4cm-6cm (approx. P/2in-2 1 /2in) diameter entrance hole on both sides
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999474" page_id="56312720"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
164
</page>
<table confidence="0.78642325" page_id="56312720"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
HOPPMANN &amp; NEUMANN - FIG PARROTS
Male Orange-breasted Fig Parrot.
Male Orange-breasted Fig Parrot (upper left), female (lower
right) and two young birds.
</table>
<equation confidence="0.310313" page_id="56312719"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
HOPPMANN &amp; NEUMANN - FIG PARROTS
</equation>
<page confidence="0.993949" page_id="56312719"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
165
</page>
<table confidence="0.719470333333333" page_id="56312719"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
Male Double-eyed Fig Parrot.
Immature Double-eyed Fig Parrot (which resembles the female) having just
been removed from its parents' aviary.
</table>
<page confidence="0.998908" page_id="56312718"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
166
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.502861" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312718" page_num="166" year="" vol="">
HOPPMANN &amp; NEUMANN - FIG PARROTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998268487804878" page_id="56312718"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
of the box. The inside of the boxes are packed full of cork tiles, which are
scuffed a bit at the entrance hole to give the birds a starting point, where they
can begin to excavate their nest cavity. When the cavity is approximately
8cm-10cm (3!4in-4in) in diameter, the female lays her eggs - she usually
lays two, but it is possible she may only lay one or as many as three. The
chicks hatch after an incubation period of about 20-22 days. The parents
adjust the size of the nest cavity to suit the size of their growing offspring.
These birds are by nature tidy - and the chicks deposit their faeces outside
the box, so that the interior remains clean.
The Double-eyed Fig Parrots are provided with a nest box made from a
section of tree trunk. The cavity is approximately 20cm wide x 25cm high
(8in wide x 9%in high) and about 15cm (6in) in diameter. The entrance
hole is about 4cm-6cm (V/iin-l&amp;apos;Am) in diameter and is situated a maximum
of 20cm (8in) above the floor of the nest cavity on which is placed a layer
of wood shavings.
As soon as a pair of fig parrots have eggs, the pair is left in peace until
the approximate date that the chicks are due to hatch. Shortly after that,
the nest box is inspected, but only after the female has left the box to feed.
When we are sure there are chicks in the box, we adjust the diet of the birds.
Our standard fig parrot diet consists of germinated seeds and a mixture of
blueberries, grapes, apples and papaya, along with dried figs which have
been soaked in water for at least 24 hours. To this we add one tablespoonful
of Versele-Laga Tropical Patee. They also have access to millet (ad lib).
Following the hatching of the chicks the standard diet is supplemented
with a mash made of three parts Versele-Laga Nutribird A21 and one part
Versele-Laga Orlux Lori. When the chicks are about 14 days old, recently
moulted white-skinned mealworms are added to the diet.
Only a few keepers that the fig parrots know well care for them and they
disrupt the birds as little as possible during the incubation period and after
the chicks hatch. After 35-42 days the young leave the nest box for the
first time, but regularly return to the nest box during the first few days after
fledging. At 60-70 days old the young are separated from their parents and
housed together in single species juvenile groups in enclosures adjacent to
those of their parents.
Because fig parrots are so sensitive to disturbances at and immediately
around the nest box, in consultation with the appropriate ministry the young
are not ringed (banded) with a closed ring, but instead are ringed (banded)
with an open aluminium ring (band) at the time they are separated from
their parents.
After the young had been removed, both breeding pairs of Orange
-breasted Fig Parrots laid a second clutch of eggs. At the beginning of
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.312178" page_id="56312717"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
HOPPMANN &amp; NEUMANN - FIG PARROTS
</equation>
<page confidence="0.998189" page_id="56312717"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
167
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9851081" page_id="56312717"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
September, one chick belonging to the first pair had already left the nest box
and the second pair hatched another chick in September. The Double-eyed
Fig Parrots also seemed to be preparing to produce a further brood.
Breeding fig parrots at Weltvogelpark Walsrode has gone well this year,
with the two breeding pairs of Orange-breasted Fig Parrots having to date
(September 20th 2012) successfully reared a total of four young and the two
breeding pairs of Double-eyed Fig Parrots each having reared one youngster.
In the year we are celebrating the 50th Anniversary of Weltvogelpark
Walsrode, we are understandably very excited about having bred these two
species of fig parrots and look forward to raising many more young.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.84116825" page_id="56312717"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
Products mentioned in the text
Nutribird A21, Orlux Lori and other Versele-Laga products: Versele-Laga nv, Kappellestraat
70, 9800 Deinze, Belgium. Website: www.versele-laga.com
Bibliography
del HoyO; I., Elliot, A. and Sargatal, J. (eds.). 1997. Handbook of the Birds of the World.
Volume 4 - Sandgrouse to Cuckoos. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona.
IUCN. 2012. IUCN Red List of Threatened Species. Version 2012.1.
An earlier account by Martina Muller and Norbert Neumann about
keeping and breeding Desmarest s Fig Parrot Psittaculirostris desmarestii,
Salvadori s Fig Parrot P. salvadorii and Edwards s Fig Parrot P edwardsii
at Walsrode was published in Vol.104, No. 2, pp.55-60 (1998).
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.946806" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312717" page_num="167" year="" vol="">
RENEWING YOUR SUBSCRIPTION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998622909090909" page_id="56312717"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
When renewing your subscription please note that the Avicultural
Society account is now at Barclays Bank. As the Nat West account has been
closed, all future standing orders, subscriptions and other payments should
be made to Barclays Bank (Bumham-on-Crouch Branch). Please quote:
Account No. 13296954, Sort Code 20 54 30. Please ensure that you include
your name as the account reference otherwise we cannot match payments.
Members can also, if they wish, pay their subscription using PayPal and
those in the USA (and elsewhere) can continue to pay in US dollars. The
subscription rate remains unchanged. In case of difficulty please contact
the Hon. Secretary and Treasurer whose details can be found on the inside
of the front cover of the magazine.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998653" page_id="56312716"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
168
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.87096" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312716" page_num="168" year="" vol="">
THE BLACK-THROATED CANARY OR SEEDEATER
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.596047">
Serinus atrogularis
by John Santegoeds
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.979904363636364" page_id="56312716"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
I acquired the birds which are the subject of this article at the beginning
of August 2005 from a dealer named Eric van Tendeloo in Nijlen, Belgium.
I was able to choose from about 30 birds which had been imported and in
the end acquired two pairs.
(c) www.Serinus-Society.eu
Showing the male's black throat.
This importer/dealer helpfully listed the scientific names of the species
- in this case Serinus atrogularis (although it may just occasionally be
found listed in the genus Crithagra) - but did not identify the subspecies
(of which there are seven). I already had a pair of this species (sometimes
called the Black-throated Yellow-ramped Seedeater), but the markings of
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.585196" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312715" page_num="169" year="" vol="">
SANTEGOEDS - BLACK-THROATED CANARY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999565" page_id="56312715"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
169
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99196225" page_id="56312715"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
The type of nest box favoured in countries such as the
Netherlands. The female is sitting on the nest and the male
is standing behind her.
Nestlings at six days old.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995385" page_id="56312714"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
170
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.883571" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312714" page_num="170" year="" vol="">
SANTEGOEDS - BLACK-THROATED CANARY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9925252" page_id="56312714"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
the new birds were clearly different to those of my original pair. So, when
I got them home, I set about trying to determine which subspecies the new
birds belong to. To do this, I used Finches &amp; Sparrows by Clement, Harris
and Davis (1993), a couple of German books and an article on birds of the
genus Serinus in Onze Vogels , August 1987, by Cees van Berkel here in the
Netherlands. Having studied these, I reached the conclusion that the birds I
had obtained in Belgium belong to the subspecies S. a. somereni. The throat
of this subspecies is darker and the dark area covers a larger area than that of
the nominate subspecies. Both the male and female show these differences,
with the male having a black or blackish mottled throat (see photo p. 168)
and the female a dark grey head and throat.
The birds were in perfect condition and, after a three-week quarantine
period at my home, I placed the birds in my uncovered outside flight. At the
time they had to share this with some White-bellied Canaries S. dorsostriatus ,
Grey Singing Finches S. leucopygius , Green Singing Finches S. mozambicus
and Yellow-rumped Seedeaters S. reichenowi , along with my original Black-
throated Canaries, African Citrils S. citrinelloides, Lemon-breasted Canaries
S. citrinipectus and domestic canaries.
This subspecies of the Black-throated Canary proved to be a typical
canary/seedeater of the genus Serinus - it has the same characteristic flight,
forages in the same way and has the same behaviour - and within days the
new birds were fully accepted into the mixed aviary. Also, the song of the
males is similar to that of the other males in the flight. The food consists of
a tropical seed mix and a wild seed mix. A tropical mix only - consisting
as it does mainly of millets - I find too one-sided. Most seedeaters also
like grass seeds, some niger, lettuce seed, chicory, plain canary seed and
perilla. The main diet is complimented, every now and then, with weeds,
mealworms and greenfood. Eggfood is also supplied regularly. Because
of a lack of facilities, I decided later that year to sell the Yellow-rumped
Seedeaters and my original pair of Black-throated Canaries and keep only
the two new pairs.
Coming into breeding condition
Imported canaries/seedeaters come into breeding condition in the autumn
in Europe and about the end of September/beginning of October 2005,
I noticed that bonding was taking place. As the pairs bonded they were
caught and placed in breeding cages. The two new pairs of Black-throated
Canaries came into breeding condition a little later than my other birds and,
therefore, remained in the outside flight a little longer. (The following year
these two pairs too, which I think were probably young birds when acquired,
came into breeding condition around about the end of September/beginning
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.58505" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312713" page_num="171" year="" vol="">
SANTEGOEDS - BLACK-THROATED CANARY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99726" page_id="56312713"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
171
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9694278" page_id="56312713"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
of October.)
The beautiful song of the males was readily heard, especially during
mating time. With their wings spread and hanging down, they would
energetically sing to the females. Just before Christmas 2005, both pairs
were placed in breeding cages measuring 40cm long x 35cm wide x 40cm
high (approx. 1 ft 4in long x 1 ft 2in wide x 1 ft 4in high). Over a short period
of time the hours of daylight were artificially extended until the the lights
in the breeding area were on from 05.30hrs-21.45hrs (5.30am-9.45pm).
The breeding area is moderately heated in such a way that the minimum
temperature does not drop below 8*C (46.4*F). The fact that few if any
canaries/seedeaters breed outside in (open) aviaries here in Europe is, in my
opinion, due to the fact that our autumn, winter and early spring weather is
too cold and the hours of daylight are too short.
Nesting
The nest box was a wooden type with metal bars at the front and the
sides removed (see photo p. 169), into which I placed and firmly secured
a pre-moulded coconut fibre nest pan. A mixture of sisal, cotton wool and
animal hair was provided as nesting materials.
Both pairs quickly set about building a nest and in both nests a clutch
of three eggs was laid. These were a dirty white with pinky/red smudges.
The eggs of one pair were, unfortunately, infertile but those of the other pair
were fertile and were successfully incubated. The males remained with the
females in the breeding cages without any problems and fed the females on
the nest. Most of the time they would also hop quickly onto the nest and
incubate the eggs when the female left the nest for whatever reason.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.534774">
Hatching and rearing
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998628230769231" page_id="56312713"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
On January 29th 2006, after a 13 days incubation period, three chicks
hatched. These had very dark coloured skin. The male continued to feed
the female on the nest, who in turn fed the chicks. The chicks grew quickly
and on the fourth day were able to be ringed (banded) with 2.3mm size
rings (bands).
The softfood I provided consisted of a homemade eggfood (made
from three crushed Dutch rusks, one egg and a small scoop of Breedmax)
complimented with mealworms, defrosted frozen maggots and buffalo
worms. Every now and again I also gave them some chickweed. After
approximately three weeks the young left the nest and three days later were
placed in a 'baby cage' (to see an example go to Vol. 117, No.4, p. 164 (2011)).
Unfortunately after a while one of the young died.
On March 26th 2006, a further three young hatched, all of which were
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998654" page_id="56312712"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
172
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.881033" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312712" page_num="172" year="" vol="">
SANTEGOEDS - BLACK-THROATED CANARY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995969290322581" page_id="56312712"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
reared to maturity. The pair which had the clutch of infertile eggs, produced
a second clutch of eggs and, on this occasion, all three eggs proved to be
fertile. Unfortunately, the male died during the breeding, however, when
the three eggs hatched the loss of the male did not prove an obstacle for
the female, which raised the three young by herself without any problems.
Hereagain, one of the young died after a while.
During the 2005/2006 breeding season, therefore, a total of seven young
were produced by the two pairs. During the summer months the birds
remained in my outside aviary with the other canaries /seedeaters and went
through a moult. For the 2006/2007 breeding season I was able to make
up three unrelated pairs from my remaining three parent birds and their
2005/2006 offspring and had the first young in the nest by mid-October
2006.
Preserving Serinus species in aviculture
Clements (2007) listed 43 species in the genus Serinus. Some of these
seldom, if ever, reached western Europe and others were imported in
restricted numbers only - several others, however, including S. canaria, the
wild ancestor of the many domesticated breeds of canary, have a long history
in aviculture. Imported Grey Singing Finches and Green Singing Finches
(the two most commonly kept species) continued to be offered for sale in
Europe in reasonable numbers until the end of 2005. None were imported
into Europe in 2006.
Now, more than ever before, it is vital that owners of Serinus species
concentrate on breeding these birds, which can with some knowledge and
not too difficult conditions be bred in breeding cages indoors. We must
endeavour to breed and, thus preserve in aviculture, as many species as
possible of the genus Serinus .
The aim of the European Society of Serinus Breeders (ESSB) is to
promote the breeding of Serinus species and bring together breeders
throughout Europe to exchange information and birds. If you are interested
please visit our website: www.Serinus-Society.eu
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.490644" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56312712" page_num="172" year="" vol="">
Reference
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.958064">
Clements, J. F. 2007. The Clements Checklist of the Birds of the World Sixth Edition.
Christopher Helm, London.
John Santegoeds, who is one of the founders of the ESSB, lives in Lierop,
in the Netherlands. E-mail: fam_santegoeds@hotmail.com
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999309" page_id="56312711"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
173
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.528470666666667" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312711" page_num="173" year="" vol="">
THE EUROPEAN FRUIT DOVE PROJECT
by Daan Witlox
Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998809057142857" page_id="56312711"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
When people talk about pigeons (Columbidae family) they are generally
referring to the feral birds which are a familiar if not always welcome feature
of big cities such as Amsterdam and London. Large groups of these feral
descendents of the wild Rock Dove Columba livia inhabit our city squares
and public parks and can be seen perched on our old buildings. There are
in all, however, some 310 different species of pigeons and doves, ranging in
size from the Diamond Dove Geopelia cuneata and Columbina spp. to the
large, spectacular, crowned pigeons Goura spp. Birds of the Columbidae
family are found almost everywhere around the world except for the polar
regions and some oceanic islands.
They can be divided into two main groups: the seed/grain-eating species
and the fruit-eating species. The seed/grain-eating species swallow whole
seeds and grains which are ground down in the strong, muscular gizzard,
while the fruit-eating species, which have a soft stomach and short and wide
gut, are dependent on the soft flesh around the seeds or stone, with the latter
being voided intact in the bird's faeces. In this way, the seeds or stones are
scattered throughout the forests they inhabit and help regenerate the forests
and provide food and nesting places for future generations of fruit pigeons
(and other fruit-eating species).
The 124 species of fruit pigeons are divided among over 10 genera.
Found on the continents of Africa, Asia and Oceania, they mostly inhabit
tropical rainforests in which sufficient food can be found throughout the
year. The ongoing destruction of their habitat as a result of human activities
such as mining, logging, clearing the land for agriculture and palm oil
production, etc., pose serious threats. Several species are placed in the
categories endangered, vulnerable or near threatened on the IUCN Red List
and others, such as the Red-moustached Fruit Dove Ptilinopus mercierii ,
are already extinct. Ex situ populations, when managed properly, could
make an important contribution to the future conservation of fruit pigeons
in the wild.
The project
Because of their colourful appearance fruit doves are very popular among
a great many aviculturists. However, others find the fact that they require
fresh fruit each day, are heat sensitive, produce copious, loose faeces and cost
more to maintain than, for example, seed-eating pigeons and doves, mean
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999656" page_id="56312710"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
174
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.556195" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312710" page_num="174" year="" vol="">
WITLOX - EUROPEAN FRUIT DOVE PROJECT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.940806564102564" page_id="56312710"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
they are less desirable as well as less affordable to buy and keep.
During the 1980s and 1990s the Jambu Fruit Dove P. jambu was
commonly kept by aviculturists, however, as the number being kept and
bred increased this species became less desirable. As it became more readily
available and, therefore more common, there was less demand for it among
aviculturists, who instead turned their attention to other more unusual species.
As a result, within a few years, the Jambu Fruit Dove had disappeared from
European aviaries.
In 2005 a temporary import ban was imposed by the EU (European
Union) and in 2007 this became a permanent ban on the import into the EU
of wild-caught birds. This meant that no new birds could be imported and we
had to develop self-sustaining captive-breeding populations of those species
currently being kept by European aviculturists. Luckily significant numbers
of fruit doves were already being kept by private breeders, zoos and bird
gardens, so there was the potential to maintain viable captive populations.
However, to guarantee the future of fruit doves in European aviculture,
a group of private breeders in Germany set up a meeting at the bird park
at Walsrode. Everybody who kept or was interested in fruit doves was
invited to attend and it was at that meeting that the European Fruit Dove
Project (EFP) came into existence. The project focuses mainly on birds of
the genera Ptilinopus, Ducula and Treron, but also embraces species of the
genera Alectronas, Gymnophaps and Phapitreron, which are rare in European
aviculture (see Table 1).
The main focus
The main focus of the EFP is to bring together breeders in order to share
information and expertise about feeding, breeding and the husbandry and
behaviour of fruit doves. Mutations and hybrids are not permitted by the EFP.
Currently the EFP is focusing on determining which of several subspecies
are being kept. The taxonomy of the African Green Pigeon Treron calva ,
which has 17 recognised subspecies, is among those which is proving to be
an especially tough challenge. At least four subspecies are being kept, but
we suspect that there may be more. Also, in the case of the Green Imperial
Pigeon Ducula aenea , four subspecies are being kept. The most obvious
of these on account of its bronze nape is D. a. paulina. The Island Imperial
Pigeon D. pistrinaria is now also believed to be a subspecies of D. aenea.
How it works
All members have to send in their stock data in time for the annual census
on December 31st. This must include the number of birds currently owned
and details of offspring and/or mortalities. Information on breeding results
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.976035" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312709" page_num="175" year="" vol="">
WITLOX EUROPEAN FRUIT DOVE PROJECT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998967" page_id="56312709"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
175
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99105684375" page_id="56312709"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
and the genetic relationships of the birds are passed onto the various species
coordinators, who manage the studbooks.
Everybody retains ownership of their birds and surplus birds preferably go
to members of the EFR This helps sustain healthy populations. Birds which
are genetically less important often go to new, inexperienced members.
The EFP has succeeded in unifying private breeders and zoological
gardens, so that they are in a position in which both can benefit from each
other and share knowledge, experience and birds. This collaboration will
help improve the genetic make-up of the fruit dove population and increase
the number of birds.
Currently 67 private breeders and 12 zoos in 12 different European
countries are members of the EFP.
Annual meetings
The EFP organises two annual meetings, the primary objective of which
is to exchange birds. The spring meeting gives members the opportunity to
make-up potential breeding pairs for the coming breeding season and by the
time the autumn (fall) meeting is held most surplus offspring are ready to go
to new owners. In addition, there are presentations on bird related issues, we
update members on the progress of the EFP and determine the future course
of the EFR The bilingual meetings are held in German and English.
The spring meeting is held at Koln Zoo in Germany, which is a modem
zoo which keeps a large collection of fruit doves and works in collaboration
with private breeders. The Curator of Birds, Bemd Marcordes, is Chairman
of the EFR The autumn (fall) meeting is held at a different location each year.
This year it was part of the International Dove Meeting which took place at
Houthalen, Belgium. The EFP was invited by the Aviomis Study Group, Wild
Pigeons and Small Game Birds, to celebrate its 25th Anniversary. It organised
this meeting which united pigeon and dove enthusiasts from all over Europe
and beyond. Over 80 species of pigeons and doves were exhibited, there
were international presentations, birds being sold and exchanged, trade stands
stocking bird foods and avicultural supplies and a number of societies were
represented (see following report by Rosemary Wiseman).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.65719">
Recent developments
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994799333333333" page_id="56312709"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
Great interest has been shown in the European Fmit Dove Project, not
only in Europe, but also by several private breeders and zoos in the USA,
Brazil and South Africa, which are in contact with the EFR Their stock
data will not be registered by the EFP, as exchanging captive-bred birds is
difficult due to import regulations. However, earlier this year 4.2 Jambu
Fruit Doves were imported and arrived at Koln Zoo from Louisville Zoo
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999529" page_id="56312708"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
176
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.555577" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312708" page_num="176" year="" vol="">
WITLOX - EUROPEAN FRUIT DOVE PROJECT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.971876131578947" page_id="56312708"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
in the USA. The six birds were genetically overrepresented in the AZA
(Association of Zoos and Aquariums) studbook and, therefore, were no longer
being used for breeding purposes. The disappearance of Ptilinopus jamhu
from European aviculture is a lesson to the EFP and, thankfully, it is now
back in European aviculture without having harmed the in-situ population.
Furthermore, the EFP is proud to announce that the first offspring hatched
within the year of importation.
In exchange 3.3.3 Beautiful Fruit Doves P. pulchellus were sent to
Louisville Zoo in order to broaden the gene pool of this species in the
AZA studbook. The birds were selected from amongst those belonging
to members of the EFP and were quarantined at Koln Zoo. This excellent
outcome could not have been achieved without the collaboration of private
breeders and the two zoos.
Imported from the Philippines
Another achievement was the importation from the Philippines in 2010
of five species which were no longer represented in European aviaries. The
five species are the Yellow-breasted Fruit Dove P occipitalis , Marche's or
the Flame-breasted Fruit Dove P. marchei, Black-chinned Fruit Dove P.
leclancheri , White-eared Brown Dove Phapitreron leucotis and Spotted
Imperial Pigeon Ducula carola , which was surplus stock made available
by a zoo in the Philippines. Although the prices were very high there was
enough interest to decide to import the birds, which when they came out of
quarantine were divided amongst EFP members. Three of the five species,
the Yellow-breasted Fruit Dove, White-eared Brown Dove and Spotted
Imperial Pigeon, bred for the first time the following year (2012).
Species and numbers
As I mentioned earlier, 38 different species and six subspecies totalling
over 1,500 individual birds of six genera are currently kept by the membership
of the EFP. The first census in 2009, revealed that 360 offspring of 22
different species and subspecies had been hatched that year, since when the
number of offspring hatched each year has continued to grow. In 2010, the
same number of species and subspecies produced 398 offspring. In the latest
census in 2011, 401 offspring belonging to 28 species and subspecies were
reported. For 2012, an increase in the number of species and subspecies
is expected, as well as an increase in the number of offspring reared. The
number of species and subspecies is likely to increase as new members join
the EFP and new subspecies are identified amongst the birds held by the
EFP membership.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.461366" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312707" page_num="177" year="" vol="">
WITLOX - EUROPEAN FRUIT DOVE PROJECT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998228" page_id="56312707"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
111
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.991124">
Table 1. Numbers of birds held by the EFP membership July 2012.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.970800181818182" page_id="56312707"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
Genus
Species and subspecies
Individuals
Ptilinopus
15 species
754 !
Ducula
14 species + 2 subspecies
415 j
Treron
6 species + 4 subspecies
313 |
Alectroenas
1 species
4
Gymnophaps
1 species
17
Phapitreron
1 species
16
Website
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.960678904761905" page_id="56312707"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
The European Fruit Dove Project website provides access to information
about these beautiful birds. The information provided by members is
published on the website, a decision which was initially very controversial,
as the small number of members without access to the internet felt it put them
at a big disadvantage. Five years later, however, it seems that all members
have found their way to the world wide web or have found someone to
provide the information for them.
The website is divided into two sections: the public section which
has information on species, subspecies, aviaries, breeding reports and
photographs; and the members' section which requires a password to access,
which members receive on joining the European Fruit Dove Project and
which allows them to contact species coordinators, access the membership
list, forums, breeding results, stock data and the list of surplus/wanted
birds.
An important requirement of new members is motivation, dedication and
the willingness to provide and share information. The annual membership
fee is [euro]15 (approx. #12). New members are required to sign a declaration
of approval which states that they agree to the publication of their data on
the password-protected membership section of the website.
If you keep fruit doves or simply have an interest in these birds please feel
free to contact us. You can find additional information on the EFP website:
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.838454333333333">
www. fmchttaubenproj ekt. eu
Daan Witlox, Project Coordinator Benelux/International E-mail:
hdwitlox@hotmail com
</reference>
<page confidence="0.99884" page_id="56312706"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
178
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8562445" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312706" page_num="178" year="" vol="">
THE AVIORNIS SHOW
by Rosemary Wiseman
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999005702702703" page_id="56312706"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
To coincide with the 25th Anniversary of the foundation of the wild
dove and quail component of Aviomis, a meeting was held at Houthalen in
conjunction with the European Fmit Dove Group (EFP). The aim of the
meeting was to stimulate interaction between societies with an interest in
these birds.
The meeting was attended by four members of the Avicultural Society,
Mike Curzon, Nick Curzon, Terry Babbs and Rosemary Wiseman, who took
with them the Avicultural Society show stand, in the hope of attracting new
continental members, which indeed we did.
The meeting which ran from Friday to Sunday was held in a community
centre which included a small area set aside for trade stands, the stand of the
Avicultural Society and those of other such organisations, an area in which
members displayed birds they had for sale, a coffee area and also a large
hall in which there was a comprehensive display of seed-eating doves plus
imperial pigeons Ducula spp. These were housed very neatly in rows of
small aviaries with branches placed above to reduce stress and seemed to
work, for most of the birds did seem very calm. Off this hall was a lecture
theatre which on Saturday was used for a series of talks.
The birds on sale included Luzon Bleeding-Hearts Gallicolumba
luzonica , Zebra Doves Geopelia striata , Black-naped Fruit Doves Ptilinopus
melanospila etc., as well as several of the small brown ground doves such
as the Peruvian, Gold-billed or Croaking Ground Dove Columbina cruziana
and the Ecuadorian or Buckley's Ground Dove C. buckleyi , which seem to
be increasingly popular at the moment.
As well as the ground doves and the African species, the exhibition birds
featured the Blue-headed Quail Dove Starnoenas cyanocephala. Hailing
from Cuba and little known in the UK this bird is indeed glamorous with a
bright blue cap, edged with a white and black line, blue-barred cheeks, black
throat, pinkish-purple breast and brown wings and back.
Aviomis has a breeding programme for the Socorro Dove Zenaida
graysoni and an example of the latter was displayed alongside an example of
the closely related Mourning Dove Z. macroura to illustrate the differences
between the two and there was also a hybrid Socorro Dove x Mourning Dove.
To celebrate the 25th Anniversary a special Socorro beer was brewed and
drank at the 'Nicobar' (sorry about that!).
There were talks, presented in English, German and French, on a variety
of subjects including; the birds of Madagascar; a new hand-rearing food
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.842601" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312705" page_num="179" year="" vol="">
WISEMAN - THE AVIORNIS SHOW
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999127" page_id="56312705"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
179
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.974441071428571" page_id="56312705"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
for pigeons with a component which aims to duplicate crop milk; and the
conservation efforts being made on behalf of the Endangered Veracruz or
Tuxtla Quail Dove Geotrygon carrikeri , endemic to the Sierra de los Tuxtla
in south-west Veracruz, Mexico. There were also lectures on the French
dove website, the European Fruit Dove Group (EFP) and the German Special
Interest Dove Group.
On Saturday evening all attendees gathered for a wonderful supper
prepared by wives of the Aviomis members.
We would like to thank the organisers both from Aviomis and the
European Fmit Dove Group for arranging a most interesting meeting and
for looking after us so well.
Rosemary is coordinator for the Avicultural Society Special Interest
Group for fruit doves , ground doves and bleeding-hearts. E-mail:
ro. wiseman@virgin. net
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995307" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56312705" page_num="179" year="" vol="">
CHAMPIONING THE AFRICAN PENGUIN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996783583333333" page_id="56312705"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
The Chari van der Merwe Tmst has followed-up its original donation of
R1.5 million (approx. #106,000 or US$170,000) with a further R2 million
(approx. #142,000 or US$230,000) to enable BirdLife South Africa to
continue for a further three years to investigate to precipitous collapse of the
African (Black-footed or Jackass) Penguin Spheniscus demersus population
and how this catastrophic decline can be reversed.
Since 2004 alone, the population has decreased by 50%. The colony on
Dassen Island, which used to be the largest colony in the world, has crashed
from 25,000 pairs to fewer than 4,000 pairs, an 80% decrease in seven years.
Those on St Croix Island in the Eastern Cape seem to have fared better,
although this colony is also smaller than it was a decade ago.
BirdLife South Africa is examining the effects of commercial fishing
around breeding colonies. One experiment will be to curtail fishing around
two breeding colonies and compare the breeding success and foraging
patterns of these penguins with those of two nearby colonies which will
remain open to fishing. Early studies suggest that if commercial fishing is
cutailed around breeding colonies, the penguins do not have to swim as far
to find food and, therefore, need to expend less energy.
A second project will study the movements of the penguins outside the
breeding season, when they need to find enough food to replenish their
body reserves which have become depleted during the breeding season.
It is possible that they again come into competition with the commercial
fishing industry and are unable to find sufficient food to regain prime body
condition.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995178" page_id="56312704"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
180
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.986689" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312704" page_num="180" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY TRIP TO
THE CZECH REPUBLIC
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995959833333333" page_id="56312704"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
by Laura Gardner and Geoff Masson
On September 14th a group of Avicultural Society members flew to
Prague for a four day trip to visit three zoos in the Czech Republic. Having
travelled out on the Friday, we arrived safe and sound at the Diplomat Hotel,
a four-star hotel on the outshirts of Prague. There we met Daan and Henk
Witlox, two of our members who had driven down from the Netherlands.
We all enjoyed the delicious buffet that was waiting for us and then retired
to our rooms.
Curator of Birds Antonin VaidI gave the group a short introduction to the
history of Prague Zoo.
On the Saturday we travelled by coach to Prague Zoo, where we were
met and escorted around the zoo by Curator of Birds Antonin Vaidl. Antonin
began the tour by giving us a short introduction to the history of Prague Zoo,
including details of the dramatic flood in 2002 when, within a matter of a
few hours, the zoo was inundated by over 10m (30ft) of water and mud. A
thousand animals had to be evacuated either to higher ground or to other
zoos in the Czech Republic. Unfortunately, not all of the animals could be
saved and a number either died or had to be put down, as there was no way
of saving them. Casualties included a Lowland Gorilla Gorilla gorilla ,
an Asiatic Elephant Elephas maximus , two Hippopotamus Hippopotamus
amphibius , 30 Waldrapp Ibis Geronticus eremita and nine African Spoonbills
Platalea alba , including two which had been the oldest living birds of this
species in captivity.
Antonin's knowledge of the 276 bird species maintained at Prague
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.265524" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312703" page_num="181" year="" vol="">
GARDNER &amp; MASSON - CZECH REPUBLIC
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998114" page_id="56312703"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
181
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997974" page_id="56312703"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
Zoo was impressive and it was a delight to see so many species breeding
successfully. The zoo has had the foresight to develop excellent off-show
bird enclosures which were shown to us by Antonin. A highlight was
seeing 20 species of laughingthrushes and to learn that 29 pairs are breeding
successfully. Antonin explained that when pairs fail to rear their own young,
other species such as liocichlas are often used as foster parents, which is
a practise which is working extremely well at Prague Zoo. We were also
thrilled to see Palm Cockatoos Probosciger aterrimus and Lear's Macaws
Anodorhynchus leari. Another highlight was seeing two pairs of Shoebills
Balaeniceps rex. One pair is housed in a state-of-the-art planted enclosure
with a mesh divider on rollers so that, if need be, the two birds can be
separated from one another.
Smaller passerines are well represented by several species of starlings
along with a number of different bulbuls. It was a pleasure to see Coleto
Sarcops calvus, Javan Hill Mynahs Gracula religiosa intermedia and what
used to be called Dumont's Grackle or Mynah Mino dumontii , all breeding
well in nicely planted aviaries.
Another memorable exhibit was the enormous walk-through bird of prey
enclosure which is built onto a section of rock face. Species include the
Bearded Vulture or Lammergeier Gypaetus barbatus, Steller's Sea Eagle
Haliaeetus pelagicus , Bald Eagle H. leucocephalus , Bateleur Terathopius
ecaudatus and Egyptian Vulture Neophron percnopterus.
The natural rock outcrop onto which the zoo is built provides excellent
habitat for mountain ungulates such as Ibex Capra ibex and Barbary Sheep
Ammotragus lervia. The top of the rock face is accessible by cable car and
those brave enough to take the trip enjoyed fantastic views.
The tour took us through a number of fascinating exhibits including a
tropical house for Chinese birds, an Indonesian jungle, wetland areas, lemur
islands and along a parrot trail. Antonin concluded the tour by kindly giving
each of us a beautiful poster showing all the laughingthrushes kept at Prague
Zoo. We had a wonderful day and would like to thank Antonin for devoting
so much time and attention to us.
It was a short journey back to our hotel where we enjoyed a lovely meal
in the restaurant and a few drinks in the bar. Some of the more adventurous
members of the group went off to visit some of the bars in Prague and enjoy
the beauty of the old town with its amazing architecture.
On Sunday morning we left bright and early for the zoological and
botanical gardens at Plzen (Pilsen), where we were met by Curator of Birds
Tomas Pes, who escorted us around the zoo which is celebrating its 85th
Anniversary. The collection has some 1,300 animals and 9,100 plant species.
The zoo is divided into six biogeographical zones - Australian, Neotropical,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997929" page_id="56312702"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
182
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.589481" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312702" page_num="182" year="" vol="">
GARDNER &amp; MASSON - CZECH REPUBLIC
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991595846153846" page_id="56312702"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
A large mixed species aviary at Plzen Zoo.
Palearctic, Oriental, Ethiopian and Nearctic.
Again we were treated to a guided tour of the bird exhibits along with
some of the other more unusual attractions such as DinoPark - an expedition
back into the Mesozoic era - we saw the enormous amphitheatre in which
flying displays are held and a unique, well-preserved war-time shelter beneath
the Japanese Garden. As Tomas was showing us around he told us about
the conservation projects which the zoo supports, such as the Cikananga
Wild Animal Rescue Centre on the Indonesian island of Java, where rare
endemic species are bred for release into the wild. It also supports projects
in the Philippines, Madagascar and the Corncrake Crex crex project in the
Czech Republic.
We were very priviledged to be taken behind the scenes to see the bird
breeding centre. This is a very intensive set up comprising many metal
cages approximately 4ft x 2ft (1.2m x 0.6m) housing breeding pairs of
species such as the Pink Pigeon Nesoenas mayeri , Bearded Barbet Lybius
dubius , Vasa Parrot Coracopsis vasa , Guira Cuckoo Guira guira, Australian
finches, mynahs, the Purple Glossy Starling Lamprotornis purpureus , Asian
Glossy Starling Aplonis panayensis , peacock-pheasants and several species
of weavers. The centre is staffed by a dedicated team of keepers and has a
very high rate of breeding success. We would like to sincerely thank Tomas
for giving us so much of his time and for sharing with us his expertise.
After checking out of our hotel on the final day, we travelled a couple
of hours by coach to visit the zoo and safari park at Dvur Kralove, which
houses some 2,000 animals of some 300 different species. We were met by
Michal Podhrazsky, who took the group around the safari park in a special
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.265611" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312701" page_num="183" year="" vol="">
GARDNER &amp; MASSON - CZECH REPUBLIC
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999258" page_id="56312701"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
183
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.933430523809524" page_id="56312701"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
open-sided electric bus. We saw many species of hoofstock including oryx,
reedbuck, lechwe and wildebeest or gnu. The birds (in common with the
hoofstock) are housed in very large paddocks. Our President, Christopher
Marler, was especially delighted to see Great White Pelecanus onocrotalus,
Dalmatian P crispus. Pink-backed P. rufscens and Spot-billed Pelicans P
philippensis. We also saw White Storks Ciconia ciconia , East African Grey
Crowned Cranes Balearica regulorum gibbericeps and Marabou Leptoptilos
crumeniferus, as well as three species of rhino, three species of zebra and
two kinds of giraffe.
Having completed the safari we returned to the zoological gardens where
we were free to walk around the collection at out leisure. The highlight was
a large walk-through aviary housing spoonbills, waterfowl, laughingthrushes,
Avocets Recurvirostris avosetta and Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber. The zoo
also has a large group of Greater Flamingos Phoenicopterus roseus and a
smaller group of Pink-backed Pelicans.
After a spot of lunch in the restaurant the group departed for the
airport.
The trip was a huge success - as have been all our previous trips to Europe
- and we would like to express our thanks to Mike Curzon, who with the help
of Karli Lisiecki at Howard Travel, made all the arrangements and ensured
that everyone had a great time and returned home safely.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.948994" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56312701" page_num="183" year="" vol="">
VULNERABLE IN VICTORIA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989219" page_id="56312701"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
There may be fewer than 1,000 breeding pairs of Leadbeater's or Major
Mitchell's Cockatoos Lophocroa leadbeateri left in the Australian state of
Victoria, the number of breeding pairs having declined by 65% in the past
15 years. In October, a survey in Wyperfeld National Park in Victoria's
semi-arid north-west, counted just 17 breeding pairs compared with 63 pairs
in 1995, according to a report in The Sydney Morning Herald.
New research shows that this cockatoo is particular about finding the
right nest site - opting for a hollow in a native Callitris (Cypress Pine)
which is about 100 years old and in excess of 75m (250ft) tall. Moreover,
the hollow has to be about 0.5m (1ft 8in) deep - pairs do not like it to be any
deeper and do not seem to like it any shallower, according to Victor Hurley,
a Biodiversity Officer with the Victorian Department of Sustainability and
Environment, who travels around with a chisel enlarging hollows which
are too small and sometimes evicting feral bees and other creatures from
suitable hollows.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999544" page_id="56312700"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
184
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9716815" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312700" page_num="184" year="" vol="">
THE SOCIETY'S VISIT TO THE OVERBROOK HOUSE
COLLECTION
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.442084" page_id="56312700"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
by Philip Schofield
Flamingo Gardens &amp; Zoological Park in the Buckinghamshire village of
Weston Underwood, was open to the public from 1968-2001. Nowadays,
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.996489823529412" page_id="56312700"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
the owner, Christopher Marler, maintains an impressive private collection
at his nearby home, Overbrook House. Elected President of the Avicultural
Society, following the death of Raymond Sawyer, Christopher hosted this
year's September, Autumn Social Meeting, which was attended by over 50
members and guests.
The original Flamingo Gardens held all six forms of flamingo and
comprehensive crane and stork collections, as well as such unusual
avicultural subjects as Lammergeier Gypaetus barbatus and Guanay
Cormorant Phalacrocorax bougainvillii. The current collection is smaller,
but equally fascinating. While mammals may seem out of place in an
avicultural journal, I feel I cannot ignore them as they are so important and
integral to Christopher's collection and way of life.
Leaving aside the whippets which greeted us on arrival and the white
wallabies which are, thanks largely to Christopher, now a relatively common
sight, there is a fine group of Llamas and six kinds of cattle on view.
Christopher has a lifetime's experience of breeding Shorthorn Cattle and has
judged them all over the world. His small herd seems to be gradually turning
white, not because of old age, but because of their owner's penchant for white
animals. There are also white Yaks, three cows and a piebald calf, awaiting
a new bull, which is proving difficult to find in the UK. The nearest to wild
cattle living in the current collection is the trio of Gayal, the domesticated
form of the Gaur Bos gaurus. Smaller than their wild ancestors, they have
wide spreading horns rather than the curved headgear of the original species.
Christopher's pair of Ankole Cattle also show impressive horn development.
Once a common sight in zoos, they are currently out of favour here in the
UK. The two appeared quite athletic for cattle and trotted around with their
heads held high at the sight of a small flock of aviculturists. Also lively, but
keeping their distance, were three Hungarian Steppe Cattle, an ancient breed
which is grey in colour and has lyrate horns. Christopher was hopeful that
one or both of the heifers were in calf. More approachable was the herd of
Dwarf Zebu, with the bull pawing the ground and tossing his head at us.
According to one breeder of these miniature Indian humped cattle, they make
engaging pets and there is a big demand for young calves of both sexes. The
last ungulates we met were three female Himalayan Long-eared Goats - the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.696592" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312699" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - OVERBROOK HOUSE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999059" page_id="56312699"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
185
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998847756097561" page_id="56312699"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
male who was shut away as perhaps overly friendly, shows a spiral twist to
his horns, suggestive of Markhor Capra falconeri connections in his distant
ancestry. The white Fallow Deer Cervus dama are in a distant part of the
estate and were not included in our tour.
Christopher has had a long involvement with domestic birds, particularly
geese. Grazing around the entrance to the property were 50 or more
assorted geese, many of them hatched during 2012. Most numerous were
the supremely elegant white Chinese Geese, with Frankish (also called
Franconian) Geese (true-breeding blue and a recent UK import from
continental Europe), Pomeranian and English Greyback Geese with, for
waterfowl enthusiasts, both Atlantic Branta c. canadensis and giant Canada
Geese B. c. maxima. The Atlantic Canada Goose, which is now so abundant
as a feral bird in the UK, is a big bird but nowhere near as big as the giant
Canada Goose. Other domestic birds include some 30 varieties of pigeons,
including elegant Brunner Pouters in red, yellow and dun, as well as my
favourite Arcangels. Various breeds have been tried at liberty, but predation
by Sparrowhawks Accipiter nisus has been a problem. We saw free-flying
Voorberg Croppers, which being relatively sendentary, do not attract the
hawk's attention in the same way as habitually high flying breeds of pigeon.
We also saw some very good Sebrights - examples of both Golden and Silver
of this 'hen-feathered' breed - and Golden Duckwing Roseeomb Bantams.
Of Christopher's non-domestic or 'wild' species of birds, his pride and joy
are his four species of pelicans. The six Great White Pelecanus onocrotalus
were in the early stages of nesting this year, when a change in the weather put
them off and they did not lay. However, they are in magnificent condition
and will, hopefully, try again next year. Their plumage was decidedly pink,
which Christopher attributes to their diet of freshwater fish, rather than the
pelagic species which are often fed to pelicans elsewhere. Housed away
from the Great White Pelicans is a mixed group of other pelicans, consisting
of a pair of Pink-backed B rufescens (wing-clipped at present but possibly to
be moved into an aviary in the future and kept full-winged in the hope that
the pair will breed), a single Chilean P thagus (said to be the least hardy of
the pelicans) and a pair of Australian Pelicans B conspicillatus .
The collection may be about to break the accepted dogma that small
groups of flamingos do not breed: two pairs of Lesser Flamingos
Phoenicopterus minor laid in an aviary less than 20ft x 20ft (approx. 6m x
6m) with a tiny pond, but were prevented from breeding successfully by the
presence of a pair of Blacksmith Plovers Vanellus armatus , which has now
been moved to a much larger aviary housing a flock of Greater Flamingos
P roseus. The offending plovers have been replaced in the Lesser Flamingos'
aviary by two pairs of black Mandarin Ducks Aix galericulata, a rare mutation
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999391" page_id="56312698"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
186
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.907209" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312698" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - OVERBROOK HOUSE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987150473684211" page_id="56312698"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
new to the collection. Christopher's other mutation waterfowl include blue
Carolina Wood Ducks A. sponsa , silver and bronze Mandarins, blue fawn
and silver Bahama Pintails Anas bahamensis and silver (or are they blue?)
Ringed Teal Callonetta leucophrys. A single Lapwing V vanellus represented
an apparent failure to maintain more than one of the species in the aviary it
shares with various ducks and King Pigeons. The extensive range of larger
aviaries, made from black plastic-covered chainlink netting on metal frames,
at least 1 Oft (3m) tall and over 40 years old, came from the old zoo up the road.
As well as Greater Flamingos - a young group not yet old enough to breed
- we saw a nesting colony of Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber , which failed to
rear young this year, two pairs each of Grey-headed Larus cirrocephalus and
Pacific Black-tailed Gulls L. crassirostris (Christopher's is one of a handful
of UK collections currently taking gulls seriously), also the widowed male
Bald Eagle Haliaeetus leucocephalus who, with his mate who died in 2011,
raised over 30 young (sometimes three in one nest).
Larger waterfowl enclosures house Orinoco Neochen jubata , Pacific
Brent Branta bernicla nigricans , Red-breasted B. ruficollis, Bar-headed
Anser indicus, a very tame and attention seeking group of four Blue Snow
Geese A. c. caerulescens and Emperor Geese A. canagicus, which are a
particular favourite of their owner. Ducks on view include American Anas
americana , ChiloeA sibilatrix and European WigeonA penelope (including
a blonde sample), normal-coloured Mandarin Duck, Red-crested Pochard
Netta rufina , Yellow-billed Duck A undulata and a group of Pacific Black
Duck A. superciliosa. The last named produced young this year, all of which
are being retained with a view to building a stock, as there are too few of this
handsome duck in the UK and it is, of course, threatened in its native lands
by genetic 'swamping' by the introduced Mallard A. platyrhynchos .
Side pens house Trumpeter Cygnus buccinator , Bewick's C. columbianus
bewickii and 'Polish' Mute Swans C. olor. The Bewick's breed annually
and we saw a single young one. The so-called 'Polish Swan' is a blonde
(leucistic) form of the common Mute Swan, with grey legs and feet and a
paler coloured beak. They are most striking when cygnets, being white
from hatching, without the grey 'ugly duckling' stage. Apparently, this form
occurs in Mute Swan populations in continental Europe (one of our party
reported seeing mixed broods of white and grey cygnets in the Netherlands),
however, I have not seen them at liberty in the UK.
Our Overbrook tour ended in Christopher's museum, which contains
many of the birds which over the years graced his collection.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998508" page_id="56312697"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
187
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.97486" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56312697" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
THREE IN A NEST
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.982709151515152" page_id="56312697"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
In September, Dr Matthias Reinschmidt, Zoological Director of Loro
Parque, Tenerife, reported the hatching of two Lear&amp;apos;s Macaw chicks
Anodorhynchus leari. In October, however, he corrected this to three
chicks, which were all being reared by their parents. As these macaws are
so belligerent when they are nesting, nest checks are kept to a minimum and
for this reason the third chick was not discovered until later. Although in
recent years these macaws have, off and on, produced clutches of three eggs,
never before have more than two chicks hatched in one nest. It is thought
that the pair has gained enough experience since 2007 to raise three young
without any problems.
Most of the young Amazons and cockatoos had fledged by autumn (fall)
but there was still a number of young macaws in the baby station. These
develop more slowly and visitors could still see several young Scarlet
Macaws Ara macao. More than 15 were raised this year, as well as several
Blue-throated Macaws A , glaucogularis. Green-&amp;apos;winged A. chloroptera and
Great Green Macaws A ambiguus .
Two pairs of White-bellied Caiques Pionites l leucogaster bred this year.
The young of the first clutches (three and one) were hand-reared and the two
pairs laid again and one pair hatched and reared a further three young and
the other pair a further two young, making a total of nine altogether.
For more than 10 years Loro Parque has been striving to maintain
a breeding strain of normal-coloured Turquoisine Parakeets Neophema
pulchella . Initially this was because of the increasing number of colour
mutations being bred and the corresponding decrease in the number
of normal-coloured birds. Nowadays, however, there is an increasing
demand for normal-coloured birds and this year 25 normal-coloured young
Turquoisine Parakeets were raised.
Three Lilacine Amazons Amazona autumnalis lilacina arrived recently
from the zoo in Dresden, Germany. Loro Parque is also collaborating with
German breeder Ulf Miinschner, who has loaned the collection a breeding
pair of Philippine or Red-vented Cockatoos Cacatua haematuropygia as
well as three, four year old females, to be paired with the fuedacion's spare
males.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.957685" page_id="56312697"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
t * *
</equation>
<page confidence="0.998358" page_id="56312690"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
188
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.944599" genericHeader="method" page_id="56312690" page_num="188" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
FROM Z MAGAZINE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9725875" page_id="56312690"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
Chester Zoo's Z Magazine , Autumn 2012, has on p. 15 a photo of two
Baer's Pochard ducklings Ay thy a baeri , which had been abandoned by their
parents and were being hand-reared by the zoo's bird keeping team. The zoo
is one of the few zoological institutions breeding this Critically Endangered
species and hopes to play a vital role in its long-term survival.
Curator of Birds, Andrew Owen, said: "There is a plan to establish a
European-wide breeding population, which will act as an insurance, should
the species continue to decline in the wild." Andrew added: "We hope that
these ducklings and the expertise of Chester Zoo's bird keeping staff will
play an important part in saving this species from extinction."
On p.9 of the same magazine there is a photo of keeper Amy Vercoe with
two young Black Storks Ciconia nigra , which had also been abandoned by
their parents and were being hand-reared. They were being fed a diet, which
included rats and trout, every three hours between 7.00am-7.00pm (19.00hrs).
The hope was that they would be successsfully reared and make a welcome
addition to the Chester Zoo population and the European Breeding Group.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.516673" page_id="56312690"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
* * *
FSC COURSES IN 2013
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.69137125" page_id="56312690"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
The Field Studies Council (FSC), an environmental education charity
with 70 years' experience of providing courses and fieldwork opportunities
for people of all ages on all aspects of the natural world, recently launched its
new programme of natural history courses for 2013. To browse through the
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.7762295">
latest list of courses and/or view the complete brochure you can visit: http://
www.field-studies-council.org/individuals-and-families/natural-history.aspx
and/or http://view.digipage.net/?id=fsc-naturalhistory-brochure-2013
* * *
</footnote>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.976356" genericHeader="method" page_id="56312690" page_num="188" year="" vol="">
APPEALING FOR PERFECT SPECIMENS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97580725" page_id="56312690"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
Taxidermist Jack Fishwick is appealing for perfect specimens of
birds. He has recently celebrated 40 years as a taxidermist, during which
time he supplied specimens to museums and exhibitions nationally and
internationally and continues to judge and give seminars at all the major
taxidermy competitions worldwide. Whilst working for National Museums
Scotland, Jack completed the largest series of study skins of the Montserrat
Oriole Icterus oberi. With many species under threat and taxidermy posts
within museums in the UK having virtually disappeared, he believes it is
important to try to preserve good specimens for future generations. If any
members can supply him with specimens, he is willing to recompense them
or make a donation to the Avicultural Society. E-mail:fishwick.j ack@gmai 1.
com
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999075" page_id="56312691"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
189
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.600098" page_id="56312691"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
Contributors to Volume 118 - 2012
Andrews, Bryan
Releasing macaws in Costa Rica.....108
Arruda, Carolina M.
The artificial incubation of the eggs and the hand-rearing of the
chicks of the Capuchinbird Perissocephalus tricolor. ...59
Brickell, Neville and Konigkramer, Trevor
A final note on the Drakensberg Siskin Pseudochloroptila symonsi .37
Chartier, Patrick and Libert, Cedric
Breeding the Blue-crowned Motmot Momotus momota in France.63
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.7968699" page_id="56312691"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
Davies, Llyr
Breeding the Spectacled Laughingthrush Rhinocichla mitrata .12
Dunn, Christopher
The successful breeding of the Sunbittem Eurypyga h. helias .77
Eitniear, Jack and Becherer, Terry
Dietary considerations when breeding Montezuma Quail
Cyrtonyx montezumae ....6
Ellis, Malcolm
Looking back at Raymond's first twenty-five years at Cobham......16
Gardner, Laura and Masson, Geoff
The Avicultural Society trip to the Czech Republic...180
Gamham, Carl
Further thoughts on the dietary requirements of quail
and their keeping and breeding.145
Green, Richard
Keeping and breeding the White-fronted Woodpecker
Melanerpes cactorum ...159
Gregson, Jo
The Southern Screamer Chauna torquata
at Paignton Zoo Environmental Park...........105
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.837280833333333">
Hickman, Justin C.
Native passerines in North American zoos...114
Hoppmann, Anne and Neumann, Norbert
Breeding the Orange-breasted Fig Parrot Cyclopsitta gulielmitertii
and Double-eyed Fig Parrot Cyclopsitta diophthalma
at Weltvogelpark Walsrode.....163
</reference>
<page confidence="0.992841" page_id="56312692"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
190
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.8206624" page_id="56312692"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
Contributors to Volume 118 - 2012 (cont'd)
Hoppmann, Anne
Rearing couas at Weltvogelpark Walsrode in Germany...97
The opening of a new Hummingbird Breeding Centre
to mark the Fiftieth Anniversary of Weltvogelpark Walsrode.89
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.693935870967742" page_id="56312692"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
Low, Rosemary
Long-lived lories....53
Magnus, Wolfgang, Gerbatsch, Janina and Hoppmann, Anne
The hand-rearing of three Dusky Lory chicks Pseudeos fuscata 55
Masson, Geoff
Paultons Park - 2011...........50
Santegoeds, John
The Black-throated Canary or Seedeater Serinus atrogularis ...168
Sayers, Bernard
Having been an aviculturist for fifty years: Part 1 .112
Having been an aviculturist for fifty years: Part 2.....150
Schofield, Philip
The society's visit to the Overbrook House collection...184
Smallbones, Peter
Breeding the Marabou Stork Leptopilos crumeniferus
at Paignton Zoo Environmental Park.....83
Sumbland, Nicola
Breeding the Buff-necked Ibis Theristicus caudatus
at Blackbrook Zoological Park.............1
Vielguth, Jurgen, Kirchhofel, Kerstin, Allner, Timo
and Hoppmann, Anne
Breeding the Toco Toucan Ramphastos toco and Black-necked
Aracari Pteroglossus aracari at Weltvogelpark Walsrode.................32
Waugh, David
First recorded case of active nests of the Scarlet Macaw Ara
macao and Great Green Macaw Ara ambiguus in the same
tree in tropical rainforest in Central America.......91
Wiseman, Rosemary
The Aviomis Show........178
Witlox, Daan
The European Fruit Dove Project........173
</table>
<page confidence="0.998785" page_id="56312693"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
191
</page>
<table confidence="0.96492975" page_id="56312693"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
Index to Volume 118 - 2012
Ara ambiguus, Ara macao, nesting in the same tree................................ 91
Aracari s Black-necked, bred at Walsrode................................................. 32
Avicultural Society, trip to Czech Republic........................................... 180
Avicultural Society, visit to Overbrook House collection...................... 184
Aviomis Show, at Houthalen, Belgium.................................................. 178
Book Reviews
Animals in the Blood: The Ken Smith Story ................................... 138
Bird Sense .......................................................................................... 39
Grassfinches in Australia.................................................................. 134
International Zoo Yearbook, Volume 46........................................... 137
Canary, Black-throated 168
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.841850571428571" page_id="56312693"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
Capuchiebird, incubation of eggs, hand-rearing chicks........................... 59
Chauna torquata, at Paignton Zoo......................................................... 105
Cobham, looking back at Raymond's first twenty-five years.................. 16
couas, hand-rearing protocols at Walsrode .............................................. 97
Cyclopsitta diophthalma , breeding at Walsrode .................................... 163
Cyclopsitta gulielmitertii, breeding at Walsrode.................................... 163
Cyrtonyx montezumae, dietary considerations when breeding.................. 6
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.544742166666667" page_id="56312693"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
European Fruit Dove Project, to bring together breeders...................... 173
Eurypyga h. helms, successfully bred at Twycross Zoo .......................... 77
Fig Parrot, Double-eyed, breeding at Walsrode..................................... 163
Fig Parrot, Orange-breasted, breeding at Walsrode............................... 163
horn bills, mixed fortunes for our two adopted pairs.............................. 103
Hummingbird Breeding Centre, opened at Walsrode.............................. 89
</table>
<reference confidence="0.981812833333333">
Ibis, Buff-necked, bred at Blackbrook Zoological Park1
Laughingthrush, Spectacled, bred at Waddesdon Manor Aviary............. 12
Leptoptilos crumeniferus, bred at Paignton Zoo...................................... 83
lories, longevity in captivity .................................................................... 53
Lory, Dusky, hand-rearing chicks at Walsrode ........................................ 55
macaws, released in Costa Rica............................................................. 108
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998948" page_id="56312694"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
192
</page>
<table confidence="0.966326391304348" page_id="56312694"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
Index to Volume 118 - 2012 (cont'd)
Melanerpes cactorum , keeping and breeding.....159
Motmot, Blue-crowned, bred in France................63
Motmotus momota , bred in France...... 63
News &amp; Views ......43,93,140,187
Obituaries
John Ellis.........95
Prof. J. R. Hodges.....47
Raymond Sawyer.............45
Wendy Duggan.......48
passerines, native species in North American zoos.....114
Paultons Park - 2011.......50
Perissocephalus tricolor , incubation of eggs, hand-rearing chicks......... 59
Pseudeos fuscata , hand-rearing chicks at Walsrode...55
Pseudochloroptila symonsi, a final note.37
Pteroglossus aracari , bred at Walsrode.....32
quail, further thoughts on diet, keeping and breeding...145
Quail, Montezuma, dietary considerations when breeding.......6
Ramphastos toco , bred at Walsrode......32
reminiscences, having been an aviculturist for fifty years.122,150
Rhinocichla mitrata , bred at Waddesdon Manor Aviary.12
Screamer, Southern, at Paignton Zoo.........105
Seedeater, Black-throated (Yellow-rumped)....168
</table>
<reference confidence="0.816653714285714">
Serinus atrogularis...... .......... 168
Siskin, Drakensberg, a final note.........37
Stork, Marabou, bred at Paignton Zoo.....83
Sunbittem, successfully bred at Twycross Zoo........ 77
Theristicus caudatus , bred at Blackbrook Zoological Park...... 1
Toucan, Toco, bred at Walsrode........ 32
Woodpecker, White-fronted, keeping and breeding.......159
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.956779" genericHeader="method" page_id="56312695" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AS WELL AS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.938702" page_id="56312695"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Not only did Richard Green's pair of White-fronted Woodpeckers
Melanerpes cactorum breed again in 2012, both of his pairs of White
Woodpeckers M. candidus bred and he also bred two White-collared
Kingfishers Todiramphus chloris , Von der Decken's Hombill Tockus deckeni
and the Ferruginous or Brazilian Pygmy Owl Glaucidium brasilianus.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.709011" page_id="56312695"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.780583" genericHeader="method" page_id="56312695" page_num="" year="" vol="">
A MOST ENDEARING CHICK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.968507083333333" page_id="56312695"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
A Red-tailed Black Cockatoo chick Calyptorhynchus banksii, described
as "very active and most endearing with its long fluffy yellow down", has
been hatched at Paradise Park, Hayle, Cornwall, where it is being hand-
reared. It is the first time this species has been bred there. Previous breeding
attempts failed due to the birds breaking the eggs, so this time the egg was
removed for incubation and the decision was taken to hand-rear the chick.
The chick's parents are two of four birds which ended up at Paradise Park,
after having been hatched from eggs smuggled into the UK from Australia,
which resulted in the smuggler receiving an eight-month prison sentence.
Another of the Red-tailed Black Cockatoos is so tame that he is considered
unsuitable for breeding and has instead become a star of the park's flying
display.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.580747" page_id="56312695"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.608292" genericHeader="method" page_id="56312695" page_num="" year="" vol="">
IN MEMORY OF WENDY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.944810909090909" page_id="56312695"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The World Parrot Trust (WPT), based at Paradise Park here in Cornwall,
is creating "Wendy's Fund" in memory of Wendy Duggan Riches (whose
obituary was published in Vol. 118, No. 1, p.48 (2012)). Over the years the
trust has amassed quite a collection of interesting and often unique, parrot
related artifacts, including ornaments, books, prints and paintings. All were
donated with the specific intention that they would be sold to raise funds for
parrot conservation. Wendy was an avid collector of all things related to
parrots and left much of her treasured collection to the World Parrot Trust.
All these items will be offered for sale on an online site and the funds raised
will go into "Wendy's Fund", with the money raised being used to support
parrot conservation around the world.
</bodyText>
<bodyText confidence="0.444415" page_id="56312696"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Further thoughts on the dietary requirements of quail and their
keeping and breeding
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.950073545454546" page_id="56312696"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Carl Gamham.145
Having been an aviculturist for fifty years: Part 2
by Bernard Sayers.150
Keeping and breeding the White-fronted Woodpecker
Melanerpes cactorum
by Richard Green.159
Breeding the Orange-breasted Fig Parrot Cyclopsitta gulielmitertii
and Double-eyed Fig Parrot Cyclopsitta diophthalma
at Weltvogelpark Walsrode
by Anne Hoppmann and Norbert Neumann.163
The Black-throated Canary or Seedeater Serinus atrogularis
by John Santegoeds.168
The European Fruit Dove Project
by Daan Witlox.173
The Aviomis Show
by Rosemary Wiseman. 178
The Avicultural Society trip to the Czech Republic
by Laura Gardner and Geoff Masson .180
The society's visit to the Overbrook House collection
by Philip Schofield.184
News &amp; Views.187
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
</table>
</algorithms>
