<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.907893" page_id="56266335"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
G~1 l
-&amp;X-I KP
AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 109
No. 3
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266334" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991894571428571" page_id="56266334"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2003 as for 2002: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.583919" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266334" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE..
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.966923181818182" page_id="56266334"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Enquiries regarding membership should be sent to:
THE MEMBERSHIP SECRETARY, Stewart Pyper, 21, Primrose Hill,
Nunney, Frome, Somerset BA11 4NP. Tel: 01373 836293
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TNI3 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments.
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998476" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266334" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982477333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<table confidence="0.154535" page_id="56266333"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
VoL 109 - No. 3 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2003
The Avicultural Society
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.986155333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266333" page_num="" year="" vol="">
FOR THE STUDY OF BRITISH AND FOREIGN BIRDS
IN THE WILD AND CAPTIVITY
OFFICERS AND COUNCIL
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.62208825" page_id="56266333"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
As from August 30th 2003
President
MISS R.M. EZRA
Vice Presidents
</table>
<construct confidence="0.57271025" page_id="56266333"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
J. M. DOLAN, Jr., Ph.D. (USA) The Rev. R. NOEGEL (USA)
K. W. DOLTON (Britain) Dr. H. QUINQUE (France)
MRS. D. HOLLOWAY (Britain) R.C.J. SAWYER (Britain)
C.J.S. MARLER (Britain) Dr. R. WILKINSON (Britain)
</construct>
<figure confidence="0.984396105263158" page_id="56266333"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Honorary Editor
M. ELLIS
Honorary Secretary - Treasurer
P. BOULDEN
Members of Council
M. CURZON
P. CONVY
J.A. ELLIS
MRS. L. GARDNER
A.V. GRIFFITHS
W. HARRISON
N. HEWSTON
S. PYPER
V.P. SARGENT
P. SCHOFIELD
B. TREMLETT
J. TROLLOPE
MS. R. WISEMAN
Chairman C.J.S. MARLER
</figure>
<page confidence="0.999468" page_id="56266332"  page_num="98" year="" vol="">
98
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.668739" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266332" page_num="98" year="" vol="">
NOTES ON A VISIT TO PAKISTAN
by Philip Schofield
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996062789473684" page_id="56266332"  page_num="98" year="" vol="">
I visited Pakistan from June 22nd-August 10th 1978, as a voluntary
worker with the World Pheasant Association project to reintroduce the Cheer
Pheasant Catreus wallichii to the Margalla Hills, and I am indebted to the
WPAfor introducing me to this fascinating part of the world. It was intended
that I should assist with the rearing and release of Cheer Pheasant poults
raised from eggs sent by UK aviculturists, and attempt to survey the bird
life of the release site, with particular reference to potential predators. This
led to the division of my time between the rearing station at Bansra Gali in
the Murree Hills (2,300m (approx. 7,500ft) above sea level, some 50km
(approx. 30 miles) north of Islamabad) and the release site in the Dhok
Jiwan basin of the Margalla Hills, which border the north side of the capital
(500m (approx. 1,650ft) above sea level). Severinghaus et al. (1979)
described this early phase of the project in detail and their coverage continued
elsewhere. This article is a belated attempt to record my impressions of
Pakistan and its wildlife.
At the time of my visit, much of the area around the release site
consisted of scrub up to about 2m (approx. 6 ft or so) in height. This
vegetation was developing following the exclusion of domestic livestock,
which had apparently grazed the area until there was just dust. However,
the release pen itself was sited in a valley along a stream bed, where some
taller trees had survived. The area was very rocky and much hard labour
was involved in fixing uprights for the pen. As it was the end of the dry
season, with the rainy (monsoon) period just beginning, the stream was
reduced to a trickle, with an occasional pool, one of which was included in
the pheasant enclosure. The Murree Hills surrounding Bansra Gali were
largely covered in mature forest, with scattered terraced cultivation. Murree
is a holiday destination and refuge from the summer heat of the plains. One
of the hill stations once favoured as a hot weather retreat by the British Raj,
it retains much of the architecture of the period.
Two of the world's faunal regions, the Palearctic and the Oriental,
meet in Pakistan. There is a blend of the familiar and the exotic, where
sparrows and sunbirds are close neighbours. At the time there was no field
guide to the Indian subcontinent, so the recently published A Field Guide to
the Birds of South-East Asia (Collins, 1975) had to suffice, supplemented
by Ali's and Whistler's classic works. This combination of a modern field
guide format with the older combination of text and a few plates made
identification difficult at times, and I am sure many species went
unrecognised, the vultures being especially confusing.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.728474" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266331" page_num="99" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - VISIT TO PAKISTAN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998078" page_id="56266331"  page_num="99" year="" vol="">
99
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998503476190476" page_id="56266331"  page_num="99" year="" vol="">
The attitudes of local people to wildlife came as something of a culture
shock. I was with two wildlife conservation officials in the Murree Hills
one day, when one of them dived on a small snake, killed it with his penknife
and flung it aside without comment. On reflection, I had come from a country
with only three species of snake, of which one is mildly venomous, to a land
where deadly kraits and cobras occur, and any snake is viewed with suspicion
and killed. Should I ever return to Pakistan, I will take with me a reptile
book. As it is, I am still not entirely sure whether the two large snakes
(some metres (feet) in length) that were either fighting or mating (but made
off in opposite directions when I almost stumbled upon them) on a path in
the Margalla Hills were cobras or not! Travelling by bus through Islamabad,
I saw an apparent Banded Krait Bunganus fasciatus , dead, on the end of a
stick being flicked into the river. Other reptiles noted were agamid lizards
(blamed for raiding strawberry beds) on the outside walls of houses in the
Murree Hills, and a soft-shelled turtle in a concrete pond at the small zoo at
the foot of the Margalla Hills, the turtle presumably having not arrived
unaided. Frogs of every size made a lot of noise in the evenings, especially
in wet weather, but again I was not in a position to identify them, nor could
I put a name to more than a few of the large and colourful butterflies that
came to drink at the pool in the release pen. Hornet-sized yellow wasps
were said to be very poisonous, and I gave them a wide berth. Less fortunate
was an unidentified scorpion-like creature found on the floor of my resthouse
bathroom at Dhok Jiwan, which I am afraid I gave the same treatment as
that given by locals to snakes.
Before dealing with the birds, brief reference to mammals may be of
interest. On the edge of Islamabad, domestic buffaloes wandered at will. I
tried to keep well away from them, a friend having been attacked by one in
Turkey. I was threatened only once, by a tethered (fortunately for me) buffalo
cow in a farmyard, whose owner was showing me her calf. I was told that a
Chinkara Gazelle Gazelle hennettii in the zoo had been killed recently by a
wild Leopard Panther a pardus ; these cats were apparently common in the
area and a badly stuffed one was displayed on a pole in a suburban front
garden. The hauntingly beautiful howling of jackals was heard every evening
at dusk, but they never showed themselves. I saw a mongoose and, although
a lot of Rhesus Monkeys Macaca mulatta had been seen earlier in the year,
they must have moved on, as I only ever saw one. A pair of muntjac came to
one of the valley's pools to drink in the evenings. The shed quills of
porcupines were occasionally found.
The municipal zoo on the outskirts of Islamabad held a selection of local
wildlife. Hoofstock housed in a series of barbed wire paddocks comprised
Chinkara Gazelle, which had bred, Hog Deer Axis porcinus, a male Nilghai
Boselaphus tragocamelus and a female Urial Ova vignei (the wild Red Sheep
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.973248" page_id="56266330"  page_num="100" year="" vol="">
100
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.922204" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266330" page_num="100" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - VISIT TO PAKISTAN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991261714285714" page_id="56266330"  page_num="100" year="" vol="">
of the hills) with the latter's daughter fathered by a domestic ram. A pair of
Lion Panthera leo cubs had recently been returned to Lahore Zoo (with
which there seemed to be frequent exchanges of stock), having outgrown
their accommodation and become expensive to feed. Their place had been
taken by a Himalayan Black Bear Selenarctos thibetanus cub, whose cage
label had its name in Urdu and English, which in the latter case read
'Himalayan Black Beer'. When this mistake was pointed out to the
management, in this Islamic alcohol-free country, they seemed to find it as
funny as I did. When I commented on the bear cub's lack of bedding and
suggested it might like some straw on the concrete floor, the reply was:
".is a wild animal, doesn't need any". A series of small enclosures held
porcupines, rabbits and guinea pigs, while several Rhesus Monkeys were
tethered or held individually in what looked like secondhand laboratory cages.
A series of cages, raised off the ground and each about 1.5m (approx. 5ft) in
length, held a battered Shikra Accipiter badius, a Mottled Wood Owl Strix
ocellata, a group of Common Quail Coturnix coturnix and a dozen (12) or
so each of assorted parakeets (an Alexandrine Psittacula eupatris. Ring-
necked P. krameri and Blossom-headed P. cyanocephala ) and doves (Red
Turtle Streptopelia tranquebarica , Barbary S. risoria dom., Collared S.
decaocto and Laughing S. senegalensis ) respectively. A range of aviaries,
each some 15m long x 3 m wide x 3m high (approx. 50ft long x 9 ft 9in wide
x 9ft 9in high), housed White-crested Kalij Lophura leucomelanos hamiltoni,
Cheer Pheasant, Himalayan Monal Lophophorus impejanus, peafowl Pavo
sp., cranes (two Demoiselle Anthropoides virgo and a Common Grus grus ),
a flock of domestic pigeons and a group of Black Francolins Francolinus
francolinus. The pheasants had been donated by the Pheasant Trust some
years previously. All these birds appeared to be in good condition in their
unplanted accommodation, but except for the domestic forms, none of them
were breeding. Food for many of the zoo animals, including the birds, seemed
to consist largely of roasted gram (chick peas).
Other captive birds seen included two pairs of Grey Francolins F.
pondicerianus . These lived in a large wire cage on the upstairs landing of
the home of a wildlife official with whom I stayed, and had apparently been
caught using a trained female Goshawk Accipiter gentilis (a baz in local
terminology), and did not seem to have been injured by this method of
capture. Their morning chorus outside the bedroom door removed the need
for an alarm clock. An Islamabad bird shop had a large stock of small wild-
type budgerigars, breeding in their overcrowded quarters. To my eyes they
appeared much more attractive than the exhibition birds that dominate UK
stocks. Nearly as numerous were apparently locally caught Red Avadavats
Amandava amandava , Spotted Munias Lonchurapunctulata and Silverbills
L. malabarica. The only other birds in the shop were a few black domestic
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.728317" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266329" page_num="101" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - VISIT TO PAKISTAN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999366" page_id="56266329"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
101
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997468619047619" page_id="56266329"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
ducks, obviously of Mallard Anas platyrhynchos origin and only slightly
larger in size. Domed wicker partridge cages were on sale here and elsewhere
in the bazaars. It seemed to be a common practice to catch chicks of the
Grey species ( chitta titar) and the Black (kala titar ) (which were called
partridges and never referred to as francolins) and rear them as house pets,
perhaps also for fighting, as described by Ezra (1934). Prices asked for the
birds made the seedeaters relatively cheap, though not in terms of local
wages, with budgerigars described to me as "very expensive parrots".
A visit to Rawal Lake late one evening was disappointing, despite
producing the only Night Heron Nycticorax nycticorax and Pied Kingfisher
Ceryle rudis of the trip. (There appeared to be an absence of waterfowl, for
apart from the odd Moorhen Gallinula chloropus , the only waterfowl I saw
during the whole trip were two small flocks of Mallard-descended domestic
ducks). The Common Kingfisher Alcedo atthis was seen beside a river
outside Islamabad and the spectacular White-breasted species Halcyon
smyrnensis was encountered most days in lowland scrub away from water.
White-eyed Buzzards Butastur teesa were among the birds seen daily in the
Margalla Hills, and were found in fewer numbers around Murree. A worker
at the rearing centre had rescued one from drowning in a water tank and was
keeping the bird in a fruit crate, in the hope that he could sell the bird to a
falconer. I secured its release on the grounds that it was not suitable for
falconry, and would not survive for long in that accommodation, on the
scraps he was feeding it.
Kalij Pheasants had been seen earlier in the year in the Dhok Jiwan area
and were probably still present when I was there. Despite many hours
watching the pools for birds coming to drink though, I never saw one; the
most certain way to see them is to flush them with dogs, which I was not in
a position to do and would not have been appropriate in the breeding season.
Grey Francolins were common, and I met a brood of very small chicks
crossing a road, whose parents must have been nearby. Black Francolins
were even more in evidence, the males challenging each other from dawn to
dusk. Laughing and Collared Doves were commonly seen and the Spotted
Dove S. chinensis was seen occasionally. Ring-necked Parakeets were
usually within earshot, even in town. I had not lived alongside Ring-necked
Parakeets in England, and the novelty of seeing wild parrots never wore off.
Small flocks of Blossom-headed Parakeets were seen occasionally both
outside Islamabad and in the foothills. Around Murree their place was taken
by the Slaty-headed Parakeet P. himalayana , which was seen in groups of
fewer than a dozen (12), usually feeding high in the trees.
The sounds of Ring-necked Parakeets are heard in the background of
many of the wildlife television programmes filmed in the Indian sub-
continent. I also now recognise such calls as the "did-he-do-it" of the Red-
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999268" page_id="56266328"  page_num="102" year="" vol="">
102
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.91297" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266328" page_num="102" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - VISIT TO PAKISTAN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996713261904762" page_id="56266328"  page_num="102" year="" vol="">
wattled Lapwing Vanellus indicus and the duetting of the Rusty-cheeked
Scimitar Babbler Pomatorhinus erythrogenys. Both were frequently heard
at the base of the Margalla Hills, the lapwing around scattered puddles and
areas of bare ground, and the babbler in thick scrub. It seems that each of a
pair of babblers utters part of what sounds like the several-syllabled call of
a single bird. This may enable the two birds to maintain contact in dense
vegetation.
I had expected to see some of the small seedeaters in numbers, but this
did not happen, partly perhaps because they were not in flocks at that time
of the year, but mainly because I did not visit any grain fields or grassland
areas. I therefore missed out on Avadavats and Silverbills, apart from those
in the bird shop. However, I came across Spotted Munias twice just outside
Islamabad, two birds on each occasion, in roadside bushes. Both times they
were located by their distinctive double-note, and allowed me to approach
within a couple of metres (yards) of them, before they flew off. A farmyard
near Islamabad (the one with the buffalo cow referred to earlier) had a lot of
weavers' nests in a tree. They had been built by Streaked Weavers Ploceus
manyar, a few of which were still about though their breeding season seemed
to have finished. I was given some of the retort-shaped nests, which are still
in good condition. Apparently they are used by the villagers as pot scourers.
The ones I brought back had pea-sized lumps of clay in the nest compartment,
as described by Ali (1941). Running around the farmyard were a 'gamey-
looking' cockerel and a few hens, which the farmer described as asil (i.e.
noble, pure-bred). While not exactly like the breed known in the West as
Aseel, they were tall, 'reachy' and broad-breasted, very much a traditional
fighting bird in appearance.
Throughout my stay, a tall Albezia tree beside the release pen was the
daily song post of a male Orange-headed Ground Thrush Zoothera citrina,
while Golden Orioles Oriolus oriolus were usually to be heard, and
sometimes seen, nearby. A white ribbon floating and waving about against
a background of dark foliage or rocks would resolve itself through the
binoculars into a male Paradise-Flycatcher Terpsiphone paradisi. The brown
females were less obvious. Common Mynahs Acridotheres tristis, with a
few Brahminy Starlings Sturnus pagodarum, were a daily sight, often
amongst short grass of roadside verges in town, like Common Starlings S.
vulgaris at home. Common Mynahs were nesting under the eaves of a
building at Bansra Gali, while Bank Mynahs A. ginginianus were observed
at the roadside when I was travelling by bus between Islamabad and Murree.
From the limited identification aids available, I confidently identified
Olive-backed Pipits Anthus hodgsoni in the Margalla Hills. My relevant
field notes have got lost in the intervening years, which is unfortunate, as
this pre-dated the first published record for Pakistan (Barker et al. 1999).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.728284" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266327" page_num="103" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - VISIT TO PAKISTAN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999719" page_id="56266327"  page_num="103" year="" vol="">
103
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.975511393939394" page_id="56266327"  page_num="103" year="" vol="">
Without the descriptions of the birds I saw, I cannot submit my record of the
species to an appropriate ornithological publication. A definite 'first' for
Pakistan was the Indian Pitta Pitta brachyura. These had been identified
earlier in the year, and single birds were observed several times flying the
length of the Dhok Jiwan valley, the blue on the wings being the most striking
feature when seen from the road above. Most of the time the pittas stayed
hidden, a loud whistle the only indication of their presence.
The rainy season was just beginning. Atmospheric pressure would build
up over a couple of days, until the atmosphere felt 'heavy' and people became
irritable with each other (The daytime fast practised by Muslims during the
holy month of Ramadan did not help). Suddenly there would be a torrential
downpour, it was my first encounter with tropical rainstorms. When the
rain stopped people would be smiling at each other and birds would appear
everywhere. Minivets were particularly active at such times, small flocks
of them hawking insects through the open areas of scrub often in company
with bee-eaters.
The forested setting of Murree produced some particularly rewarding
birding in the early mornings. I saw my first Yellow-billed Blue Pie Urocissa
flavirostris in an apple tree outside the resthouse in which I was staying,
before the bird flew off with its long tail floating behind. This and the
formerly aviculturally common Red-billed species U. erythrorhyncha are
stunning when seen in flight. Of the various flycatchers, the Verditer Eumyias
(. Muscicapa ) thalassina was another garden bird. Out in the woods, I met
with groups of Russet Sparrows Passer rutilans and Himalayan Greenfinches
Carduelis spinoides , and single examples of the noisy Greater Himalayan
Barbet Megalaima virens.
It was disappointing not to see any wild pheasants, one of my main
objectives in going to Asia, but I will just have to try again when
circumstances permit. Enduring memories remain of the unexpected
brilliance of shrikes and minivets, combined with an awareness of the many
small warblers that I never really got to grips with.
List of 110 species seen in Pakistan 22.6.1978 - 10.8.1978
Abbreviations: DJ = Dhok Jiwan MH = Margalla Hills
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.5456085" page_id="56266327"  page_num="103" year="" vol="">
I = Islamabad RL = Rawal Lake
M = Murree
</equation>
<reference confidence="0.552713">
Cattle Egret Bubulcus ibis (I, MH)
Night Heron Nycticorax nycticorax (RL)
Honey-Buzzard Pernis apivorus (I, MH)
Black-winged Kite Elanus caeruleus (I, MH)
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999727" page_id="56266326"  page_num="104" year="" vol="">
104
</page>
<table confidence="0.972344372093023" page_id="56266326"  page_num="104" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - VISIT TO PAKISTAN
Black Kite Milvus migrans (I, MH)
White-backed Vulture Gyps bengalensis (I, MH)
Himalayan Griffon Vulture Gyps himalayensis (M)
Shrikra Accipiter badius (M)
White-eyed Buzzard Butastur teesa (I, MH, M)
Common Buzzard Buteo buteo (I, MH)
Long-legged Buzzard Buteo rufinus (I, MH)
Tawny Eagle Aquila rapax (I, MH)
Laggar Falcon Falco jugger (I, MH)
Kestrel Falco tinnunculus (I, MH)
Red-footed Falcon Falco vespertinus (I, MH)
Black Francolin/Partridge Francolinus francolinus (I, MH)
Grey Francolin/Partridge Francolinus pondicerianus (I, MH)
Moorhen Gallinula chloropus (RL)
Red-wattled Lapwing Vanellus indicus (I, MH)
Rock Pigeon Columba livia (I, MH)
Spotted Dove Streptopelia chinensis (I, MH)
Collared Dove Streptopelia decaocto (I, MH)
Laughing Dove Streptopelia senegalensis (I, MH)
Slaty-headed Parakeet Psittacula himalayana (M)
Ring-necked Parakeet Psittacula krameri (I, MH)
Blossom-headed Parakeet Psittacula cyanocephala (I, MH)
Pied Crested Cuckoo Clamator jacobinus (I, MH)
Plaintive Cuckoo Cacomantis merulinus (I, MH)
Common Hawk Cuckoo (Brainfever Bird) Hierococcyx varius (I, MH)
Koel Eudynamys scolopacea (I, MH)
Sirkeer Malkoha/Cuckoo Phaenicophaeus leschenaultii (I, MH)
Common Coucal Centropus sinensis (I, MH)
Himalayan Barred Owlet Glaucidium cuculoides (M)
Mottled Wood Owl Strix ocellata (I, MH)
Franklin's Nightjar Caprimulgus ajfinis (I, MH)
Eurasian Nightjar Caprimulgus europaeus (I, MH)
Jungle Nightjar Caprimulgus indicus (I, MH)
House Swift Apus ajfinis (I, MH)
Alpine Swift Tachymarptis melba (I, MH)
Pied Kingfisher Ceryle rudis (RL)
Common Kingfisher Alcedo atthis (I)
White-breasted Kingfisher Halcyon smyrnensis (I, MH)
Little Green Bee-eater Merops orientalis (I, MH)
Indian Roller Coracias benghalensis (M)
Hoopoe Upupa epops (I, MH)
Great Himalayan Barbet Megalaima virens (M)
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.727383" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266325" page_num="105" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - VISIT TO PAKISTAN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998146" page_id="56266325"  page_num="105" year="" vol="">
105
</page>
<table confidence="0.98054469047619" page_id="56266325"  page_num="105" year="" vol="">
Black-ramped Flameback (Woodpecker) Dinopium benghalense (M)
Brown-fronted Pied Woodpecker Dendrocopos auriceps (M)
Indian Pita Pitta brachyura (DJ)
Crested Lark Galerida cristata (I, MH)
Red-rumped Swallow Hirundo daurica (I, MH)
Wire-tailed Swallow Hirundo smithii (I, MH)
Olive-backed Pipit Anthus hodgsoni (I, MH)
Long-billed Pipit Anthus similis (I, MH)
Short-billed Minivet Pericrocotus brevirostris (M)
Small Minivet Pericrocotus cinnamomeus (I, MH)
Red-vented Bulbul Pycnonotus cafer (I, MH)
White-cheeked Bulbul Pycnonotus leucogenys (I, MH)
Black Bulbul Hypsipetes madagascariensis (M)
Rufous-backed Shrike Lanius schach (M)
Bay-backed Shrike Lanius vittatus (I, MH)
Blue-fronted Redstart Phoenicurus frontalis (M)
Pied Bushchat Saxicola caprata (I, M)
Grey Bushchat Saxicola ferrea (M)
Indian Robin Saxicoloides fulicata (I, MH)
Blue-headed Rock Thrush Monticola cinclorhynchus (MH)
Orange-headed Ground Thrush Zoothera citrina (DJ)
Plain-backed Mountain Thrush Zoothera mollissima (M)
Grey-winged Blackbird Turdus boulboul (M)
Tickell's Thrush Turdus unicolor (M)
Rusty-cheeked Scimitar Babbler Pomatorhinus erythrogenys (MH)
Black-chinned Babbler Stachyris pyrrhops (MH)
Common Babbler Turdoides caudatus (I, MH)
Jungle Babbler Turdoides striatus (I, MH)
Streaked Laughingthrush Garrulax lineatus (M)
Eastern Crowned Warbler Phylloscopus coronatus (I, MH)
Grey-headed Flycatcher Warbler/Grey-hooded Warbler Seicercus
xanthoschistos (M)
Brown Hill Warbler/Striated Prinia Prinia criniger (I, MH)
Franklin's Wren-Warbler/Grey-breasted Prinia Prinia hodgsonii (I, MH)
Greater Brown Wren-Warbler/Plain Prinia Prinia inornata (I, MH)
Fan-tailed Warbler/Zitting Cisticola Cisticola juncidis (I, MH)
Common Tailorbird Orthotomus sutorius (I, MH)
Little Pied Flycatcher Ficedula westermanni (M)
Sooty/Dark-sided Flycatcher Muscicapa sibirica (M)
Verditer Flycatcher Eumyias ( Muscicapa ) thalassina (M)
Grey-headed Canary Flycatcher Culicicapa ceylonensis (M)
White-throated Fantail (-Flycatcher) Rhipidura albicollis (M)
</table>
<page confidence="0.999285" page_id="56266324"  page_num="106" year="" vol="">
106
</page>
<table confidence="0.987058125" page_id="56266324"  page_num="106" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - VISIT TO PAKISTAN
Asian Paradise-Flycatcher Terpsiphone paradisi (MH)
Grey Tit Parus major (I, MH)
Chestnut-bellied Nuthatch Sitta castanea (M)
Purple Sunbird Nectarinia asiatica (I, MH)
Oriental White-eye Zosterops palpebrosa (I, MH)
Crested Bunting Melophus lathami (M)
Himalayan Greenfinch Carduelis spinoides (M)
Spotted Munia Lonchura punctulata (I, MH)
House Sparrow Passer domesticus (I, MH)
Russet Sparrow Passer rutilans (M)
Streaked Weaver Ploceus manyar (I (village setting))
Brahminy Starling/Mynah Sturnus pagodarum (I, MH)
Bank Mynah Acridotheres ginginianus (M)
Common Mynah Acridotheres tristis (I, MH)
Golden Oriole Oriolus oriolus (MH)
Black Drongo Dicrurus macrocerus ( adsimilis ) (I, MH)
Ashy Drongo Dicrurus leucophaeus (I, MH)
Black-throated/Lanceolated Jay Garrulus lanceolatus (M)
Yellow-billed Blue Magpie Urocissa flavirostris (M)
Indian/Rufous Treepie Dendrocitta vagabunda (I, MH)
Raven Corvus corax (M)
Jungle Crow Corvus macrorhynchos (M)
House Crow Corvus splendens (I, MH)
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.534998" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266324" page_num="106" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.9980284375">
Ali, S. 1941. The Book of Indian Birds. Bombay Natural History Society, Bombay.
Ali,S.1949. Indian Hill Birds. Oxford University Press, Bombay.
Barker, C., Bean, N., Davidson, P., Drijvers, R. and Showier, D. 1999. Some Recent Records
of Birds around Islamabad, Pakistan. Forktail, Journal of the Oriental Bird Club No. 15, August
1999.
Ezra, A. 1934. Partridge and Bulbul Fighting in India. Avicultural Magazine, Fourth Series,
XII ,1:155-156.
Grimmett, R., Inskipp, C. and Inskipp, T. 1999. The Pocket Guide to the Birds of the Indian
Subcontinent. Christopher Helm, London.
Gruson, E. S. 1976. A Checklist to the Birds of the World. Collins, London.
King, B., Woodcock, M. and Dickinson, E. C. 1975. A Field Guide to the Birds of South-East
Asia. Collins, London.
Severinghaus, S. R., Mirza, Z. B. and Asghar, M. 1979. Selection of a Release Site for the
Reintroduction of Cheer Pheasants in Pakistan. World Pheasant Association Journal IV, 1978-
1979.
Whistler, H. 1949. Popular Handbook of Indian Birds. Gurney and Jackson, London.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999502" page_id="56266323"  page_num="107" year="" vol="">
107
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8433876" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266323" page_num="107" year="" vol="">
CAPTIVE BREEDING OF THE WHITE-BELLIED
BUSTARD Eupodotis senegalensis AT JACKSONVILLE
ZOOLOGICAL GARDENS
by Allison S. Cox
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985610333333333" page_id="56266323"  page_num="107" year="" vol="">
August 1999-October 2002, 11 White-bellied Bustards Eupodotis
senegalensis were hatched at Jacksonville Zoological Gardens, Florida, USA.
The mortality rate of chicks within the first 160 days was 45%. Inadequate
parental care contributed to three of the five deaths. Nutritional bone disease
was suspected in the other two cases of mortality. Musculoskeletal disorders
were seen in 100% of chicks that lived over 30 days. Parental neglect
stemmed from chick favouritism and dietary factors related to calcium
metabolism were identified as risk factors in the successful propagation of
these birds.
Introduction
The White-bellied Bustard is a medium-sized, buff-coloured, terrestrial
species usually found in grasslands of central and southern Africa (Bailey et
al. 1996a; Collar, 1996). It is sexually dimorphic with the males being slightly
larger and having a black crown and throat (Collar, 1996). The precocial
chicks are covered in pale down with dark stripes and can stand within
hours of hatching (Bailey et al. 1997). In the wild, they are omnivorous and
their diet includes insects, snails, lizards, seeds, berries and flowers (Collar,
1996).
History and exhibits
Jacksonville Zoological Gardens (JZG) received a male White-bellied
Bustard in 1999 to be paired with a female already in the collection. August
1999-June 2002, this pair produced eight chicks. In 2002, this pair's first
offspring 'Tank' mated with an unrelated female, 'Amelia', and sired three
chicks.
Pair 1. Our original pair is housed in the Rift Valley Aviary. This is
approximately 18m long x 12m wide x 6m high (60ft long x 40ft wide x 20ft
high) and has a 3m long x 3.5m wide x 3m high (approx. 10ft long x 12ft
wide x 10ft high) 'howdy' pen at one end. The pen has large doors at each
side, one side giving access to the aviary and the other opening up to the
outside. It is covered in fine ZooMesh(TM) for added security. The howdy
pen has been very useful when introducing birds, separating aggressive and
injured birds, and recapturing escapees. It also proved beneficial when the
bustards began to breed. When the eggs hatched, the sire, dam and chicks
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999532" page_id="56266322"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
108
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.754144" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266322" page_num="108" year="" vol="">
COX - WHITE-BELLIED BUSTARD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.984109121212121" page_id="56266322"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
were immediately moved into the howdy pen, in which keepers were better
able to observe and care for them. It also allowed for protection from rodent
pests, aggressive aviary companions and curious guests (members of the
public), while at the same time eliminating competition for the chicks' food.
Having the birds in a confined area also made it easier to catch them so that
they could be weighed and undergo medical examinations.
Pair 2. Tank and Amelia were placed together in 2000 but did not show
any courtship behaviours until July 2002 when they were moved to the
Seronera Bat Exhibit. This domed exhibit is 4.5m (approx. 15ft) tall at the
peak. The circular base of the exhibit is 6.4m (approx. 21ft) in diameter.
Grass in one section was left uncut to provide cover. The pair had previously
been kept in several different enclosures in which the two birds showed no
interest in each other. However, within days of being moved into the new
exhibit, Tank began to show courtship behaviours, e.g. following Amelia
around the exhibit very slowly with his beard extended; he also started feeding
her with insects. Less than a month after being moved to the new exhibit,
Amelia laid her first egg.
Reproduction and growth
White-bellied Bustards at JZG have laid clutches of one or two eggs
between the months of April-August. The nests were shallow depressions
in the earth often situated between tall grasses. The incubation period was
17-22 days. The chicks were weighed every three days to monitor their
growth. Newly hatched chicks ranged from 30.5g-43.2g, the average weight
being 37.7g. Most of the chicks showed similar growth rates (Fig. 1). The
chicks were offered insects (mealworms and crickets) three times a day.
Twice a day a l U cup of Mazuri Small Bird Breeder, a l U cup of finely
chopped fruit and 60g of a bird of prey mix was placed in the enclosure.
Our fruit mix consisted of 20% each of apple, melon and banana, plus 10%
each of kale, squash, grapes and papaya or pear. The bird of prey mix was
80% Nebraska Brand Bird of Prey, 10% Formax Egg Ration Crumbles and
10% Aquamax(R) Starter Brand Fingerling 300. The chicks were first
observed picking up insects on their own at about 15 days old. They were
usually weaned by 40 days.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.80576">
Social interactions
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9549965" page_id="56266322"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
Studies of White-bellied Bustards in the wild have revealed they are
monogamous and can be found living in small groups with little aggression
within the groups (Mwangi and Karanja, 1989; Collar, 1996). Although
group size and sex ratio of our birds have been determined artificially by
zoo staff, many of their breeding behaviours mirror those of White-bellied
Bustards observed in the wild.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.382619" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266321" page_num="109" year="" vol="">
COX - WHITE-BELLIED BUSTARD
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999424" page_id="56266321"  page_num="109" year="" vol="">
109
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.996562142857143" page_id="56266321"  page_num="109" year="" vol="">
Pair 1. Among bustard genera, Eupodotis bustards are the only group
wherein the female is not entirely responsible for the rearing of the young
(Collar, 1996). With our original breeding pair we found the role of the sire
not only important, but essential. The female selected the nest site, incubated
the eggs, and defended the eggs and the young. However, it was the sire
that seemed to be solely responsible for feeding the chicks. He would pick
up insects and take them to the chicks, allowing them to pick these from his
beak. When the chicks were sufficiently mobile, the male would pick up
insects and with soft purr-like vocalizations call the young to him. After
this feeding technique was mastered, he would turn away from the chicks or
hold insects higher off the ground, providing challenges to the young birds.
Our dam did not participate in the feeding of the chicks, moreover we
discovered that the sire seemed to show favouritism when there was more
than one chick to feed. With three of the pairs' five clutches, two chicks
hatched (Table 1). When this occurred the sire would feed the majority of
the food to one chick despite active and vocal begging by the other offspring.
Keepers attempted to solve this by removing the dam and one of the chicks
to another location, but she still would not feed her young. This usually
resulted in the hand-feeding of one of the chicks from each clutch.
White-bellied Bustards in the wild will often allow a young male offspring
from a previous clutch to stay and help defend the territory. In bustards, this
trait is unique to Eupodotis spp. The young male is probably not seen as a
threat because as with most bustard species, young male White-bellied
Bustards can defer maturity for a year or longer (Collar, 1996). Birds acting
as 'helpers' have also been observed here at JZG. Occasionally, older siblings
were seen feeding chicks even long after they had been weaned. One bustard
in particular was observed routinely taking insects to his two-month old
sibling. He would respond to our morning operant conditioning programme
in the aviary, pick up a mealworm and take it to the other bird roughly 25ft
(approx. 7.6m) across the aviary. During the time the chicks and parents
were in the howdy pen, the offspring from the previous clutch was usually
left in the aviary, separated from the rest of the family by 12mm (Van) mesh
chicken wire. This did not prevent the helper birds from participating in the
rearing as they would bring items of food from the aviary and feed the hungry
chicks through the wire.
At times older siblings were found to be more of a distraction than a
help. In May 2001, our pair only had one chick hatch. The chick, parents
and juvenile were all moved into the howdy pen. The sire chose to feed the
juvenile rather than the chick, so the older sibling was moved into the main
aviary. Unfortunately, the sire continued to concentrate primarily on feeding
the juvenile through the wire, so the bird was moved to another enclosure
on the other side of the zoo. After being removed from the group, the juvenile
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997165" page_id="56266289"  page_num="110" year="" vol="">
110
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.752587" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266289" page_num="110" year="" vol="">
COX - WHITE-BELLIED BUSTARD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990243" page_id="56266289"  page_num="110" year="" vol="">
started to grow black feathers on the crown and throat, indicating that it was
a male. Three months later, keepers attempted to reintroduce the young
male back into the group, but the sire aggressively rejected it.
Pair 2. The inexperienced sire, Tank, repeatedly pecked at his first chick
as it attempted to hatch and the chick died from its injuries the following
morning. A little over a month later, two chicks hatched successfully. Tank
had been separated behind a wire fence a few days before they were due to
hatch and was reintroduced when the chicks were three days old. The social
interactions between the new parents and their chicks were very different
from those of our original pair. Both parents fed the chicks equally and
showed no favouritism. However, as soon as the chicks could feed on their
own they had to be removed to another location due to excessive plucking
by the parents.
Morbidity and mortality
August 1999-November 2002,11 White-bellied Bustards hatched at JZG
(see Table 1). Our study focused on the first 160 days of life as previous
research determined complete ossification of the long bones and thus skeletal
maturity is reached at this age (Naldo et al. 1998). Of the chicks that survived
over 30 days, all showed some form of musculoskeletal disorder.
The most common problem was 'dropped wing', an extension of the
elbow and carpal joint with an apparent inability to maintain the wing in a
flexed position (see photo p.l 11). This condition was encountered with all
seven chicks that lived longer than 30 days. With six of these chicks, the
dropped wing was accompanied by an outward rotation of the wing tips.
This is commonly referred to as 'angel wing' (Naldo et al. 1998). To correct
these abnormalities, the growing primary feathers were pulled out in an
attempt to decrease the weight on the joint. If the deformity was more
severe, the wings were taped up in the correct position until they began to
grow normally (see p. 112). This was an effective treatment protocol and
little or no evidence of skeletal deformities were seen in adulthood. In an
effort to prevent the heavy primary feathers from growing too early, the
amount of protein in the diet was reduced by removing Aquamax(R) from
their pellet diet. We continued to encounter angel wing in subsequent clutches
and may further reduce the protein component.
One bird in the study was found to have nutritional bone disease. This
was discovered in August 2000 in our second clutch when a 39-day old
chick with a dropped wing was found to have a palpable fracture of the left
humerus. Radiographs revealed very poor bone mineralization of the long
bones, folding fractures of the right humerus and ulna, and recent fractures
of the left humerus and ulna. The compound fracture of the left humerus
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.382633" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266290" page_num="111" year="" vol="">
COX - WHITE-BELLIED BUSTARD
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999086" page_id="56266290"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
111
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.993221090909091" page_id="56266290"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
Ten-day old parent reared White-bellied Bustard
chick with 'dropped wing' at JZG.
was so severe that the left wing had to be amputated. To improve bone
mineralization in the chicks, we began dusting their food, including insects,
with X U teaspoon of Osteoform. The addition of this was made permanent
after which we saw no further evidence of poor bone mineralization until
June 2002 when a necropsy examination on a 23-day old chick found
unexpected soft and flexible bones. As a result the food will in future be
dusted with ground oyster shell, which may be more easily absorbed than
Osteoform.
Of the 11 chicks that hatched during the study, five did not survive to
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999009" page_id="56266291"  page_num="112" year="" vol="">
112
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.714609" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266291" page_num="112" year="" vol="">
COX - WHITE-BELLIED BUSTARD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9945985" page_id="56266291"  page_num="112" year="" vol="">
Sixteen-day old parent reared White-bellied Bustard
chick with taped wings at JZG.
160 days (see Table 2). The chick that had a wing amputated seemed to be
thriving but died spontaneously at 104 days. In 2002, our original pair had
another chick die spontaneously and no abnormalities other than poor bone
mineralization were found. Inadequate calcium levels are suspected as having
contributed to these deaths. One chick from our first clutch in 1999 died at
six days old. It was being ignored by its parents and was found away from
the family and had mud in one of its eyes, which led to an eye infection.
The chick was treated for the infection and fed by hand, but did not survive.
Another chick died at seven days of age after getting separated from its
parents and becoming cold and muddy, which led to it getting pneumonia.
As stated earlier, the first chick to hatch to our second pair, expired after
being injured by the sire during hatching.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.37217" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266292" page_num="113" year="" vol="">
COX - WHITE-BELLIED BUSTARD
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.968215" page_id="56266292"  page_num="113" year="" vol="">
113
</page>
<figure confidence="0.98416475" page_id="56266292"  page_num="113" year="" vol="">
Bustard weights
-*-699048 12/08/1999
--*--600344 22/07/2000
--*--600345* 22/07/2000
-*-601355 30/07/2001
-*-602362 07/10/2002
-\0x2666-602363 07/10/2002
-*-600345* Chick
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.68715">
with wing amputated
Fig.l. Growth curves of six parent reared White-bellied Bustard chicks
hatched at JZG.
</figureCaption>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.953356">
Discussion
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9996721" page_id="56266292"  page_num="113" year="" vol="">
This study has greatly expanded our knowledge of breeding the White-
bellied Bustard in captivity. Most previous research on rearing the chicks
of this species in captivity has involved hand-reared birds. In an effort to
allow the birds in our collection to raise their own young, it was important
for us to observe the social interactions between the chicks and the rest of
the family.
Based on these observations, we were able to quickly adjust our
husbandry protocol to reduce the likelihood of deaths due to environmental
factors following parental neglect. However, the medical issues have been
more difficult to overcome. The two most common instances of morbidity
in our collection, angel wing and fractures, were also the most prevalent
conditions found at the National Avian Research Center (NARC). It reported
83.3% of its White-bellied Bustards showed musculoskeletal disorders and
noted that angel wing was more common in the White-bellied Bustard than
in the other three bustards in its study (Naldo et al. 1998). All of the
musculoskeletal deformities found at JZG were diagnosed within 13 weeks
of age. Researchers at NARC noted that long bone growth rates are at their
peak during this period of time (Naldo et al. 2000). Nutritional deficiencies,
early growth of heavy primaries and high protein diets were all causes of
musculoskeletal deformities noted by Bailey et al. (1996b) and Naldo et al.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999678" page_id="56266293"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
114
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.673289" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266293" page_num="114" year="" vol="">
COX - WHITE-BELLIED BUSTARD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98787875" page_id="56266293"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
(1998). It is encouraging to find that the frequency of nutritional bone disease
seen in bustards at NARC was reduced after changes were made to calcium
and vitamin Ds levels in the diets (Bailey et ah 1996a; Bailey et ah 1997).
Hopefully, with further diet modifications, we will also succeed in decreasing
the occurrence of skeletal deformities in our White-bellied Bustards.
Although we continue to face obstacles when rearing White-bellied
Bustard chicks, the data collected during the rearing of previous clutches
helps us anticipate such difficulties. Keepers are now watchful for signs of
musculoskeletal disorders as well as parental behaviours that are not
conducive to raising healthy chicks. Early recognition of these problems
allows us to react quickly and correct the conditions, until through diet and
environmental modifications we can prevent the problems from occurring.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.990473">
Table 1. Reproduction of White-bellied Bustards at JZG from 1999-2002.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.990530510638298" page_id="56266293"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
Clutch size
Hatch date
% survival
to 30 days
% survival
to 160 days
Pair 1 2
12 &amp; 14 August 1999
50
50
2
22 July 2000
100
50
1
13 May 2001
100
100
2
29 &amp; 30 July 2001
50
50
1
31 May 2002
0
0
Pair 2 1
29 August 2002
0
0
2
6 October 2002
100
100
Table 2. Causes of mortality of captive-hatched White-bellied Bustard chicks
at JZG.
ISIS#
Age at
death
(days)
Cause of death
Parental factors
699049
6
Eye infection/septicemia
Parental neglect
600345
</figure>
<page confidence="0.707059" page_id="56266293"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
104
</page>
<figure confidence="0.9917321875" page_id="56266293"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
Poor bone mineralization/
amputation of left wing
None
601354
7
Pneumonia
Parental neglect-
602356
23
Poor bone mineralization
None
602359
1
Compound fracture of right
humerus
Parental injury
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.774127" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56266293" page_num="114" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.933021" page_id="56266293"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
I would like to thank Dr Andrew Teare, Dr Nick Kapustin and the
members of the Bird Department for contributing to the data reported here.
I am also grateful to Karl Kranz for commenting on an earlier version of the
manuscript.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.38287" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266294" page_num="115" year="" vol="">
COX - WHITE-BELLIED BUSTARD
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998166" page_id="56266294"  page_num="115" year="" vol="">
115
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.975229" genericHeader="references" page_id="56266294" page_num="115" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.816601" page_id="56266294"  page_num="115" year="" vol="">
B alley, T. A., Samour, J. H., Naldo, J., Hewlett, J. C. and Tarik, M. 1 996a . Causes of morbidity
in Bustards in the United Arab Emirates. Avian Diseases 40:121-129.
Bailey, T. A., Nicholls, P. K., Samour, J. H., Naldo, J., Wemery, U. and Howlett, J. C. 1996b.
Postmortem findings in Bustards in the United Arab Emirates. Avian Diseases 40:296-305.
Bailey, T. A., Naldo, J., Samour, J. H., Sleigh,I. M. and Howlett, J. C. 1997. Bustard pediatric
diseases: A review of clinical and pathological findings. Journal of Avian Medicine and Surgery
11,3:166-174.
Collar, N. J. 1996. Family Otididae (Bustards). In: Handbook of the Birds of the World. Vol.3,
Hoatzin to Auks, del Hoyo, J., Elliott, A. and Sargatal, J. (eds.). Lynx Edicions, Barcelona.
Mwangi, E. M. and Karanja, W. K. 1989. Home range, group size and sex composition in
White-bellied and Kori Bustards. Bustard Studies 4:114-121.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.973538666666666">
Naldo, J. L., Bailey, T. A. and Samour, J. H. 1998. Musculoskeletal disorders in Bustard
pediatric medicine. Journal of Avian Medicine and Surgery 12,2:82-90.
Naldo, J. L., Bailey, T. A. and Samour, J. H. 2000. Radiograph analysis of the growth rate of
long bones in Bustards. Research in Veterinary Science 69:233-240.
Allison S. Cox, Jacksonville Zoological Gardens, 8605 Zoo Parkway,
FL 32218, USA. E-mail: gatorbirdgirl@peoplepc.com
NEW HON. SECRETARY &amp; TREASURER
Members are reminded that future subscription renewals and general
(non-editorial) enquiries and correspondence, etc., should be sent to:
Paul Boulden, Hon. Secretary &amp; Treasurer, The Avicultural Society,
Arcadia, The Mounts, Totnes, Devon TQ9 7QJ, UK. E-mail:
Paul @ pboulden .fsnet .co .uk
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999601" page_id="56266295"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
116
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.991466333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266295" page_num="116" year="" vol="">
THE CAPTURE OF EIGHT MONTSERRAT ORIOLES AND
THEIR SUBSEQUENT ESTABLISHMENT AND BREEDING
AT JERSEY ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.950352628571428" page_id="56266295"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
by Andrew Owen
Introduction
The small island of Montserrat in the eastern Caribbean has experienced
volcanic activity from the Soufriere Hills volcano since July 1995. Irregular
eruptions, heavy ash falls and pyroclastic flows have caused severe damage
to the infrastructure of the island and to much of its remaining forest (Arendt
et al. 1999)
The island's only endemic bird species is the Montserrat Oriole Icterus
oberi, whose primary habitat before 1995 was in the mountain forests and
gullies (ghauts) in the south of the island. The majority of this forest has
been destroyed by the volcanic activity. Following research undertaken by
the Royal Society for the Protection of Birds and staff from the Montserrat
Forestry Department, it was found that the oriole still survived in remaining
forested areas and that its numbers were still reasonably high, within the
region of several thousand birds.
Despite the relatively high number of birds still surviving at the time
and the reduced activity from the volcano, the Montserrat Alliance (a working
group comprising members of the Montserrat Ministry of Agriculture, Trade
and the Environment (MATE), Durrell Wildlife Conservation Trust, Royal
Society for the Protection of Birds (RSPB), World Wide Fund for Nature
(WWF), Fauna and Flora International (FFI) and The Royal Botanical
Gardens, Kew), decided that because of the unpredictable nature of the
volcano, it would be prudent to collect from the wild a small number of
orioles. Therefore, an expedition was mounted to collect four pairs and
establish them at Jersey Zoo, in order to carry out trials into the husbandry
and captive breeding requirements of this aviculturally unknown species.
The Montserrat Oriole
The Montserrat Oriole was first described by G. N. Lawrence in 1880
(Jaramillo and Burke, 1999). It was declared the national bird of Montserrat
in 1982. It is a member of the family Icteridae, which comprises some 103
species, 49 of which belong to the genus Icterus , the New World Orioles.
Description
Adult male, 20cm-22cm (approx. 8 in- 8 V 2 in). The eyes are dark reddish-
brown and the bill is black with the base of the lower mandible pale grey.
The head, mantle, breast and wings are black. The black breast ends abruptly,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.527574" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266296" page_num="117" year="" vol="">
OWEN - MONTSERRAT ORIOLE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.980806" page_id="56266296"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
117
</page>
<table confidence="0.81146975" page_id="56266296"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
Andrew Owen
Male Monserrat Oriole captured at Woodlands, Centre Hills.
Andrew Owen
Female Monserrat Oriole captured at Blackwood Allen, Centre Hills.
</table>
<page confidence="0.999171" page_id="56266297"  page_num="118" year="" vol="">
118
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.844446" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266297" page_num="118" year="" vol="">
OWEN - MONTSERRAT ORIOLE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99837365" page_id="56266297"  page_num="118" year="" vol="">
the lower breast and belly to the vent being a rich yellow colour; these feathers
being faintly tinged with tawny brown. The lower back, rump and upper
tail-coverts are lemon yellow. The tail is black. The legs and feet are bluish
grey and the claws are black.
Adult female, 20cm -22cm (approx.8in-8Van). The eyes, bill, legs and
feet are the same colours as those of the male. The crown is yellow-olive,
becoming olive on the nape and mantle. The rump is olive with a yellow
wash. The lores are black and the face is yellowish with a chestnut wash on
the cheeks. The underparts are entirely olive-yellow. The wings are olive-
brown. The greater wing-coverts, tertials, secondaries and primaries are
edged with tawny. The lesser and median wing-coverts are tipped olive-
yellow, and the tail is olive with a yellowish wash.
Distribution and status
The species is sedentary and, prior to 1995, was widely distributed in
suitable habitat (moist tropical forest and bamboo forest) across the island's
three main interior mountain ranges, the Soufriere Hills, the South Soufriere
Hills and the Centre Hills. Since 1995 the oriole and its habitat in the
Soufriere and South Soufriere Hills has been lost (Arendt et ah 1999).
The species was previously considered Near Threatened (Collar et ah
1994) but as half to two-thirds of its former range has now been lost, Arendt
et al. (1999) recommended that it be classified as Globally Threatened
(endangered) due to the loss of breeding habitat since 1995.
Capture and maintenance of orioles on Montserrat
Construction of holding aviaries
On arrival in Montserrat the first task was to find a suitable site for the
establishment of temporary holding cages or aviaries for the birds that were
to be trapped. On the advice of ministry personnel, a site was chosen at the
Ministry of Agriculture's plant nursery in St Peters. This location offered
shade and seclusion for the birds, and was situated relatively close to areas
of forest in which the trapping would take place, and was within walking
distance of my accommodation.
Two possible sites were available in the plant nursery. The first, a range
of low chainlink cages which had been used to house dogs prior to their
evacuation from the island, was dismissed immediately as the cages would
require a large amount of modification before they would be suitable for
accommodating small passerines. Furthermore, the cages were being used
by a local farmer to house pigs and chickens and hygiene standards were
very poor. Therefore, we chose to build the holding aviaries in a large
wooden-framed structure, which was being used for growing local forest
plants.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.536434" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266298" page_num="119" year="" vol="">
OWEN - MONTSERRAT ORIOLE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999433" page_id="56266298"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
119
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.992504880952381" page_id="56266298"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
The decision was taken to build eight individual aviaries within the
existing structure, as it was not known whether the orioles would behave
aggressively towards each other once in captivity. The eight aviaries (3m
long x 1.5m wide x 2.5m high (approx. 9ft 9in long x 5ft wide x 8ft Sin
high)) were constructed using a timber framework with the walls and roof
made from black shade cloth. The latter was chosen because it would give
the birds some protection from the intense sunshine and would reduce any
interactions between birds in adjacent aviaries. Using this material,rather
than wire mesh, also facilitated the quicker construction of the aviaries,
which were built within four days.
Access to each aviary was through small interconnecting doors, built
into the shade cloth. Thick cover for the birds was provided using cut leafy
branches. Plastic trays were attached to each aviary frame for food and
water receptacles. The floor substrate was soil and leaf litter.
Capture of Montserrat Orioles
As there were ongoing studies of the Montserrat Oriole taking place
along several transects within the forest of the Centre Hills, many of the
most suitable areas could not be used for trapping. Therefore, alternative
locations were chosen by Forest Department rangers. Mist netting attempts
took place at various locations between July Ist-July 10th 1999. These
began early in the morning, when the temperature was cooler and the birds
were most active. Each of the sites was a known oriole site or an area which
appeared to be suitable oriole habitat. These were normally in an area with
a number of stands of Heliconia carihaea plants, the favoured nest site for
this oriole. If located in an area of thick vegetation, a strip approximately
2m-3m (some 6ft 6in-9ft 9in) wide, and the length of the nets, was cleared.
Up to four three-shelf mist nets were used, depending on the steepness of
the terrain. Each net was 15m (approx. 50ft) in length and attached to
aluminium poles and supported by guy strings. The nets were set from
ground level to 4m (approx. 13ft) high.
Up to three lines of nets were set in one area to maximize the chances of
catching the orioles. Once the nets were set, all personnel sat quietly at one
end of the net, and a tape recording of a calling male Montserrat Oriole was
played at intervals in an attempt to attract orioles defending territories in the
vicinity into the nets. The forest rangers also imitated calling orioles.
During the mist netting procedure a number of other bird species were
inadvertently caught. These were photographed and released. If after one
to two hours there were no signs of orioles in the area, one of the rangers
searched for a more suitable area. If such an area was located, the nets were
closed and moved to the new area. No more than two orioles were caught
on any one day. During 10 full days of mist netting (approximately nine
hours per day), on three days no orioles were caught.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.959822" page_id="56266299"  page_num="120" year="" vol="">
120
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.447578" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266299" page_num="120" year="" vol="">
OWEN - MONTSERRAT ORIOLE
</sectionHeader>
<tableCaption confidence="0.994522">
Table 1. Birds caught during mist netting.
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.97102575" page_id="56266299"  page_num="120" year="" vol="">
Bridled Quail-Dove Geotrygon mystacea 3
Antillean Crested Hummingbird Orthorhyncus cristatus 3
Purple-throated Carib Eulampis jugularis 5
Pearly-eyed Thrasher Margarops fuscatus 12
Scaly-breasted Thrasher Allenia fuscus 1
Forest Thrush Cichlherminia Iherminieri 8
Bananaquit Coereba flaveola 5
Montserrat Oriole Icterus oberi 8
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.9972970625" page_id="56266299"  page_num="120" year="" vol="">
Establishment in the holding aviaries
Upon being caught, each oriole was ringed with a coloured split plastic
ring, and the skull, bill, tarsus, wing and tail measured using adjustable
callipers. The bird was then placed in a cloth bag and weighed using a
Pesola 3Q0g spring balance, accurate to 2g. The bag with the bird inside
was then placed in a shady area and mist netting continued. If, after an
hour, no further orioles were located or caught, the nets were closed and the
captured bird or birds taken to the holding aviaries and given a brief
examination before being released into an aviary. The orioles were kept in
pairs, one pair in each of four of the eight aviaries. Close observation was
kept on each pair to ensure no aggression occurred.
Water for drinking and bathing was provided in shallow dishes. Food
was provided in a number of receptacles, shallow ceramic saucers and plastic
D-pots at various locations around the aviaries, to ensure that the birds had
no difficulty finding food and that individual birds would not dominate
favoured feeding stations. Although several authors and observers had stated
that the Montserrat Oriole feeds almost exclusively on insects and other
invertebrates (Arendt and Arendt, 1984; Raffaele et al. 1998; Jaramillo and
Burke, 1999), I decided to offer the captive birds as varied a diet as possible
in order to encourage them to feed. A variety of proprietary brands of dry
insectivorous mixtures were offered: Witte Molen Low Iron, Universal and
High Insect, as well as Witte Molen Low Iron Mynah pellets which had first
been soaked in water. Although little or no fruit is thought to be taken by
Montserrat Orioles in the wild, to the dishes of dry insectivorous food, I
added finely diced apple, grape and banana, and large slices of mango or
papaya were spiked on branches in the aviaries. Small mealworms, house
crickets and waxmoth larvae brought from Jersey were offered in the food
dishes. All insects offered, as well as mango and papaya, were readily taken
by the birds. Little or none of the proprietary brands of insectivorous food
was taken during the holding period.
The birds were fed and watered early each morning, usually at 6.00am
prior to further mist netting in the forest. They were checked at midday and
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.536391" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266300" page_num="121" year="" vol="">
OWEN - MONTSERRAT ORIOLE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997813" page_id="56266300"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
121
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.953932545454546" page_id="56266300"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
again late in the afternoon, when they were given a second insect feed. During
the midday check, the aviaries were given a thorough soaking using a hose
pipe. This helped the cut branches retain their leaves and seemed to be
appreciated by the birds, which bathed in the freshly replenished water dishes.
Whenever the aviaries were approached or entered the orioles became
nervous and flew from end to end, or attempted to hide amongst the foliage.
When observed from a distance they remained calm, and were seen feeding,
bathing or sitting quietly in amongst the foliage. No interactions were seen
between birds sharing aviaries or in adjoining aviaries.
Andrew Owen
One of eight holding aviaries in Montserrat.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997625" page_id="56266301"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
122
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.838308" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266301" page_num="122" year="" vol="">
OWEN - MONTSERRAT ORIOLE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997964857142857" page_id="56266301"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
Transportation from Montserrat to Jersey
Once all eight orioles were caught and established in the holding aviaries,
there was some urgency to transport them to Jersey Zoo as soon as possible
as food supplies, particularly of insects, were running low. Following health
clearance by the local veterinarian and the completion of all permits and
transportation arrangements, the birds were caught on July 13th 1999 and
placed in two wooden travelling crates 77cm wide x 30cm deep x 25cm
high (approx. 2ft 6in wide x 1ft deep x lOin high). These were divided into
four compartments per crate, each 19cm x 30cm x 25cm (approx. 7V2in x
lP/rin x 9 3 Ain). One bird was placed in each compartment, and provided
with food and water in small plastic drinking tubes.
Once crated, the orioles (and nine Mountain Chicken Frogs Leptodactylus
fallax also collected on the trip) were transported by road the short distance
to the island's helipad. From there they were flown to Antigua, where they
were inspected and given clearance by the Ministry of Agriculture's Chief
Veterinary Officer. They remained there for 11 hours awaiting the connecting
flight to London, during which time I was able to visit them regularly to
ensure they remained fit and well.
They were flown to Gatwick Airport and then travelled by road to
Heathrow Airport, finally arriving in Jersey on July 14th after spending
over 30 hours boxed and in transit.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.6228935">
Establishment in Jersey
Housing and husbandry
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991865777777778" page_id="56266301"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
On arrival at Jersey Zoo, the birds were taken to the zoo's quarantine
facility. There they were removed from their travelling crates and given a
brief physical examination by the zoo veterinarian. All eight birds appeared
to be in good physical condition. The orioles were then placed in small
indoor aviaries in the quarantine facility. Each aviary measured 2m long x
2m high x lm wide (approx. 6ft 6in long x 6ft 6in high x 3ft 3in wide). The
birds were kept in the same pair combinations as they had been in the holding
facility in Montserrat.
Each aviary was furnished with a variety of branches for perching and
cut leafy branches of Holm Oak Quercus ilex to provide cover amongst
which the birds could hide. They were checked and fed three times a day,
when in addition to the diet they were given in Montserrat, they were offered
a shallow dish containing the same softbill mixture as that offered to all the
zoo's insectivorous and omnivorous softbills. This is a mixture of Witte
Molen Low Iron, High Insect and Universal feeds, finely grated carrot,
wholemeal bread, hard-boiled egg and soaked Witte Molen Low Iron Mynah
pellets. The complete mixture is dusted with Nutrobal multivitamin powder.
A shallow dish of water was provided for drinking and bathing.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.53642" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266302" page_num="123" year="" vol="">
OWEN - MONTSERRAT ORIOLE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999064" page_id="56266302"  page_num="123" year="" vol="">
123
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.98520405882353" page_id="56266302"  page_num="123" year="" vol="">
The quarantine building was kept at a minimum temperature of 20*C
(68*F) and was fitted with a timer clock to provide the birds with 12 hours
of light. The latter was in addition to natural daylight provided by windows
along one side of the building.
Health
Whilst in isolation the orioles completed a mandatory quarantine period
of 45 days. During this period they underwent regular faecal examinations
for bacteriology, parasitology and Chlamydia testing. Bacteriology and
parasitology tests revealed a number of parasites or their ova in all individuals.
Cestodes were treated using the injectable drug Droncit. Nematodes,
Histomonas and flagellates were treated using the three-day course of 10%
Panacur, administered by injecting the drug into waxmoth larvae, a favourite
food item. Samples taken for Chlamydia testing from two individuals,
initially proved positive. However, a second sample was tested before any
treatment was administered, and this was negative. Some concerns were
expressed over the sensitivity of the method of Chlamydia testing, and,
despite the negative result, these individuals completed a 45-day course of
Aureomycin (2.5g administered ad libitum in 1 litre of drinking water), after
which a third test again proved negative.
As the end of the quarantine period coincided with the onset of winter in
Jersey, it was decided to maintain the orioles in these warm conditions until
the following spring. One pair though was moved to an annexe, where the
birds had a warm indoor building, but also had the option of using an attached
outdoor planted aviary. This gave us the opportunity to undertake research
(Williams, 2000) and also acclimatise this pair, which continued to use the
outdoor aviary during fine weather, although the pair remained inside during
very cold or wet spells and always roosted inside.
Breeding
All eight birds adapted to life in captivity remarkably well and have
since bred. Six young were reared in the first year (2000), eight in 2001,10
in 2002 and seven this year (2003). Two pairs of Jersey bred birds were sent
to London Zoo, which subsequently lost a male and will be getting another
male. Pairs have also been sent to Edinburgh Zoo and Chester Zoo. To date
the species has bred only at Jersey Zoo.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.963813" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56266302" page_num="123" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.745579" page_id="56266302"  page_num="123" year="" vol="">
Many thanks to all the staff at the Montserrat Ministry of Agriculture,
Trade and the Environment who helped me during this project, and Gerard
Gray who helped on an earlier visit. Particular thanks to forest rangers,
Lloyd Aymer and Philamon 'Pie' Murraine for their kindness, expertise and
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999244" page_id="56266303"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
124
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.835095" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266303" page_num="124" year="" vol="">
OWEN - MONTSERRAT ORIOLE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.922890416666667" page_id="56266303"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
companionship in the field; without their help and hard work the success of
this trip would not have been possible. Many thanks to DFID 'Mr Fix-it'
Tony Hill for all his help in logistics, sorting out vet visits, permits, flight
arrangements and generally smoothing the way whenever possible. Thanks
to Eluned Price and Anna Feistner for their suggestions, encouragement
and gentle persuasion during the writing of this paper. Thanks to Geoff
Hilton, RSPB, who provided the figures.
Products mentioned in the text
Pesola spring balance: Pesola AG, Rebmattli 19, CH-6340 Baar, Switzerland.
Witte Molen Universal Food, High Insect Food, Low Iron Mix, Low Iron Mynah Pellets: Witte
Molen BV, Moleneind 2,4268 GD, Meeuwen, The Netherlands.
Nutrobal multivitamin powder: Vetark Animal Health, PO. Box 60 Winchester, Hampshire S023
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.266722666666667">
9XN, UK.
Plastic coloured split rings: Lamboumes Bird Rings Ltd., Ryelands Road, Leominster HR6
8NZ, UK.
</footnote>
<table confidence="0.741338461538462" page_id="56266303"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
Droncit (praziquintel): Bayer PLC, Animal Health Business Group, Eastern Way, Bury St
Edmunds, Suffolk IP32 7AH, UK.
Aureomycin (chlortetracycline hydrochloride): Cyanamid UK, Animal Health Division,
Gosport, Hampshire, UK.
Panacur (fenbendazole): Hoechst-Roussel Vet Ltd., Walton Manor, Walton, Milton Keynes,
Buckinghamshire MK7 7AJ, UK.
References
Arendt, W. J. and Arendt, A. I. 1984. Distribution, Population Size, Status and Reproductive
Ecology of the Montserrat Oriole Icterus oberi. US Department of Agriculture, Forest Service,
Institute of Tropical Forestry.
Arendt, W. J, Gibbons, D. W. and Gray, G. 1999. Status of the volcanically threatened
Montserrat oriole Icterus oberi and other forest birds in Montserrat, West Indies. Bird
Conservation International 9:351-372.
</table>
<reference confidence="0.935891333333333">
Collar, N., Crosby, M. and Statterfield, A. 1994. Birds to Watch 2: The World List of Threatened
Birds. Birdlife International, Cambridge.
Jaramillo, A. and Burke, P. 1999. New World Blackbirds. Thelcterids. Christopher Helm/A &amp;
C Black, London.
Raffaele, H., Wiley, J., Garrido, O., Keith, A. and Raffaele, J. 1998. Birds of the West Indies.
Christopher Helm/A &amp; C Black, London.
</reference>
<bodyText confidence="0.921273333333333" page_id="56266303"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
Williams, T. 2000. A Behavioural Study of Montserrat Orioles Icterus oberi at Jersey Zoo.
Unpublished report,Durrell Wildlife Conservation Trust, Jersey.
The above account is based on an article by Andrew Owen which was
published in Dodo 36:51-61 (2000), to which information has been added
about the breeding of this species at Jersey Zoo. Andrew is at present in the
process of writing guidlines for the Montserrat Oriole and has offered to
describe the breeding of this species in a future issue of the magazine.
After six years at Jersey Zoo, he has recently left the Channel Islands
and moved to Oxfordshire.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995247" page_id="56266304"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
125
</page>
<title confidence="0.39225">
A HISTORY OF THE GENUS Picathartes IN CAPTIVITY,
</title>
<page confidence="0.920016" page_id="56266304"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
1948-2002
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.83278" page_id="56266304"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
by Marvin L, Jones
The genus Picathartes consists of two species both of which live in West
Africa. Picathartes areas (Reichenow 1899) (the first of the two to be kept
in captivity) is known under a variety of vernacular names; Grey-necked
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.643935571428572" page_id="56266304"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
Picathartes, Grey-necked Rockfowl, Blue-fronted Rockfowl, Blaustirn
Stelzenkrahe, Blauwkap Picathartes and Red-headed Rockfowl. P.
gymnocephalus (Temminck 1825) is also known under a variety of vernacular
names: White-necked Picathartes, White-necked Rockfowl, White-winged
Rockfowl, White-headed Rockfowl, Bald Crow, Yellow-headed Bald Crow,
Weisshals Stelzenkrahe, Kaalkopkraai, Witnek Picathartes, Hvidstmbet
KragedrosseL
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.973592666666667" page_id="56266304"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
Picathartes areas painted by Roland Green
Both species have been exhibited in a number of collections. They were
primarily taken as nestlings and hand-reared in Africa and brought to captivity
by only a few animal suppliers, who have never written about how they
were collected and how they were reared. They have bred in a few of these
collections, often successfully. As few were banded (ringed), there are few
accurate records of the longevity of the longest surviving birds. Moreover,
few of them were sexed, even after death, and few were saved for zoological
museums.
</bodyText>
<bodyText confidence="0.943141" page_id="56266305"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
The following list has been prepared from reports to the International Species Information System (ISIS). Other data was
received from many of the exhibiting collections or was in articles written by zoo staff. All this will be summarized later by my
good friend Josef Lindholm.
Also included is census information from the International Zoo Yearbook (hereafter abbreviated to IZY). The yearly census
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.987451" page_id="56266305"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
126
</page>
<figure confidence="0.902965913793104" page_id="56266305"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
JONES - GENUS PICATHARTES
T3 &amp;lt;L&gt;
&amp;lt;L&gt; #
O G
&amp;lt;L&gt; #
~ o
O &amp;lt;3
# #
c x
g c
3 &amp;
S 22
c
# O
*a y
G y
X X
G O
&amp; y
&amp;lt;/3 G
G O
03 X
X ^
y
(U
Oh
___ C/3
g x
2 S)
G
a b
__ _ cy3
O
O X
.2 x
c g
c3
G X
G --
g rG
5 G
2 2
y X
B #
o
CD
x
&amp;lt;D
O
^H
G
S S
21 G
X i--&gt;
&amp;lt;D
03 H
O g
Oh Jh
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.943019699346405" page_id="56266305"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
Oh X
G X5
y
03 X
G
# 2
#H X
 |g
2
&amp;lt;S
CD
a
G
G
X
&amp;lt;D
X
y
G
X
O G
x a
a) o
c /3
X
y
x
O
G
X
Ch
O
X
y
&gt;
X
*G
, X
G G
G
_y
X
G
Oh
.22 &gt;&gt;
x
X G
22 y
1 j*
G
y c
Oh
Oh +- 1
G X
H_J I--I
G 30
2 X
G y
G &gt;
X 03
# g
G y
y a
G
X
&gt;&gt; ^
G C
a "
X &gt;
y ^
X o
^ a
C" 03
G x
8 x
.2 a
y g
Oh ^
S&quot; y
H-&gt; X
03 &apos; 4_&gt;
X
2 1
1 &gt;
O G
y
a
o
X
X
X
#
x
y
G
y
x
2 *
y ^ d)
^ GO 3
2 M G
S *
&quot;
*a # o
y i/s
X X
tS 03 y
ax
G o
" G
o
Co a
/3 y y
--i y &gt;
O Oh X
X 03 3h
G ^ G
X y y
S c 2
03
X
G X
03 03
_ o
u X
y G
y x *
Vh G
y y
o
o
G _
n G (D
x e
x ^ 2
y * &amp;lt;
o
N
G
3
O
N
h-n G
s a
2 3
2 1 # #
O &apos; 3 b 03
03 fcj -- ^
S m
S 1 &gt;,
43 '
Oh
^ OO^
</equation>
<page confidence="0.493552" page_id="56266305"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
30
</page>
<figure confidence="0.973152118644068" page_id="56266305"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
03
+H O
8 ^
o
o
G X
.3 43
8 8
N N
a B
2 S
#
So g3
2 #
S o
T3 -O
O O
H X
O -H
A o
|l
c/5 6
x o
*5 N
"D
u
w o
&gt;, 'g
X S
C j
S4
o a
o # PQ
^ 3 *S
1^5
c &gt;
t?cS
I *8
M &quot;c
o e
N 2
c "
2 x
Gh O
o o
Q\ o
-- N
C/3 tn
3 03
c" cd
C C
&amp;lt;D &amp;lt;D
O 03
h M
KS
fcj #
*8 8
g N
8 3 1
N PQ S
e PQ ^
" G 5
&quot;O 22 T3
O g &amp;lt;U
hU^
0X3 0
d e# d
o
J
*C
PQ
#
3
e
(c)
hJ
3
X
2
Gh
&gt;
2
2
Gh
03
#
oo
&amp;
#
x
r-
S
oo
d
g2
o
X
03
&amp;lt;D
-S
1
d
4J
#
i(c)
03
03
X
3(c)
03
#
(c)3
3D
r-
03
r-
03
i--&amp;lt;
</figure>
<page confidence="0.72869" page_id="56266305"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<figure confidence="0.99826090625" page_id="56266305"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
t+H
C/3
'Oh
1
.#
H--(
o
03
^=H
Cl,
-S
o
o
o
Oh
d
*--1
oj
CO
X
.#
o
03
o
(c)
CL,
03
Q
oo
3
&amp;lt;Z3
(c)
</figure>
<page confidence="0.787976" page_id="56266305"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<figure confidence="0.995133936170213" page_id="56266305"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
00
r-
d
30
03
SCh
(c)
c(c)
cx
&amp;lt;
G-
O
o
oo
3
T-!
3
hS
ed
#
&amp;lt;N
"
CO
1
^ O
g h u
S " r2
C /3 03 $--I
"=&amp;lt; "=&amp;lt; r ^
^ T) -o J
o
"SS tH o o
^ x ^ #
*S Q o o
a, o u u
CO 2
&apos;#&gt; c3
cd
X X
.2 S3
x jB
d &gt;,
o PQ
c n ''O ^ '&quot;O
Q x Q
d x Q Q
^ d d --i
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.369019" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266306" page_num="127" year="" vol="">
JONES - GENUS PICATHARTES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.774327" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
127
</page>
<figure confidence="0.994761782608696" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
o o
ts ts
a a
M -M
S S
a #
Oi Om
&amp;lt; &amp;lt;
o o
Ala
PM
^J,
r- r-&gt;
os os
&amp;o m
3 3
&amp;lt; &amp;lt;
Q
O (c)
N hS
tJ N
a n
m a
</figure>
<page confidence="0.980806" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
11
</page>
<equation confidence="0.9888264" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
# 2
&quot;&apos;t
OS I&apos;-
^ OS
o &quot;O o &quot;d
O
E^N 13
^ #
&amp;lt;-&gt; 3
O 1-9
tn eo
-o
p
-d
p
T 3
p
T 3
P
cd
</equation>
<page confidence="0.621166" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
3
</page>
<figure confidence="0.7894686" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
r-
as
*2
-a
p
</figure>
<page confidence="0.965818" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<figure confidence="0.392208" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
C
</figure>
<page confidence="0.979866" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<figure confidence="0.549384" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
a
</figure>
<page confidence="0.980776" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<figure confidence="0.370554" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
s
</figure>
<page confidence="0.971021" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<figure confidence="0.784311" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
d
C 3
*r?
</figure>
<page confidence="0.963105" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<equation confidence="0.5952865" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
o
cd
</equation>
<page confidence="0.968689" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<figure confidence="0.914303857142857" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
&quot;O
O
5 t
o
d
p
cd
</figure>
<page confidence="0.952138" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<equation confidence="0.946102142857143" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
T 3
p
st
o
d
P
cd
</equation>
<page confidence="0.679413" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<equation confidence="0.747074714285714" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
*d
_P
#
o
c
O
&quot;3
</equation>
<page confidence="0.750145" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<equation confidence="0.977450769230769" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
T 3
_P
.2
o
*d .2
.2 tS
p
GQ
C
PM
P
T 3
O
</equation>
<page confidence="0.8259155" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
3
43
</page>
<figure confidence="0.98108968" page_id="56266306"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
-d
.2
-3
1
H
&apos;O
1
'S
1
o|
&apos;S
,p
cm
-d &amp;lt;p
0 )
2
-d
&amp;H 03
fe 2
&amp;lt;D
ca
ed
cd
#
CO
^ # (c)
a ^ &gt;
N
ti
#
tN
l&gt;
Os
r~-
OS
T jS
&amp;lt;2
"n
cm
p p
(c)
&amp;,
p
W (R) 43
d&gt; ^ *
04 so o
2
#
(c)
1
P
00
OS
m
S
o
1.1
_ -a
o - p
(c) -a
* O o
* . Cv3
CNS O,
Si
&amp;lt;" S
if
* a
kN '{3
sy -s
\0x25A0o I
p rt
JZFcensus 1973: Frankfurt Zoo 1.1.3 (cb 0.1.2); *0.0.1 hatched 12 Aug 1975 Frankfurt Zoo
Wasseeaar Zoo 0.0.1 0.0.1 died 19 Aug 1975 Frankfurt Zoo
IZY census 1974: Frankfurt Zoo 1.1.1 (cb 1.0.1); cd infection associated
Walsrode Bird Park 0.0.2; Wassenaar Zoo 0.0.1
</figure>
<figure confidence="0.990876152112676" page_id="56266307"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
/ZE census 1976 : Frankfurt Zoo 1 . 2.0 (cb 1 . 1 . 0 ). * 0 . 0.1 hatched 23 Apr 1979 Frankfurt Zoo
0 . 0.1 died 30 Apr 1979 Frankfurt Zoo
* 0 . 0.1 hatched 7 Mar 1976 Frankfurt Zoo cd unknown
0 . 0.1 died 16 Mar 1976 Frankfurt Zoo
cd unknown * 1 . 0.1 hatched 27 Dec 1979 Frankfurt Zoo
128
JONES - GENUS PICATHARTES
o
o
o
N
C
.(c)
d
O
o
N
o
o
"
d
O
o
N
O
o
o
N
O
N
N
ts
ts
a
a
x
o
ts
a
N
ts
X
O
X
o
ts
a
ts
a
(c)
c 4
ts
,3
ts
a
a
x
CO
o
X
a
&amp;lt;N
oj
X
X
y--&gt;
.X
X
X
G
3
"H
X
G
3
X
* 3 '
G
C
3
O
c 4
o
o
1
X
o
X
G
3
X
&amp;lt;N
O
O
c 4
o
o
G
3
X
CN
G
3
X
CN
X
o
o
G
3
\0x25A0~-
X
G
3
X
CO
&amp;lt;N
oo
ON
oo
ON
a
N
ts
00
ON
O
OO
ON
N
ts
N
ts
OO
On
oo
On
N
ts
00
ON
00
ON
S-&amp;lt;
X
&amp;lt;
&quot;O
2
&gt;
o
a
NO
o
05
&amp;lt;D
a
M
c
3
X
3
a
NO
bJ)
3
&amp;lt;
a
X
G
3
N*
a
X
G
3
s_
i
a
CN
3
2
CN
a
X
G
2
X
o
X
CN
3
s
CO
NO
o
CN
&apos;o
X
&amp;lt;N
X
X
X
CN
3
c
.2
.2 o
^ a
--\0x25A0 c
Q a
3
G
-o .2
.2 o
^ a
O G
Q 22
o &gt;
# !S g
o ^ |
d *. I
o H .-o
--
CO CO
ON ON
C/5 C/5
G 3
CO CO
C G
&amp;lt;D 4&gt;
O O
X X
N N
o ^
I I S
hH &quot;O X
o' &quot;S i
d (R) &quot;d
* o o
O G
-S  |.S
_&amp;lt; T3 &gt;
* -- G
O * a)
O ^ &quot;O
* (c) O
bH
NO
NO
i&quot;- on
ON
7 el
&amp;lt;
*s.l
t ^
d 1 S
X Q --
o o
o o
N N
tS tS
3 ^3
X X
c c
2 2
x x
NO NO
r&quot; r-
On ON
X X
&amp;lt; &amp;lt;
O NT)
o &gt;
3 I S
_ (c) X
0^3
8 o
N N
ts 2
3 N_
s a
c X
cd G
# I
on r~
T--I ON
3* G
S 5
x .2
--&amp;lt; &quot;O
d a
d Q
o o
o o
N N
ts ts
.3 .3
TJ X
^ G
O O
O O
N N
tS IS
a a
X X
CO i--&amp;lt;
X3
X.
X
Ct5
a
&amp;lt;J1
o
X
X
a
5-
NO
NO
ca
oo
oo
3
t-*
r-
.2
ON
. ON
o
ON
ON
'&gt;
N ,
3
&gt;
o
Z
&gt;
o
Z
A
#
&amp;
S
X
&amp;lt;u
X
T--I
r-
r-
3-
ON
o
ON
a
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.826844076923077" page_id="56266308"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
JONES - GENUS PICATHARTES
do (c)
2 tS
33 ^
a) *2
43 85
2 6J0
ed g
- c v
o s
o
cn #h (c) (c) n
c4 c4 c4 -Hj
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.705535" page_id="56266308"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
d d d d ,s
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.968307142857143" page_id="56266308"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
ca M "3 M
O
&amp;lt;D
O
o --&apos;
(c) -O
N "
a y
\0x25A0S S
1 t3
N N N N N
" g
* #
Q --
</equation>
<page confidence="0.810655" page_id="56266308"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
8
</page>
<figure confidence="0.978047484536082" page_id="56266308"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
On .
o -d -O
* S3 (c)
"d O
w S o
1 fS *
o O *
J c S
w
5=1
2
1
O
ON
On
l&quot;
ON
3
*QQ
in
ON
cfl
bfl
DO
Ph
in
#
\o
1Xi
r-
PL,
OO
On
b0
3
O
CL,
d
C
Cfl
ca
bO
.s
(c)0
00
(X)
OO
OO
&amp;lt;
GO
CD
3
Os
On
ON
On
ON
ON
NO
fi
ca
O
&amp;lt;u
CO
ca
ca
ca
ca
1--1
OJ
e3
s
-(c) -o
2 &amp;lt;u
&amp;lt;N Jtj
d 3
o U
o o
o o
O
8
8
o
o
N N
N
N
N
N
^-s
d d
a a
1 c
cd C3
t# Pm
d
eg
C
d
&amp;lt;5
ed
#
d
a
M
a
2
&amp;N
d
c5
cd
tS
o
r4
S CJ
O
co to
co
OO
On
co
CO
co
o
OO OO
ON ON
OO
ON
QO
ON
OO
On
N
d
S=N l=!
be
b0
b0
On On
&gt;s~"
d
d
3
&amp;lt; &amp;lt;
"2 33
5 "
&amp;lt;
&amp;lt;
&amp;lt;
1
ON On
&gt;--i
cn
O
M
n--N *--1
1 . 3
Cn!
Ph
3 3
S |
i2 -3
33
&amp;lt;D
43 d S3
J-8 1-8 I
5 &apos;-3 ! =3 I
(c) 3 5 3 a
5S
1
(c)
(c)
"
S
fee
2
12
(c)
1
On
CD
m
u S&gt;
pq "
g
a .2
o -g
W -Q
5m O
" On
-2 x
33
d
c3
</figure>
<page confidence="0.735714" page_id="56266308"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<figure confidence="0.999531" page_id="56266308"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
-O
d
cd
&amp;lt;d
o (c)
tS 3
1 S
33 0)
O W
J d
In S&gt;
On ,g
H -2
5 o
t o
M 3
(O G
So
S ^
ffi o
8 I
O 5
s S
33 -a
# 1
(c) O
o O
\0x25A0is o
3 N
&amp;lt;3 o
On O
" N
&amp;lt;D ^
" g
\0x25A0s *S
(c) o
ffi N-l
</figure>
<page confidence="0.97457" page_id="56266308"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
129
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.986472666666667" page_id="56266308"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
0.0.1 reed 20 Apr 1957 London Zoo 0.0.1 died 4 Jul 1957 London Zoo
Collected as a nestling in Sierra Leone and hand-reared by Jim Meezies,
who presented it to the zoo. TO BE CONTINUED
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.992657" page_id="56266309"  page_num="130" year="" vol="">
130
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7277745" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266309" page_num="130" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE AND ME: A SYMBIOSIS
by Derek Goodwin
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.983520105263158" page_id="56266309"  page_num="130" year="" vol="">
Replying to a letter from me with queries about sundry matters, our
Membership Secretary, Stewart Pyper, was kind enough to say, or rather
write: "...your contributions to the magazine have been monumental over
the years." Needless to say I was very pleased by this compliment which I
felt ("Vanity, vanity, all is vanity!") was not entirely undeserved, but at the
same time I was very conscious that my relationship with our magazine
had, if only by a series of coincidences, been symbiotic and probably far
more advantageous to me than to the magazine.
Many other ornithologists, some very eminent, have, for reasons I will
mention later, been glad to have some of their works published in the
Avicultural Magazine. For example Jean Delacour, Reg Moreau, Magdelena
Heinroth, Konrad Lorenz and my friend Ken Simmons who in February
2002 died tragically after a long crippling illness.
So far as I know though, no one else, except perhaps the magazine's
various editors, had their lives so chanced for the better as I did. In August
1945 I returned, as a soldier of 25, from service overseas in Egypt, Libya
and Malta and was granted four weeks leave. During this period I visited
the Zoological Department of Gamages emporium in London. There I saw
on sale some 1920s copies of the Avicultural Magazine , including one for
January 1929 with an article on the Common Bronzewing Pigeon Phaps
chalcoptera by Mr T. H. Newman, illustrated with a beautiful and accurate
painting of this species by Mr H. Goodchild. I purchased this copy (which
I still have) and several others and fell into conversation with the young
man who served me with them. To my surprise, he told me that the Avicultural
Magazine was still being published and gave me the address of its then (and
for long after) Hon. Editor, Miss Phyllis Barclay-Smith, who then had rooms
at the British Museum (Natural History) in South Kensington. I wrote to
her and this led to my becoming a member of The Avicultural Society. I
was tempted to become a Life Member, but felt I could not afford the cost of
that which, if I remember correctly, was then #10 (about US$16 at the present
exchange rate)!
In June 1946 I was demobbed and began seriously to consider whether
to try for some more congenial job than my pre-war one in a mail order
business. But I soon ascertained that there were very few jobs in any way
connected with birds and wildlife and for those there were a doctorate was
essential. However, Miss Barclay-Smith suggested I visit her at the museum
when next in London. There she introduced me to Mr J. D. Macdonald,
who was then in charge of the Bird Room, as the three-storey department,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.743777" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266310" page_num="131" year="" vol="">
GOODWIN - THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE AND ME
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998714" page_id="56266310"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
131
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9990855" page_id="56266310"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
each with several individual rooms within it, which then housed the bird
collection was called because long before, it had been merely one room, or
so I was told.
Mr Macdonald, to my great surprise, offered me a job as temporary
assistant. Luckily for me, it was then (but only for a few more years) possible
to get on to the permanent staff in due course, if one could satisfy the
examining board that one was suitable even if one did not have any paper
qualifications. I managed to do so just in time. Of course, working in the
Bird Room, I had access to study skins of all the birds in the museum
collection, and the superb ornithological library. I also met many interesting
ornithologists from all over the world. Some of whom became life-long
friends or pen friends.
Needless to say, such employment ideally dove-tailed with my studying,
keeping (preferably free-flying), watching and enjoying the beauty of living
birds. I was able to combine the fruits of both my employment and my
hobby in the six books on birds I have written, four of which were done as
part of my official work and written in my working time in the museum.
I often think how different, and worse, my life might have been had I
never seen those old copies of the Avicultural Magazine in Gamages.
Now to turn to some of the virtues of our magazine, too often overlooked
by some bird addicts, including, or perhaps especially some in influential
positions in scientific, conservational and legal organisations.
Anyone who has written letters or articles to be (he or she hopes)
published in magazines devoted to ornithology (using that term in its widest
sense) will know how the editors of such publications (as also those of the
newspapers) feel it incumbent on themselves to edit all such offerings by
cutting out all that they consider irrelevant which too often includes the
author's carefully explained reasons for his or her opposition to any currently
politically correct (in ornithological or conservational circles) opinions and
any of those anecdotal or humorous asides which so often make pre-1900
copies of the Ibis, Auk, J. Orn. and other such prestigious publications so
much more interesting to read and to re-read, than the post-1980 volumes of
the same journals.
I have found the Avicultural Magazine one of the most fertile sources of
information on bird behaviour and very often of items I have not found
elsewhere. Even if sometimes one gets exasperated at the lack of detailed
description of some activity mentioned.
However, the fact that contributors to our magazine often write in
everyday language is more often than not more agreeable to the professional
ornithologist as well as more understandable to readers generally. I recall,
long ago, when a great friend of mine, now alas, no longer with us, in an
article he was about to submit to a scientific journal did not like a line he
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998535" page_id="56266311"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
132
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.884795" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266311" page_num="132" year="" vol="">
GOODWIN - THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE AND ME
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996887137931034" page_id="56266311"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
had written: "Some Arctic-breeding waders have their escape-reactions set
at a high threshold level of response where Man is concerned as a predator."
I mildly suggested that he change it to "Some Arctic-breeding waders have
little fear of Man". He did, and, to his credit, the editor accepted it.
Because they have been able to have their offerings published in full
has, I believe been one reason that many renowned ornithologists as well as
less well known but not necessarily less knowledgeable bird addicts have
written articles for the Avicultural Magazine. Another advantage, which I
have realised more fully in my old age, is that although as one gets older
one recalls very vividly past events in one's life, one does not recall all of
them, especially not minor but still relevant details. Often, referring back to
what I wrote in past copies of the Avicultural Magazine , I have been able to
re-read what I had once written and re-leam facts that I could no longer
remember. Similarly I (and others) have written articles for the Avicultural
Magazine summarising my experience with this or that species including
much that many editors of other bird journals would have excised as
sentimental or anecdotal irrelevancies but which, I believe and hope are not
so regarded by many of my readers.
At least I am in good company as not only are the writings of such
rightly revered past naturalists as Darwin and Wallace thus enriched, but so
are those of one, Alexander Skutch, whom I regard as one of the greatest
field ornithologists and (an unusual combination) one of the greatest and
most humane thinkers (and publisher of his thoughts in eminently readable
books) whose working life has largely overlapped my own. Though, I hasten
to add, his writing abilities and general knowledge are much superior to my
own.
Though I do not suppose many of my readers will benefit so much from
our magazine as I have, I hope they will also enjoy reading back issues and
contributing to future numbers of it.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.629467" page_id="56266311"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.978832" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56266311" page_num="132" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINES BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.957383" page_id="56266311"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
A large stock is available including some early issues. Further details
are available from: The Membership Secretary, Stewart Pyper, 21 Primrose
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.6269265">
Hill, Nunney, Frome, Somerset BA11 4NP, UK. Tel:01373 836293 or
E-mail: Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998992" page_id="56266312"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
133
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.416175333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266312" page_num="133" year="" vol="">
THE SOCIETY'S VISIT TO BLACKBROOK ZOOLOGICAL
PARK (APRIL 5th 2003)
by Philip Schofield
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998307894736842" page_id="56266312"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
There has been an animal collection open to the public on the Blackbrook
site for a considerable time. Initially Blackbrook Farm, it has undergone
various name changes, each one reflecting the current emphasis of the
collection. Taken over in 1991 by Diana Holloway (who at the April 5th
2003 Council Meeting was elected a Vice President of the Avicultural
Society) and her son Mark Rubery, the collection is now designated
Blackbrook Zoological Park. This reflects its present status as a proper zoo,
with mammals, reptiles, fish and invertebrates, although birds still greatly
outnumber all the other groups on show. This was my first visit -1 do not
usually venture so far north.
The collection holds some 300 bird species, of which 130 are waterfowl,
on the 70 acre (28 hectare) site. This must be one of the most comprehensive
collections of waterfowl ever assembled, given that there are in total only
146 species of ducks, geese and swans. For me, the most noteworthy
waterfowl at Blackbrook divide easily into two groups. The first of these
being the sea ducks, some of which can be difficult to keep in conventional
collections, but high on the Staffordshire moors they do well and look as fit
as wild birds. The main sea duck lake (8ft (approx.2.4m) deep) is at the
highest point on the property. I imagine this enables the occupants to enjoy
the same benefits as those of the new penguin enclosure at Whipsnade Wild
Animal Park, with the relatively cool and windswept conditions making it
difficult for disease organisms to flourish. I counted 20 Long-tailed Ducks,
looking as fit as I have ever seen them. The males were calling and their
'song' of four or five syllables was for me evocative of time spent in Iceland.
This very un-ducklike sound is difficult to render into words, so if you have
not heard it and would like to, try to access a good sound recording. A
species which the Wildfowl &amp; Wetlands Trust once described as being too
difficult to keep, the Long-tailed Duck seems to thrive under the semi-natural
conditions at Blackbrook. The other startling sea duck on show, less dramatic
in voice and behaviour, is S teller's Eider, represented by two males. Smaller
and different in shape to the other eiders, Steller's is still comparatively
little known as an avicultural subject. One could spend many hours at
Blackbrook concentrating on the sea duck alone, given that there are also
King, Spectacled and Pacific Eiders, Common and Velvet Scoters, Barrow's
Goldeneye and Smew. Any one of these would be the talking point of any
collection that included them. Admittedly Smew have become relatively
cheap and available in recent years, but they still attract attention wherever
they are seen.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999554" page_id="56266313"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
134
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.85803" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266313" page_num="134" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - BLACKBROOK ZOOLOGICAL PARK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987007285714286" page_id="56266313"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
The second notable category of waterfowl at Blackbrook is what I call
the neglected species. These are the ones that do not make it into most
collections by virtue of being too similar to something else, not brightly
coloured, too aggressive or too subtle for most people. A shining example
is the Koloa or Hawaiian Duck. An Hawaiian endemic, between a Mallard
and Laysan Teal in appearance, it would benefit from a large captive
population as an insurance against catastrophe overtaking the wild
population. Unfortunate ly, most people just do not bother with it. Lacking
the engaging tameness of the closely related Laysan Teal, the slightly larger
Koloa is rarely kept and dealers tell me they cannot sell them. Several pairs
of Hawaiian Duck have their own enclosure at Blackbrook. Perhaps I should
put my money where my mouth is and get some! If all aviculturists were as
committed to conservation as we say we are, there should be as many Koloas
in collections as there are Nene. Coming from the same part of the world,
the latter, like the Laysan Teal, sells itself by its tameness and is also visually
striking; thus it has in a few decades gone from near extinction to being one
of the commoner ornamental waterfowl. Continuing on the theme of Mallard-
type ducks, Blackbrook has a nice group of Chinese Spotbills. Passed over
by many in favour of the Indian nominate form, they are worth keeping for
their deep purple speculum and boldly stripped face markings. Other birds
in my neglected species category present in the collection include the
American Black Duck (not colourful and can be quarrelsome), Lesser Snow
Goose (nowadays usually passed over in favour of the more petite Ross's),
Greenland and Pacific White-fronted Geese (almost everybody keeps the
Lesser White-front).
A comprehensive collection of geese are displayed. The only absences
I noted were the Greater Snow Goose (has this subspecies disappeared from
UK collections due to neglect?), Kelp (nobody has ever kept a stock going)
and Aleutian Canada. Everything else seemed to be there, even the common
Greylag and Atlantic Canada Goose. The black Spur-winged Goose is
represented in the collection, as is the enchanting 'musky scented' Magpie
Goose. Other unusual species include the Comb Duck and a pair of the
impressive, but aggressive Flightless Steamer Duck. It is fashionable in
some avicultural circles to decry mutations; I do not subscribe to this, as
long as the original wild type of a species is not neglected. Mutations look
at their best with the normal form available for comparison. The only
mutation waterfowl I noted at Blackbrook were silver Mandarins, in company
with normal birds. A large group of Spotted Whistling Ducks bore witness
to breeding success, as did three of last year's Whistling Swan cygnets, still
with their parents and very much a family group. The Madagascar Teal,
established recently in aviculture via Jersey Zoo, also produced young in
2002.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.564936" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266314" page_num="135" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - BLACKBROOK ZOOLOGICAL PARK
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999147" page_id="56266314"  page_num="135" year="" vol="">
135
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.987283095238095" page_id="56266314"  page_num="135" year="" vol="">
In an account of this kind, it is difficult to avoid lists, and the cranes at
Blackbrook make an impressive one: Wattled, Common, East and West
African Crowned, Sarus, Demoiselle, Sandhill, White-naped, Stanley and
Black-necked - 10 of the world's 14 species. The Black-necked must be the
only ones in the UK; now that Whipsnade no longer displays a collection of
cranes, this must be the best collection on view in this country.
A good collection of pheasants continues my neglected species theme.
Berlioz's Silver Pheasant is on show, subtly different from the commonly
seen nominate form, most noticeably in the lacing on the female's breast.
Various kalij are represented, as is the once relatively abundant Hume's
Pheasant. This and other pheasant species may be building up their numbers
slowly after a few difficult years, occasioned by inappropriate transport
regulations. It was good to see Green and Sonnerat's Junglefowl as well as
the conservation sensitive Edwards' and Vietnamese Pheasants. The latter
share a well planted aviary with a small group of Scarlet Ibis. There are also
Blue, Brown and White Eared Pheasants, none of them as commonly kept
as they should be.
Minor specialisms at Blackbrook are pelicans (small flocks of several
species on open lake settings, where they look immaculate and do not smell
of fish as they can do in more restricted quarters), ibises (at least five species,
of which the Black-faced was on eggs) and storks. Hammerkops laid fertile
eggs last year and the only UK-bred Marabou, hatched in 1999 (see
Avicultural Magazine Vol.106, No.4, pp. 182-184), can be seen. White,
Painted and Maguari Storks are also on view.
Noticeable by their absence are parrots; outside the pets' comer the only
psittacines are a pair of Sun Conures. Parrots are a charismatic group that
form the backbone to many collections, so it was nice to see storks and
ibises being promoted for a change. Owls are represented by a tethered
European Eagle Owl (apparently well socialised to people), Snowy, Hawk,
Boobook, White-faced Scops, Great Grey and Ural Owls.
A pair of purpose-built lengthy aviaries house Great Blue and Ross's
Turacos, and a full-winged pair of Secretary Birds that used to live at Rode
have an aviary here. The enigmatic Guira Cuckoo has been imported recently
from South America, and a pair is on view, as is a pair of Australasian Piping
Crows.
All the above birds are housed outside. There is plenty of interest indoors
as well. The smaller tropical house comprises a single densely planted aviary
(viewed from a darkened corridor), which is occupied by Bronze-tailed
Peacock Pheasants, Black-chinned Fruit Doves and a Luzon Bleeding Heart.
The larger tropical house has aviaries along one side, with Blue and
Sheepmaker's Crowned Pigeons among other species. There are reptile
units along the opposite side and a long saltwater pool down the middle,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999386" page_id="56266315"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
136
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.856335" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266315" page_num="136" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - BLACKBROOK ZOOLOGICAL PARK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9860355" page_id="56266315"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
occupied by small tropical sharks and rays. The end opposite the entrance
is of glass, looking out on a pool aviary with Hottentot and Madagascar
Teal, which were due to be joined by a flock of Carmine Bee-eaters (held in
off-exhibit winter quarters) when the weather warmed up.
Mammals are sufficiently prominent to provide enough interest for the
non bird-minded visitor. In addition to the almost obligatory Meerkats,
there are some spectacular badger-sized Giant Marmots from the eastern
Asian steppes, five species of lemur in a purpose-built complex, Crested
Porcupines, Alpacas, Guanacos, Llamas, Bennett's and Parma Wallabies,
Dwarf Zebu cattle, Capybara and a Brazilian Tapir awaiting a mate. The
two last-named species share an enclosure with South American waterfowl.
A brief account like this (I have left a lot out) cannot do justice to this
important and well laid out collection. It is even more impressive when one
remembers the nearby Hillside Bird Oasis (formerly Hillside Ornamental
Fowl) now operates as a private breeding establishment for the Blackbrook
collection.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.858258" page_id="56266315"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.708033" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266315" page_num="136" year="" vol="">
GENEROUS DONATION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97199625" page_id="56266315"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
Following a visit to Chestnut Lodge, Cobham, West-Vlaamse Parraket
Club of Belgium, made a #70 (just over US$ 100) donation to The Avicultural
Society. The donation, for which the society is most grateful, was presented
to Raymond Sawyer by club President Carlo Mattheeuws.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.570745" page_id="56266315"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.922772" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266315" page_num="136" year="" vol="">
LIBRARY GOES ONLINE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.5121482" page_id="56266315"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
You can now search much of the Zoological Society of London library
catalogue via the zoo website:www.zsl.org The online catalogue provides
details of all the library's journals and more than 12,000 books. Details are
available of all books added since 1991 plus all books published before
1860. You can even check if a book is on the shelf or out on loan.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998673" page_id="56266316"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
137
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.994717666666667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266316" page_num="137" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
PHOTOGRAPHIC GUIDES TO THE BIRDS OF INDIA,
SOUTH-EAST ASIA AND INDONESIA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996946972972973" page_id="56266316"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
These three guides published recently by Christopher Helm (an imprint
of A &amp; C Black Publishers Ltd.) here in the UK are identification guides to
a wide selection of the easy-to-see species of these regions and although
intended primarily for birdwatchers and tourists, are sure to be of considerable
interest to aviculturists.
All three are fairly thick paperbacks that follow more or less the same
format: each starts with the usual introductory chapters, which include
descriptions of the different habitats within the regions and some of the best
places to watch birds; the main part of each guide though is the Systematic
Section (i.e. species guide), with two species per page, each species illustrated
with one or two colour photos. There is a brief text covering Description,
Voice and Habits, and a small distribution map, with the species' range shown
clearly in red (breeding) and/or blue (migratory/non-breeding), as well as a
written description of the distribution of each species.
A Photographic Guide to the Birds of India including Nepal, Sri Lanka,
The Maldives, Pakistan, Bangladesh &amp; Bhutan by Bikram Grewal, Bill
Harvey and Otto Pfister (ISBN 0-7136-6403-7), is just over 500 pages long
and includes some 800 species and distinct subspecies, illustrated with just
over 1,000 colour photos. Many of the species are familiar or once familiar
avicultural subjects. The bird trade from India up until 1991, when a total
ban was introduced, is touched upon. The authors estimate that between
1970-1976, 13 million birds were exported, mostly munias and parakeets.
Hunting, which was at its peak during the time of the British Raj, is also
touched upon, using as an example some of the record bags at Bharatpur,
where on November 12th 1938, during the visit of H. E. The Viceroy Lord
Linlithgow, 3,044 birds were shot in the morning and 1,229 in the afternoon,
a total for the day of 4,273 birds.
A Photographic Guide to the Birds of Southeast Asia including the
Philippines &amp; Borneo , text and photos by Morten Strange (ISBN 0-7136-
6402-9), 398 pages, covers mainland south-east Asia, the Philippines and
Borneo, and includes birds of Peninsular Malaysia, Thailand and Indochina,
as well as south China, Hong Kong and Taiwan. Six hundred and sixty-
eight species are included, illustrated with more than 700 colour photos. A
Photographic Guide to the Birds of Indonesia, with text and photos by Morten
Strange (ISBN 0-7136-6404-5), covers 686 species, illustrated with almost
700 colour photos.
Both contain fascinating collections of photographs. Many are of species
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998834" page_id="56266317"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
138
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.971687" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266317" page_num="138" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9975119" page_id="56266317"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
which are known in aviculture, or belong to families that are familiar within
aviculture, e. g. the pheasant family, pigeons and doves, parrots, bee-eaters,
kingfishers and rollers, hornbills, barbets, pittas, laughingthrushes and
munias; others are of species which are rare or unknown in aviculture. A
few of the photos are of captive birds, but most were taken in the wild; some
were photographed specially, this was especially true of those Indonesian
species found only in Nusa Tenggara (or the Lesser Sunda Islands, stretching
from Lombok to Tanimbar) and West Papua (formerly known as Irian Jaya).
All three guides are priced #19.99 in the UK. For more information you
can visit the A &amp; C Black website:www.acblack.com
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.440972">
Malcolm Ellis
</subsectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.984915" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56266317" page_num="138" year="" vol="">
SWAN KEEPER'S HANDBOOK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997580964285714" page_id="56266317"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
Swans are fascinating, regal, have a long association with man, and
needed a treatise devoted to them. Such a work has now been published...and
by a group of authors and photographers that have a long list of credits. The
principal author, G. R. Gardner, took over from his father as caretaker of
Lakeland's Lake Morton (a lakeside community in northern Florida), where
the current flock descended from a pair donated in 1957 by H. M. Queen
Elizabeth II. The information gathered, complemented by superb colour
photographs, provides an in-depth view of a bird with a long captive history.
In Europe Mute Swans have lived in close proximity to man for perhaps
1,000 years or so. Elsewhere their history is shorter but they are equally
popular. This may be because they are such large flighted birds, because
they have been regarded as portraying royalty and beauty, and/or because
they are such long-lived birds that usually mate for life. Whatever the reason
or reasons, the current work will provide the answers to any questions about
them that you may have.
The 15 chapters include descriptions of appearance, history in aviculture,
captive husbandry, reproduction, plants and flowers suitable for a display
pond, and a description of each of the swan species. The information is
complemented by photographs that often illustrate the matter being discussed.
In Chapter 5 (Diseases and Infections), for example, the authors describe
such problems as foot infections which are often associated with poor
environment and may appear in the form of "crusted blister-like vesicles or
nodules", as illustrated on plate 5.10; bumblefoot is illustrated on plates
5.11 and 5.12; while taking the temperature and blood pressure are illustrated
on plates 5.14 and 5.16.
I wholeheartedly recommend that if you are interested in these birds or
other aquatic birds that you acquire this book.
Swan Keeper&apos;s Handbook: a complete guide to the care of captive swans
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909697" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266318" page_num="139" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99908" page_id="56266318"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
139
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.861674" page_id="56266318"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
by G. R. Gardner, F. F. Funk, S. A..Bolin, R. W. Wilson and S. A, Bolin is
published by Krieger Publishing Company, PO. Box 9542, Melbourne, FL
32902, USA. Price #35.95 UK, $44.50 USA.
Berian A. L. Silva Moraton
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998648" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56266318" page_num="139" year="" vol="">
GREENFOODS AND SEEDS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994276862068965" page_id="56266318"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
In these days, when the emphasis is on style over substance, it is a real
pleasure to come across a reference work - Growing and Collecting Wild
and Cultivated Greenfoods and Seeds by Dave Coles - which avoids this
pitfall. Those who are familiar with the author's previous publications such
as Management of Laughing Thrushes in Captivity (reviewed in the
AviculturalMagazine Vol. 106, No.3, pp.129-130 (2000)) and the excellent
Culture and Collection of Livefood will be familiar with the style, namely
44 A4 pages of word-processed text in a limp plastic cover. To dwell on the
simple appearance and lack of colour and/or illustrations would be to entirely
miss the point. This publication (and each of its predecessors) is all about
useful content and this is packed with solid, reliable, practical and usable
information which can only be of benefit to serious birdkeepers, especially
those who wish to provide the best for their stock and who prefer natural
products to the processed additives and supplements which seem to be so
much in fashion.
It is divided into sections covering Flowering Plants, Trees and Shrubs,
Grasses, Dry Seeds, Greenfood and Sprouting Seeds, Grains and Pulses.
There are details on growing, harvesting, storing and feeding, as well as
many useful tips and warnings, all presented in a readable, concise style.
Although aimed primarily at a UK readership I am sure that most of the
principles will apply in other parts of the world, as many of the plants
mentioned are not native to the UK anyway. To get the most out of this
work it will be useful to have a decent guide to wild plants and there are
many titles recommended for further reading at the end of each section.
Until reading this work I was unaware of the potential dangers of pampas
grass, turacos' fondness for honeysuckle and the free food available in my
garden. Truly a unique publication, it has information to enable you to both
save money and improve the health of your birds and should find a place on
the bookself of all hands-on birdkeepers.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.8846308">
Growing and Collecting Wild and Cultivated Greenfood and Seeds by
Dave Coles is priced #10 in the UK and #13 overseas, both prices include
p&amp;p. It is available from: Dave Coles, PO. Box 4262, Goring, Reading
RG8 9ZQ,UK. Website:www.dcbooks.co.uk
Paul Boulden
</reference>
<page confidence="0.996035" page_id="56266319"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
140
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.994884" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266319" page_num="140" year="" vol="">
CD REVIEW
BRINGING THE FIELD GUIDE TO LIFE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998705921052631" page_id="56266319"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
In 1997 Pica Press published A Field Guide to Birds of The Gambia and
Senegal by Clive Barlow, Tim Wacher and Tony Disley, the definitive field
guide to the birds of Senegambia. Excellent though this is, as with other
field guides, one's appreciation for the birds it covers has been constrained
to a short, though informative text and attractive two-dimensional
illustrations.
For the armchair buff the concise text and illustrations help in conveying
a good idea of what the birds actually look like - and coupled with better
quality nature programmes on television and video these days sometimes
even the terrain in which the birds reside can be better appreciated. If
anything, the only real area of uncertainty lay with the transliteration of
song. For example, on p. 189, the Wattled Plover Vanellus senegallus is said
to have a repeated "ke-weep" alarm call, with other calls based on a rising,
shrill and screaming "peep-peep-peep". Now I have never heard a Wattled
Plover's calls either in the wild or in captivity, but I have heard those of the
Ringed Plover Charadrius hiaticula. In A Field Guide to the Birds of Britain
and Europe by Peterson, Mountford and Hollom (3rd Edition, Collins, 1979),
the Ringed Plover's calls are given as "a melodious too-li" or "coo-eep"
and the song is said to begin slowly, becoming a trilling repetition of the
phase "quitu-weeoo".
Obviously, the calls of both species are transliterated by the authors as
they believe they heard them, but it is extremely doubtful that I would have
transliterated the Ringed Plover's calls I have heard (which would have
been the same) identically to that of Peterson et al. (1979). And as familiar
as I am with the Ringed Plover's calls but not the Wattled Plover's am I to
deduce that both being plovers there is some similarity and, therefore, can
imagine how the calls of the Wattled Plover may really sound?
The Ringed Plover is a migrant to Senegal and is listed by Barlow et al.
(1997). Interestingly, there (p.186) its calls are described as "a fluty tee-lee
or tooeet with an upward inflection". Comparing this with Peterson et al.
(1979) it becomes immediately evident that only "too-li' and "tee-li" are
similar - but one call is described as "melodious" and the other as "fluty",
the latter with an "upward inflection". However, "melodious" and "fluty"
are abstract and do not necessarily mean the same! Clearly, the printed word
cannot convey the actual calls of the birds, only someone's personal
interpretation - with such interpretations varying in almost every different
field guide published.
Happily, the problem of transliteration has now been addressed by Clive
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.930601" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266320" page_num="141" year="" vol="">
CD REVIEW
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998692" page_id="56266320"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
141
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.995489810810811" page_id="56266320"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
Barlow. In collaboration with John Hammick and Pat Sellar, a set of three
CDs has been produced comprising of 265 species found in A Field Guide
to Birds of The Gambia and Senegal. Included are 13 pigeons and doves, 10
cuckoos and coucals, eight bee-eaters, seven kingfishers, nine flycatchers,
12 sunbirds, seven starlings and a wide selection of weavers, bishops and
waxbills. A comprehensive collection of all parasitic Vidua spp. and their
estrildid hosts possibly present in Senegambia are incorporated, including
the previously unrecorded Mali Firefinch or Fonio Indigobird V.
camerunensis and an extended repertoire of the Mali Firefinch Lagonosticta
virata itself.
So, now bird lovers are able to peruse the field guide (which lists over
660 species) while at the same time listening to the actual calls of almost
half the birds of the Senegambia region - and all in the comfort of one's own
home! This is the closest one can get to reality without venturing out into
the field.
The species order of the CDs follows that in the field guide and an
accompanying booklet which provides the corresponding page and plate
numbers of the field guide, allows one to easily marry up the bird with the
correct call. The only niggle I have, and it is a very minor one, is that one
could be forgiven for misidentifying a bird's call on one track with that of
the preceding one as only a short silence separates each track. However, if
one has a track number display on their CD player this alleviates the problem
as it means one can locate a species' call immediately.
The recordings are of an excellent professional quality. At times other
species are evident in the background but this in no way distracts from the
calls of the targeted species. Indeed, it gives a greater feeling of the
surroundings in which the recording was made.
Whether one is seriously interested in ornithology, armchair birding or
aviculture, Clive Barlow and his sound recording colleagues have
undoubtably brought the field guide to an entirely new level - one which
future authors and their publishers will have to emulate.
The 3-CD set Bird Song of The Gambia &amp; Senegal - an aid to
identification is available from: Mandarin Productions,Little Merley, Merley
House Lane, Wimbome, Dorset BH21 3AA, UK. Price #24.99 per set plus
recorded delivery #2.25 or special delivery #5.00 in UK. Add #5.00 for
postage to other EU countries or #6.00 for postage to the USA and the rest
of the world. Website:www.mandarinproductions.com.uk
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.384961">
Ian Hinze
</subsectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998732" page_id="56266336"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
142
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.978999" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266336" page_num="142" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
BARBET BRED IN UK AND USA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.992506" page_id="56266336"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
The Bearded Barbet Lybius dubius has been bred at Paradise Wildlife
Park, Broxboume, Herts. Two chicks hatched, one of which died after 10
days, the other was reared successfully by the parents and left the nest on
July 1st 2003. In a forthcoming issue of the magazine, Susan Congdon will
describe how in 2002, three chicks were raised at Disney's Animal Kingdom,
Florida, one was fledged in 2001 and, in 1999, two eggs were artificially
incubated and the chicks were hand-reared there.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.807773" page_id="56266336"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.512798" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266336" page_num="142" year="" vol="">
FROGMOUTH BRED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9347315" page_id="56266336"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
A Tawny Frogmouth Podargus strigoides has been bred at Paultons Park,
near Romsey, Hants., believed to be one of only three UK collections with
this species. Removed from the nest when a day old, it was hand-reared,
following concern after the second egg that the parents were incubating
disappeared. By the time you read this magazine, the bird will be part of a
breeding programme at Audubon Zoo, New Orleans, USA.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.9117557" page_id="56266336"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
* * *
WHO WAS PESQUET?
Can you help? Michael Watkins co-author, with Bo Beolens, of Whose
Bird? Men and Women Commemorated in the Common Names of Birds (A
&amp; C Black, 2003) asks, who was Pesquet, after whom Pesquet's Parrot
Psittrichas fulgidus is named?
* * *
COULD BE TWO SEPARATE SPECIES
Examination of DNAof the Asian and European populations of the Azure-
winged Magpie Cyanopica cyana has found that there is a relatively deep
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.967124666666667" page_id="56266336"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
genetic divergence between the two. It has been recommended that the two
populations could be treated as separate species, with the Asian population
remaining as C. cyana and the European population becoming C. cooki with
the suggested name of Iberian Magpie.
Fossilised remains said to be more than 44,000 years old, discovered
recently in a cave in Gibraltar, rule out the theory that the species was
introduced to the Iberian Peninsular in the sixteenth century by Portuguese
sailors or brought to Spain by early traders with China and subsequently
became established in south-west Europe.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700236" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266337" page_num="143" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998357" page_id="56266337"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
143
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995323" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266337" page_num="143" year="" vol="">
SECRETARY'S SUCCESS WITH SIBIAS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990655928571429" page_id="56266337"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
New Hon, Secretary and Treasurer Paul Boulden's pair of Black-headed
Sibias Heterophasia desgodinsi has this year successfully reared four young,
having failed to rear any of the seven chicks hatched last year. The pair
occupy the same 12ft x 6ft x 7ft (approx. 3.6m x 1.8m x 2.1m) aviary as last
year but without the other occupants, pairs of Pekin Robins Leiothrix lutea ,
Chinese Hawfinches Coccothraustes migratorius, Crested Bronzewing
Pigeons Ocyphaps lophotes and a California Quail Lophortyx californica
which, although no antagonism had been noticed, are now housed elsewhere.
From the first nest this year a single chick was reared, with a further three
being reared from the second nest. Every chick hatched was reared to
maturity. The chick from the first nest was left with the adults whilst the
second brood of young was being reared. Paul puts the reason for his success
this year down to the lack of competition for livefood - large quantities of
waxworms were provided every two hours - and improved weather.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.8768682" page_id="56266337"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
* * *
UPDATED BREEDING REGISTER
Samples from Dave Coles 5 eagerly awaited updated First Breeding
Records For Birds Reared To Independence Under Controlled Conditions
In The United Kingdom, which now contains some 2,000 entries, can be
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.741295875" page_id="56266337"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
viewed on his new website:www.dcbooks .co .uk Each sample page has an
update page in order to keep the information as current as possible. Copies
of the above publication (price #10 in UK, #13 overseas, including p &amp; p)
can be ordered through the website, as can copies of his other publications:
The Management of Laughing Thrushes in Captivity; The Management of
Pekin Robin and Silver-eared Mesia in Captivity; Cultivating and Collecting
Livefood; Growing and Collecting Wild and Cultivated Greenfoods and
Seeds.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.44198" page_id="56266337"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.763884" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266337" page_num="143" year="" vol="">
PARENT-REARED TOCO TOUCANS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996091" page_id="56266337"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
Here in the UK this year, at least five Toco Toucans Ramphastos toco
have been successfully parent-reared. Two were raised at Leeds Castle
aviaries, near Maidstone, Kent, and three at London Zoo. The latter emerged
in late July, after an incubation period of 17-18 days and a period of 50 days
within the confines of the nest. Black-necked Aracaris Pteroglossus aracari
have successfully reared two young at London Zoo, Abdim's Storks Ciconia
abdimii have bred again after a period of inactivity and immediately prior to
this magazine going to the printer, Sun Bitterns Eurypyga helias had just
hatched a chick. Fifty-two Whipsnade-bred Corncrakes Crex crex were
released in Cambridgeshire.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999594" page_id="56266338"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
144
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.779519333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266338" page_num="144" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
SUCCESS WITH GREEN ARACARI
Avicultural Society member Chris lies has achieved the UK's first
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.7809106" page_id="56266338"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
breeding of the Green Aracari Pteroglossus viridis. His adult pair which he
bought last year, reared five chicks to independence from two clutches. More
about Chris's achievements - this year he has also bred the Rufous
Laughingthrush Garrulax poecilorhynchus and Azure-winged Magpie
Cyanopica cyana - can be found on his website:www.birdtrek.co.uk
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.296208" page_id="56266338"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.394053" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266338" page_num="144" year="" vol="">
DESERT SUCCESSES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.859222923076923" page_id="56266338"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
In International Zoo News Vol.50, No.5, pp.276-279 (2003), Simon
Bruslund Jensen and Sven Hammer describe how in 2002 chicks of both the
Greater Bird of Paradise Paradisaea apoda and King Bird of Paradise
Cicinnurus regius were successfully hand-reared in the bird nursery of A1
Wabra Wildlife Preservation, owned by Sheikh Saoud Bin Mohammed Bin
Ali A1 Thani, in Qatar. Much new data was collected and will be included
in articles currently in preparation, which may function as protocols for the
artificial rearing of these two species, which require significantly different
husbandry.
A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation also achieved the first ever captive
breeding of the Flamed Bowerbird Sericulus aureus ardens. The single egg
was artificially incubated and the chick, which was covered in silvery-grey
down, was hand-reared.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.844004" page_id="56266338"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.903625" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266338" page_num="144" year="" vol="">
CONCERN FOR ABBOTT'S STARLING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9762045625" page_id="56266338"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
The African Bird Club Conservation Fund has given #720 (approx.US$
1,000) to Nickson Otieno of the National Museums of Kenya Ornithology
Department to survey the population size and density of Abbott's Starling
Pholia ( Cinnyricinclus)femoralis in the Kikuyu Escarpment Forest Reserve,
and to identify the species' habitat preferences and breeding requirements.
It is also hoped to determine the patterns and intensity of logging in the
forest, and the overall effect of this on the starling population.
Abbott's Starling is a little-known, rare East African endemic that is
restricted to the canopy of highland forest at altitudes of l,800m-2,600m
(approx. 5,900ft-8,500ft) in central Kenya and north-eastern Tanzania. Its
tiny population is thought to be declining throughout its range, due mainly
to human activities that have led to the loss and degradation of much of its
habitat. In the same issue of the Bulletin of the African Bird Club Vol.10,
No.2, pp. 125-126, R. J. Dowsett, P.S.M. Berry and D. Foot report the
unexpected discovery of Sharpe's Starling Cinnyricinclus {Pholia) sharpii
in north-eastern Zambia. It is an extension of its range southwards.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995624" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266339" page_num="" year="" vol="">
LAKE BOGORIA WORKSHOP
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996849621621622" page_id="56266339"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
A workshop on Ecosystem Health, an introduction to this new discipline
which links ecology with medicine, was held in July at Lake Bogoria, Kenya.
It was the first of a number to be funded by the Darwin Initiative, part of the
UK's response to the Convention on Biodiversity. The workshop was
organised by Dr David Harper and co-tutor Prof. John E. Cooper. Lectures
were also given by John's wife Margaret, a lawyer with extensive experience
of legislation relating to conservation, who along with David's wife Maureen,
a teacher, also participated in educational extension work in local schools.
In keeping with the aim of transferring knowledge and technology from
the UK to Kenya, all 29 workshop participants were Kenyans, from a wide
range of backgrounds. There were ecologists, veterinarians, museum
personnel, students and staff from Lake Bogoria and other protected areas.
Robert Llewellyn-Smith, African Programme Manager, Earthwatch Institute
(Europe), which administers the Darwin Initiative for the British Government,
was also actively involved in the workshop.
They heard lectures and participated in discussions regarding the
interactions between natural systems and human activity. The aim being to
seek valid parameters and measures of the health of ecosystems. The
emphasis was on aquatic environments, with in this instance particular
emphasis on Lake Bogoria. The Lesser Flamingo Phoeniconaias minor
provided a focus: there appears to have been a dramatic increase in mortality
of this species in recent years and this may be an indication of changing
ecosystems. The participants were taught specialised techniques for the
pathological examination of flamingos and protocols were drawn up to assist
future researchers. They also looked at aquatic ecosystems, both alkaline
(soda) lake and freshwater, and were instructed in methods of assessing the
health of these, by, for example, sampling and counting invertebrates.
The workshop proved very successful and represented a landmark in the
development of ecosystem health as a bona fide discipline. It offered young
Kenyans the opportunity to learn how to tackle the question of reconciling
conservation of biodiversity with increasing human activity in a challenging
environment. The fact that everyone participating in the workshop stayed
in tents or in a local inn, meant they were able to build links with the local
community whose history, traditions and future are intimately interwoven
with Lake Bogoria, its flamingos, its hot springs and its magnificent scenery.
Further information about the workshop and plans for future activities,
funded by the Darwin Initiative, are available from: Dr David Harper, Senior
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.978396">
Lecturer in Ecology, Department of Biology, University of Leicester LEI
7RH, UK. E-mail: dmh@le.ac.uk or Prof. John E. Cooper, School of
Veterinary Medicine, Faculty of Medical Sciences, The University of the
West Indies, St. Augustine, Trinidad and Tobago. E-mail:NGAGI@vetaid.net
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9580715" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266340" page_num="" year="" vol="">
SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION LIBRARIES
CONTENTS
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.57528" page_id="56266340"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society.97
Notes on a visit to Pakistan
by Philip Schofield.98
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.602398727272727" page_id="56266340"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Captive breeding of the White-bellied Bustard Eupodotis
senegalensis at Jacksonville Zoological Garden
by Allison S. Cox. 107
The capture of eight Montserrat Orioles and their subsequent
establishment and breeding at Jersey Zoo
by Andrew Owen.116
A history of the genus Picathartes in captivity, 1948-2002
by Marvin L. Jones. 125
The Avicultural Magazine and me: a symbiosis
by Derek Goodwin. 130
The society's visit to Blackbrook Zoological Park
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.4714075" page_id="56266340"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Philip Schofield. 133
Book Reviews
Photographic Guides to the Birds of India, South-east Asia and
Indonesia.
Swan Keeper's Handbook
Greenfoods and Seeds.
CD Review
Bringing the Field Guide to Life. 140
News &amp; Views. 142
138
139
3 9088 01769 6519
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</figure>
</algorithms>
