<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.855959857142857" page_id="56265668"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
QL #
un\
a^AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 108
No. 3
2002
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="method" page_id="56265669" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991764" page_id="56265669"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2002 as for 2001: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.614284" genericHeader="method" page_id="56265669" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.914342" page_id="56265669"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, P.O. BOX 47, EDENBRIDGE, KENT TN8 7WP, ENGLAND.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TNI 3 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail:lee.palm@virgin.net
Enquiries regarding membership should be sent to:
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.7927695" page_id="56265669"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE MEMBERSHIP SECRETARY, Stewart Pyper, 21, Primrose Hill,
Nunney, Frome, Somerset BA11 4NP.
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.99669025" page_id="56265669"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998437" genericHeader="method" page_id="56265669" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.9972025">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.835601" genericHeader="method" page_id="56265670" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.524628" page_id="56265670"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 108 - No, 3 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2002
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7609285" genericHeader="method" page_id="56265670" page_num="" year="" vol="">
WORLD OF BIRDS REVIEW 2001/2002
by Isabel Wentzel
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.965748766666667" page_id="56265670"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The 2001/2002 breeding season at the World of Birds Wildlife Sanctuary
and Monkey Park, Cape Town, South Africa, proved to be an exciting one,
with young being produced by numerous species which had never bred here
before.
We bred for the first time two Mountain Caracaras Phalcoboenus
megalopterus , from the first clutch of eggs from a relatively young pair,
three Cape Eagle Owls Bubo capensis, eight Giant Wood-Rails Aramides
ypecaha, four European White Storks Ciconia ciconia , one Nicobar Pigeon
Caloenas nicobarica and one Dumonti's Myna Mi no dumontii.
Other species bred included three Great Homed Owls B. virginianus ,
three Bengal Eagle Owls B. bubo bengalensis, three Spotted Eagle Owls B.
africanus , two African Bam Owls Tyto alba , one African Goshawk Accipiter
tachiro , one Rock Kestrel Falco tinnunculus, four Jackal Buzzards Buteo
rufofuscus and two Yellow-billed Kites Milvus mi grans. Pale Chanting
Goshawks Melierax canorus and Booted Eagles Hieraaetus pennatus had
eggs but these were infertile, as were those of the Turkey Vultures Cathartes
aura. The egg laid by the adult female Black or Verreaux's Eagle Aquila
verreauxii was also infertile, probably due to the fact that she is paired with
a new younger male, the previous male having been imprinted.
Two female Marabou Leptoptilos crumeniferus which have laid eggs in
previous years have been paired with young males acquired from
Johannesburg Zoo. Maybe next breeding season we can look forward to
fertile eggs. In the 75m (approx. 250ft) long enclosure housing storks, herons,
spoonbills, ibises and egrets, a pair of Saddle-billed Storks Ephippiorhynchus
senegalensis built a huge nest, but failed to produce eggs. We are looking
forward to the pair's next attempt. Eleven Spoonbills Platalea alba , four
Yellow-billed Egrets Egretta intermedia , 20 Little Egrets E. garzetta and 25
Cattle Egrets Bubulcus ibis were produced in The Heronry. We hand-reared
three Southern Bald Ibis Geronticus calvus , because their parents failed to
rear them and also raised 30 Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999551" page_id="56265671"  page_num="98" year="" vol="">
98
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.741492" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265671" page_num="98" year="" vol="">
WENTZEL - WORLD OF BIRDS REVIEW 2001/2002
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.891606133333333" page_id="56265671"  page_num="98" year="" vol="">
Three Blue Cranes Anthropoides paradiseus were raised successfully,
two of which were hand-reared. The park had its first Double-wattled
Cassowary Casuarius casuarius eggs, laid by a new female which was
obtained recently for our males. The smaller of the two males took an
immediate liking to the female, but seemed to be intimidated by her size
and the eggs were infertile. We have obtained a second young female,
bringing our cassowary population to four. The Greater Rheas Rhea
americana produced fertile eggs, but the chicks failed to survive. All the
eggs laid by the Emus Dromaius novaehollandiae were infertile. Two pairs
of Ostriches Struthio camelus reared seven chicks.
Thirty Carolina Wood Ducks Aix sponsa, 40 Mandarin Ducks A.
galericulata, 15 Yellow-billed Ducks Anas undulata, five Fulvous Whistling
Ducks Dendrocygna bicolor , one Hawaiian Goose Branta sandvicensis , one
Ruddy Shelduck Tadorna ferruginea and seven Mute Swans Cygnus olor
were raised in the waterfowl complex.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.831322142857143" page_id="56265671"  page_num="98" year="" vol="">
Six African Penguins Spheniscus demersus and one Brown Pelican
Pelecanus occidentalis were reared successfully by their parents.
Three Lesser Sulphur-crested Cockatoos Cacatua sulphurea and three
Goffin's Cockatoos G. goffini were reared, as well as seven Black-headed
Conures Nandayus nenday , six Green-cheeked Conures Pyrrhura molinae,
two Pale-headed Rosellas Platycerus adscitus, 10 Quaker or Monk Parrakeets
Myiopsitta monachus, four Indian Ring-necked Parrakeets Psittacula krameri
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.910175363636364" page_id="56265671"  page_num="98" year="" vol="">
manillensis, seven Lilian's or Nyasa Lovebirds Agapornis lilianae and five
Rosy- or Peach-faced Lovebirds A. roseicollis.
Two pairs of Yellow-billed Hornbills Tockus leucomelas produced eggs,
one clutch was infertile and the second pair hatched the eggs but failed to
rear the chicks. Four Von der Decken's Hombill T. deckeni were successfully
hand-reared. The arrival of a pair of Black-and-white-casqued Hornbills
Bycanistes subcylindricus brought our hornbill collection to eight species.
As our Nicobar Pigeons were new to the collection, a highlight of the
breeding season was to succeed in hatching and rearing one, after the previous
clutch had been destroyed during a storm. Other pigeons and doves bred
included eight Speckled or Rock Pigeons Columba guinea , five Crested
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.862396777777778">
Pigeons Ocyphaps lophotes, eight Laughing Doves Streptopelia senegalensis ,
four Red-eyed Doves S. semitorquata, five Cape Turtle Doves S. capensis,
one Pygmy Dove Columbina minuta, two Green-winged Doves Chalcophaps
indica, four Lemon or Cinnamon Doves Aplopelia larvata and one Diamond
Dove Geopelia cuneata.
Twelve Masked Plovers Vanellus miles were hatched and reared, as well
as six Water Dikkops Burhinus vermiculatus and two Black-winged Stilts
Himantopus himantopus. Two Silver Lophura nycthemera, one Ring-necked
Phasianus colchicus, two Golden Chrysolophus pictus and two White-crested
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.64076" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265672" page_num="99" year="" vol="">
WENTZEL - WORLD OF BIRDS REVIEW 2001/2002
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.929415" page_id="56265672"  page_num="99" year="" vol="">
99
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.764096551724138" page_id="56265672"  page_num="99" year="" vol="">
Kalji Pheasant L. leucomelanos chicks fledged, as did five Helmeted
Guineafowl Numida meleagris, 12 Indian Peafowl Pavo cristatus and 18
Chinese Painted Quail Coturnix chinensis.
Five Red Bishops Euplectes orix, 15 Zebra Finches Taeniopygia guttata,
six Java Sparrows Padda oryzivora, three Olive Thrushes Turdus olivaceus,
four Asian Glossy Starlings Aplonis panayensis, four Red-winged Starlings
Onychognathus morio and one White-tailed Jay Cyanocorax mystacalis were
reared successfully.
Numerous new enclosures were built during the past year, including
many aviaries urgently needed for the growing parrot population. Most of
the parrots used to be pets and there is increasing pressure to accommodate
all of these. Five more aviaries were completed to house breeding pairs of
birds of prey. A suitable enclosure is being built to house a tiny Eurasian
Scops Owl Otus scops brought to the sanctuary after landing on a container
ship near the Canary Islands. It will also house the mate we hope to find for
it.
Mammals bred included five Pygmy Marmosets Cebuella pygmaea, 16
Common Marmosets Callithrix jacchus, three Black Tufted-eared Marmosets
Penicillata kuhli , four Cotton-top Tamarins Saguinus oedipus, five Common
Squirrel Monkeys Saimiri sciureus and two Dama Wallabies Macropus
eugenii. A number of smaller enclosures have been added to house pairs of
marmosets and tamarins, as well as enclosures for Suricates Suricata
suricatta , Ground Squirrels Xerus inaurus , Porcupines Hystrix africaeaustralis
and Dama Wallabies. A pair of Mongoose Lemurs Lemur mongoz was moved
to a new, larger enclosure and a second baboon enclosure was extended to
separate the young Chacma Papio ursinus and Yellow Baboons P.
cynocephalus.
Staff at the sanctuary are looking forward to the next breeding season
and lots more happenings in the near future.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.94729325">
Isabel Wentzel is Head Curator of Birds and Animals at World of Birds
Wildlife Sanctuary and Monkey Park, Valley Road, Hout Bay, Cape Town
7806, South Africa . Tel:+27 +21 790 2730/Fax:+27 +21 790 4839/E -
mail:worldofbirds@mweb. co.za
</reference>
<page confidence="0.976436" page_id="56265673"  page_num="100" year="" vol="">
100
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.950932" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265673" page_num="100" year="" vol="">
SOME FAMOUS AVICTJLTURISTS I HAVE KNOWN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990256282051282" page_id="56265673"  page_num="100" year="" vol="">
by R. C. J. Sawyer
At the Centenary Celebrations held in September 1994 at Bristol Zoo
Gardens, I spoke about some of the famous aviculturists who were around
when I joined the Avicultural Society in 1949. A written account of my talk
was published in th &amp; Avicultural Magazine Vol.100, No.4, pp. 149-154, and
the following notes amount to a continuation of that. Most of the following
aviculturists, the majority of whom sadly are no longer with us, were
members of the society, many for a great number of years, usually until the
time of their death.
I well remember Cecil Webb, who was Curator of Mammals and Birds
at London Zoo, before leaving in 1951 and the following year becoming
Superintendent of Dublin Zoo. He was an outstanding man who had collected
in many countries, but especially in Africa. He always brought back his
birds, softbills mainly such as robin-chats Cossypha spp., in excellent
condition. In 1948, he brought back to London Zoo the first Grey-necked
Picathartes Picathartes oreas ever kept in captivity. The expedition to what
was then the British Cameroons was the last of over 20 expeditions he made
and which were described by him in A Wanderer in the Wind , The Odyssey
of an Animal Collector (Hutchinson, 1953), in the foreword of which he
thanked the Editor of the Avicultural Magazine for permission to draw freely
from articles about these expeditions which he had written for the magazine.
By the time I met him he had finished collecting and later moved to Kenya,
where he died in 1964. In Memoriam - Cecil Stanley Webb by Geoffrey
Vevers, illustrated by a photo of Cecil Webb, was published in the Avicultural
Magazine Vol.70, No.5, pp. 173-176.
Cecil Webb was followed as Curator of Birds by John Yealland and,
during his time as curator, it seemed that each issue of the magazine included
his London Zoo Notes, with the latest news about the zoo's bird collection.
In those days, when people mentioned "The Zoo", they meant the London
Zoo. John grew up with birds, his father having been in charge of the
collection of the Marquess of Tavistock (Hon. Editor of the magazine 1924
and 1925 and later 12th Duke of Bedford), which was housed in aviaries in
the garden of the Yealland family home at B instead on the Isle of Wight. He
went to work at London Zoo when he was 17, but when his father died in
1922, John left the zoo to take charge of the Duke of Bedford's collection
which was then at Warblington, Hants., and later was moved to Rye in Sussex
and then Haywards Heath.
At the outbreak of the Second World War John was in Belgium, just
outside Brussels, looking after the private collection of Dr J. M. Derscheid.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.527097" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265674" page_num="101" year="" vol="">
SAWYER - FAMOUS AVICULTURISTS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999255" page_id="56265674"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
101
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998160904761905" page_id="56265674"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
John spent 1946 at Slimbridge helping Peter Scott start the Wildfowl Trust.
The following year he teamed up with Gerald Durrell and in December
1947 they sailed from Liverpool on an animal collecting expedition to the
Cameroons, which was later the subject of Durrell's best selling book The
Overloaded Ark (Faber &amp; Faber, 1953). John travelled to Hawaii in 1950
and brought back the first Hawaiian Geese or Nene Branta sandvicensis ,
which were the founders of the Wildfowl Trust's breeding programme which
saved this species from extinction - surely aviculture's greatest success story.
In 1951 John returned to London Zoo, this time as Curator of Birds. He was
a great friend and we used to meet at the zoo at least once a week. He was
extremely popular and well liked and respected.
John retired from the zoo in 1969. He returned to the Isle of Wight and
in 1974 succeeded Phyllis Barclay-Smith as Hon. Editor of the Avicultural
Magazine, which he edited until the end of 1978. John died in January
1983. Peter Olney succeeded John as Curator of Birds at London Zoo.
It was a great privilege to have met Wilfred Frost, who in my early days
was already old. His speciality was birds from the Far East. Every year he
used to bring back a collection usually from New Guinea or other islands
out that way. He brought back many birds of paradise, lories, parrakeets
and Palm Cockatoos Probosciger aterrimus. He continued to bring back
shipments even when he was in his 80's. By then his eyesight was failing
and in order to check that a bird had enough water he would put a finger into
the pot. I bought a male Greater Bird of Paradise Paradisaea apoda from
him and he also had some King Birds of Paradise Cicinnurus regius and
Wilson's Diphyllodes respublica. He always brought back his collections
by boat, looking after them himself during the voyage, and usually landed
them in good condition. Towards the end of 1957, he sailed for Borneo on
what would have been his 54th expedition had he not died shortly afterwards.
He was 82.
Frost was one of the last collectors to bring back his birds by boat. In the
early 1950s birds were starting to be sent by air. A box of hummingbirds
from a dealer named Randau in Recife, Brazil, cost me #48 (approx. US$70)
for a dozen (12) birds, which included the cost of the air freight. At that
time, Heathrow Airport had only some former army huts in which the
paperwork was processed and from which the birds were collected.
I also received some lovely hummingbirds in the 1950s from Charles
Cordier, the famous collector who had worked for Jean Delacour. Cordier
spent a great many years collecting birds in Central and South America. In
1942 he had sent a massive collection to the Bronx Zoo, New York, when
Jean was the Director. It included 18 Resplendent Quetzals Pharomachrus
mocirino, tanagers, manakins, Bare-necked Umbreilabirds Cephalopterus
glabricollis and 11 different species of hummingbirds. Jean wrote in 1943
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999148" page_id="56265675"  page_num="102" year="" vol="">
102
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.859063" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265675" page_num="102" year="" vol="">
SAWYER - FAMOUS AVICULTURISTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.933174904761905" page_id="56265675"  page_num="102" year="" vol="">
about the collection. The hummingbirds Cordier sent me arrived beautifully
packed and in good condition. Such collectors have long gone and nowadays
many birds appear to have been trapped and sent over by air almost
immediately. Hummingbirds and tanagers were probably amongst the first
birds sent by air to Europe.
Sydney Porter was a great friend, who due to his asthma used to go
abroad each winter to enjoy a warmer climate and visited fellow aviculturists
and collected a few birds. Singapore was a favourite destination and he also
visited East and South Africa, Australia, New Zealand and California. Sydney
maintained a fine collection of birds in his aviaries at Derby and at various
times owned eight different species of pitta. Other birds he kept included
Azure-winged Magpies Cyanopica cyanus and Keas Nestor notabilis , a
species for which he received the society's medal for the first breeding in
1946. He was an important contributor who wrote numerous articles for the
magazine, was very generous to zoos and to Nottingham University to which
he left his large collection of monographs when he died in January 1958, at
the early age of 58.
David Roberts sent some lovely birds from Kenya. I had some of the
earliest birds sent by him, which he handled in a very professional way,
packing them in magnificent travelling boxes, often with foam padded roofs.
The first collections included Bristle-crowned Onychognathus salvadorii
and Magpie Starlings Speculipastor bicolor , d'Arnaud's Trachyphonus
darnaudii and Yellow-billed Barbets Trachyphonus or Trachylaemus
purpuratus. Black-billed Weavers Place us melanogaster , Red-headed
Bluebills Spermophaga ruficapilla, Blacksmith Vanellus armatus and Spur-
winged Plovers V. spinosus and Crowned Lapwings V coronatus. These
went to London Zoo and were distributed from there. He sent over many
waterbirds, including African Jaganas Actophilomis africanus and flamingos
Phoenicopterus &amp; Phoeniconaias spp.
David died at a very early age, leaving a widow and six young children.
Betty, his widow, continued exporting birds until the Kenya Government
ban. She continues to live at Lake Baringo, where she has a campsite and
tourist accommodation which are very popular, especially with birdwatchers.
Birds such as the Yellow-billed Barbets, Black-billed Weavers and Red-
headed Bluebills sent over by David Roberts Wildlife, were collected by
Tim and Jane Bamley, who farmed on the Cherangani Hills in western Kenya,
and who for several years supplied birds to David Roberts, before later trading
on their own account as T. &amp; J. Barnley. They sent over lovely collections
which also included Grey-crowned Negro Finches Nigrita canicapilla, Oriole
Finches Linurgus olivaceus, several species of sunbird, wonderful robin chats
including the Blue-shouldered Cossypha cyanocampter , along with Splendid
Starlings Lamprotornis splendidus and Ross's Musophaga rossae and White-
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.527114" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265676" page_num="103" year="" vol="">
SAWYER - FAMOUS AVICULTURISTS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999677" page_id="56265676"  page_num="103" year="" vol="">
103
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99389" page_id="56265676"  page_num="103" year="" vol="">
crested Turacos Tauraco leucolophus, which they had hand-reared from
nestlings. The Little Stints Calidris minuta they sent me were greatly
admired. I showed a pair at the National Exhibition of Cage &amp; Aviary Birds
in 1975 and 1977 at Alexandra Palace and both times the pair was awarded
the special for Best Foreign Bird Artistically and Suitably Staged for the C.
T. Maxwell Memorial Shield.
Tim Barnley died at a relatively early age, following a back operation
which went badly wrong. His widow, Jane, and youngest daughter Julia,
continue to live in the farmhouse. They too have a campsite and
accommodation, and cater mainly for birdwatchers wishing to see the rich
variety of birds which inhabit that part of Kenya, close to Mt Elgon and the
border with Uganda.
Lena Scamell and her husband Kenneth were great supporters of the
society. I knew them from my early days when they lived in Dulwich before
moving to Newdigate in Surrey, where Lena had incredible success breeding
softbills. She was awarded 15 first breeding medals by the Avicultural
Society. Her most outstanding successes were breeding for the first time
the Malachite Sunbird Nectarinia famosa (1964) and Sparkling Violetear
Colibri coruscans (1967). Other notable first breedings included the Daurian
Redstart Phoenicurus auroreus. Common Rubythroat Luscinia calliope and
Himalayan Rubythroat L. pectoralis. Lena also bred the Festive or Red-
necked Tanager Tangara cyanocephala though this was not the first breeding.
The Scamell's garden is best described as having been in a wood with
fairly small aviaries designed with breeding in mind. Lena was quite a large
person and when she walked through the long and narrow aviaries, the birds
had to fly over her shoulders to get past her; but what success she achieved
in them, she even got a Scarlet Cock-of-the-Rock Rupicola peruviana chick
to 23 days before it died. To have bred this species would have been her
crowning glory. It was to her that Dave Coles dedicated his First Breeding
Records of Birds Reared to Independence Under Controlled Conditions in
the United Kingdom.
She was also a very successful exhibitor and on several occasions took
the Best Foreign Bird award at the National Exhibition of Cage &amp; Aviary
Birds at both Olympia and Alexandra Palace. In 1963 her pair of Lesser
Niltavas Niltava macgrigoriae went on to become Supreme Winner of the
Haddon Silver Challenge Trophy which I judged. She proved that it is
possible to both breed and show birds successfully.
In 1970, Lena and Kenneth Scamell moved to Cornwall, taking only
part of the bird collection with them. By then they were not in the best of
health and Lena was not so successful in Cornwall, though while there she
did achieve the first breeding of the beautiful Silverbird Empidornis
semipartitus , a species of flycatcher from eastern Africa, that had been sent
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999653" page_id="56265677"  page_num="104" year="" vol="">
104
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.825907" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265677" page_num="104" year="" vol="">
SAWYER - FAMOUS AVICULTURISTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987447571428571" page_id="56265677"  page_num="104" year="" vol="">
over by Tim and Jane Barnley. It is a species I have also had here at Cobham.
Kenneth Scamell, who worked for the Birds Eye company and had been
awarded the OBE (Order of the British Empire), gave great support to his
wife.
Claude Payne is a great friend of mine who lives in Warwickshire. He
has lovely aviaries in his garden with lots of parrakeets, including the Derbyan
Psittacula derby ana, and also has cranes. He was awarded the society's
medal for the first breeding of the Knysna Turaco T. corythaix, Spotted
Towhee Pipilo erythrophthalmus maculatus and Evening Grosbeak
Coccothraustes vespertinus. He used to keep British birds and was the legal
consultant to the NCA (National Council of Aviculture).
Reg Partridge had an enormous collection even before the Second World
War. He owned a farm near Evesham, Worcestershire and was also a dealer,
who sent collectors to Australia. Tom Goodwin brought back bowerbirds,
but when the war broke out, it became difficult to dispose of birds. People
brought their birds to Mr Ezra and wanted to give them to him in the belief
that he would be able to feed them; however, he was in the same position.
After the war Reg built up perhaps the best collection of Australian parrakeets
that there has been in this country. A successful breeder, he also kept various
other parrots, including lutino and blue Ring-necks P. krameri and helped
establish albino Cockatiels Leptolophus hollandicus in this country. Although
he never kept many softbills, he succeeded in being first in the UK to breed
the Magpie Starling Speculipastor bicolor, Golden-crested Mynah
Ampeliceps coronatus and Scrub Jay Aphelocoma coerulescens. Reg was a
gentleman dealer and money was not an essential part of his dealings. He
enjoyed handling and dealing with birds - that was his life.
Donald Risdon was a staunch supporter of the society who over a 50
year period contributed numerous articles to the magazine. I met him first
when he was General Manager of Dudley Zoo, before he and his wife Betty
founded the Tropical Bird Gardens at Rode, which they opened in 1962.
The Tropical Bird Gardens were famous for the free flying macaws and
there were five UK first breedings there, including the first breeding of the
Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber. Interested originally in pigeons, he kept these
right up until his death in 1994. He also greatly appreciated red factor
canaries; he greatly appreciated birds with red in their plumage, but hated
some of the other new colour canaries that have appeared. He never went in
for small exotic birds that need heat or a tropical house, which are he
maintained very expensive to run and the general public do not appreciate.
Donald Risdon was awarded the President's Medal in 1993, and is only the
sixth person to have been awarded this medal.
As well as birds, he also loved fairground music. Prior to being appointed
General Manager of Dudley Zoo in 1949, he was manager of Keston Foreign
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.527126" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265678" page_num="105" year="" vol="">
SAWYER - FAMOUS AVICULTURISTS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99951" page_id="56265678"  page_num="105" year="" vol="">
105
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9566805" page_id="56265678"  page_num="105" year="" vol="">
Bird Farm. It was the first of its kind and probably the best. There were in
the past numerous reports in the magazine about Keston but suffice it to say
that the many small aviaries were on a terraced, southern slope. It bred
commercially Australian finches and parrakeets, and also bred other birds
and received several first breeding awards, including for breeding the Blue-
fronted Amazon Amazona aestiva, which bred there for several years. Other
species bred there for the first time in the UK, include the Fairy Bluebird
Irena puella, White-capped Redstart P. leucocephalus and Purple Grenadier
Uraeginthus ianthinogaster. The Duke of Bedford was the greatest supporter
of Keston Foreign Bird Farm. He left it #4,000 (approx. US$6,000 at the
present exchange rate) in his will and Boosey used Westmoreland stone to
construct a water garden there in the duke's memory. Boosey was a dedicated
aviculturist who also kept a private collection of choice seedeaters and
softbills. He served as a Vice President of the society and was a prolific
writer for the magazine.
Ken Norris lived not far from here at Purley, Surrey. He had numerous
breeding successes, including the first breeding of the Rufous-bellied Niltava
N. sundara. He also succeeded in breeding the Mountain Bluebird Sialia
currucoides. His aviaries, in the Persian or Moorish style, although not
large had quite a few softbills in each of them. Although a pigeon enthusiast
mainly, as well as softbills, he also kept some cockatoos and parrakeets. He
was a chairman of the British Aviculturists' Club and on occasions gave
film shows. He was very keen on natural history and was a very good artist.
For many years a bachelor, Ken Norris married late in life.
N. T. (Ted) Vane lived at Great Missendon, Bucks., having previously
lived at Pinner, Middlesex. He built up a large collection of parrot species
and was widely regarded as one of the experts on this family. He made a
partial living from selling birds he bred and wrote numerous articles for the
magazine. Another good artist, he was writing a book about parrots at the
time of his death.
Andy Wilson was a dealer from Glasgow, who the first time I met
him had two hill mynahs Gracula sp. on display at the Horticultural Hall.
He was a character and was often called upon to judge. Toucans, motmots
and birds of paradise were amongst the most spectacular birds kept by George
Whitmore. When the Duke of Bedford died, he paid #25 (approx. US$35)
for his pair of Musschenbroek's Lorikeets Neopsittacus musschenbroekii, a
rare species in this country before about 1985. George Whitmore was an
exhibitor who had numerous successes on the show bench and in 1964 was
awarded the society's medal for the first breeding of the Thick-billed Green
Pigeon Treron curvirostra.
Effy Clarke and her husband George, who from time to time entertained
the Duke of Bedford, had an enormous collection of parrot species. They
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999143" page_id="56265679"  page_num="106" year="" vol="">
106
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.807025" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265679" page_num="106" year="" vol="">
SAWYER - FAMOUS AVICULTURISTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970776071428572" page_id="56265679"  page_num="106" year="" vol="">
bred the Queen of Bavaria's Conure Guarouba guarouba and a delightful
hybrid Barraband Parrakeet Polytelis swainsonii x Princess of Wales
Parrakeet P. alexandrae. It was a beautiful bird with its orange and lots of
other colours.
Newton Steele lived in Sussex and then moved near Dartmouth in south
Devon. A cattle breeder, he also kept a large collection of domestic pigeons
and large birds mainly such as species of parrot, turacos and the Nicobar
Pigeon Caloenas nicobarica. He was awarded the society's medal for the
first breeding of the Grey Crowned Crane Balearica regulorum gibbericeps
and Ross's Turaco.
Viscount Chaplin was Secretary of the Zoological Society of London,
and in 1935 had been Hon. Editor of our magazine. He was one of the most
charming people you could meet and very enthusiastic about his birds. He
was extremely keen on nectar-feeders, particularly sunbirds. He used to
keep a sunbird in his room for many years and fed it smoked haddock from
his breakfast. He also kept a few hummingbirds. He too was a talented
artist and paintings by him of hummingbirds and sunbirds were reproduced
as the frontispiece of the December 1933, January 1934 and October 1935
issues of the magazine.
By profession a veterinary surgeon, Tom Spence kept a large collection
of birds at Newburgh, Fife, Scotland. I used to go and stay there. He had
screamers, numerous cranes, curassows, and a collection of lories, which at
the time may have been the largest in the UK. He bred the Purple-capped
Lorius domicellus in 1954, for which he received the society's medal, it
being the first breeding of this species in the UK. He also kept numerous
pigeons of which the Crested Pigeons Ocyphaps lophotes lived at liberty in
his garden. Later he became Superintendent of the Zoological Gardens,
Perth, Western Australia.
Tom Goodwin lived not far from here at Ripley, Surrey. I went there in
the early 1950s and remember his lovely Jackson's Euplectes jacksoni and
Giant Widowbirds E. progne and Hartlaub's Turacos T. hartlaubi. Mr Ezra
supported him in pre-War years when he went to Australia and collected
many interesting birds.
Jack Indge ('Jolly') was one of the earliest people from whom I bought
birds. George Lynch took me to meet him at his bungalow at Trimstone,
Thorpe, Surrey, in which he had a large birdroom in the roof space. He used
to deal in birds and I bought many birds from him, he also had quite nice
aviaries in the garden for his own birds about which he was very enthusiastic
and, in 1962, received the society's medal for the first breeding of the Red-
sided Eclectus Eclectus roratus polychloris. George Lynch was a wonderful
all-rounder who was already going strong when I started. Involved with
Hounslow CBS (Cage Bird Society), he had only a few aviaries but managed
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.527124" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265680" page_num="107" year="" vol="">
SAWYER - FAMOUS AVICULTURISTS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999586" page_id="56265680"  page_num="107" year="" vol="">
107
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.990264380952381" page_id="56265680"  page_num="107" year="" vol="">
to keep a varied selection of birds. Always interested in canaries and British
birds, he also achieved the UK first breeding of the Purple Finch Carpodacus
purpureus. When I started showing, he was showing a Satin Bowerbird
Ptilonorhynchus violaceus that he had bought from Reg Partridge, which
during the war he had kept going on mashed potatoes and sultanas. He also
had a long-lived Donaldson-Smith's Turaco T. leucotis donaldsoni . A very
well known all-round show judge, he was for many years the canary expert
of Cage Birds , which later became the present Cage &amp; Aviary Birds and was
Editor of Birds Illustrated. He lived to be 90 years old. His son Tommy
remains active and lives near Famham.
Percy Hastings was perhaps the leading dealer supplying nectar-feeders
and other softbills, and had been going strong since before the Second World
War. In the 1950s he imported wonderful birds from Central and South
America, including my Scarlet Cock-of-the-Rock which was Supreme
Exhibit at the 1958 National Exhibition at Olympia, London. He used to
telephone me to tell me what he had got in and one day told me he had some
lovely "red and black flowerpeckers". Knowing that flowerpeckers do not
come from South America, I was especially curious! They proved to be
Rhodospingus Finches Rhodospingus cruentus - the first ever imported into
the UK. He also imported a lot of hummingbirds from Randau in Brazil.
Percy Hastings was also the proprietor of Stimulite, the only nectar mixture
available in those days. When new brands started to appear in the mid-
1960s there was considerable correspondence in the magazine as to how the
products compared and which was the best. So far as I know, Stimulite
continues to be British-owned.
Allen Silver had joined the society in 1904 and was the oldest member
at the time of the 75th Anniversary, and wrote about the society's first 75
years in the 75th Anniversary Special Supplement (Vol. 75, No.6, p.225
(1969)). Allen, who had lost a leg in the First World War, lived near Newport,
South Wales, and ran a pet shop. He was a great friend of mine. Not only
was he very knowledgeable about birds - he was the foreign bird expert for
Cage Birds magazine and well known for his British birds and mules and
hybrids - but was also a great horticulturist. He achieved the first breeding
of the Rufous &amp; Black Warbling Finch Poospiza nigrorufa.
Alfredo Marques lived at Tankery House, Bedfordshire, where the gin
of the same name was first produced. At one time he had a vast collection
of parrot species, including many mutations. Avery kind man, he gradually
drifted out of aviculture. Unlike myself, very few people seem to remain in
aviculture all their lives.
George Mottershead, a great person in both the bird and zoo world, was
a Vice President of the Avicultural Society from 1962 until his death in
1978, and was a great host to us during the society's numerous visits to
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999502" page_id="56265681"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
108
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.828973" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265681" page_num="108" year="" vol="">
SAWYER - FAMOUS AVICULTURISTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995272833333333" page_id="56265681"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
Chester Zoo. He began from very humble origins running a pet shop and in
the 1920s was able to acquire some land to the west of Chester and with
good fortune laid the foundations for Chester Zoo which opened in 1931.
With money in short supply he did wonders with next to nothing and his
earliest buildings would not stand comparison with the modern buildings
which the zoo now boasts. The Polar Bear enclosure was made using concrete
tank traps left-over after the Second World War. Chester's latest major
building project, Spirit of the Jaguar, cost, with the support of Jaguar Cars,
#2 million (approx. US$3 million) and today the zoo's bird collection is
probably the best in this country.
In the previous issue (Vol. 108, No.2, pp 93-94), News &amp; Views included
a report about the WCS (Wildlife Conservation Society) acquiring two of
the Falkland Islands, Grand Jason and Steeple Jason. These two islands
were once owned by Len Hill. A builder by trade, he had as a small boy
growing up in the picturesque Cotswold village of Bourton-on-the-Water,
Glos., lived next door to a large house named Chadwell, which he longed to
own one day and eventually acquired together with 4 acres (approx. 1.6
hectares) of land. There in 1958 he open the first real bird garden in this
country and called it Birdland. He obtained birds from around the world
and developed the grounds with great taste. Birdland proved a great attraction
and during its first season there were 30,000 visitors. By 1966 the number
of visitors had risen to more than 300,000.
In 1965 a second tropical house was opened. The two housed a variety
of species including hummingbirds, tanagers, pittas, Hoopoe Upupa epops
longirostris, a small flock of Cinnamon-chested Bee-eaters Merops oreohates
from Kenya, and Carmine Bee-eaters Merops sp. Mountain Witch Dove
Geotrygon versicolor , White-browed Robin Chat Cossypha heuglini, Snowy-
headed Robin Chat C. niveicapilla and Spotted Morning Warbler (called
now the Spotted Morning-Thrush) Cichladusa guttata , were amongst the
species bred in these houses. The last three were UK first breedings, the
latter a joint first breeding with Winged World.
A pair of Great Hornbills Buceros bicornis nested but nothing came of
it. In the late 1960s and early 1970s, he had Lear's Macaws Anodorhynchus
leari and Swift Parrakeets Lathamus discolor , species most people had never
seen before. Len Hill also liked smaller owls, such as the Spectacled Pulsatrix
perspicillata, and falconets. He also enjoyed having birds at liberty, there
were cranes and flamingos on the lawns in front of the house, and macaws
were allowed to fly free and were trained to return to their roosting barrels
at dusk (colour photos of the house, the interior of the new tropical house, a
hummingbird and two macaws, one looking out of a sleeping barrel, can be
seen in Vol.74, No.l, between pp.24-27 (1968)). His pet African Grey
Psittacus erithacus also flew free and other birds wandered at liberty.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.527131" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265682" page_num="109" year="" vol="">
SAWYER - FAMOUS AVICULTURISTS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999502" page_id="56265682"  page_num="109" year="" vol="">
109
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.992927903225806" page_id="56265682"  page_num="109" year="" vol="">
In 1967 a Lecture Hall was opened by Peter Scott. A mural of a view in
the neighbourhood of Bourton-on-the-Water with a flight of ducks rising
over a stream, painted by Peter Scott, was unveiled by Jean Delacour. It
was in the Lecture Hall that the society later held the farewell presentation
for Phyllis Barclay-Smith, who edited the magazine from 1938-1973.
Len Hill, a good and generous friend to the society, will be remembered
most of all for his many penguins. He had King Aptenodytes patagonica,
Gentoo Pygoscelis papua, Rockhopper Eudyptes crestatus , Macaroni E.
chrysolophus and Magellanic Spheniscus magellanicus from the Falklands,
as well as other species such as the Humboldt S. humboldti and Black-footed
or African S. demersus. He was fortunate in having a supply of ice cold,
spring water, and housed them in glass-fronted pools, enabling visitors to
see them swimming underwater. Birdland was the first collection in the UK
to breed the Rockhopper Penguin.
I am going to end these notes with Reginald Greed, the father of our
recently retired Hon. Secretary and Treasurer, Geoffrey Greed. In my early
days, I remember going to Bristol to judge at a bird show and being asked to
visit the zoo to meet Reg Greed, the Director, with the view to helping
design some large display cages for birds of paradise. Those that the zoo
had at the time included a Red Bird of Paradise P. rubra and he wanted
better accommodation for them. The zoo had a tropical house and a room
with some glass-fronted cages. Always a beautifully laid out zoo, with the
horticulture of a terrifically high standard, it used not to have a great many
birds, but in recent years the number has grown and there have been some
notable breedings, including a few first breedings.
In those early days, when Bristol Zoo was the only zoo in the UK with
Okapis Okapia johnstoni, his son Geoffrey was just starting out on his zoo
career, having done his training in Germany. When his father retired, he
succeeded him as Director of Bristol Zoo (called now Bristol Zoo Gardens),
a post he himself retired from last year and was succeeded by Jo Gipps from
London Zoo.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997645" page_id="56265683"  page_num="110" year="" vol="">
110
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9988705" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265683" page_num="110" year="" vol="">
HAND-REARING THE BLACK-FACED IBIS AT THE
COTSWOLD WILDLIFE PARK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.981556815789474" page_id="56265683"  page_num="110" year="" vol="">
by Jamie Graham
The Black-faced Ibis Theristicus melanopis lives and breeds in a wide
range of habitats ranging from farmland to swamps in southern South
America. Its highly adaptable nature means that nesting is not a problem; it
prefers rocky outcrops but will also nest in reedbeds and in trees sometimes,
making a large nest platform of dry sticks, which it lines with grass, and on
which it lays two to three eggs.
The pair has been at the Cotswold Wildlife Park for two years and is
housed in a large mixed exhibit that includes Black Storks Ciconia nigra ,
Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber and Waldrapp Ibis Geronticus eremita. The
Black Storks and the Waldrapp are the only birds to have successfully parent-
reared chicks in the aviary, we have had eggs and chicks from the Scarlet
and Black-faced Ibis but these have mysteriously vanished. At the start of
this breeding season the decision as to whether or not to remove the Black-
faced Ibis eggs was decided for us. The female started laying at the beginning
of February when frosts remained rife, and rather than risk losing the eggs
or chicks, the three eggs that had been laid were removed for artificial
incubation.
Two were fertile and hatched on February 25th 2002, the first at 9.00am
and the second at 11.00am. Both chicks were placed together, though in
separate baskets, in a brooder running at 36*C (96.8*F). At 4.00pm they
were given 2ml of our starting mixture consisting of 5ml of distilled water
and a pinch of Avipro paediatric. Both were given 2.5ml of the same mix at
8.00pm. The next day at 8.00am they had their first solid food. This consisted
of lOOg cat food (fish or chicken), 40ml distilled water, a pinch of paediatric
and a pinch of Neutrobal.
The ingredients were mixed in a juicer and fed to the chicks at 8.00am,
12.30pm, 4.30pm and at about 8.00pm, when they received their last feed of
the day. It is most important never to feed the chicks more than 10% of their
body weight. This basic mixture was devised many years ago by our Assistant
Curator whilst he was working at Birdland, Bourton-on-the-Water, Glos.
We have seen a few different hand-rearing diets and all seem to be far too
high in protein which can cause many different growth defects, therefore
we prefer to stick with the above diet.
The two chicks were fed on it for 19 days, during which time the amount
given was increased gradually (see Table 1) and it was also gradually made
thicker. The two were moved to a larger brooder on day 20 and the first
major change in their diet took place. Thigh meat was removed from day
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.321625" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265684" page_num="111" year="" vol="">
GRAHAM - BLACK-FACED IBIS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999275" page_id="56265684"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
111
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99741925" page_id="56265684"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
old chicks, no bone just meat, and they took this as well as the mix. At 24
days they had to be moved again and two days later minced chick as well as
the mix was fed to them. The chicks had the head, skin and feet removed
and were then blended very finely and fed to the ibis chicks using a 20ml
syringe with the end cut off. Gradually more and more feather material was
left on the chicks and over the next eight days taking the ibis chicks to 34
days old, the amount of mix was reduced and the amount of blended chick
was increased, until they were getting only blended chicks plus a pinch of
Neutrobal. At this stage the last feed was cut out and the ibis chicks were
fed just three times a day. Over the next 10 days they were encouraged to
pick up food for themselves. Ibis chicks are very messy at the best of times
and during this stage things got a lot messier, with food being flicked
everywhere. I wanted to leave food with them overnight, which meant cutting
up the chicks by hand, which in turn meant that the ibis chicks got used to
eating slightly larger pieces of food and, due to the fact that I removed the
yolk sac, the chicks were clean come the next morning.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.957995">
Table 1. Development of chick 1 during its first 50 days.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.95283994" page_id="56265684"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
Days
old
Weight/
Feed 1
Weight/
Feed 2
Weight/
Feed 3
Weight/
Feed 4
Remarks
1
57g/2ml
57g/2.5ml
mix 1, large faeces passed
2
55g/2.5ml
54g/3ml
53g/3ml
55g/3ml
mix 2 solid food, vocal and alert
3
55g/3ml
56g/5ml
56g/4ml
58g/5ml
coordination very good
4
56g/5ml
58g/5ml
61g/6ml
63g/5ml
very vocal
5
62g/5ml
65g/5ml
66g/6ml
68g/5ml
put chicks 1 &amp;2 together, both trying to stand
6
69g/5ml
70g/6ml
73g/6ml
76g/5ml
sticks put in basket to help grip
8
80g/6ml
80g/7ml
83g/7ml
85g/7ml
</figure>
<footnote confidence="0.969505">
4ml mix, the rest solid chunks of cat food
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.963424" page_id="56265684"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
13
</page>
<figure confidence="0.976060637931034" page_id="56265684"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
132g/12ml
136g/12ml
140g/13ml
144g/13ml
first preening behaviour
15
153g/13ml
156g/13ml
164g/14ml
170g/15ml
pin-feathers starting to come through
17
175g/16ml
182g/16ml
187g/17ml
193g/17ml
standing well
20
234g/22g
240g/22g
254g/22g
253g/23g
boneless chick thigh meat given j
26
364g/32g
382g/33g
395g/34g
41 lg/35g
finely minced chick given,
feathers growing well
33
664g/66g
675g/67g
727g/72g
last feed cut out, feeding 10% of body weight
34
692g/69g
724g/72g
802g/80g
first pellet produced
44
1086g/106g
1130g/l lOg
1134g/l 13g
started to pick food up from dish over the
last few days
46
115lg/115g
1210g/115g
1250g/115g
dropped off 10% as they are eating food
left with them in between meals
50
1198g
1218g
1233g
self-feeding just putting chick mix in with
them
</figure>
<page confidence="0.995391" page_id="56265685"  page_num="112" year="" vol="">
112
</page>
<figure confidence="0.224478333333333" page_id="56265685"  page_num="112" year="" vol="">
GRAHAM - BLACK-FACED IBIS
Louise Peat
Black-faced Ibis chick
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.974769222222223" page_id="56265685"  page_num="112" year="" vol="">
The two chicks developed at very similar rates, the main differences
between the two being in their characters. As can be seen from the table (p.
Ill), most of the important developments happened in the first 20 days.
Everything happened so quickly and so much information was recorded
every day, detailing growth, movement, diet and changes made to it as the
chicks grew bigger, that it is not possible to record it all here, besides which
a lot of it would probably make boring reading for the majority of members.
Therefore, what I have tried to do is to provide details of the most important
stages in the chicks' development and the changes in their diet.
These are the first Black-faced Ibis to have been bred at the park and the
first ibis that I have had the pleasure to hand-rear. I have been reliably
informed that they were the quietest and cleanest of all the ibis that have
been reared here. If this is the case, by the time you read this, I am likely to
have spent much of the remainder of the breeding season cleaning up after
our other ibis chicks.
Jamie Graham is a bird keeper at the Cotswold Wildlife Park, Burford,
Oxon. 0X18 4JW, UK . Tel:01993 823006/Fax:01993 823807/Website:
cotswoldwildlifepark. co. uk
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999546" page_id="56265686"  page_num="113" year="" vol="">
113
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.928554" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265686" page_num="113" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE BLUE-TAILED OR BANDED PITTA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8425725" page_id="56265686"  page_num="113" year="" vol="">
Pitta guajana AT VOGELPARK WALSRODE
by Dieter Rinke and Bernd Marcordes
Introduction
Although pittas have for a long time been kept in zoological institutions
and by private aviculturists, little information about their maintenance in
captivity has been published in scientific and avicultural journals.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.6033105" page_id="56265686"  page_num="113" year="" vol="">
Dieter Rinke
Adult female Banded Pitta
Dieter Rinke
Adult male Banded Pitta
</figure>
<page confidence="0.999477" page_id="56265687"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
114
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.519557" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265687" page_num="114" year="" vol="">
RINKE &amp; MARCORDES - BANDED PITTA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985517634146342" page_id="56265687"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
Several species have been bred in captivity, of which the breedings of
the Hooded Pitta P. sordida , Banded Pitta P. guajana irena, Noisy Pitta P.
versicolor. Elegant Pitta P. elegans and Giant Pitta P. caerulea are well
documented (Delacour, 1934; Lee et al. 1989; Vernon, 1974; Parrish, 1983;
Pagel, 2001; McKelvie &amp; Miller, 1979). In addition. Hooded Pittas are
breeding prolifically in the huge tropical house at Burgers' Zoo, Arnhem (J.
Wensing pers. comm.), while Blue-winged Pittas P. moluccensis at Frankfurt
Zoo (S. Stadler pers. comm.), Blue-tailed Pittas at Copenhagen Zoo (F.
Nielsen pers. comm.) and Gurney's Pittas P gurneyi in the collection of a
Thai bird fancier in the 1960s (cf. Collar, 2001) bred occasionally and reared
young successfully.
Nevertheless, no pitta species has yet been bred to a sufficient level to
achieve a sustainable captive population. In the regional collection plan for
passerines in European zoos, the Hooded and Banded Pittas have been
recommended for monitoring status with the aim of establishing viable
populations within the institutions of the European Association of Zoos and
Aquaria (EAZA). The North American Passerine TAG has recommended
that the Hooded and Elegant Pittas be included in the regional collection
plan (D. Rimlinger in litt.).
Maintenance
Three pairs of Banded Pittas were imported in 1999 from Indonesia, all
of which were housed initially in the newly opened Nusantara Rainforest
Paradise (NRP), a large tropical greenhouse for Indonesian birds. Two pairs
could roam the entire area of 2,800sq m (approx. 30,000sq ft), while the
third pair was placed in a 3m x 9m (approx. 10ft x 30ft) aviary. These are
densely planted and offer a lot of hiding places.
The exhibit houses various frugivorous, insectivorous and carnivorous
birds. Feeding places are distributed evenly, and the pittas take their share
of livefood and freshly killed insects (mealworms, crickets, zophobas,
waxmoth larvae, etc.) and dry insectivorous food, which is offered at all the
feeding stations. The pittas also search the leaf and wood chip litter for
insects and other invertebrates and often capture small earthworms. They
use their bills intensively for turning over the ground.
At the same time that the Banded Pittas were introduced into the NRP,
so was a small group of Hooded Pittas. Interactions between the pittas were
observed very rarely, but it soon became clear that one pair dominated all
the others, and it was only this pair that bred. When one pair was housed in
one of the aviaries within the tropical house, the male of the dominant pair
spent most of its time close by, and the pair in the aviary was very nervous.
In small enclosures, male pittas may sometimes attack others and kill them;
such attacks may happen even between young birds which have not yet
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.293094" page_id="56265688"  page_num="115" year="" vol="">
RINKE &amp; MARCORDES - BANDED PITTA
</equation>
<page confidence="0.999104" page_id="56265688"  page_num="115" year="" vol="">
115
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.990109476190476" page_id="56265688"  page_num="115" year="" vol="">
attained adult plumage. Consequently, except for the breeding pair of Banded
Pittas, all the other pittas were removed from the NRP, even those in the
separate aviary.
With our pairs of pittas we have rarely observed interactions between
the male and female or between the pittas and other birds. Even juveniles
do not seek close contact with their parents and approach them only when
they are hungry. We have never seen pittas preening each other - the closest
contact the male and female seem to have, apart from during copulation, is
at the entrance of the nest, when they change over.
In November 2001, one of the aforementioned pairs of Banded Pittas
was introduced into the large walk-through aviary (70m x 15m (approx.
230ft x 50ft)) in our old tropical house. This exhibit is similarly well planted
and has three feeding stations spaced evenly throughout its length.
Reproduction
The nests of Banded Pittas are very rough constructions made of various
kinds of materials, with the preferred material being dead leaves of various
sizes. The materials are formed into a globular structure up to the size of a
football, with the entrance at one side. There has been only one instance of
the same nest being used twice.
The pair in the NRP has always chosen very similar nest sites, always at
the meeting point of two sections of the exhibit's support structure, by the
outside wall, and always at a height of 2.5m (just over 8ft) above the ground.
Some of the nests have been hidden behind vegetation but others have been
clearly visible from several metres (feet) away.
Although we learnt very quickly where to look for new nests, the pittas
often constructed several new nests, so it has not always been easy to confirm
the exact date that breeding began.
The pair in the old tropical house choose different nest sites, mostly
close to the roof of the exhibit. This pair prefer to build in amongst or onto
densely tangled vines. In addition, two nests have been built on tree trunks,
one in a relatively open position between bromelias and the other in a thorny
Bougainvillea. This pair is generally more secretive than the pair in the new
tropical exhibit, and it took us quite a time to find most of the nests.
Banded Pittas lay clutches of three to four eggs; four eggs seems to be
the normal clutch size. The eggs measure on average 26mm x 21mm and
are whitish with dark brown spots mainly at the blunt end. We have not
succeeded in determining the exact incubation period, which is approximately
13 days according to Lambert &amp; Woodcock (1996). If the pittas are disturbed,
they start to build a new nest after a short period of time. Even having
successfully reared chicks, they commence a new breeding cycle soon
afterwards. In both of our tropical houses, the pittas breed more or less all
year round (see Tables 1 &amp; 2).
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.87205" page_id="56265689"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
16
</page>
<figure confidence="0.893674815789474" page_id="56265689"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
RINKE &amp; MARCORDES - BANDED PITTA
Dieter Rinke
Male incubating in the NRP
Dieter Rinke
Young Banded Pittas at 13 days old
Table 1. Record of known breedings of the Banded Pittas in the NRP.
2000
07/06
25/07
07/08
22/09
11/10
16/11
3 eggs
3 juv.
4 eggs
3 eggs
2 juv.
2 juv.
2001
21/05
25/06
20/07
07/09
28/09
04/10
3 juv.
4 juv.
3eggs
x eggs destroyed
1 juv.
2 eggs
2002
10/03
02/04
06/05
20/05
05/06
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.793027" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265689" page_num="116" year="" vol="">
3 juv.
4 eggs*
3 eggs*
4 eggs*
4 eggs
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.252438" page_id="56265689"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
* Eggs removed for artificial incubation and rearing.
</table>
<equation confidence="0.281174" page_id="56265690"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
RINKE &amp; MARCORDES - BANDED PITTA
</equation>
<page confidence="0.958694" page_id="56265690"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
117
</page>
<table confidence="0.7541574" page_id="56265690"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
Dieter Rinke
Young at 30 days - female to the left. The sexual dimorphism is
clearly visible
Dieter Rinke
Fledgling reared by its parents in the old tropical house
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.879619">
Table 2. Record of known breedings of the Banded Pitta in the old tropical
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.822277470588235" page_id="56265690"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
house.
2002
25/01
25/02
20/03
09/04
03/05
10/06
1 juv.
2 juv.
x eggs destroyed
3 eggs*
4 eggs*
1 fledgling
* Eggs removed:
for artificial incubation and
l rearing.
</figure>
<page confidence="0.998375" page_id="56265691"  page_num="118" year="" vol="">
118
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.389553" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265691" page_num="118" year="" vol="">
RINKE &amp; MARCORDES - BANDED PITTA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986307095238095" page_id="56265691"  page_num="118" year="" vol="">
Hand-rearing
In the NRP, the Greater Birds of Paradise Paradisaea apoda often robbed
the nests, therefore, we decided to remove the chicks and hand-rear them.
At the beginning, we waited until the chicks were over five days old, because
we were uncertain about our ability to successfully rear younger nestlings.
However, having achieved good results, and because many nests were robbed
even of the eggs, we soon began to remove the eggs for artificial incubation.
Following the discussion about future conservation measures for the critically
endangered Gurney's Pitta (see later), the hands-on management of pittas
became an additional challenge to us.
The nestlings are fed for the first time approximately 18 hours after
hatching. Each gets one piece of baby mouse or baby rat (one to two days
old, as for such young birds the skin of older baby rats is almost indigestible),
powdered with lactobacillus, and a small quantity of added water at the
start. They continue to receive this amount of food at intervals of 90-120
minutes from 6.30arn-8.30pm (06.30hrs-20.30hrs) for the first two days,
but with the lactobacillus powder added only once a day. After this, the
intervals between feeds are increased gradually to approximately every two
to three hours, and until day six continue to consist only of baby rats and
mice, though by then each receives several pieces until they stop begging
for food. Once a day traces of a vitamin and mineral powder (Korvimin)
and calcium are added to the food.
Since changing to this starting diet for the nestlings of our insectivorous
and carnivorous species, we have had extraordinary success, with an
enormous increase in the survival rates of our young chicks. With trogons
(Rinke &amp; Marcordes in press), birds of paradise, catbirds, vangas, couas,
barbets and bee-eaters, being amongst the most notable species we have
reared using this diet.
From day seven, beef heart, crickets and waxmoth larvae are added to
the pittas' diet and gradually take the place of the pieces of rat and mice. At
about day 18, the young pittas start feeding by themselves and we also offer
them mealworms, dried insectivorous food and a little bit of fruit.
Earlier this year we took five clutches of eggs from our two breeding
pairs, totalling in all 18 eggs (see Tables 1 &amp; 2). One embryo died during
incubation and out of the 17 pittas hatched, we lost four, they died at eight,
four, four and four days of age respectively. Thirteen survived, a relatively
high survival rate for a small to medium insectivorous species.
The nestlings were kept in artificial nests, each of which contained two
nestlings. However, two of the deaths were caused by the young birds being
soiled by the faeces of their nest companion. Therefore, it seems advisable
to keep young birds singly in separate nests placed close together so that the
birds have vocal and, later on, visual contact.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.293073" page_id="56265692"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
RINKE &amp; MARCORDES - BANDED PITTA
</equation>
<page confidence="0.999185" page_id="56265692"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
119
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.994928" page_id="56265692"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
Nestlings are completely naked and have shining blackish skin. The
papillae and the entire inside of the mouth are bright orange-yellow. Young
Hooded Pittas look very different, having pink skin and a black head on
hatching. The eyes of young Banded Pittas open at about eight days of age.
At the same time, black feather shafts begin to develop and the chicks take
on the appearance of tiny hedgehogs or sea urchins. The chicks fledge at
15-18 days of age.
At this early age the fledglings already show striking sexual dimorphism.
Young males have dark brown breasts with faint streaks and show some
banding on the flanks. Young females have the breast and upper belly lighter
brown with cream coloured spots which get denser towards the centre, and
lack any sign of banding on the flanks or elsewhere on the underparts. There
is also a slight difference in the colour tone of the crown, which is darker in
young males. These differences appear not to have been described before
(cf. Lambert &amp; Woodcock, 1996). Appendix 1 (p. 121) charts the growth
rate of seven of the hand-reared nestlings. Lambert &amp; Woodcock (1996)
give the weight of adult birds as 90g-120g.
Our hand-reared pittas do not develop a close bond with those who rear
them and have shown hardly any signs of having become imprinted on
humans. After they have fledged we keep them in small groups and the
birds continue to develop their innate shyness in the presence of humans.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.851219">
Discussion
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999673388888889" page_id="56265692"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
Our experience clearly demonstrates that pittas can with extensive
management be produced in relatively large numbers. Their reproductive
potential, at least under optimal captive conditions, is high, as can be seen
from the relatively short intervals between successive breedings. If the eggs
are removed at an early stage of incubation, these intervals can be shortened
to less than one month between clutches for at least three to four successive
breedings.
Our experience may give the impression that breeding pittas is a simple
task. This is clearly not the case, because it is exceptional for these birds to
reproduce in captivity. There are apparently certain basic conditions which
must be met for pittas to breed successfully.
What are the requirements for successful reproduction?
An important factor may be space, for pittas appear to require large
territories with numerous hiding places in order to reproduce successfully.
We will, however, shortly attempt to keep a pair of pittas in a densely planted
outdoor aviary with similarly planted indoor facilities in order to figure out
whether a large area is really necessary. The crucial point seems to be that
it should have hiding places, because pittas often abandon nest sites once
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.959523" page_id="56265693"  page_num="120" year="" vol="">
120
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.50537" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265693" page_num="120" year="" vol="">
RINKE &amp; MARCORDES - BANDED PITTA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99896725" page_id="56265693"  page_num="120" year="" vol="">
they have been disturbed. It is our impression that pittas are highly sensitive,
even to being watched from a distance, when they are constructing their
nest. In a small enclosure, even the daily routine of feeding and cleaning
may be sufficient disturbance to prevent the birds from breeding successfully.
Hiding places may also help a bird to escape the attention of its mate. As
mentioned earlier, pittas show very little social behaviour, and even the male
and female of a pair live relatively solitary lives.
We had a pair of Hooded Pittas P. s. cucullata that attempted to breed in
a relatively small enclosure, that following this unsuccessful breeding
attempt, showed aggressive behaviour towards each other and did not start
building again for more than a year. Aggression between male and female
pittas can be reduced by housing them in large enclosures and providing
sufficient hiding places, mainly in the form of dense plant cover. This seems
to be particularly important when establishing new pairs. In two cases, the
male killed the female in a small aviary, whereas in our large walk-through
enclosures, no such incidents have occurred.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.737304">
Important implications
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.972223869565217" page_id="56265693"  page_num="120" year="" vol="">
The number of young which we could produce from two pairs of Banded
Pittas in only a short period of time has important implications for the
conservation of one of the rarest species of bird on earth - Gurney's Pitta.
With perhaps just 20 individuals remaining in a few forest patches in
peninsular Thailand, it may become extinct within the next few years in
front of the eyes of the conservation community. If it does, it will probably
be the best documented extinction of a species. What types of "protection
and active conservation efforts" (Lambert &amp; Woodcock, 1999 (p. 112)) have
brought its number from some 45 pairs in 1986 to approximately 20 birds in
1997 (BirdLife International, 2000)?
With a limited period of intensive hands-on management and moderate
funding, Gurney's Pitta would have a good chance of recovery. It is though
crucial to start a recovery programme as soon as possible, because every
single bird that is lost from the dwindling population will reduce considerably
the species' chance of survival.
The first step should be to increase the number of birds regardless of
other considerations. Arearing facility should be built near Khao Nor Chuchi,
the last stronghold of this species. Eggs and/or young should be collected
from as many nests as can be found, to ensure that the genetic base for the
recovery programme is as diverse as possible.
The young birds should be used for the following purposes:
1. The release into the wild of a number of birds (to be determined) from
every single pair in order to stabilize the small wild population. The
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.294074" page_id="56265694"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
RINKE &amp; MARCORDES - BANDED PITTA
</equation>
<page confidence="0.995306" page_id="56265694"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
121
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.7490605" page_id="56265694"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
release of all reared birds would be unwise, as the carrying capacity of
the reserve seems to be very low.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.9800884" page_id="56265694"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
2. The establishment of a breeding facility at Khao Nor Chuchi, with the
aim of producing more young pittas for a release programme at other
potentially suitable sites. Such a breeding facility could also be used as
an education centre.
3. The transfer of a genetically diverse group of young pittas to at least two
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.9450095" page_id="56265694"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
renowned institutions to initiate an ex-situ captive breeding programme
under the umbrella of the EAZA (European Association of Zoos and
Aquaria). This group of birds could also be used for research on this
species and as a back-up population in case of a catastrophic event in the
pitta's native range.
It has been stated (BirdLife International, 2000 (p.403)) that conservation
measures for Gurney's Pitta have "met with limited success", which is a
rather positive assessment of the situation. Only with intensive hands-on
management as outlined above, can Gurney's Pitta be brought back from
the brink of extinction; and once we have a good number of birds to work
with, we can think about future measures needed to guarantee its survival in
the wild.
Appendix 1. Growth of seven hand-reared Banded pittas (single data and
median).
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997005" page_id="56265695"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
122
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8871965" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265695" page_num="122" year="" vol="">
RINKE &amp; MARCORDES - BANDED PITTA
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.840099166666667">
BirdLife International. 2000. Threatened Birds of the World. BirdLife International, Cambridge,
UK and Lynx Edicions, Barcelona, Spain.
Collar, N. 2001. Captive breeding for Gurney's Pitta: a brief comment. Oriental Bird Club
Bulletin 34:67.
Delacour, J. 1934. Breeding of the Hooded Pitta {Pitta cucullata). Avicultural Magazine
12:222-226.
Erritzoe, J. 2001. Gurney's Pitta again - Habitat protection and/or captive breeding? That's the
question. Oriental Bird Club Bulletin 34:66-67.
Erritzoe, J. &amp; Erritzoe, H. 1998. Pittas of the World. The Lutterworth Press, Cambridge, UK.
Lambert, F. &amp; Woodcock, M. 1996. Pittas, Broadbills and Asites. Pica Press, UK.
Lee, G., Haeffner, S. &amp; Zajicek, J. 1989. Breeding and hand-rearing of the Hooded Pitta Pitta
sordida at the Denver Zoo, Colorado, USA. Avicultural Magazine 95,3:119-128.
McKelvey, S. D. &amp; Miller, M. W. 1979. Breeding of the Giant Pitta at the San Antonio Zoo.
Avicultural Magazine 85,3:109-111.
Pagel, T. 2001. Zuchterfolg mit der Schmuckpitta im Kolner "Regenwald". Gefiederte Welt
125:55-57.
Parrish, R. 1983. Breeding the Noisy Pitta. International Zoo News 30(5): 17-19.
Rinke, D. &amp; Marcordes, B. (in press). Wieder Welterstzuchten im Vogelpark Walsrode:
</reference>
<table confidence="0.816123111111111" page_id="56265695"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
Nachwuchs bei drei Arten asiatischer Trogone (Gattungen Apalharpactes und Harpactes ).
Gefiederte Welt 127.
Vernon, P. 1974. The breeding of van der Bosch's Pitta Pitta guajana irena. Avicultural
Magazine 80,2:42-45.
Dieter Rinke and Bernd Marcordes, Vogelpark Walsrode, Zoologischer
Garten, D-29664 Walsrode, Am Rieselbach, Germany. Tel:(0 51 61) 20 15/
2016 - 6 04 40/Fax:(0 51 61) 82 10/E-mail:office @ vogelpark~walsrode.de/
Website: http ://www. vogelpark-walsrode. de
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.98507" genericHeader="introduction" page_id="56265695" page_num="122" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.924223" page_id="56265695"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
A large stock is available including some early issues. Further details
are available from: Hon. Secretary/Treasurer, The Avicultural Society, PO.
Box 47, Edenbridge, Kent TN8 7WP, UK or E-mail:lee.palm@virgin.net
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998919" page_id="56265696"  page_num="123" year="" vol="">
123
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8894975" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265696" page_num="123" year="" vol="">
THE GREAT BLUE AND OTHER TURACOS
by Louise Peat
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998363162162162" page_id="56265696"  page_num="123" year="" vol="">
In 2000, our first major disappointment happened on April 17th, when
our male Great Blue Turaco Corythaeola cristata was found dead on the
nest. The pair was nine days into incubating a clutch of three eggs. The
chilled eggs were rushed to our incubation room and the dead male was sent
to Jason Waine for post mortem, which revealed it had suffered a heart attack
from old age (the bird was wild-caught so we had no idea of its true age).
Two of the eggs proved to be clear, but the third went on to hatch, but
unfortunately despite all our efforts the chick died four days later. We will
never know if this was due to the egg having become chilled for an
undetermined length of time. Our limited success with the Great Blue
Turacos was very frustrating, we had several clutches of eggs from the pair,
several chicks hatched and at one point we had three chicks in the nest. Our
longest surviving chick lived 50 days. It was parent reared, and we began to
have doubts as to whether the adults were up to the job of rearing their own
chicks. We knew that Steve Bishop, who is in charge of Michel Klat's
collection at the Old House Bird Garden, Hare Hatch, had also had little
success with this species rearing their own young, but had tremendous success
hand-rearing them. We decided to follow suit and remove one or two chicks
from each clutch for hand-rearing, but at that point our male died. We later
exchanged our female for a pair that had been captive-bred at the Old House
Bird Garden.
For some reason our usually successful pair of Western Grey Plantain-
eaters Crinifer piscator was having a bad breeding season, with all six eggs
from the first two clutches covered with hairline cracks. It was decided to
remove one of the eggs from the next clutch for artificial incubation and
hand-rearing. Keeper Nathan Crockford, who had hand-reared a Western
Grey Plantain-eater before, realised that the critical part of hand-rearing
would be the diet during the first few days. Believing that there are
similarities between the plantain-eater and the Great Blue Turaco, Nathan
phoned Steve Bishop, who kindly provided him with details of the diet with
which he has been so successful. Nathan has used this diet for both the
Great Blue Turaco and Western Grey Plantain-eater.
The three stages to the diet:
Stage 1 (first nine days)
Every three hours for the first 24 hours chicks are given warm distilled
water with a pinch of Avipro chick starter. On day two chicks start being
fed, by syringe, the hand-rearing mixture made from 75% distilled water,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998683" page_id="56265697"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
124
</page>
<table confidence="0.253908333333333" page_id="56265697"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
PEAT - GREAT BLUE TURACO
Louise Peat
Adult Great Blue Ttiraco
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.99846755" page_id="56265697"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
20% banana, with the remaining 5% consisting of racing pigeon pellets,
budgie protein, nectar mix, shredded wheat and multi-vitamins, ground
together into a fine powder. As the days progress, this changes to 50%
distilled water, 40% banana and 10% powder, as the consistency of the
mixture is made thicker. In addition to the main diet, wheat grass juice is
fed by syringe to the chicks from day one through to independence.
Stage 2 (days nine to 11)
There is an overlap with Stage 1, with from about days six to seven
small pieces of paw paw (papaya) and banana and whole soaked pigeon
pellets occasionally being fed to chicks. The amounts of these are increased
gradually until by days nine to 11 they form the bulk of their diet; with them
still occasionally being offered the initial hand-rearing mixture. The wheat
grass juice is especially important at this stage, for even though the pigeon
pellets have been soaked, they can still soak up more moisture in the gut and
the juice will help compensate for this.
Stage 3 (day 11 onwards)
By this stage chicks should be receiving 50% fruit and 50% pigeon pellets.
They continue to receive wheat grass juice at each feed and different fruits
are introduced gradually and the pigeon pellets are slowly phased-out until
just a few are sprinkled on the top of each feed.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.350563" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265698" page_num="125" year="" vol="">
PEAT - GREAT BLUE TURACO
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.989683" page_id="56265698"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
125
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.2933815">
Louise Peat
Nestling Great Blue Ttiraeo
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986483444444444" page_id="56265698"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
By day 23 our plantain cater chick was pretty much feeding itself. There
had been a slight hiccup when on day 12 the chick refused to eat and over a
24 hour period lost 20g * one third of its body weight. Nathan put the chick
on a course of Baytril and within four days it had regained the lost weight
and went on to grow into a healthy bird. Ironically, the adult pair succeeded
in hatching and rearing a chick from the same clutch from which we had
removed the egg, from which the chick was being hand reared
Over the previous four years the pair had successfully reared 10 chicks,
all of which had been snapped up by other collections. We were beginning
to become concerned about flooding the UK with birds from the same
bloodlines, as at that time nobody else seemed to be successfully breeding
this species. However, in 1999, Birdworld, near Famham, Surrey, began to
breed from its pair. So, in 2000, we exchanged birds with it in order to
establish a second pair. Shortly afterwards, International Touraco Society
committee member Les Disley donated a pair to the park, meaning that we
had three pairs and a considerably enlarged gene pool.
Later that year we exchanged our two female Fischer's Turacos Tauraco
fischeri with Nigel Hewston for a breeding pair of Red-crested Turacos I
erythrolophus . All went well until the male escaped somehow and spent 10&amp;apos;
days living on wild berries. Fortunately he never strayed out of earshot of
the female and eventually entered our catching cage, baited with tempting
tit-bits. A thorough search of the aviary failed to discover how he had
managed to get out. The only logical explanation seemed to be that he had
somehow succeeded in squeezing through the 2in (5cm) square mesh.
Therefore, both birds were moved to a different aviary which has smaller
sized mesh.
Our pair of Violaceous Turacos Musophaga violacea managed to surpass
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998828" page_id="56265699"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
126
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.716629" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265699" page_num="126" year="" vol="">
PEAT - GREAT BLUE TURACO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999068212121212" page_id="56265699"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
themselves again that year and even though I tried to slow down the pair's
eagerness to breed, the pair produced four male offspring. During my
observations I noticed both birds off the nest at the same time while they
had a very young chick in it. I had never noticed this behaviour before and
due to the lateness of the season grew increasingly worried about the chick,
which when I checked appeared strong but hungry. I gave the chick a feed
and left it in the nest and went back to continue my observations. After a
major bonding session the adults went back to brooding the chick. A few
days later I grew concerned again, as I had seen no sign of the chick which
was at the age when it should have been much more visible. Worried that
there might be a problem, I reached into the nest to feel for the chick and to
my surprise, although small for its age, it was fine and was sitting between
two new eggs. The eggs were removed as it was felt that the birds would be
unable to rear the chick and incubate the eggs at the same time. Only one of
the eggs hatched and the chick was successfully hand-reared; the earlier
chick was successfully reared by the parents.
I believe that the behaviour just described is not uncommon amongst
turacos. Seeing it first-hand brought about a rush of questions, for example
do wild turacos do this and, if so, why? If they do not, what are the captive
conditions which bring this about, is it the plentiful supply of food? Surely
it is not in the birds' best interests to 'over' breed like this, as not only will
the adults exhaust themselves and lose condition, but it will ultimately affect
the viability of the eggs and chicks. I know many breeders who have had
turacos lay clutch after clutch after clutch, and I would be interested to learn
the thoughts of other aviculturists on this matter.
We also had success with our White-cheeked Turacos T. leucotis which
bred for the first time in our walk-through aviary. Nigel Hewston very
kindly donated an old pair of White-cheeked Turacos which he had used in
the past for foster rearing. They arrived in excellent condition despite their
age - the male being a remarkable 26 years old!
On our section at the park we had eggs from 48 species of birds and a
total of 76 young were reared to independence. The highlight was a second
generation parent reared Black Stork Ciconia nigra.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.944125" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56265699" page_num="126" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998424666666667" page_id="56265699"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
I would like to thank Nathan Crockford and Jamie Graham (two dedicated
keepers) for their contributions to this article.
The above article is based on one which was published first in the
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.9852725">
International Touraco Society Newsletter, which used to be edited by Louise
Peat. Louise is a keeper at the Cotswold Wildlife Park, Burford, Oxon.
0X18 4JW, UK. Tel:01993 823006/Fax:01993 823807/ Website:
www. cotswoldwildlifepark. co. uk
</reference>
<page confidence="0.995956" page_id="56265700"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
127
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.905725" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265700" page_num="127" year="" vol="">
RAISING OSTRICH CHICKS AT POTAWATOMI ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.707932666666667" page_id="56265700"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
by Greg Bockheim
Introduction
On June 23rd 2001, seven one and two day old ostrich chicks Struthio
spp. were acquired by the Potawatomi Zoo, Indiana, USA. Details of their
weights and food consumption were recorded from the time of their arrival
to the time they were returned to their owners, 90 days later, on September
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.836233722222222" page_id="56265700"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
21 st. The chicks were exhibited in a relatively large paddock intended for
hoofstock, with their nearest neighbours being Addax Addax nasomaculatus
on one side and Warthogs Phacochoerus africanus on the other. Zoo visitors
viewed them along the southern boundary of the exhibit, with the northern
boundary being the location of a small barn and indoor stall facilities. A
water-filled moat acted as a barrier at the front of the exhibit. Further details
about their accommodation and husbandry are given later.
Objectives
1. To fill the otherwise empty exhibit (the male Addax being shifted in
with the female during the breeding and gestation periods).
2. To increase the zoo staff's experience of ostrich husbandry.
3. To collect data regarding the chicks' food, water and grit consumption.
4. To collect data regarding aspects of the chicks' behaviour, such as their
impact on the exhibit and regarding their husbandry (e.g. the extent of
their grazing, aggressive tendencies towards each other and their human
caretakers (keepers), potential enrichment opportunities, etc.).
5. To facilitate public relations and media opportunities for the zoo.
6. To encourage visitor education through zoo talks.
</listItem>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.582288">
Husbandry
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970486375" page_id="56265700"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
The chicks were selected by the ranch owners to be raised for sale to
future potential ostrich breeders. All were descendents of hybrids between
the red-necked and blue-necked species S. camelus (and various of its
subspecies (unspecified)) and S. c. molybdophanes. When delivered to the
zoo the chicks were less than 72 hours old, making it necessary to follow
strict husbandry guidelines. These were gleaned from the ostrich owners
and later reviewed and posted in the ostrich stall by the zoo's animal care
team.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.793945333333333" page_id="56265700"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
Care guidelines
Enclosure
1. Please leave the red pig heaters, hanging from the bam ceiling, turned
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.695747">
on at all times.
</figureCaption>
<page confidence="0.997779" page_id="56265701"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
128
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.334673" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265701" page_num="128" year="" vol="">
BOCKHEIM - OSTRICH CHICKS
</sectionHeader>
<listItem confidence="0.890573105263158" page_id="56265701"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
2. Leave the electric blower heater off as well as the bam ventilation system.
3. At night leave on only the barn hall lights, not the stall lights.
4. The chicks' stall will need only to be spot cleaned for the first one to
three weeks.
5. The chicks must not be left out in the rain at any time during the first
month.
6. The heat lamps will need to be raised as the chicks grow taller.
Food and water
1. The chicks will eat very little during the first week. It is unlikely that
food will need to be added to their dishes for the first several days.
2. They will lose weight as their yolk sacs are absorbed and then begin to
gain weight during their second week as their food consumption increases.
3. Diet: provide the chicks with turkey grower and the ground mix (in which
alfalfa is visible) in their respective dishes at all times (add more food to
the dishes when less than three cups of food remain in them).
4. Offer them water only in the shallow dish provided as chicks are prone
to drown in deeper water.
5. Water consumption must be monitored closely. The water dish will have
to be filled frequently (two to four times a day) as their food consumption
and drinking increases. Sprinkle a small amount of clover leaves on the
water and on top of the food to stimulate the chicks to eat and drink.
6. Grit will be sprinkled in the yard once the chicks are given more frequent
access to it. The size of the grit will be increased as the chicks grow
bigger.
Outdoor access
1. During the first few days the chicks should be given access to the outdoor
howdy cage for one to two hours, during which they must be monitored
the entire time. As they grow and become more acclimated to the howdy
cage area they should be monitored throughout the time they are outdoors
(we are uncertain if the domestic cats in the area, which initially showed
interest, will be a danger).
2. Food and water dishes need to be placed outside when the birds are
outside and then brought inside (in the stall with the heat lamps) when
the chicks are brought inside.
3. The more time spent with the chicks, i.e. sitting with them in the howdy
cage or in the stall, the more manageable and human friendly they may
become.
4. Once the chicks are eating and drinking well and coming in and out of
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.9675285" page_id="56265701"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
the barn on their own, the howdy cage can come down and the birds
given access to the entire yard (this is likely to be after approximately
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.480172" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265702" page_num="129" year="" vol="">
BOCKHEIM - OSTRICH CHICKS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998716" page_id="56265702"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
129
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9716325" page_id="56265702"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
one to two weeks). The chicks should be weighed again before being
given access to the large yard.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.716392333333333" page_id="56265702"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
5. The fence keeping the chicks away from the water-filled moat must
remain in place the entire time that the birds are at the zoo. Though they
might drink the water and swim in it, it is likely they would be unable to
get out of the water and could therefore become exhausted and drown.
Closing up at night
1. The chicks must be brought in every night. Gradually herd them from
behind (with arms out, like when herding the flamingos) and they will
slowly go indoors.
2. Confine them for the night in the single stall with the heat lamps, until it
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.948886035714286" page_id="56265702"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
is decided that they can be allowed into both stalls. Be sure to place the
board at the base of the interior shift door, between the stalls, to block
the gap.
As the chicks grew and became more familiar with the husbandry routine,
it became easier to shift them into the indoor stalls. By the time they were
30 days old, the keeper could simply enter the yard, kneel on the ground at
the stall entrance, pick at the ground with her hand, and the chicks would
come running to investigate. The birds would then follow the keeper indoors.
This proved to be the quickest and safest way to shift the birds.
Ostrich exhibit
Site preparation
The paddock selected for the ostrich chicks was first inspected by the
owners to check for anything that might affect the birds' well being.
Containment parameters were determined and it was decided to give the
group of ostrich chicks access to half of the unoccupied hoofstock paddock.
The yard was then gone over carefully with metal detectors. A 4ft (approx.
1.2m) tall lin (2.5cm) hexagon vinyl-coated chicken wire fence was placed
diagonally from the stall entrance to the foremost western corner of the
exhibit. This effectively cut down the space available to the chicks and kept
them more to the front of the exhibit for increased visitor viewing. It also
allowed the keepers to run the chicks into the stall in the evening, the idea
being that the birds would follow the fence leading them directly to the
indoor stalls.
The open-topped howdy cage made from fencing stakes and the same
lin (2.5cm) hexagon vinyl-coated wire was constructed in the outside yard
at the stall entrance. It was 20ft (approx. 6m) in diameter and used to
introduce the chicks to the yard during their first week. The chicks were
also able to become familiar with the husbandry routine that included shifting
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994326" page_id="56265703"  page_num="130" year="" vol="">
130
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.814948" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265703" page_num="130" year="" vol="">
BOCKHEIM - OSTRICH CHICKS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997111333333333" page_id="56265703"  page_num="130" year="" vol="">
them indoors and outdoors, as well as food, water and grit presentation, and
animal and visitor activity in the area. This was also the time when the
keepers and chicks could familiarise themselves with each other.
It was felt initially that wild birds of prey, namely Great Horned Owls
Bubo virginianus and Red-tailed Hawks Buteo jamaicensis, living in the
park and surrounding area might be a threat to the tiny chicks. However, at
no time were native raptors observed to take an interest in them. This was
also true of the other prowlers found in the zoo grounds, such as cats,
Raccoons Procyon lotor and opossums Didelphis sp.
The ostrich owners felt that the chicks would drink from the water-filled
moat and might even swim in it, given the opportunity. The danger would
be the birds' inability to climb out of the moat because of its steep sides.
Also, it continues along the fronts of three other hoofstock paddocks and
there would be nothing to prevent the birds swimming its entire length. Our
solution to these problems was to install welded wire pig fencing, 2ft 8in
(approx. 81cm) tall, 1ft (approx. 30cm) back from the moat. Both barriers,
the chicken wire and the pig wire, proved effective in confining the chicks
from the time they were tiny until they reached 90 days of age, when they
were approximately 5ft (about 1.5m) tall, and were returned to their owners.
Chick rearing parameters
Ostrich chicks can be reared on a sand or straw substrate. It is important
that this remains the same while they are being reared. Placing chicks on a
new substrate once they have grown accustomed to another may confuse
them and they may consume the new or foreign substrate. It was decided to
raise our chicks on straw. The existing crushed limestone covering the floors
of both indoor stalls was covered with straw to a depth of 6in (approx. 15cm).
A 3ft (approx. 90cm) square x 2ft 6in (approx. 76cm) tall wood frame draped
with a lightweight black plastic tarp was placed in the heated stall to simulate
a parent bird. This was believed to have a calming effect on the chicks and
to provide a hiding place for them should they feel the need for this. However,
the chicks seemed to pay little attention to it and on only one occasion was
a chick observed to sit with its head beneath it. Two ceramic pig heaters
were hung 2ft 6in (76cm) from the floor and 2ft (61cm) apart.
The howdy cage had the typical grass and earth floor found at most
paddock barn entrances. The paddock itself, to which the chicks were
eventually given all-day access, had a dense covering of pasture grasses and
clover. This was mowed to 4in (10cm) high several days before the chicks
were released into the paddock. Constant grazing by the birds meant that
no further upkeep was necessary.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.479939" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265704" page_num="131" year="" vol="">
BOCKHEIM - OSTRICH CHICKS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996321" page_id="56265704"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
131
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.520589">
Feeding
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.961469043478261" page_id="56265704"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
Those familiar with ratites know that ostriches will consume just about
anything, be it food or foreign objects. When rearing ostrich chicks additional
considerations come into play, such as how food and water are presented to
the chicks, so that these are recognisable to them. When newly hatched
they are often less than 1ft (30.5cm) tall and water dishes more than lin
(2.5cm) deep may be one of the greatest dangers to them, not only because
they could drowned in them but also because they may fail to learn to reach
over the top into deeper dishes, causing the chicks to quickly dehydrate.
Much the same is true for feeding dishes, which must be easy for the chicks
to feed from. As the chicks grow, larger dishes are needed to accommodate
the larger quantities of food necessary to maintain their rapid growth. When
the food and water dishes are replaced by larger dishes, the birds must be
carefully monitored to make sure that they eat and drink from these normally
as before. Our food dish or bowl size (when the chicks were 3ft plus (approx.
1m) tall) eventually increased to the industry standard black rubber tubs 4 m
(10cm) deep (two being used), with water being provided in 1ft (30.5cm)
deep tubs of the same make.
Food consumption
The table below reviews the amounts of food consumed by the seven
ostrich chicks during their 90 days at the zoo. Very little food was eaten
during the chicks' initial 10 days but the amounts soon increased as the
birds began to grow faster. The total cost estimate for this was $304.74 (just
over #200).
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.987908">
Table 1. Food consumption 1-90 days of age.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.950585888888889" page_id="56265704"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
Age in days/Mo of days
Food consumed
Grit consumed
1-28/28
2001b starter
441b grind
501b small ratite grit
at the end of 55 days
29-55/27
1501b starter
100 lb grind
501b medium size ratite
grit up to 90 days of age
56-79/23
5301b grind
80-90/11
4021b grind
Commercially made Mutrena(TM) turkey starter (28% protein) and a grind
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.990173666666667" page_id="56265704"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
mix (19% protein) made by the ostrich owners (largely from alfalfa, ground
com, soy meal and vitamin and mineral additives) were offered to the chicks
during their first two months. By the middle to the end of their second
month, the chicks were weaned gradually onto eating just the grind mix.
This feeding regime proved effective in raising healthy ostrich chicks, as
well as being far more economical, because the grind mix is produced by
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.990802" page_id="56265705"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
132
</page>
<figure confidence="0.3063485" page_id="56265705"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
BOCKHEIM - OSTRICH CHICKS
&amp;apos;
Jason Jacobs
Two ostrich chicks
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.949189821428571" page_id="56265705"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
the grower at a cost far below that of commercially manufactured diets.
Adult, farm-raised ostriches, are recorded as eating approx. 81bs (3.6kg) of
commercially produced ratite pellets per days.
Freshly ground batches of grind mix were picked up twice a week. The
chicks would consume less of this if it became old and stale. Grit was
scattered in the howdy cage and then in the paddock nearly every two days
throughout their stay at the zoo. It was suggested that the birds should from
the time they were 60 days of age, also be offered grit in a bowl. However,
we found that the chicks ignored this, therefore, we simply continued to
scatter grit in the paddock, to avoid digestive and impaction problems.
During their first four weeks the chicks were offered their food and water
in stainless steel pans lOin x 1ft 2in x lin deep (approx. 25.5cm x 35.5cm x
2.5cm deep), after which the chicks were fed from the 4in (10cm) deep
black rubber hoofstock tubs mentioned earlier, which were approximately
2ft (60cm) in diameter. When the chicks were approximately 50 days of
age, water was offered in the larger black rubber tubs. The husbandry
protocol required that the chicks always had food and water before them.
To achieve this, food and water were placed in the paddock when the birds
were locked outside and were then brought into the indoor stall when the
chicks were brought in at night. Several times each day the keeper checked
that the birds had sufficient food and water. If there was still a large quantity
of food remaining, the keeper would stir the food and add more water to the
water bowls. Stirring the food would stimulate the chicks to eat and drink.
The water bowls needed to be refilled more frequently on very hot days.
As the birds increased in size so did their wastefulness and larger
quantities of food would be tossed on the surrounding ground by them. We
estimated that approximately 10%-15% of the food fed to them during the
90 day period was wasted in this manner.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.479986" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265706" page_num="133" year="" vol="">
BOCKHEIM - OSTRICH CHICKS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998589" page_id="56265706"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
133
</page>
<author confidence="0.492033">
Jason Jacobs
</author>
<bodyText confidence="0.975464875" page_id="56265706"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
The author with two chicks
Weighing chicks
As can be imagined weighing young ostrich chicks is far easier than
weighing adults. Small chicks can be placed in a bucket on a scale. As they
grow they can be hand-held and weighed, with the handler's weight then
being subtracted. Once they are larger a sock can be placed over their heads
and then they can be walked backwards onto a scale. This is sometimes
more easily done by holding the bird's neck while walking it backwards.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.902037">
Table 2. Chick weights (in pounds - lib = 0.453kg).
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.888263857142857" page_id="56265706"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
Age and Weight
Specimen ID #
1-2 days
16-17days
36-37 days
90-91 days
21
2
4.8
12.2
77
22
2.2
3.2
73
23
1.7
4
74
24
2.2
1.4
74
25
1.8
4.7
86
41
2
4.8
12.2
75
45
2.3
4.6
</figure>
<page confidence="0.816065" page_id="56265706"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
83
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.404254">
Enrichment
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.984744" page_id="56265706"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
Actively motivating captive animals, especially those in zoos and
educational settings, positively benefits not only the animals, but also sparks
interest in the person or persons observing the behaviour. Such motivation
translates into enrichment.
Various enrichment strategies were implemented during the chick rearing
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999493" page_id="56265707"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
134
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.325453" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265707" page_num="134" year="" vol="">
BOCKHEIM - OSTRICH CHICKS
</sectionHeader>
<tableCaption confidence="0.97148">
Table 3. Enrichment activities on a scale of 1-5.
</tableCaption>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.52941225">
Enrichment Item
Enrichment defined
Success
Rating
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8719588" page_id="56265707"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
Broccoli stem or
corn on the cob
Broccoli stem or corn cob tied onto string
and hung from stall wall or fence at just
below birds' eye (pecking) level.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.617635" page_id="56265707"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
5
</page>
<figure confidence="0.849559" page_id="56265707"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
Broccoli stem or
com cob
Fed in food bowl.
4
Small cherry
tomatoes and
grapes
Fed as a training tool to bring birds into
arms' reach in order to reduce their
apprehension of approaching keepers.
5
Kale or tossed
greens
Chopped and fed in large bowls.
4
Raking exhibit
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.7316305">
Chicks followed and occasionally peck at
keeper, rake and detritus.
</figureCaption>
<page confidence="0.777877" page_id="56265707"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
4
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.558825">
Sprinkler
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.947005" page_id="56265707"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
On warm days a sprinkler was turned on
in the exhibit and the birds bathed in the
spray.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.889158" page_id="56265707"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
5
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.885364333333333" page_id="56265707"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
Red ball
Children's ball about half the size of a
soccer ball was placed in the exhibit. The
birds' initial interest quickly dwindled but
they frequently reinvestigated the ball
throughout the day.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.969635" page_id="56265707"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
4
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.612141">
Shift training
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97353975" page_id="56265707"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
Any enrichment food including tomatoes,
chopped kale, corn or broccoli was placed
in a stall attracting the birds to shift into
the area.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.666268" page_id="56265707"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
5
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.7180975" page_id="56265707"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
Mirror
Medium sized mirrors were hung in the
exhibit and were occasionally investigated
by the birds.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.807663" page_id="56265707"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
3
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.935765714285714" page_id="56265707"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
Incidental pond
misting
A continuous flow of water produced a
strong breeze and fine mist that sprayed
into the front of the ostrich exhibit. When
the birds discovered this they were
frequently seen frolicking in the spray.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.938641" page_id="56265707"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
5
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.480179" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265708" page_num="135" year="" vol="">
BOCKHEIM - OSTRICH CHICKS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999085" page_id="56265708"  page_num="135" year="" vol="">
135
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.989952761904762" page_id="56265708"  page_num="135" year="" vol="">
process. Each of these achieved varying degrees of success. Training birds
to shift from stall to stall and from indoors to outdoors could also be
considered as enrichment, as it motivated them to act (i.e. walk, trot and run
to a given area). Offering various common and strange food items, some in
unusual manners or as rewards, were part of the birds' daily enrichment
activities. The table (on the opposite page) lists some of the enrichments
implemented and their success ratings. All were implemented once the chicks
had passed 30 days of age, when their size had increased and they had become
familiar with their surroundings and their daily staple diet.
Summary
Raising ostrich chicks from one and two days of age proved to be an
exciting challenge and a great success for Potawatomi Zoo. The knowledge
shared with us by the ostrich breeders enabled the project to succeed without
incident. The projects earlier stated objectives all obtained high ratings.
The chicks provided exceptional photo and film opportunities for the media
and allowed close-up viewing by zoo supporters. Raising these birds from
such a young age gave zoo volunteers and visitors a unique opportunity to
learn about these ratites during the energetic and quirky days of their youth,
an experience not often available in a zoo setting. During their stay the
chicks led healthy and active lives and did not present any significant medical
problems.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.857301" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56265708" page_num="135" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98097323076923" page_id="56265708"  page_num="135" year="" vol="">
I would like to thank the owners of the ostrich chicks, Nick Stama and
Todd Femwalt, for their confidence in the zoo staff's ability to undertake
this project, for providing for the dietary needs of the birds and for making
themselves available for consultation. I would also like to thank the animal
care team at Potawatomi Zoo, especially Jeri Ellis, Fred Wagner, Jeremy
Goodman, Laura Arriaga, Debbie Shepperd and Stephanie Miller, for the
exceptional care they provided for these birds. Thanks also to Jason Jacobs
for his photographs and Zoo Director Clarence Wright for his support of
this project.
If you would like further information, Greg Bockheim, General Curator,
can he contacted via e-mail: Gregbockheim@aol.com or at Potawatomi
Zoo, 500 South Greenlawn, South Bend, Indiana 46615, USA. Tel:(219)
235-9800/Fax:(219) 235-9080.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999393" page_id="56265709"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
136
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993876666666667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56265709" page_num="136" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
VOLUME SEVEN OF HANDBOOK OF THE BIRDS OF
THE WORLD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994474" page_id="56265709"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
It is increasingly difficult to add anything to the superlatives that have
greeted the first six volumes of the Handbook of the Birds of the World.
Now comes number seven - effectively the volume which propelled what I
believe was to have been a 12 volume set into a 16 volume odyssey. Nothing
wrong with that. The additional volumes are certain to make a further
significant contribution to our knowledge of the world's birds.
This particularly spectacular volume deals with some of the world's most
eye-catching and colourful families - Jacamars, Puffbirds, Barbets, Toucans,
Honeyguides and Woodpeckers. It is in every sense a 'big book' in size,
weight and content, including superlative colour plates and hundreds of
colour photographs of birds in the wild. Its publication marks the conclusion
of material about non-passerine species; Volume 8, to be published in 2003,
will cover Broadbills, Asities, Ovenbirds, Woodcreepers, Antbirds, Antpittas,
Tapalucos, Gnateaters, Cotingas and Manakins.
Volume 7 includes 317 outstanding colour photographs of birds in the
wild taken by some of the world's leading wildlife photographers. The 70
colour plates have been painted by Hilary Burn, Clive Byers, Ian Lewington,
Tim Worfolk, Albert Earl Gilbert, lan Willis, Dave Numey, Chris Rose, John
Cox, Mark Hulme and Angels Jutglar. There are also 408 distribution maps
and an informative 50-page foreword about extinct birds contributed by
Errol Fuller.
The text is, as usual, impeccable, informative, scientifically accurate
and remarkably readable - the latter a rare and utterly commendable feature
of a work of this substance. For those unfamiliar with these volumes it is
worth noting that each family is treated to a very comprehensive introduction
which is arranged under the headings Systematics, Morphological Aspects,
Habitat, General Habits, Voice, Food and Feeding, Breeding, Movements,
Status and Conservation. These are illustrated with colour photographs.
All species accounts are accompanied with colour plates which, where
necessary, take account of sexual dimorphism and distinctive subspecies.
The amount of detail contained in these narratives is remarkable. Concise
but detailed information about habitat, food and feeding, breeding, status
and conservation - plus a useful introductory paragraph which deals with
taxonomic aspects - and despite the extremely high quality of colour plates,
detailed descriptive notes are provided throughout.
So far as the photographs are concerned they at least match, and perhaps
enhance, the high standards achieved in preceding volumes. Many are
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909714" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265710" page_num="137" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998818" page_id="56265710"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
137
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99646347826087" page_id="56265710"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
exciting, some are remarkable and one can only wonder what time and skill
lies behind acquisition of the images. I particularly like a picture by Bernard
van Elegem of a pair of Coppersmith Barbets Megalaima haemacephala
indica photographed high in the branches of a dead tree in Thailand's Kaeng
Krachan National Park.
Also worth a second look are three digitally coloured pictures of the
now extinct Ivory-billed Woodpecker Campephilus principalis photographed
in Louisiana during the 1930s by James T. Tanner who studied some of the
last breeding pairs in the USA. There are many excellent pictures of flickers,
piculets and woodpeckers at the nest, in some cases feeding well-grown
young - but then, these birds have always tended to be amenable subjects as
they cling tenaciously to the bark below their nest hole. There are many
more superb photographs enhancing a further magnificent volume from Lynx
Edicions.
As a gift to purchasers of Volume 7, Lynx Edicions are including with
each volume a handy, plasticised index of all non-passerine groups. With
pictures and a list of the names of all bird groups covered in HBW to date,
this index makes it easy to locate exactly where in the seven volumes so far
published any given non-passerine group is dealt with. A nice touch.
Handbook of the Birds of the World Volume 7, Jacamars to Woodpeckers,
edited by J. del Hoyo, A. Elliot &amp; J. Sargatal, is published by Lynx Edicions,
Montseny, 8, E-08193 Bellaterra, Barcelona, Spain. It is priced #110. Further
information, samples and ordering are available online at :www.hbw.com
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.555605">
Frank Woolham
</subsectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.841788" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56265710" page_num="137" year="" vol="">
ESTRILDXD FINCHES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985412571428571" page_id="56265710"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
Hancock House Encyclopedia of Estrildid Finches by Matthew
M. Vriends and Tanya M. Heming-Vriends is an attractive and well produced
title. As expected in an encyclopedia, the text is detailed and informative.
It is divided into two main parts. The first covers the origins of the
Estrildid finches and the requirements for their aviculture. This extends
from management to illness, nutrition and breeding. In the chapter on
breeding, the authors rightly warn of the dangers of crossbreeding and
producing hybrids. With the current situation of ever increasing restrictions
on bird importations, they remind aviculturists of the need to maintain clear
groups of bird species, to provide a breeding nucleus for the future. This
part of the text is supported by some excellent colour photos showing all the
materials required for Estrildid husbandry, from aviaries to seeds.
The second part consists of detailed profiles of the Estrildid species.
This part includes some superb colour photos. These include many interesting
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998834" page_id="56265711"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
138
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.971802" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265711" page_num="138" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.979916714285714" page_id="56265711"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
and seldom seen subjects, such as subspecies of the Green-backed Twinspot
(shown together on the same page), nestlings of the Vinaceous Firefinch,
munias and Australian finches.
There are two classification lists, Vriends (after Wolters et al.) p.254 and
Sibley, Ahlquist and Monroe, p.255. The publication details for these lists
are not included in the Bibliography and I was suiprised to see that Derek
Goodwin's Estrildidfinches of the world (British Museum (Natural History)
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.688270142857143" page_id="56265711"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
&amp; Oxford University Press, 1982) is also not included.
Hancock House Encyclopedia of Estrildid Finches (ISBN 0-88839-493=
4) is a hardback volume. It has 264 pages, 344 colour photos and over 100
line illustrations. It is published by Hancock House Publishers, 1431 Harrison
Avenue, Blaine, WA 98230-5005, USA. It is priced US$60.00 and can be
ordered online at: www.hancockhouse.com or email: sales@hancockhouse.com
Jeffrey Trollope
</listItem>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.284742" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56265711" page_num="138" year="" vol="">
DUCKS, GEESE AND TURKEYS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.952418" page_id="56265711"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
Victoria Roberts has produced another gem - Ducks, Geese and Turkeys
for anyone - which deals with more than 50 breeds of these domestic birds.
Ducks command the major share of this informative book, followed by geese
and turkeys. It may not be immediately apparent that you are on a learning
curve as you read the author's often amusing but always informative accounts
of how to care for birds ranging from call duck to - so far as I am concerned
- unheard of turkey breeds such as the Nebraskan Spotted and Narragansett.
Victoria - Tor to her many friends in aviculture, farming, conservation
and other activities connected with the countryside - is now up among the
bestsellers in her field. This is not a boring volume which expounds the
need for dropping board cleanliness and how to avoid red mite. Rather it is
an exposition of the joys of keeping domestic poultry - coupled with some
cautionary notes about the perils involved.
The text is bright, breezy and informative. Michael Corrigan's 90 colour
photographs are a beautiful complement to the words. It&amp;apos;s a good book!
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.85463">
Ducks, Geese and Turkeys for anyone , by Victoria Roberts BVSc,
MRCVS costs #19.99 and is published by Whittet Books Limited, Hill Farm,
Stonham Road, Cotton, Stowmarket, Suffolk IP 14 4RQ, UK. It is available
from all good booksellers.
Frank Woolham
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998939" page_id="56265712"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
139
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.978469" genericHeader="method" page_id="56265712" page_num="139" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
CONGRATULATIONS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970719777777778" page_id="56265712"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
Members will wish to congratulate Mike Curzon on the award of the
MBE (Member of the British Empire) in the Queen's Golden Jubilee birthday
honours list. Mike, an Avicultural Society Council Member and until its
closure a director of The Tropical Bird Gardens, Rode, Somerset, received
his award for "services to the prevention of bird smuggling." He continues
to keep a small collection of birds of his own, including Grey Hornbills
Tockus nasutus , fruit pigeons, Orange headed Ground Thrushes Zoothera
citrina , tanagers, sugarbirds and breeding Red-flanked Lorikeets
Charmosyna placentis.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.778667" page_id="56265712"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.870616" genericHeader="method" page_id="56265712" page_num="139" year="" vol="">
LONG LOST PARROT REDISCOVERED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9990685" page_id="56265712"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
After months of searching, an expedition from Bogota University has
succeeded in finding a flock of 14 Fuertes's Parrots Hapalopsittacafuertesi
near the summit of the highest volcano in Colombia. It is thought to be the
first definite sighting of this species since 1911, when seven were captured
by American ornithologists near the peak of the same volcano.
All subsequent expeditions had failed to find this species again, until
July 28th this year, when Jorge Velasquez and his team of ornithologists
found the parrots 10,000ft (approx. 3,000m) up the densely vegetated
volcano, which is often shrouded in mist. Expedition members took detailed
notes, photographs, video footage and sound recordings of the birds and
will develop a plan to save the colourful Fuertes's Parrot and its habitat.
It has also been reported that Renato Gaban-Lima and Marcos Raposo,
graduate students at the University of Sao Paulo, Brazil, believe they have
discovered a new species of parrot. The orange beaded birds, thought
previously to be immature Vulturine Parrots Gypopsitta vulturina, have been
given the scientific name Pionopsitta aurantiocephala.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.659081" page_id="56265712"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.985221" genericHeader="method" page_id="56265712" page_num="139" year="" vol="">
SUCCESS WITH THE BUCK TOWN SUCKIE'
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998235444444444" page_id="56265712"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
An account in Cage &amp; Aviary Birds (July 20th issue), described how UK
aviculturist Peter Blake had to date this year bred six Burnished Buff Tanagers
Tangara cayana from three clutches, having bred a single female last year.
He put his success breeding this species and the Blue-headed I cyanicollis
down to providing the parents with large quantities of soft-skinned white
mealworms. The Burnish Buff Tanager was first bred in the UK by H.
Murray in 1961. Called then Cayenne Tanagers, his birds were imported
from what was then British Guiana (now Guyana), where the species was
said to be known as the &amp;apos;Buck Town Suckie'.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995338" page_id="56265713"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
140
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9820035" genericHeader="method" page_id="56265713" page_num="140" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
AFTER A LONG ABSENCE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.963183666666667" page_id="56265713"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
A pair of Choughs Pyrrhocorax pyrrhocorax, thought to have originated
from Ireland, which have settled on the cliff-tops at Kynance Cove, west
Cornwall, earlier this year hatched four young, three of which were reared
to independence. All three are said to be males. It was the first time for at
least 50 years that this member of the Crow family has nested in Cornwall
or anywhere else in England. Also this year, for the first time in almost 50
years, a pair of Bee-eaters Merops apiaster nested in England, in a disused
quarry in a nature reserve at Bishops Middleham, near Sedgefield, County
Durham.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.799394833333333" page_id="56265713"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
* * *
NEW TITLES
A &amp; C Black has acquired T &amp; A D Poyser and Academic Press Natural
World from Elsevier Science. In doing so, it has acquired a backlist of some
70 titles, which will he integrated into the Christopher Helm division of
A &amp; C Black.
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.9845817" page_id="56265713"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
The seventh and final volume of Birds of Africa will be published in
2004, followed a couple of years later by, Birds of Madagascar, a companion
volume in the same format. There are also plans for a major new Field
Guide to the Birds of Northeast Africa (Ethiopia, Eritrea, Somalia and Sudan),
the first comprehensive guide to the birds of the islands of Melanesia and
the third edition, by far the biggest yet, of Howard &amp; Moore's Checklist of
the Birds of the World (scheduled for next year).
The second volume of Birds of the Thai-Malay Peninsula is also expected
shortly and there are plans for a field guide to African raptors and a 10-CD
guide to East African Bird Sounds.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.5587355" page_id="56265713"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
* * *
AFTER 50 YEARS OF TRYING
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.8833165" page_id="56265713"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
After 50 years of trying, the Wildfowl and Wetlands Trust, Slimbridge,
Glos., has succeeded in breeding the White-backed Duck Thalassornis
leuconotus. Six ducklings were hatched. There are said to be only 28 White-
backed Ducks in UK collections.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.180785" page_id="56265713"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.296951" genericHeader="method" page_id="56265713" page_num="140" year="" vol="">
SEPTEMBER CLOSURES
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.743753142857143">
Hillside Bird Oasis, Mobberley, Cheshire, where in 1999 the Lesser
Flamingo Phoeniconaias minor bred for the first time in the UK ( Avicultural
Magazine Vol.106, No.3, pp. 126-128 (2000)), has closed to visitors. In
future it will act as a private breeding centre for Blackbrook Zoological
Park, near Leek, Staffordshire. September also witnessed the closure of
Gatwick Zoo, credited with having been the first collection in the UK to
breed the Military Macaw Ara militaris.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700229" genericHeader="method" page_id="56265714" page_num="141" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995962" page_id="56265714"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
141
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993665" genericHeader="method" page_id="56265714" page_num="141" year="" vol="">
UNPRECENDENTED INTEREST
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.94941" page_id="56265714"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
To allay many South African farmers' concerns about the potential impact
of animal dips on oxpeckers Buphagus spp., the Poison Working Group
(PWG) there has compiled a chart that lists every animal dip on the market
and indicates which are safe to oxpeckers and this information is also included
now on the labels of all animal dips on sale in South Africa. This has triggered
unprecendented interest in these birds and the PWG has designed a protocol
to attract and keep oxpeckers on farms. All the information is combined in
the latest edition of the Oxpecker Compatibility Chart available from the
Poison Working Group, PO. Box 72334, Parkview 2122, South Africa.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.603783" page_id="56265714"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.658841" genericHeader="method" page_id="56265714" page_num="141" year="" vol="">
PAINTED BUNTING UPDATE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9809408" page_id="56265714"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
Preliminary data analysis by Eduardo E. Inigo-Elias, Kenneth V.
Rosenberg and Jeffrey V. Wells at Cornell Laboratory of Ornithology
(.Birdscope Summer 2002/Volume 16, Number 3), reveals that for the
domestic market in Mexico alone, more than 100,000 Painted Buntings
Passerina ciris were trapped between 1984 and 2000, an average of 5,800
per year. This does not include those trapped illegally. Illegal trapping is
said to be commonplace, but it is of course impossible to put a figure on the
number of birds involved.
The export of wild caught birds from Mexico was banned from 1982-
1999. Since the ban was lifted, more than 6,000 Painted Buntings have
been exported to Belgium, Italy, Germany, the Netherlands, Greece, Spain
and Japan. It is those of the larger western population P. c. pallidior that are
subject to trapping for the bird trade in Mexico. This population migrates
first to so-called staging areas in south-western USA and north-western
Mexico, before flying on to its wintering grounds in southern Mexico, Belize,
Guatemala, Honduras, El Salvador, Nicaragua, Costa Rica and Panama. The
eastern population moults on its breeding grounds just before migrating to
southern Florida and the Caribbean islands. Because the two populations
are isolated from each other, moult at different times and vary in other ways,
it has been suggested that they should in fact be treated as two distinct species.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.70913325" page_id="56265714"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
* * *
DR JEAN-MARIE DERSCHEID (1901-1944)
Raymond Sawyer (p. 100) mentioned that at the outbreak of the Second
World War, John Yealland was looking after the private collection of Dr J.
</table>
<reference confidence="0.9928896">
M. Derscheid in Belgium. I recently received an enquiry about Jean-Marie
Derscheid, it came from Daniel A. Reboussin, Ph.D., Assistant Bibliographer,
Africana Collection, George A. Smathers Libraries, Dept, of Special and
Area Studies Collections, University of Florida. He wanted to know if I
could confirm that Jean-Marie Derscheid had been a member of the
</reference>
<page confidence="0.99856" page_id="56265715"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
142
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.889236" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265715" page_num="142" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985431487804878" page_id="56265715"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Society and whether I could provide him with a description of
an article by Dr Derscheid which had been published postumously in the
magazine in 1947?
I was able to confirm that Dr Derscheid had been a member of the society
and with the help of Daniel Shearing was able to trace three articles by him
that were published in the magazine that year. These were: The Charm of
Small Waders in Captivity (Vol.53, No. 1, p.8, continued No. 5, p.145);
Strange Parrots - 1. The Kea (No. 2, p.44); The Goldeneye in Captivity (No.
6, p. 217). By coincidence, a few days earlier I had come upon a reference
to Dr Derscheid in News &amp; Views, Vol.77, No.5,pp. 177-178(1971). Arthur
Prestwich had written: "Mention of Keas in the last number of the Magazine
is a remainder that before the War the late Dr. Derscheid had a pair in his
extensive collection at Sterrebeek, of which John Yealland was curator. 13th
March is a date imprinted on the memory of some older Members of the
Society, for on that day in 1944 Jean Marie Eugene Derscheid, the father of
our present Hon. Fellow Jean-Pierre, was shot, after thirty months'
imprisonment in Germany, as a political prisoner. Dr. Derscheid was in the
forefront of the Resistance Movement and took a major part in the Escape
Service. Many British and American servicemen have particular cause to
be very grateful to Dr. Derscheid for his incalculable help. And at how
great a cost to himself."
I was curious as to why Dr Derscheid had aroused the interest of the
Africana Collection, until Daniel Reboussin told me that in the university
library there is on microfilm a master negative of Dr Derscheid's scholarly
notes and papers on Rwandan history. He in turn had been surprised to
learn that Dr Derscheid had been a noted aviculturist, as there is no evidence
of his ornithological or any biological interests on the microfilm. It would
be of great interest to him to learn if any of Dr Derscheid's work on birds
has been preserved and, if so, where it is to be found?
Dr Reboussin has begun a webpage - http://www.uflib.ufl.edu/cm/
africana/derscheid.htm - documenting his research on Dr Derscheid, who
he describes as "a very impressive individual who exhibited distinction in
so many areas of his rather short life." According to the webpage Dr
Derscheid was beheaded in Brandenburg Prison, Berlin. He is also mentioned
briefly on another website: http://home.clara.net/clinchy/index.htm
In John James Yealland 1904-1983 (Avicultural Magazine Vol.89, No.2,
p. 111 (1983)), Mary Harvey recalled how in 1940 "John managed to get on
one of the last boats leaving before the German invasion. Whilst the other
refugees on the crowded boat were clutching their precious belongings, John
doggedly nursed a pair of rare ducks in a cardboard box all the way back to
safety in England."
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700237" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265716" page_num="143" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998357" page_id="56265716"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
143
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.994355" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56265716" page_num="143" year="" vol="">
FOUND IN EMU
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996587375" page_id="56265716"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
The Masked Plover Vanellus miles , which has in recent years become a
familiar bird in many collections, in 1994 extended it range to New Caledonia
(home of the Kagu Rhynochetos jubatus). The first record of it breeding
there was confirmed in 1998,though it probably bred there first two years
earlier, reports Nicholas Banc in Emu Vol.102, No,3, pp.313 314 (2002).
In the same issue (pp.223-231), Olsen, Wink, Sauer-Gurth and Trost report
the discovery of a new species of owl on the island of Sumba, Indonesia.
Their report is illustrated by some good colour photos of the species, named
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.710976" page_id="56265716"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
the Little Sumba Hawk-Owl Ninox sumbaensis.
* * *
TROGONS BREED IN AQUARIUM
The White-tailed Trogon Trogon viridis, bred first in captivity in 1995 at
Vogelpark Walsrode, Germany, Now a pair is breeding in the walk-through
neotropical rainforest display at the National Aquarium in Baltimore,
Maryland, USA. Three young were reared successfully earlier this year.
This species bred there first in 2000, when a chick found outside the nest
was hand-reared. Last year two chicks were successfully raised by the parents.
* * *
SACRED SIGHTING
Earlier this year a Sacred Ibis Threskiornis aethiopicus was seen at
Moreton Lakes, Astbury, near Congleton, Cheshire, UK. Later, what was
thought to be the same escapee, was seen and photographed in the car park
of Staffordshire University, Stoke-on-Trent,
* * *
THIRD (REVISED) EDITION
Australian Parrots by Joseph M, Forshaw and William T. Cooper has
</table>
<reference confidence="0.787963666666667">
recently been published in a Third (Revised) Edition under the Alexander
Editions imprint, a division of Avi Trader Publishing. The trade edition is
priced AU$149.95 plus AU$12.05 postage and handling (with an additional
AU$20.05 for overseas shipping). Further information is available from
Avi-Trader Publishing Pty. Ltd., Suite 351, Locked Bag 1, Robina Town
Centre, Queensland 4230, Australia. Tel:+61 7 55 620 870/Fax: +61 7 55
620 849. It can be purchased online at:www.australianparrots.com The
above is also the new postal address of Pet &amp; Aviary Birds incorporating
Australian Am-Trader (new websiteiwww.petandaviarybirds.com).
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999541" page_id="56265717"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
144
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.502639">
Egg Food
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.966073" page_id="56265717"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
WITTE MOLEN Eggfood is a
complimentary food enjoyed by all seed-
eating birds. This food contains the
correct amount of vitamins, minerals and
the essential amino and fatty acids to keep
your birds in good health.
Witte Molen Eggfood is composed of
light digestable egg products, bakery
products and various seeds. This food is
made from the highest quality products to
ensure your birds are maintained at their
optimal standard.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.9345225" page_id="56265717"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
5kg Tub #16.95
2 Tubs 10kg #28.50
25kg Sack #39.95
Wimo Eggfood Red
5kg Tub #17.95 2 Tubs 10kg #29.95
Parrot Mixes
Frozen Foods
Lorikeet
Nectars
Supplements
Mynah Pellets
Dried Fruits
Berries
Handrearing
Formulas
Universal Food
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.319887" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265717" page_num="144" year="" vol="">
WITTE MOLEN Universal food is a
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.95979" page_id="56265717"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
complete food for insectivorous and fruit
eating birds. This ideal nutritional blend
contains the right proportion of proteins,
vitamins, minerals and all the essential
amino and fatty acids. This food is
enriched with juniper berries and fresh
water shrimps and also contains honey
and brewers yeast and the correct amount
of vitamin C. With Witte Molen
Universal food you can keep your birds as
healthy and as active as they are in the
wild.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.86163625" page_id="56265717"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
5kg Tub #17.95 2 Tubs 10 kg #29.95
25kg Sack #42.95 Prices include Delivery
Softfood With Fruit
WITTE MOLEN Softfood with fruit is a
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.984154916666667" page_id="56265717"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
complete food for insectivorous and fruit
eating birds such as thrushes, blackbirds,
starlings, turacos, toucans, green
magpies, birds of paradise and jays.
This ideal, balanced diet has a uniquely
low iron content of less than 70ppm. It
contains the right proportion of proteins,
vitamins, minerals and all the essential
amino acids and fatty acids. This food is
enriched with berries and pieces of
papaya, pineapple, figs and apricots. It
also contains honey, brewers yeast and
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.8869344" page_id="56265717"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
vitamin C.
5kg Tub #19.95 2 Tubs 10 kg #34.95
25kg Sack #53.95 Prices include
Delivery
Vitamins &amp; Minerals
Sunbird Nectars
Livefoods
Soak Mixes
Nuts
Eggfoods
Softbill Diets
Straights
Seed Mixtures
Egg Rearing Food With Hedgerow
Plants
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.618358" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56265717" page_num="144" year="" vol="">
WITTE MOLEN Egg Rearing food is a
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.988530833333333" page_id="56265717"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
complimentary food fit for all seed
eating birds. This rearing food has a
unique low iron content and contains all
vitamins, minerals and amino acids in
the right proportions. A mixture of a
selected number of natural herbs is
added, which has a positive influence on
the taste and acceptance by the birds.
Witte Molen Egg Rearingfood is also
gladly eaten by budgerigars and parrots.
Mix with seed to produce a delicious
meal for your parrots.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.743769428571429" page_id="56265717"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
5kg Tub #17.95 2 Tubs 10 kg #29.95
25kg Sack #47.95 Prices include
Delivery
P&amp;P only #4.95 up to 45kg unless included in price (for most postcodes). Rob Harvey Specialist
Feeds, Kookaburra House, Gravel Hill Road, Holt Pound, Famham, Surrey, GU10 4LG, UK.
Tel: 01420 23986 Fax: 01420 23078 E-mail: rob@robharvey.com Website: www:robharvey.com
Sole UK agent for Witte Molen &amp; Avi-Plus All major CC taken
</table>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.912483">
Stop Press
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.953298545454545" page_id="56265718"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Insectivorous Feast already helping
endangered species
Tony Blackler, from the UK, has been having trouble raising
Bali starlings to maturity. But as soon as he used Insectivorous
Feast he produced his first fully weaned chick.
We are particularly pleased with this since Tony is the only
UK breeder to have had this product prior to its launch!
Insectivorous Feast is a low iron product containing all the
unique nutrients of our other Feast products including the
health promoting Flourish herbs.
Another innovative product from The
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.63018880952381" page_id="56265718"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Birdcare Company that really makes a
difference.
photo: Tony Tilford
Your Insectivorous Feast
is a real winner with my
birds. Even species that
don t normally eat
My Mali Firefinches
love your new
Insectivorous Feast.
Ian Hinze.
softfoods are loving it.
Phil Bailey.
The Birdcare Company, 21-22 Spring Mill Ind. Est.,
Avening Road, Nailsworth, Glos., GL6 OBS.
Tel: 0845 130 8600 (local call charge only)
E-mail: advice@BirdcareCo.com, web site:
www.BirdcareCo.com
Birdcare Company products are available by mail order or
through over 200 retailers around the UK and overseas.
Leading the way - naturally
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.977339" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56265719" page_num="" year="" vol="">
SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION LIBRARIES
CONTENTS
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.90101" page_id="56265719"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
3 9088 01769 6477
World of Birds Review 2001/2002
by Isabel Wentzel.
</table>
<page confidence="0.919696" page_id="56265719"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
97
</page>
<construct confidence="0.6670765" page_id="56265719"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Some famous aviculturists I have known
by R. C. J. Sawyer...100
</construct>
<table confidence="0.8943905" page_id="56265719"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Hand-rearing the Black-faced Ibis at the Cots wold Wildlife Park
by Jamie Graham.110
Breeding the Blue-tailed or Banded Pitta Pitta guajana
at Vogelpark Walsrode
by Dieter Rinke and Bemd Marcordes.113
The Great Blue and other turacos
by Louise Peat.123
Raising Ostrich chicks at Potawatomi Zoo
by Greg Bockheim.127
Book Reviews
Handbook of the Birds of the World (Vol. 7).136
Estrildid Finches.137
Ducks, Geese and Turkeys.138
News &amp; Views.139
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</table>
</algorithms>
