<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.6387154" page_id="56293343"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 112
No. 1
2006
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293344" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990837" page_id="56293344"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2006 as for 2005: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.5855" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293344" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.972357" page_id="56293344"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, ARCADIA, THE MOUNTS, TOTNES, DEVON TQ9 7QJ, UK.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TNI3 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail: Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998476" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293344" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982477333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.751158" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293345" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.213354" page_id="56293345"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 112 - No. 1 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2006
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.347872">
The Avicultural Society
</subsectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99027" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293345" page_num="" year="" vol="">
FOR THE STUDY OF BRITISH AND FOREIGN BIRDS
IN THE WILD AND CAPTIVITY
OFFICERS AND COUNCIL
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.72666825" page_id="56293345"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
As from January 1st 2006
President
MISS R.M. EZRA
Vice Presidents
</table>
<construct confidence="0.7130735" page_id="56293345"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
J.M. DOLAN, Jr., Ph.D. (USA) Dr. H. QUINQUE (France)
MRS. D. HOLLOWAY (Britain) R.L. RESTALL (Venezuela)
C.J.S. MARLER (Britain) R.C.J. SAWYER (Britain)
The Rev. R. NOEGEL (USA) Dr. R. WILKINSON (Britain)
</construct>
<figure confidence="0.972499571428571" page_id="56293345"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Honorary Editor
M. ELLIS
Honorary Secretary - Treasurer
P. BOULDEN
Members of Council
R. S. ABREY
P. CONVY
M. CURZON MBE
J.A. ELLIS
MRS. L. GARDNER
R.B. GIRLING
A.V. GRIFFITHS
N. R. HEWSTON
S. PYPER
V.P SARGENT
P. G. SCHOFIELD
J.G. THURLOW
B. TREMLETT
J. TROLLOPE
MS. R. WISEMAN
Chairman C.J.S. MARLER
</figure>
<page confidence="0.899119" page_id="56293346"  page_num="2" year="" vol="">
2
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.74544525" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293346" page_num="2" year="" vol="">
FURTHER SUCCESS WITH THE BROWN TWINSPOT
Clytospiza monteiri INCLUDING THE FIRST
PARENT-REARED YOUNG
by Andy Chaney
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999512111111111" page_id="56293346"  page_num="2" year="" vol="">
Now that I have finally succeeded in breeding parent-reared Brown
Twinspots, albeit just a single brood so far, it is, I feel, a good time to update
my earlier account of breeding this attractive African estrildid. My earlier
account, members may recall, was published in the Avicultural Magazine
Vol. 110, No.l, pp.32-35 (2004) and on that occasion all of the eggs were
hatched under Bengalese and Bengalese also reared all the young.
After the success I achieved in 2002 and after moving home in 2003 and
the subsequent erection of a new birdroom, I was again in a position to plan
a breeding programme for my Brown Twinspots.
The new birdroom measures 20ft x 12ft (approx. 6m x 3.6m) and around
the internal walls has four banks of cages, which with the use of sliders
(slides or partitions) can be subdivided into various lengths or alternatively
they can be removed to create a flight cage that runs along three sides of the
room. A slider inserted into a comer cage, creates a dark, discreet area, into
which the birds can retreat if disturbed.
It was these cages that I put aside for three pairs of Brown Twinspots,
one pair being housed in each of the three cages which measured 3ft 4in
long x 2ft deep x 1ft 8in high (approx. 1m long x 0.6m deep x 0.5m high). A
nest basket was placed on the inside of each of the three cage fronts. They
were facing inwards and inside each of them there was a nest which had
already been built by some Bengalese that I had in a stock cage. I did this
because I had noted on my previous breeding of this species, that I could not
get the birds to build their own nests. They would pick up nesting material,
but would not build a nest, but merely seemed to move the nesting material
around. An inward-facing plastic nest-box was attached to the outside of
each cage and this also had a pre-made nest in it.
This time I hoped to get the twinspots to rear their own young. However,
I first had to wait for the birds to settle down and lay eggs. It seems from
this and my previous experience that this species takes some time to settle
into new surroundings. It was almost three months before they started to
lay and then, strangely, as in the past, all three pairs laid their first clutch
within a week of each other. As I wanted to build up my stock of these
birds, I removed the first round of eggs and placed them under Bengalese.
There were 17 eggs from which 14 young were reared to independence.
Once settled these birds seem to be prolific egg-layers, producing clutches
that range from four to seven eggs.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.751886" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293347" page_num="3" year="" vol="">
CHANEY - BROWN TWINSPOT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.91962" page_id="56293347"  page_num="3" year="" vol="">
3
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.973585206896552" page_id="56293347"  page_num="3" year="" vol="">
The second round soon followed and I left the pairs to incubate their
own eggs and rear their young. Although I found them to be very attentive
parents, they failed to get the chicks past a week old. At no time did I
inspect the nest or disturb the birds except to feed them. I was able, however,
to get a good idea of what was going on, based on my observations of the
adult pairs and the experience I have gained over 25 years of bird keeping.
When the third round was laid, I removed two of the clutches and left
one with the twinspots. The clutch left with the twinspots hatched
successfully and to my delight the chicks were reared to independence. The
incubation period for the eggs placed under the Bengalese was 12-13 days,
with the young fledging at 21 -22 days. In the case of the clutch left with the
twinspots I tried to leave well alone, however, from the birds' behaviour I
would guess that the incubation period was about the same, with the young
fledging a day or two earlier.
Over the past couple of years I have somewhat simplified my softfood
mix. It now consists of lkg (21b 2oz) Cede Tropical, two packets of wheat
germ flakes and X U teaspoon Spirulina. This is mixed dry, then cous cous
which has been soaked overnight is used in the morning to moisten the
softfood mix, to which I then add in frozen buffalo worms and pinkies (but
not huge quantities). The surplus mix is refrigerated and used for the evening
feed.
During the course of the 2005 breeding season, 41 Brown Twinspots
were reared and, although only four of these were parent-reared, I feel that
progress is being achieved.
As described above, the Brown Twinspot Clytospiza monteiri , has again
been bred by Andy Chaney with, on this occasion, four young being parent-
reared. This is probably the first such successful breeding of this species in
Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who knows of a previous such breeding is
asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.744822">
Andy Chaney, who keeps a collection of estrildids, is a UK member who
lives in south Devon.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.909113" page_id="56293348"  page_num="4" year="" vol="">
4
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.955957" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293348" page_num="4" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE SOOTY-HEADED BULBUL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.964376948717949" page_id="56293348"  page_num="4" year="" vol="">
Pycnonotus aurigaster
by Jim Jerrard
In the autumn of 2004, I purchased four Sooty-headed Bulbuls. This
species has a black head with a slight crest, white or dusky white cheeks,
slightly darker dusky white underparts and a yellow or red vent, depending
on the subspecies. My birds have a yellow vent. The upperparts are
brownish-grey, with a whitish patch on the upper tail-coverts; the tail has a
white tip.
This bulbul is a common and widespread resident in south-east Asia,
from Myanmar (Burma) and Thailand eastwards into China and southwards
to Java and Bali; it is said (Strange, 2002) to have been introduced onto
Sumatra and southern Sulawesi, where it is now well established and has
recently been recorded in southern Kalimantan and on Timor. This expansion
is thought to have resulted from escaped cage birds. There seems to be
some question as to whether or not those introduced onto Singapore continue
to survive (King et al. 1976).
Not knowing their sexes, I housed all of my four birds in a flight
measuring 9ft x 3ft x 6ft (approx. 2.7m x 0.9m x 1.8m). All went well
through the winter months, until the end of February, when I found one bird
dead. I left the remaining three birds together, then a week later I found
another of them dead. Unlike the first bird which did not have a mark on it,
the second bird had been pecked about the head. This led me to believe that
the remaining two birds must be a true pair.
In April I put up a nesting tray 7in square x Sin deep (18cm square x
7.5cm deep), into which I had stuffed some hay. In May the two started to
build a nest of coconut fibre and lined it with hessian. The first egg was laid
May 17th and eventually there was a clutch of three eggs. They hatched on
June 1st, after a 12 day incubation period. One chick died the next day, but
the other two survived, fed on buffalo worms, fruit flies, small crickets and
a little fruit. I ringed the chicks when they were seven days old, using IOA
rings size K. Dull replicas of their parents, they left the nest at 13 days.
On June 16th the female laid again. On that occasion she laid a clutch of
four eggs. Incubation started on June 19th and after 12 days two of the eggs
hatched. The other two were clear. All went well until the chicks were four
days old, when the parents deserted the nest. I do not know why this
happened, other than that two days before the eggs were due to hatch, I had
removed the two young from the first brood. The pair did not nest again.
These bulbuls were more restless and noisy than other species I have
bred in the past. On my entering their flight, they soon left the nest and
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.378489" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293349" page_num="5" year="" vol="">
JERRARD - SOOTY-HEADED BULBUL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.919408" page_id="56293349"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
5
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9924245" page_id="56293349"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
chattered and screeched until I was out of sight. Were they in a larger flight
with more cover, perhaps they would have been more successful.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.977868" genericHeader="references" page_id="56293349" page_num="5" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.741412666666667">
King, B.. Woodcock, JVL, Dickinson, E.C. 1976. A Field Guide to the Birds of South-East
Asia. Collins, St James's Place, London.
Strange, M. 2002. A Photographic Guide to the Birds of Indonesia. Christopher Helm, London.
</reference>
<table confidence="0.71174" page_id="56293349"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
Jim Jerrard is a UK member who lives in South Yorkshire .
* * t
THE AUTUMN SOCIAL MEETING - 2005
On Saturday, September 24th 2005, 50 members and their guests visited
Paignton Zoo Environmental Park, Devon. They spent the morning viewing
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.937143" page_id="56293349"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
the extensive collection, while Avicultural Society Council Members met in
the zoo boardroom. The boardroom houses a full set of the Avicultural
Magazine dating back to 1894, many of the magazines having been collected
by the great Herbert Whitley, who founded the zoo.
After lunch the Chairman of the Avicultural Society, Christopher Marler,
presented Curator of Birds and Reptiles Colin Bath with the society's
Certificate of Merit for the first breeding in the UK of the Pigeon Guillemot
Cepphus columba , at the zoo's Living Coasts exhibit at Torbay. Following
the presentation there was an escorted tour of the collection, for which
members and their guests split into two groups, one led by Colin Bath and
the other by Jo Gregson, Senior Head Keeper of Birds.
The bird collection is wide ranging and includes severall species, such as
the Socorro Dove Zenaida graysoni, Giant Wood Rail Eulabeornis ypecaha
and the Grey Gull Lams modestus , which are not often seen in UK
collections. For many, the highlight of the visit was the behind the scenes
tour of the new Avian Breeding Centre, from which the Bird Section is run.
This large building contains food preparation areas, incubation and rearing
rooms, in which members and their guests saw 2005 Paignton-bred Orange-
headed Ground Thrushes Zoothera citrina, Hooded Pittas Pitta sordid a, Bali
Starlings Leucospar rothschildi , Yellow-shouldered Amazons Amazona
barbadensis and a Grey-winged Trumpeter Psophia crepitans .
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.49352" page_id="56293349"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
Paul Boulden
Hon. Secretary/Treasurer
</figure>
<page confidence="0.965866" page_id="56293350"  page_num="6" year="" vol="">
6
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.922502333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293350" page_num="6" year="" vol="">
COTSWOLD WILDLIFE PARK
REVIEW OF 2005
by Louise Peat
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.86794825" page_id="56293350"  page_num="6" year="" vol="">
The past three years have been very busy here on the Bird Section at the
Cotswold Wildlife Park, Burford, Oxon., during which time an impressive
24 new species have been added to the collection.
The new species are:
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.978250875" page_id="56293350"  page_num="6" year="" vol="">
Hamerkop Scopus umbretta
Madagascar Teal Anas bernieri
Hottentot Teal Anas punctata
Turkey Vulture Cathartes aura
Delacour's Crested Fireback Lophura ignita macartneyi
White-naped Crane Grus vipio
Sunbittem Eurypyga helias
Southern Lapwing Vanellus chilensis
Blacksmith Plover Anitibyx or Vanellus armatus
Scheepmaker's Crowned Pigeon Goura scheepmakeri sclaterii
Pheasant Pigeon Otidiphaps nobilis nobilis
Duyvenbode's Lory Chalcopsitta duivenbodei duivenbodei
Greater Roadrunner Geococcyx californianus
White-browed Coucal Centropus superciliosus
Boreal Owl Aegolius fiunereus
Tawny Frogmouth Podargus strigoides
Blue-winged Kookaburra Dacelo leachii
Blue-bellied Roller Coracias cyanogaster
Snowy-headed Robin Chat Cossypha niveicapilla
New Caledonian Crow Corvus moneduloides
Red Shoveler Anas platalea
Baikal Teal Anas formosa
Blue-eared Glossy Starling Lamprotornis chalybaeus
Red-billed Whistling Duck Dendrocygna autumnalis autumnalis
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.984619714285714" page_id="56293350"  page_num="6" year="" vol="">
The influx of new species is a result of the park's collection plan, which
has resulted in us now having one of the most varied bird collections in the
UK. We have been privileged to have received three species on loan. Two
of these, a pair of Delacour's Crested Fireback Pheasants Lophura ignita
macartneyi and a pair of Great Blue Turacos Corythaeola cristata , are on
loan from Michel Klat. We are very pleased to have Great Blue Turacos
back in our collection. This species had been absent from the park since
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.273514" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293351" page_num="7" year="" vol="">
PEAT - COTSWOLD WILDLIFE PARK
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.991122" page_id="56293351"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
7
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998845658536585" page_id="56293351"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
2000, and the morning chorus had not been the same since then.
The third species, a pair of New Caledonian Crows Corvus moneduloides,
is on loan from Oxford University, where research is being undertaken into
tool use and the intelligence of this species. For a while the pair was housed
in an aviary in the Walled Garden, but despite attempts by keeping staff to
offer more cover, the pair never really settled in this aviary. The pair is now
in an off-show aviary, where keepers can concentrate on breeding this crow
in a more settled environment.
Another new species of special note is the Greater Roadrunner Geococcyx
californianus . In the UK, only Banham Zoo and the Cotswold Wildlife
Park currently hold this fascinating species. Our male was bred at Banham
Zoo and it took us over a year to locate a female. She came from Tierpark
Berlin and within months of arriving here began laying eggs, but all proved
infertile. Unfortunately, this female died suddenly in July 2005. We were
able to obtain an unrelated female from Vogelpark Marlow, and hopes are
high that we will succeed in breeding this species this year.
Early in 2004, a male Blue-winged Kookaburra Dacelo leachii arrived
from Rotterdam Zoo. So far though we have failed to locate an unrelated
female to pair him with. All of the 18 birds known to be held in UK
collections are related and can be traced back to the original Rotterdam
birds. The situation is not much better in the rest of Europe. We are now
monitoring this species on behalf of EAZA (European Association of Zoos
and Aquaria) and hope that new bloodlines may be able to be sourced from
Australia.
Highlights of 2005 breeding season
Two male Black Storks Ciconia nigra were parent-reared in 2005. It
was the third year in a row our Black Storks have successfully reared their
own young. Over the years we have been very successful with this species.
Our offspring have been sent to six other collections in the UK. Early in
2005, Edinburgh Zoo organised the import from Denmark of four unrelated
birds. These have been distributed among four collections including our
own, to be paired with some of the birds bred at the park. Using the
knowledge and experience we have gained, we hope to encourage this second
unrelated pair of birds to breed here in the park.
Our flock of Chilean Flamingos Phoenicopterus chilensis had its best
breeding season to date, with 10 out of the 12 chicks that hatched being
reared successfully. We are going from strength to strength with this species.
During a two year observational study of our flock we have collated much
needed information on nesting behaviour, which has given us a better
understanding of these unique birds. During the study, some interesting
behaviours were observed, including same sex egg and chick 'napping' and
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.630119" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293352" page_num="8" year="" vol="">
PEAT - COTSWOLD WILDLIFE PARK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998196166666667" page_id="56293352"  page_num="8" year="" vol="">
'trio' pairing.
After seven years of keeping the Masked Plover Vanellus miles miles ,
we bred this species for the first time in 2005, with three young being
produced. We believe the success was due to subtle changes the keepers
made within the aviary. On the back of this success a new area in the walk-
through enclosure in the Walled Garden has been built by the keepers. It
offers a much improved environment for our two species of plover, and
allows space and suitable conditions to bring Pied Avocets Recurvirostra
avosetta back into the collection.
In November 2004 we received a pair of Scheepmaker's Crowned Pigeon
Goura scheepmakeri sclaterii from Cologne Zoo, Germany. The pair was
placed in our recently renovated Tropical House. The pair settled in extremely
well, despite the female having a problem with one of her legs, resulting
from a break or some other injury that causes her to walk with a slight limp.
In September 2005 the pair successfully reared a chick. It was the first
recorded breeding of this species in the UK.
Other species that have done well in the Tropical House include a pair of
Blue-bellied Rollers Coracias cyanogaster . The conditions in the house
seem to be particularly conducive for this species, for not only have the
adults thrived but last year they produced four young from two clutches.
There has been conflict between the rollers and a pair of Red-crested Turacos
Tauraco erythrolophus and, as the turacos have failed to breed in the Tropical
House, they will be moved elsewhere. The general feeling is that the Tropical
House holds too many distractions for the turacos, which is why they have
failed to show any breeding behaviour since they were moved there.
Our group of Speckled Mousebirds Colins striatus produced a total of
20 chicks in the Tropical House, all of which were eagerly snapped up by
other collections. We have high hopes for our pair of Pheasant Pigeons
Otidiphaps nobilis nobilis which last year produced 10 clutches of eggs,
many of which were fertile but failed to hatch. The keepers have tried several
techniques in order to achieve success. These have included foster and
artificial incubation and placing dummy eggs under the pigeons until their
own eggs had started to pip when they were returned to them, but so far our
efforts have failed. However, we hope our persistence will eventually pay
off.
Our group of Wonga Pigeons Leucosarcia melanoleuca continues to be
productive. Last year a total of three chicks were parent-reared or foster-
reared. We have finally obtained a second pair of these pigeons and once
this pair has settled and started to breed, we hope to create some unrelated
pairs which we can distributed to other collections.
In October 2004 we received six White-browed Coucals Centropus
superciliosus from Parc Paradisic, Belgium. Three of these were placed at
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.26844" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293353" page_num="9" year="" vol="">
PEAT - COTSWOLD WILDLIFE PARK
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.955483" page_id="56293353"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
9
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.969004617647059" page_id="56293353"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
Exmoor Zoo in Devon and bred there. It is the first record of this species
having bred in the UK. Unfortunately, in February last year we lost one of
our trio. However, the remaining two proved to be a true pair and laid
fertile eggs, one of which was successfully hatched and the chick hand-
reared. Later in the year the pair went on to successfully rear four young.
We are currently keeping the birds as a family group.
In June three fertile eggs from a pair of Purple Glossy Starlings
Lamprotornispurpureus were received from a private collection. They were
placed in the nest of a pair of Red-winged Starlings Onychognathus morio
and the pair incubated the eggs and managed to rear one chick, which is
now with our group of Purple Glossy Starlings.
Among other species successfully reared in 2005 were Black Curassow
Crax alector , White Stork C. ciconia, Humboldt Penguin Spheniscus
humboldti , Striated Caracara Phalcoboenus australis , Boobook Owl Ninox
novaeseelandiae, Crested Pigeon Ocyphaps lophotes , Himalayan Monal
Lophophorus impeyanus, Temminck's Tragopan Tragopan temminckii and
Black-headed Weaver Ploceus cucullatus bohndorffi. In all, 37 species
produced young, with 31 of these species successfully rearing a total of 127
young.
Plans for the future
In January 2006 we received two male Guira Cuckoos Guira guira which,
like the male Greater Roadrunner, were bred at Banham Zoo, Norfolk.
The Walled Garden is about to have a face-lift. Its layout has changed
little over the past 35 years and even though enclosures have been rebuilt,
improved and extended sometimes, the overall layout has generally remained
the same. Our new approach to this area is to move some of the aviaries
away from the perimeter walls in order to create a more interesting route for
visitors and allow us to create better environments for the animals. The
remodelled area will include new aviaries, a carp pond and a heated pond
for our giant water lilies, all surrounded by exotically planted border.
The first phase of this project was completed earlier this year (2006) and
included the rebuilding and enlargement of our Great Hornbill Buceros
bicornis enclosure, which now includes an arched, netted canopy, offering
the birds greater height.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.777268">
Louise Peat works at the Cotswold Wildlife Park, Burford, Oxon.
OX18 4JW, UK. Tel:01993 823006/Fax:01993 823807/Website:
cotswoldwildlifepark. co. uk/E-mail:records@cotswoldwildlifepark. co. uk
</reference>
<page confidence="0.986646" page_id="56293354"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
10
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.959584" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293354" page_num="10" year="" vol="">
THE CHESTNUT-BELLIED SEED-FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.395073" page_id="56293354"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
Oryzoborus angolensis IN THE WILD
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.972784" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56293354" page_num="10" year="" vol="">
AND IN AVICULTURE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.947254916666667" page_id="56293354"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
by Robin Restall
Introduction
The Chestnut-bellied Seed-Finch, also called the Lesser Seed-Finch, is
widespread across tropical South America east of the Andes. It has a very
attractive song consisting of various melodious trills and warbles, usually
recognisable despite many variations. Despite being widespread and
potentially common, its singing ability has made it a victim of bird trappers
and as a result it is rare or uncommon to locally common at best. Most of
the birds are trapped for the South American market, this species only
occasionally occurs in aviculture in Europe and North America and there is
little if anything of value about it in the avicultural literature outside of
Brazil. It is subject to considerable variation in size and plumage, and being
comparatively easy to breed in captivity, is known to have several plumage
variants. It has also hybridized with several other finches.
Habitat
In Colombia the Chestnut-bellied Seed-Finch is found at woodland edges,
on wasteland and in shrubbery. In Guyana it may be found in swamps and
abandoned previously cultivated forest clearings and also in partly grassy
and partly cultivated clearings in and near the edge of forests. In Surinam it
is said to occur on sandy ground at the edge of forests and at the edge of
plantations. In French Guiana it is a bird of secondary growth and open
country bordering large forests. In Ecuador it is found in shrubby clearings
that are usually not grassy and tends to avoid areas of intensive agriculture.
In Brazil it is primarily a bird of undisturbed wet grassland and is a typical
species of riparian thickets and thick bush alongside rivers in the cerrado.
It is also said to be found in the burrizales. These are wet swampy grasslands
with grasses up to 2m (6ft 6in) tall, scattered with Moriche Palms. These
also occur in Venezuela where they are known as morichales. Mention has
been made of the Chestnut-bellied Seed-Finch inhabiting pastures and areas
that are densely bushy near water in Argentina. Here in Venezuela it is
found it in a variety of habitats, it is said to occur in shrubby forest clearings
and grassy forest borders and I have encountered it in habitats ranging from
montane forest in Tachira to open savannah in southern Bolivar State. In
Tachira I netted a male in dense montane second growth woodland not far
from a path and river and several kilometres (miles) from open grassland. It
appeared to be travelling through the woodland in the direction of an open
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.87379" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293355" page_num="11" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - CHESTNUT-BELLIED SEED-FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998962" page_id="56293355"  page_num="11" year="" vol="">
11
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.991130833333333" page_id="56293355"  page_num="11" year="" vol="">
area. It seems that most sightings of the bird are in areas not far from water
or wet areas.
Food and feeding
It is apparently vegetarian, however, the stomach of one individual
contained insect fragments. It may often be found foraging singly but has
also frequently been seen feeding in loose congregations of seed-eating birds
in open areas. On the Gran Sabana in Venezuela I have found it foraging
with other seed-eaters - Sicalis grassland finches, Zonotrichia sparrows and
different Sporophila seedeaters - on open grassland that had been burned
recently and which was still smouldering. This area was not far from running
water. Favourite seeds of this species in Brazil, include those of the sedges
Tiririca , Cyperus rotundus and the navalha-de-macaco, Hypolytrum
schraderianum. In Guyana it was seen feeding exclusively on Scleria
pretensis sedges. It seems to me that it is primarily reliant, if not dependent,
on seeds of sedges (family Cyperaceae). It is also one of several seed-eaters
observed feeding in Cecropia trees, eating at the fruits and also taking
Mullerian bodies from the leaves, petioles and stems.
Variation in O. angolensis
The following analysis is based on a series of 118 specimens in the
Coleccion Omithologica Phelps in Caracas, Venezuela, occasional sets of
measurements taken opportunistically during visits to various other
collections over about 10 years, observations on live birds captured during
field-work and seven live birds observed under controlled conditions over
three years, together with an extensive search of the literature.
Bill, colour, shape and size
Juvenile birds, that is birds that have not yet had their first body moult,
have a bill with a curved culmen, not unlike that of a Sporophila in character.
The bill is large and apparently no different from that of an adult, but a
qualified comparison of 18 specimens showed that they are on average 10%
smaller in all dimensions. A typical set of measurements is: exposed culmen
average 11.5mm, with a range 10.5mm- 13.6mm; height of bill from base of
mandible to highest point of exposed culmen average 11.2mm, with a range
of 10.0mm-12.6mm; width across the base of the mandible average 9.7mm,
with a range of 9.1 mm-10.7mm. The bill is dark brown, usually with some
horn-colour infused, especially at the base and along the cutting edges. The
bill is smooth, without ridges or grooves. It becomes increasingly blackish
as the bird matures.
By the time the bird is in immature plumage, that is between the first
body moult at four to six months of age and the first full moult at 10-12
months, the bill has begun to change shape, with the base of the culmen
swelling and rising, thus giving the culmen a flatter appearance. In addition
the base of the culmen begins to extend back along the skull in the form of
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994309" page_id="56293356"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
12
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.94151" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293356" page_num="12" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - CHESTNUT-BELLIED SEED-FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.78974625" page_id="56293356"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
a narrow strip (Fig. 1). The process of change is greater in males than females
at all ages, but in the immature the comparison is more noticeable and the
shape of an immature female's bill may seem exactly like that of a juvenile.
Fig.l. Examples of how the bill varies according to the age of the bird.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.9869444" page_id="56293356"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
1. The juvenile has a slightly curved culmen that is the same in the male and female.
2. The adult female has a flattened culmen.
3. The adult male has a flattened culmen that begins to swell at the base and extend
backwards.
4. The culmen usually extends further back in old males.
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.99836524" page_id="56293356"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
The bill of the adult female (from 21 specimens) typically measures:
exposed culmen average 13.15mm, with a range 11.6mm -14.5mm; average
height 11.7mm, with a range 10.7mm-13.25mm; width across base of bill
average 10.1mm.
There is an enormous variation in bill size among adult males. This is
possibly age related, but one of the largest bills I found was that of a bird
that was just finishing its first full moult, thus it was only about a year old.
Two individuals that had been in captivity for several years, both had fairly
modest sized bills. I do not know at what age the bill stops changing shape,
but it seems it may take a couple of years or more. In the two main aspects
of the adult bill, i.e. size and shape, the latter appears to be more age related.
The growth of the narrow strip from the peak of the culmen back along the
skull (Fig.l) is part of this ageing process, for I have failed to find it in
young adult males regardless of the size of their bills.
The range of bill sizes is quite amazing. On a total size basis, measuring
the volume of the bill in cubic mm (Restall, 2002), the smallest of 78 adult
males measured 167 cubic mm and the largest 379 cubic mm. Thus the
largest bill was more than double the size of the smallest. Adult males had
the following bill measurements: exposed culmen average 13.25mm, with a
range of 11.1mm- 14.65mm; average height 11.8mm, with a range of 10.0mm-
14.0mm; width of bill at base average 10.2mm.
There are at least three possible explanations for the variation in the size
of the bill. The first is sexual attractiveness. The Lonchura munias of the
Asia-Pacific region are in many ways the Old World analogue of Oryzoborus .
I found at least in the subgenus Muni a, larger bills are a bigger attraction to
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.873775" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293357" page_num="13" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - CHESTNUT-BELLIED SEED-FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999116" page_id="56293357"  page_num="13" year="" vol="">
13
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999077357142858" page_id="56293357"  page_num="13" year="" vol="">
females, conspecifie and congeneric, whether already paired or not, and
apparently are a strong sexual stimulant (Restall, 1996). It could be that
Oryzoborus males with larger bills attract females and may well mate with
birds that are paired to other smaller-billed birds. The principles of this
phenomenon are well known among many families of birds.
The second possible explanation is that a group of distinct-size-billed
birds might in fact be a cryptic species but this would almost certainly have
to be tied in with some other equally distinct characteristics such as longer
tarsi, or a plumage character, as in the case of the Ring-necked Seedeater
Sporophila insularis (Restall, 2002). I have not found any natural grouping
of figures within the data for the Chestnut-bellied Seed-Finch that would
support such a hypothesis.
In Africa the Pyrenestes seedcrackers have a similar, over-sized, sharp
bill like that characteristic of Oryzoborus . Chapin discovered in 1924 that
there is a considerable range in bill sizes and that they fall into three clearly
definable groups without intermediates. Smith (1991, 1993) subsequently
discovered this is trophic polymorphism, associated with feeding. The
phenomenon is known in Neotropical ornithology where, for example, in
the case of the Hook-billed Kite Chondrohierax uncinatus, birds with
different sized bills feed on different sized snails. In the case of the Black-
bellied Seedcracker P. ostrinus, each different bill morph feeds on a different
species of sedge, and what separates the sedges is the size and hardness of
their seeds. Apparently, it is the width of the mandible at the base that most
determines the strength of the bill as a seed-cracking tool (Smith, 1993).
Smith worked for two years studying Pyrenestes seedcrackers in the field in
Cameroon, West Africa. This was complemented by the shipping of 97
birds to a special special purpose-built breeding complex at Riverbanks Zoo,
South Carolina, USA. There they were bred to three generations and the
bill morph genetics were worked out. Until something of this order is
conducted with the Chestnut-bellied Seed-Finch, the possibility that it is a
trophic polymorph, must remain hypothetical. As it is, I have not been able
to place bill measurement data into any grouping that might support this
hypothesis.
Moult and plumage variation
Between the juvenile and immature stages there is a small but distinct
change in plumage coloration. This is most noticeable in males, but as with
the bill change, it can be the same in both sexes. With the first moult, the
upper surfaces become a denser, more intense and slightly darker brown,
while the breast and underparts become a richer, more rufous brown.
The male's moult into adult plumage tends to follow the pattern of first
the head, nape and upper breast showing some small black feathers. Then,
the wing-coverts, especially the median and greater, start to change, beginning
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998875" page_id="56293358"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
14
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.970597" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293358" page_num="14" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - CHESTNUT-BELLIED SEED-FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998005534883721" page_id="56293358"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
with the innermost feathers. The tertials drop within the somewhat random
body sequence. The wing feathers typically start moulting from the middle,
with the first primary and the innermost secondary and gradually moving
towards the outermost primary and the innermost secondary. The tail starts
with the outermost pair of feathers. This is the general pattern, but there
appears to be a haphazard element as well, with some feathers being dropped
and re-grown without any sequence.
The adult male, but not the juvenile nor immature male, has a highly
variable white speculum at the base of the inner seven primaries and usually
all of the secondaries. I have never found white on either of the outermost
two primaries, although occasionally the seventh is without white. The
white is on the leading edge of the six inner primaries, but on the trailing
edge of all the remiges except primaries eight and nine. The white is always
visible when the bird is in flight, but it is very variable in size and can vary
from a narrow strip to a broad band. When the wing is folded, the white
may be visible as a large white patch, or may be completely hidden, giving
the appearance of an all-black wing. There is no apparent correlation between
the amount of white and the size of the bill or the size of the bird.
The underwing of both sexes in all plumages is pure white. This may
extend up over the inner bend of the wing of the adult male and show as a
white patch at the shoulder and is sometimes quite bold. There are also
irregular white patches that occur at random. I have twice seen a bird with
a pair of matched white throat patches, and a bird with a white patch central
on the throat. Another had white on the scapulars, while yet another had
white edgings to the median wing-coverts and along the flanks. I have also
seen a bird with a white coronal line. Other sports have also been seen and
recorded. In every case that I have seen, the bird was otherwise perfectly
normal, and I have never seen a case where mixed breeding might explain
the presence of the white. There have been a few cases where the pattern of
black and brown on the breast has varied. All-black birds have been recorded
that have been totally melanistic, even lacking white on the bases of the
remiges.
There are three colour variants with different coloured breasts. The
common or basic colour of the breast is chestnut, but with some birds this is
a deeper more intense bay colour and with some others it is a brighter, lighter,
burnt sienna. In the large series I studied, about 20% of the old males had a
bay coloured breast while about 10% of the birds had a burnt sienna coloured
breast. The under tail-coverts are typically chestnut with the outer edge of
the feathers being black. However, there are variations from all-chestnut to
all-black (see plate p. 17 for examples).
Finally, the males vary considerably in total length - never a scientifically
reliable data - but an indication of variability nonetheless. Adult males varied
by some 20%, from 125mm-150mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.865055" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293359" page_num="15" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - CHESTNUT-BELLIED SEED-FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.965672" page_id="56293359"  page_num="15" year="" vol="">
15
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.530048">
Mutations
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.982228658536585" page_id="56293359"  page_num="15" year="" vol="">
Various mutations have appeared in the wild, and a concentration of
birds either showing or carrying mutant genes in captive populations means
that they occur in considerable numbers of breeders' stocks. A breeder of
Oryzohorus in Brazil, Araujo Flecha (1987), described the mutations in his
collection and how some were related. Mutants owned by this breeder
included all-black males, white males, cinnamon (presumably on the belly
and undertail), slate and ash (presumably instead of black and chestnut), as
well as harlequin males. Among females listed by him were light and dark
cinnamon, ash and a shade of ash that was almost green (presumably very
olivaceous), and white. He listed all-black males with yellow bills and all-
ash females with yellow bills. The mutations appear at random and it seems
that the genetic characters have not yet been worked out. Evidence of this
was offered by the mention of a cinnamon male that sired an ash son.
Correlation between the variables
With the exception of bill shape, there appears to be no correlation
between any of the variables. Larger birds do not necessarily have larger
bills, birds with more white in their wings may be old or young, young birds
may have large bills and old birds may have small bills. Variation of body
colour is independent of any other variable.
The Chestnut-bellied Seed-Finch in aviculture
Trade
The trapping of Chestnut-bellied Seed-Finches occurs throughout the
species' range. A calling or singing male is used to lure the birds to where
they are trapped. Sometimes the cage containing the calling or singing male
has several sticks painted with sticky gum attached around the outside. Birds
lured to the cage containing the calling or singing male perch on these and
become trapped by their feet and/or plumage and are unable to escape. They
are pulled free by the trapper and cleaned with vegetable oil. At other times
they are trapped in baited cages or in mist nets. This cheerful and
accomplished songster is a great favourite among Brazilian bird keepers.
Trapping is a widespread and major industry and buyers travel to Venezuela,
Guyana and Surinam to buy birds to take back to Brazil. In Venezuela
(where incidentally, trade in wild birds is illegal, a fact almost totally ignored
by the authorities and virtually encouraged in rural areas) there are
few dedicated trappers of this species, the birds being caught only
opportunistically (the Large-billed Seed-Finch O. crassirostris is much
preferred by local songbird keepers). Wholesalers sell newly-caught young
birds to their regular customers for the equivalent of about #2 (US$3.50)
each. They will hold them if they have an advance order from Brazil. Fine
adult males in full song can sell for the equivalent of several hundred pounds
or several hundred US dollars in big cities. In Guyana there maybe a dozen
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996772" page_id="56293360"  page_num="16" year="" vol="">
16
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.880099" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293360" page_num="16" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - CHESTNUT-BELLIED SEED-FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.968341071428571" page_id="56293360"  page_num="16" year="" vol="">
(12) villages in which several men in each village earn their living by trapping
the seed-finch. They earn the equivalent of about #1(US$1.75) for each
bird, and maybe catch two or three a week. Generally they keep young
males and release females and old males. The newly-caught birds are fed
with bunches of sedges and grasses, they are known to feed on locally and
are gradually introduced to hard dry seeds. The birds go to Georgetown
where they are bought locally and a few occasionally get into the international
trade to countries such as the Netherlands and the UK, by which time their
price has increased by about 1,000%. Birds that have proved to be strong
songsters go to expatriate Guyanese living in New York and a few other
locations. Competition winners may be sold for several thousand US dollars
each.
Breeding
The Brazilians have developed their breeding skills well. Their
recommended technique is to place a female in a standard breeding cage
measuring maybe lm x 0.5m x 0.5m (approx. 3ft 3in x 1ft 7 3 /4in x lft 7 3 /4in)
until she steadies down. A fit male is then placed in a small cage hung on
the outside. He remains there until he is singing to the female regularly and
it is apparent that she has accepted him. This process can take a few weeks.
A canary nest pan is hung inside the cage, on the wire front, to one side. It
is screened by a bunch of leaves (e.g. Ficus benjamina) placed against the
nest pan on the outside of the cage. The male is subsequently introduced
into the cage. They are fed a variety of seeds, fresh lettuce and fresh growing
grasses and sedges. When young are in the nest, livefood is offered, but few
birds take it. They are also offered canary rearing food.
Song
The song of the Chestnut-bellied Seed-Finch is usually described as being
"melodious with trills", which hardly explains why it is the favourite songbird
kept in captivity in South America. In fact the song can be a very pleasant
and pleasing continuum of warbles and trills, the equal of, or surpassing
that of a song variety of canary. The birds learn vocabulary and can be
taught different singing techniques. In one year alone, in just five states of
Brazil, there were 38 singing competitions held just for this species. Like
the song of the domestic canary, its song has many variations that become
fine tuned among birds in captivity. Specialist breeders in Brazil keep other
songbirds out of earshot of the new youngsters, unless it is intended that
elements of their song are incorporated into the young bird's fast-growing
repertoire. Of course, as with all songbirds, there is an innate song, but in
addition this species has a great propensity for learning, acquiring twists
and phrases, alternative techniques and simply getting better with practise.
Purists take the subject very seriously and try to keep the songs of their
birds within the group of songs pertaining to the species, as do canary song
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.870922" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293361" page_num="17" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - CHESTNUT-BELLIED SEED-FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994052" page_id="56293361"  page_num="17" year="" vol="">
17
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.55764" page_id="56293361"  page_num="17" year="" vol="">
Examples of plumage variation in Oryzoborus angolensis.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997988" page_id="56293362"  page_num="18" year="" vol="">
18
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.970543" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293362" page_num="18" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - CHESTNUT-BELLIED SEED-FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9987205" page_id="56293362"  page_num="18" year="" vol="">
specialists in Germany. Young birds may be kept in the company of
competition winners, so-called master singers, and may be exposed to the
repeated playing of recordings of the songs of great songsters. There are
competitions in which these birds sing and are judged. The types of song
recognised have names such as Classical, Seaside, Viviteteo, Repetitions,
Black Stream and another is called Iron Lungs!
It must be obvious that birds caught young and raised in captivity in the
company of many songbirds and those deliberately exposed to other singing
species, will develop wider vocabularies than birds in the wild, where parental
influence is dominant. It is equally certain that having an element of song
from another species in its vocabulary is no evidence of hybrid origin of the
individual.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.93829">
Implications for aviculture
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999657529411765" page_id="56293362"  page_num="18" year="" vol="">
The Chestnut-bellied Seed-Finch is undoubtably on the decline in the
wild and this is exclusively due to trapping for the cage bird trade. The
demand in Brazil is considerable. It is the Brazilians' favourite songbird.
To the credit of Brazilian bird keepers, it is increasingly being bred in captivity
there and is on the road to domestication. The appearance of mutations is a
great help in giving momentum to this. However, it is unlikely to happen as
long as birds continue to be supplied from the wild.
The trappers in Guyana all say that they have to travel farther than they
used to in order to find this species. Whereas as recently as five to 10 years
ago, birds were being caught within the village boundaries, trappers now
have to travel for two days or more to get to where they may be found. Here
in Venezuela they are no longer regularly available at wholesalers' premises,
but become available only occasionally. In my judgement, this species Is
heading for endangered status and the few birds that appear on the market in
Europe will soon be memories from the past. There is a real opportunity for
European aviculturists to follow the example of Brazilian aviculturists and
work towards domesticating this most desirable and rewarding songbird.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.873343" genericHeader="references" page_id="56293362" page_num="18" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.783299636363636">
Araujo Flecha, E. de 1987. Criacao e mutacaos de Curio. Atualidades Orntologicas 17:8-10.
Restall, R. L. 1996. Munias and Mannikins. Pica Press, UK/Yale University Press, USA.
Restall, R. L. 2002. Is the Ring-necked Seedeater ( Sporophila insularis ) from Trindad extinct,
or is it a cryptic species widespread in Venezuela? Studies in Trinidad and Tobago Ornithology
Honouring Richard ffrench (Hayes, F. E. and Temple,S. A. eds). Dept. Life Sci., Univ. West
Indies, St. Augustine. Occ. Pap. 11, 2002.
Smith, T. B. 1991. A Double-billed Dilemma. Natural History 1,91: 41-46.
Smith, T. B. 1993. Disruptive selection and the genetic basis of bill size polymorphism in the
African finch Pyrenestes. Nature 363:618-620.
Robin Restall is Research Associate at the Phelps Ornithological
Collection, Caracas, Venezuela. E-mail:restall@cantv.net
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998867" page_id="56293363"  page_num="19" year="" vol="">
19
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.974282" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293363" page_num="19" year="" vol="">
HAND REARING A SPANGLED COTINGA Cotinga cayana
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998777743589744" page_id="56293363"  page_num="19" year="" vol="">
by John E. R Francis
The Spangled Cotinga is a member of the Cotingidae family. It is found
in lowland tropical forest in northern South America, in Colombia, Venezuela,
the Guianas, Brazil, Peru and Bolivia. It measures about 20cm (approx.
7V2in-8in) in length. The male is shining turquoise blue, with black scollops
showing on many of the feathers. His throat is purple-red and his wings and
tail are black. The female is greyish-brown with pale scaling on the breast.
In 2002,1 purchased a pair of Spangled Cotingas from Cl Birds. Not
much happened in the first year, but in 2003 the female started to carry
nesting materials. She chose a Cierodendrum sp. on which to build a very
sparse nest in which she laid her single bluish-grey egg with brown mottling.
Unfortunately, the egg fell through the nest and smashed on the ground.
After several more mishaps I decided to replace the Cierodendrum with a
small evergreen shrub which I dug up and fixed upside down with the roots
spread out in a cup-shaped fashion. She took to this straight away and
proceeded to lay a few pieces of nesting material in the base of the roots.
The first egg laid hatched after 23 days. The female would only feed the
chick with waxworms. All seemed to be going well until the chick reached
28 days, when it developed breathing problems and, unfortunately, 24 hours
later it died. On two further occasions a chick was hatched successfully.
Again the female would only feed them waxworms. On these two occasions
I injected the waxworms with vitamins and minerals, etc., but both chicks
died.
Then tragedy struck when the male escaped and was never seen again.
So I returned to C. J. Birds to see if Phil Cleeton could get me another male,
which luckily he succeeded in doing. This new male was hated by the female,
which chased him non-stop around the aviary. After several clear eggs had
been laid one hatched on June 12th 2005, after an incubation period of 21
days. When the chick was seven days old, I made the decision to try to
hand-rear it. I searched the internet and scoured the available bird books,
but much to my dismay I could find nothing whatsoever on hand-rearing a
cotinga chick.
On being removed from the nest, the chick was immediately placed in a
brooder set at a constant temperature of 32*C (89.6*F) for the first two weeks,
after which the temperature was reduced by one or two degrees each week.
(The ambient temperature in June-July 2005 was quite hot). At this stage
the chicks eyes were still closed, which made feeding it extremely difficult,
especially as it was unwilling to open its beak to be fed. A matchstick with
a spade-like end was fashioned and used to prise open its beak. The beak
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.953503" page_id="56293364"  page_num="20" year="" vol="">
20
</page>
<table confidence="0.803738" page_id="56293364"  page_num="20" year="" vol="">
FRANCIS - SPANGLED COTINGA
Adult male.
Fifteen days old.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.425644" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293365" page_num="21" year="" vol="">
FRANCIS - SPANGLED COTINGA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.966568" page_id="56293365"  page_num="21" year="" vol="">
21
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.4958815" page_id="56293365"  page_num="21" year="" vol="">
Twenty-four days old.
Five months old.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996611" page_id="56293366"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
22
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.773422" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293366" page_num="22" year="" vol="">
FRANCIS - SPANGLED COTINGA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9645018" page_id="56293366"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
was very soft, so this was performed with great care for fear of damaging it.
At the beginning, it was extremely difficult for one person to manage this
on their own and my wife's help was invaluable.
The first few days it was mostly trial and error, as we had no idea how
much and how often we should feed the chick. However, eventually we
were able to establish some sort of routine. We started by feeding it
approximately every two hours from 6.00am-9.00pm (06.00hrs-21 .OOhrs).
The main foods fed to the chick were:
pinky mice cut into lmm-2mm slices and soaked in a solution of water
to which had been added four drops of Abidec
wax worms
crickets
blueberries
pawpaw (papaya)
We used a small pair of tweezers to feed the chick. Each offering of
food was first dipped in the Abidec solution, then lightly coated with SA-37
intervet powder and then dipped into a parrot rearing formula, which we
had mixed with water to make into a thick paste. Mealworms were added to
the diet at approximately two weeks.
On a typical day during the first week the chick received:
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.996413913793103" page_id="56293366"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
6.00am
2 slices of pinky
2.00pm
1 cricket
(06.OOhrs)
1 waxworm
(14.OOhrs)
3 waxworms
2 x 'A blueberry
2 x 1 A blueberry
2 cubes of pawpaw
8.00am
2 crickets
(08.OOhrs)
1 waxwonn
4.00pm
2 x 'A blueberry
2 x 'A blueberry
(16.OOhrs)
2 slices of pinky
2 x 5mm cubes of
2 cubes of pawpaw
pawpaw
10.00am
3 waxworms
6.00pm
2 slices of pinky
(10. OOhrs)
2 x X U blueberry
2 cubes of pawpaw
(18. OOhrs)
2 waxworms
12.00am
1 slice of pinky
9.00 pm
3 waxworms
(12.OOhrs)
1 waxwonn
(21.OOhrs)
2 crickets
2 x &amp;apos;A blueberry
1 cricket
2 x &amp;apos;A blueberry
At four weeks old the chick was
fed:
6.30am
2 waxworms
3.00pm
4 slices of pinky
(06.30hrs) 2 slices of pinky
(15.OOhrs)
2 crickets
2 crickets
4 x x h blueberry
2 cubes of pawpaw
2 cubes of pawpaw
2 x &amp;apos;A blueberry
2 waxworms
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.392499" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293367" page_num="23" year="" vol="">
FRANCIS - SPANGLED COTINGA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.880558" page_id="56293367"  page_num="23" year="" vol="">
23
</page>
<figure confidence="0.995907756756757" page_id="56293367"  page_num="23" year="" vol="">
8.30am
2 slices of pinky
5.30pm
3 slices of pinky
(08.30hrs)
2 crickets
(17.30hrs)
3 crickets
2 cubes of pawpaw
3 cubes of pawpaw
2 x x ti blueberry
3 waxworms
10.30am
2 slices of pinky
8.00pm
2 crickets
(10.30hrs)
2 crickets
jE!
o
o
o
tN
2 mealworms
2 cubes of pawpaw
2 waxworms
2 x x h blueberry
7 cubes of pawpaw
1 mealworm
2 x x h blueberry
1.00pm
3 slices of pinky
(13.00hrs)
3 crickets
2 mealworms
3 cubes of pawpaw
3 x x h blueberry
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.982206913043478" page_id="56293367"  page_num="23" year="" vol="">
The chick first opened its eyes at approximately two weeks old, it also
started to regurgitate undigested food in the form of pellets. At 26 days old
the chick flew across the bedroom in which it was being reared. At 33 days
it started to take food from the dish.
When the chick was 36 days old, it was noticed that its breathing had
become laboured and a slight clicking sound could be heard coming from
its throat. Baytril - one drop in the morning and one drop in the evening for
five days - was administered directly into the chick's beak and, fortunately,
this did the trick. The chick was successfully persuaded to drink water by
floating a mealworm on the top of it.
At the time of writing (late 2005), the young Spangled Cotinga is nearly
six months old and is fit and well. It will not be possible to sex it until it has
reached maturity, which could take up to a year.
Bibliography
del Hoyo, J.. Elliot, A., Christie, D. 2004. Handbook of the Birds of the World. Volume 9.
Lynx Edicions, Barcelona, Spain.
Ortiz Merry, L. J. 2004. The Hand-rearing of an Umbrellabird. Avicultural Magazine 110,
3:108-115.
John and his wife have now raised three young Spangled Cotingas and
the female is sitting on another egg. The cotingas are, he wrote, kept in a
small tropical house heated to a temperature of 55 *F-60 *F (12.8 *C-15.6 *C),
with the birds having access to an outside flight all year round. They share
the accommodation with a number of other species, namely Blue-winged
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.915678">
Leafbird Chloropsis cochinchinensis, White-throated Bee-eater Merops
albicollis, Rufous-bellied Niltava Niltava sundara, Egyptian Plover or
Crocodile Bird Pluvianus aegyptius and a pitta Pitta sp. - Ed.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998115" page_id="56293368"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
24
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.992868" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293368" page_num="24" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE ST VINCENT PARROT Amazona guildingii
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.976835305555555" page_id="56293368"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
by Henry Quinque
My childhood passion - still intact today - for all forms of life, some
scientific rigour and a fair amount of luck have enabled me to achieve some
notable breeding results.
To think that some bird is fancier or more endearing than another is
definitely subjective yet no aviculturist can escape this feeling. I admit
willingly to this failing and it was thus that for decades amongst the species
I most longed for was the St Vincent Parrot.
History
This dream took time and infinite perseverance to achieve, while all the
time this wonder of nature was facing extinction.
Our association had to negotiate for five long years before we managed
to obtain the birds. The miracle happened in the form of a convocation by
the Government of St Vincent &amp; the Grenadines that it was ready to place
on loan with us St Vincent's emblematic parrot.
There, before the media, the minister in charge handed us four St Vincent
Parrots. The next day in the government newspaper it was explained that
the loan of these parrots was in the interest of the survival of the species,
almost wiped out by the eruption of the Soufriere volcano in 1979. The
opposition newspaper did not publish any photographs of the event and
accused the government of squandering the country's assets to the profit of
incompetent foreigners.
Eventually, after overcoming more unforeseen administrative hurdles
we reached France and put away the 5kg (1 libs) of letters and documents
that had been accumulated during the lengthy negotiations.
Selection of the pair
After a period adapting to their new surroundings, we had our four birds
DNA-sexed and discovered that only one of them was a female. All large
parrots have strong personalities and feelings one must be attentive to. Thus,
it took us three seasons, during which the female laid infertile eggs, to form
a compatible pair. Finally, the female accepted a male which was very mobile,
flew well and was very attentive.
After three months in adjacent cages, we put the two birds together at
the beginning of January. We saw the first mating on March 29th 2004. It
is similar to that of the macaws, i.e. the male does not mount the female but
the fairly long copulation takes place with the birds side by side.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.508786" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293369" page_num="25" year="" vol="">
QUINQUE - ST VINCENT PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.980728" page_id="56293369"  page_num="25" year="" vol="">
25
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.985382833333333" page_id="56293369"  page_num="25" year="" vol="">
Behaviour
The birds have 12m (approx. 39ft) of flying space in the aviary which is
linked to a heated shelter. We set up one nest-box outside and one inside.
The boxes are custom-built for these large Amazons, with a 70cm x 70cm
(2ft 3V2in x 2ft 3V2in) square base and are 150cm (4ft 1 lin) in height. The
bottom of the boxes have a layer of wood chips and strips of wood are
nailed on the inside at the level of the birds' beaks. The boxes are set 2m
(approx. 6ft bin) high. Each is equipped was a camera linked to a monitor
in the service corridor of the building.
After a careful inspection of both nest-boxes, during which they put
their heads inside but did not enter the boxes, the birds chose the box inside
the shelter. The male enters the box first and chews the wood chips and the
softwood strips nailed inside and this chewed-up wood lines the bottom of
the box. The female goes in next and remains inside for longer and longer
periods over the next few days. Meanwhile, the male sits on guard on the
entrance perch or on the roof of the box.
On April 6th 2004, the female laid her first egg, followed by the second
on the 9th and the third egg on the 12th. Only the first egg was fertile. It
was put in an incubator on the fifth day. It hatched on May 3rd but the chick
died two days later. It is possible that it died as the result of me overfilling
its crop.
After this disappointment, we had to wait until the 2005 season to fulfil
our dream. The same box was used by the birds under identical conditions.
The first egg was laid on April 24th, the second on the 26th and the third egg
on the 29th. I had witnessed a coupling during the previous week.
The female incubated perfectly and carefully turned the eggs. The first
few days she did not leave the nest-box but later went out at around 10.00am
(lO.OOhrs) and 6.00pm (18.00hrs) for a few minutes, always protected by
the male which became very aggressive when he saw a human being.
Apart from that, she brooded the eggs while the male guarded the entrance
to the nest and went down to feed her and then settled beside her. He often
remained there alongside her for a long time before leaving the nest. The
male went down into the nest-box head first, whereas the female entered the
box backwards and was careful to position her feet well away from the
eggs.
To avoid any risk, we regretfully removed the three eggs from this
wonderful couple on May 12th while the female was momentarily away.
All three were fertile with very mobile embryos of a size consistent with
their age. The nest was perfectly clean with no trace of faeces on the wood
chips.
Description of the eggs
The first egg, laid April 24th, measured 44.55mm x 32.57mm and was
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.993142" page_id="56293370"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
26
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.818779" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293370" page_num="26" year="" vol="">
QUINQUE - ST VINCENT PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.983527725" page_id="56293370"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
23.01 cubic cm in volume. It weighed 20.91g on May 15th and 20.62g on
May 17th, the daily weight loss being 0.14g. We can infer an initial weight
of 23.85g which indicates a normal density of 1.03 on the day it was laid.
On the 21st day, the density was 0.90.
The second egg, laid April 26th, measured 40.96mm x 32.19mm and
was 22.31 cubic cm in volume. The density was 0.94 on the 21st day and it
weighed 21.29g.
The third egg, laid April 29th, measured 40.96mm x 33.24mm and was
23.08 cubic cm in volume. On the 21 st day, it weighed 21.08g and its density
was 0.91.
The brood of A. guildingii eggs measured 44.55mm x 32.57mm, 40.96mm
x 32.19mm and 40.96mm x 33.24mm, thus giving an average of 41.91mm
x 32.66mm. The three eggs were 23.01 cubic cm, 22.31 cubic cm and 23.08
cubic cm in volume, thus giving an average of 22.80 cubic cm.
Artificial incubation
They were installed in a high precision electronic incubator set at a
temperature of 37.3*C (99.1*F) and 50% humidity. They were turned eight
times a day at irregular intervals. Several times a day they were checked
visually and the pulse was taken with an infrared electrocardiogram.
Hatching of the first chick
The internal pipping of this egg, laid on the morning of April 24th, started
on May 17th at 4.00pm (16.00hrs). A very faint, external pipping appeared
on May 18th in the form of a series of three parallel superficial cracks 5mm
in length. The egg remained immobile.
On May 19th at 4.00am (04.00hrs) the shell looked the same. At 8.00am
(08.00hrs) however a minute chip of shell about 1mm long had lifted up at
the end of one of the cracks. There was no further change until midnight
(24. OOhrs). The egg remained immobile but the chick was alive and showed
a stable pulse rate of 260 beats per second.
On May 20th at 4.00am (04.OOhrs) the egg looked similar in appearance
but the chick's heartbeat had slowed and become irregular. Therefore I took
the decision to open the shell and the membrane which had still not been
broken by the chick's beak. Several of the blood vessels remained full of
blood, which became more obvious after the membrane was moistened with
lukewarm serum. The chick opened its beak and breathed. The temperature
of the incubator was left at 37.3*C (99.1*F) but the humidity was raised to
80%.
At 11.00am (11.OOhrs) the hole in the shell and the membrane were
enlarged, as the blood vessels were by then practically empty. At 11.45am
(11.45hrs) the chick chirped softly and was then carefully extracted from
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.51307" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293371" page_num="27" year="" vol="">
QUINQUE - ST VINCENT PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997332" page_id="56293371"  page_num="27" year="" vol="">
27
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998201170731707" page_id="56293371"  page_num="27" year="" vol="">
the shell. A small quantity of meconium (the dark green mucoid material
that forms the first faeces of the newly-hatched chick) had been passed by
the chick in the egg and confirmed that the timing of the extraction was
right. The humidity was raised to 90% and the umbilical cord was severed
after having been pinched but without the use of a ligature.
The chick hatched (with our assistance) at noon (12.00hrs) on the 26th
day and weighed 15.78g. It remained in the incubator set at 37.2*C (99*F)
and 50% humidity for three days. The chick was fed for the first time in the
late afternoon. An eye dropper with a latex tip was used and the powder
was diluted in six times its volume of warm water. On the second day, May
21st, the chick was fed every two hours during the day and every three
hours at night. The following day, May 22nd, a small amount of food was
regurgitated at 2.00am (02.00hrs), otherwise it was a normal day.
May 23rd at 4.00am (04.00hrs) the chick was on its back, it was restless
and its abdomen was bloated. It was breathing irregularly and ate very
little. It had not passed any droppings. Despite being wedged with tissue
paper in an adapted nest, it kept turning onto its back. At the end of the day,
it produced a green, fairly compact dropping. The food was made thinner
(more liquid) and the temperature was reduced to 36*C (96.8*F) and the
humidity was raised to 65%. The chick remained on its back and was very
dehydrated. Treatment was started using human medicines.
May 24th the chick was eating better and turning over less often. May
28th there were obvious signs of amelioration. The rehydration treatment
was stopped and the temperature was reduced to 35*C (95*F). A thicker
mix of three parts water to one part powder was given and the normal feeding
pattern resumed.
I relate these events in the hope of showing that the chick would probably
not have survived without human intervention during hatching and the
dehydration incident. I am uncertain whether the parents would have helped
very much, even if they can help with the hatching as some macaws do. I
hope our nest cameras will provide us with more information on this subject
this coming breeding season.
Hatching of the second chick
The hatching of the second egg, which was laid on April 26th, was very
similar to the hatching of the first egg, described above, in that we had to
intervene in order for the chick to hatch successfully. The internal pipping
started on May 19th with a stable heartbeat of 260 pulsations per minute. A
single external dot pip appeared on May 20th at 5.00pm (17.00hrs). The
egg weighed 20.79g. The temperature was left at 37.3*C (99.1*F) and the
humidity was raised to 80%. On May 22nd, the lack of progress and a
slower and irregular pulse led us to open the shell and the membrane.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.929407" page_id="56293372"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
28
</page>
<figure confidence="0.849083333333333" page_id="56293372"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
QUINQUE - ST VINCENT PARROT
Copyright Gregory Guida
St. Vincent Parrot chick at one day old.
Copyright Gregory Guida
The author with St. Vincent Parrot chicks at 29 days old.
t...
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.512418" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293373" page_num="29" year="" vol="">
QUINQUE - ST VINCENT PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994765" page_id="56293373"  page_num="29" year="" vol="">
29
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.225039">
Copyright Gregory Guida
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993434428571428" page_id="56293373"  page_num="29" year="" vol="">
Fifty days old.
A vascular membrane was found stuck to the chick's nostrils. It was
removed with a damp pad and allowed the chick to breathe normally. It
hatched (with our assistance) on May 22nd, the 26th day of incubation and
weighed 16.60g. It developed normally without suffering any of the problems
of its sibling and by the second day already weighed 20.87g.
Hatching of the third chick
The third egg was laid on April 29th. It developed in much the same
way as the others, with the chick being incapable of hatching on its own.
We extracted it from the egg on the 26th day. It weighed 16.15g. The
umbilical cord was ligatured. It was well supplied with blood vessels but
the membrane was not. The chick was of normal size, without anomalies
but was weak and inanimate. It died 24 hours after hatching.
I suppose I could have been responsible for its death by acting too early
but the presence of meconium in the shell suggested that the time of hatching
had been reached or even passed.
Artificial rearing
The food is a commercially available powder which we diluted in hot or
boiling water. During the first few days, the mix was watery in consistency,
after which it was made progressively thicker as indicated by the
manufacturer's instructions, so that by the third week it was almost half
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995868" page_id="56293374"  page_num="30" year="" vol="">
30
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.810109" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293374" page_num="30" year="" vol="">
QUINQUE - ST VINCENT PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998067292682927" page_id="56293374"  page_num="30" year="" vol="">
powder and half water. The mix was given to the chicks at a temperature of
37*C-38*C (98.6*F-100.4*F).
During the early days, a glass eye dropper with a small latex tip was
used. The chicks were fed every two hours during the day and three times at
night as a safety measure. The chicks took a few drops at first, then a V 2
cubic cm, with the quantity being increased steadily. A syringe with a latex
tip was then used. First a 5cc syringe was used, then a lOcc syringe during
the sixth week. At that stage, the birds were fed five times a day and received
30 cubic cm - 40 cubic cm per meal. Starting on the third week, the night
time feeds were cancelled, as long as the last meal was given late in the
evening and the first meal was given early the next morning.
Healthy chicks grow fast and after the sixth week, it was sufficient to
feed them just four times a day; then three times a day and finally, on the
10th week, twice a day. When they were between three and four months old
there came the difficult weaning period and a complete change of food.
Despite some interest in solid food, the chicks still begged to be fed with
a syringe. It is probably a psychological issue for the person who is rearing
them, as at this stage they should actually be losing weight in preparation
for starting to fly. To alleviate this problem, I suggest continuing to give the
birds the same quantity of food twice a day, but diluted to half its normal
consistency, so that the birds feel fulfilled and are kept hydrated.
As they discover new foods, such as almonds, apple, banana, carrots,
germinated sunflower seeds, berries and salad items, their curiosity must be
encouraged. It is difficult at first because they can only grasp their food and
do not yet know how to use their feet to transfer the food to their beak.
Little by little, one must continue to act like their parents and present and
hold edible items of food for them.
They will eventually start swallowing small pieces of fruit, pistachios,
peanuts, pyracantha berries and biscuit. It is difficult to get them to accept
parrot pellets but they love green beans held for them so that they can split
open the pods and eat the beans.
It was with almonds and green beans that we finally persuaded our birds
to start feeding themselves, before going on to accept the great variety of
food we now give them each day.
Description of the chicks and their development
On hatching, the chicks' bodies were pink and were covered with sparse
white down. Progressively, the down became grey in irregular patterns where
the feathers would grow later. The eyes opened one after the other at two-
day intervals, starting on the 15th day. They were black.
As early as the third week, sheaths of small black feathers started to
appear on the chest and the chicks developed a white crown, made up of
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.51294" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293375" page_num="31" year="" vol="">
QUINQUE - ST VINCENT PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999771" page_id="56293375"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
31
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99881975" page_id="56293375"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
many tiny feathers. Soon afterwards the posterior edge of the crown took
on a golden yellow tint. After a month, the chest sheaths started to sprout
little tufts of feather which at first appeared to be black but soon turned to a
beautiful deep emerald green. The tail was also growing and the quills were
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.594075" page_id="56293375"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
2cm ( 3 Ain) long.
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.990838694444445" page_id="56293375"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
One of the birds had the skin of its nostrils flesh coloured and had a pink
tongue with a black tip, whereas the other bird had black nostrils and a
black tongue. The first bird had a horizontal line of yellow feathers below
the eyes, which the second bird lacked. The rest of the body was covered in
down which became a darker grey.
Our birds grew very quickly and by the fifth week weighed 500g, which
is about twice the weight of a normal Amazon. At two and a half months,
the birds were 50cm (19 3 Ain) tall. They had almost reached their final
dimensions, except for the remiges and retrices (the main wing and tail
feathers) which were still growing.
The colours, such as the white and yellow of the cap, the blue of the
cheeks and neck, the bright electric blue of the remiges with orange in the
centre and the buttercup yellow of the tip of the tail, already were as
magnificent as those of the adult birds. The surface of the wings, which
was green originally, got a gold tint. The chest and back were still much
darker than those of the adult birds. The eyes, which were completely black
the first month, remained the same around the iris, but the periphery was
pale pink. The toes, which were pale in the case of one bird and pink in the
case of the other, in both birds became grey and very large. The large golden
green feathers of the thighs completely covered the tarsometatarsus.
The birds' large wingspan meant that their flight quickly improved.
Behaviour
On hatching, each chick was placed separately in a round plastic container
and held in a semi-vertical position with tissue paper. When their eyes
opened, we put the chicks together, to their obvious delight. Necks entwined,
they stayed together without any rivalry. They became good friends and at
six weeks of age grabbed each others' beaks and made crooning noises and
fake feeding actions.
To rear such rare and precious birds requires much care and hard work.
I took care of them from the moment they hatched and I have been rewarded
for my efforts by their mutual affection. They each, of course, have a name
and when called, even when they are far away, come to perch on my hand.
They also climb onto my head and search my pockets and extract keys,
paper and pens, which they were fully able to hold from the age of three
months. They are calm and trusting, as are most adults. Pressed against my
chest, with their head hidden beneath my chin, they still make baby noises.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99826" page_id="56293376"  page_num="32" year="" vol="">
32
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.480107" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293376" page_num="32" year="" vol="">
QUINQUE - ST VINCENT PARROT
Copyright Gregory Guida
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995048181818182" page_id="56293376"  page_num="32" year="" vol="">
The author with young St. Vincent Parrot at 134 days old.
When they flew away, enjoying their new found mobility, they could at
only 10 weeks old, already call as loud as the adults.
They are intelligent creatures and each is different in character. The one
with the yellow cheeks is calm and gentle in its movements even when
eating. The other is livelier and somewhat grouchy but is not aggressive
even when I clean its beak with a wet sponge. I think they are probably a
male and a female.
I acknowledge the great happiness of having been granted the complete
trust of these two wonderful parrots who now share part of my life.
I can already hear the criticism which is bound to come from
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.513007" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293377" page_num="33" year="" vol="">
QUINQUE - ST VINCENT PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99928" page_id="56293377"  page_num="33" year="" vol="">
33
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99698985" page_id="56293377"  page_num="33" year="" vol="">
ornithologists who will reproach me for having hand-reared such rare birds,
on the grounds that they will not breed successfully later on. I can only
answer that they might not exist at all had it no been for our help and that,
contrary to what seems to be the accepted wisdom, I have during my long
career as an aviculturist often obtained some wonderful offspring, and
sometimes some very wild offspring, from hand-reared parrots. I would
also add that contrary to popular belief, I have often seen parrot siblings
become partners, even when there were many other individuals from which
they could have chosen.
It, of course, remains clear that in such circumstances, healthy offspring
can only be obtained from individuals without genetic anomalies, recessive
or dominant.
We can only hope to be as successful this year as we were last year, so
that we can again modestly contribute to the survival of this exceptional
parrot, which is the most beautiful of the last four large Amazons surviving
in the Caribbean.
Dr Henry Quinque's account of breeding the St Vincent Parrot Amazona
guildingii at the Conservatoire des Animaux en Voie d 'Extinction, Le Mesnil
Aubry, north of Paris, was translated from French to English by Gregory
Guida, who also took the photographs.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995003" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56293377" page_num="33" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.96342125" page_id="56293377"  page_num="33" year="" vol="">
The society has a large stock of back issues mostly from 1935 onwards
but there are also some earlier issues still available. They are priced #3.00
each (including p&amp;p). Please check availability before placing an order.
Overseas members may be able to pay by credit card through a Paypal
invoice, but this service is not available in all countries. All enquiries should
be addressed to: P. Boulden, Hon. Secretary/Treasurer, Avicultural Society,
Arcadia, The Mounts, East Allington, Totnes, Devon TQ9 7JQ, UK or
E-mail: admin@avisoc.co.uk
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998247" page_id="56293378"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
34
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.906263" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293378" page_num="34" year="" vol="">
HORNBILLS IN THAILAND - 2005
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.898517538461538" page_id="56293378"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
Through the Hombill Family Adoption Project of the Hombill Research
Foundation, the Avicultural Society in 2005 again adopted a pair of
Rhinoceros Hombills Buceros rhinoceros and a pair of Great Hombills B.
bicornis in Thailand.
Rhinoceros Hornbill.
This is the project in which villagers who previously earned extra money
by taking hombill nestlings and selling them, are now paid to protect the
nests and collect data on the birds' breeding biology and ecology.
There follows details of the nesting of the society's adopted pairs of
hombills in 2005, details of main foods brought to the nests by these two
species and a summary of hombill nesting in 2005 at Khao Yai National
Park, Huai Kha Khaeng Wildlife Sanctuary and Budo Sungai-Padi National
Park.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.721546" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293379" page_num="35" year="" vol="">
HORNBILLS IN THAILAND - 2005
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995058" page_id="56293379"  page_num="35" year="" vol="">
35
</page>
<table confidence="0.926611777777778" page_id="56293379"  page_num="35" year="" vol="">
Species of hornbill: Rhinoceros Hombill Buceros rhinoceros
Location of nest: Budo Mountain (part of Budo Sungai-Padi National Park), Ruso
District, Narathiwat Province, Thailand
Nesting data:
Female imprisoned in nest: March 8th 2005
Female emerged: May 27th 2005
Chick fledged: July 3rd 2005
Type of parental care: Biparental care (female joined her mate to feed the chick)
Period of data collection: March 8th-July 3rd 2005
Breeding status: This nest was successful in fledging one chick
Nest tree data:
Villager responsible for the nest: Mr Asae Jaroo/Tapoh Group
Year nest was found: 2000
Species of nest tree: Shorea leprosula
Diameter of tree at breast height: 99cm (approx. 3ft 3in)
Height of nest tree: 50m (approx. 164ft)
Coordinate (UTM): No data
Altitude above sea level: 410m (approx. 1,350ft)
Slope of nest tree: 10%
Diameter at nest height: 97cm (approx. 3ft 2in)
Height of nest above ground: 6m (approx. 20ft)
Size of nest entrance: 20cm wide x 15cm long (approx. 8in wide x 6in long)
Direction of nest entrance: 60* (ENE)
Species of Hornbill: Great Hombill Buceros bicornis
Location of nest: Budo Mountain (part of Budo Sungai-Padi National Park), Raman
District, Yala Province,Thailand
Nesting data:
Female imprisoned in nest: February 24th 2005
Female emerged: May 17th 2005
Chick fledged: June 12th 2005
Type of parental care: Biparental care (female joined her mate to feed the chick)
Period of data collection: February 24th-June 12th 2005
Breeding status: This nest was successful in fledging one chick
Nest tree data:
Villager responsible for nest: Mr Haseng Kariya/Jakoa Group
Year nest was found: 2004
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.8111799" page_id="56293379"  page_num="35" year="" vol="">
Species of nest tree: Syzygium sp.
Diameter of tree at breast height: 700cm (approx 23ft)
Height of nest tree: 30m (approx 102ft)
Coordinate (UTM): No data
Altitude above sea level: 480m (approx. 1,575ft)
Slope of nest tree: 4%
Diameter at nest height: 150cm (approx. 5ft)
Height of nest above ground: 20m (approx. 65ft)
Size of nest entrance: No data
Direction of nest entrance: 123* (SE)
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.953229" page_id="56293380"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
36
</page>
<figure confidence="0.908132933333334" page_id="56293380"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
HORNBILLS IN THAILAND - 2005
Food brought to the nest by the male Rhinoceros HombilL
Fruit
Average feeding
frequency/day
Average
number, day
Average
weight(g)/day
Ficus spp. (size 0 &amp;lt; 1 cm)
1.0
4.0
3.0
Ficus spp. (size 0 1-2 cm)
1.0
</figure>
<page confidence="0.711592" page_id="56293380"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
39.0
462.0
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.322431" page_id="56293380"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
Ficus spp. (size 0 &amp;gt; 2 cm)
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.8704725" page_id="56293380"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
0.4
3.4
</page>
<figure confidence="0.99033390990991" page_id="56293380"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
52.0
Ficus sp.
0.7
4.0
64.0
Knema sp.
0.4
4.0
4.1
Oncosperma horridum
0.4
3.0
20.4
Animal
Millipede
0.04
0.2
-
Lizard
0.04
0.2
-
Centipede
0.04
0.04
-
Snake
0.04
0.04
-
Scorpion
0.04
0.1
-
Food brought to the nest by the male Great HombilL
Fruit
Average feeding
frequeney/day
Average
weight(g) /day
Average
eumber/day
Ficus spp. (size 0 1-2 cm)
3.0
35.0
414.0
Ficus spp. (size &amp;gt; 2 cm)
1.0
15.0
228.0
Aglaia spectahilis
0.6
2.0
34.0
Chisocheton erythrocarpus
0.4
0.4
2.3
Dysoxylum sp.
0.7
0.7
3.0
Polyalthia sp.
0.4
2.0
13.0
Oncosperma horridum
0.7
4.0
-
Canthium sp.
0.6
1.0
23.0
Animal
Millipede
0.1
1.0
-
Centipede
0.1
0.1
-
Lizard
0.1
0.1
-
Scorpion
0.1
0.2
-
Locust
0.1
0.1
-
Leaf Insect
0.1
0.1
-
Cicada
0.1
0.1
-
Flying Lizard
0.1
0.3
~
Walking Stick
0.1
0.1
-
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.718333" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293381" page_num="37" year="" vol="">
HORNBILLS IN THAILAND - 2005
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.989271" page_id="56293381"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
37
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.83194" page_id="56293381"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
Duration of main foods which Rhinoceros Hombill brought to nest during
the 2005 breeding season at Budo Sungai-Padi National Park.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.994154490566038" page_id="56293381"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
Type of food
March April May June July
Fruits
Ficus spp.
4 \0x25BA
Oncosperma sp.
. --
Knema sp.
\0x25C4------ \0x25BA
Animals
Lizard &amp;lt; \0x25BA
Millipede
Snake
*
Centipede
*
Scorpion
----
Duration of main foods which Great Hombill brought to nest during the
2005 breeding season at Budo Sungai-Padi National Park.
Type of food
March
April May June July
Fruits
Ficus spp.
\0x25C4--
------------- - \0x25BA
Aglaia spectahilis
\0x25C4----\0x25BA
Chisocheton erythrocarpus
*
Dysoxylum sp.
*
Polyalthia sp. &amp;lt; \0x25BA
Canthium sp.
*
Oncosperma horridum &amp;lt;- ------ \0x25BA
Animals
Lizard
*
Flying Lizard &amp;lt; \0x25BA
Millipede * *
Cicada
*
Centipede
*
Locust
*
Walking Stick
*
Leaf Insect
*
Scorpion
</figure>
<page confidence="0.990014" page_id="56293382"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
38
</page>
<figure confidence="0.87798225" page_id="56293382"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
HORNBILLS IN THAILAND - 2005
Summary of hornbill nesting in 2005
Khao Yai National Park
No.
nests
Female
imprisoned
Successes
Failures
No
data
Great Hornbill
</figure>
<page confidence="0.73715075" page_id="56293382"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
38
33
20
13
</page>
<figure confidence="0.948915666666666" page_id="56293382"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
0
Wreathed Hornbill
White-throated
18
16
16
0
0
Brown Hornbill
</figure>
<page confidence="0.745206333333333" page_id="56293382"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
19
17
17
</page>
<figure confidence="0.913855" page_id="56293382"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
0
n
Oriental Pied Hornbill
</figure>
<page confidence="0.926782333333333" page_id="56293382"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
51
32
31
</page>
<figure confidence="0.985207333333333" page_id="56293382"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
1
0
Total
</figure>
<page confidence="0.8646445" page_id="56293382"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
126
98
</page>
<figure confidence="0.9674086" page_id="56293382"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
84
14
0
Huai Kha Khaeng Wildlife Sanctuary
No.
nests
Female
imprisoned
Successes
Failures
No
data
Great Hornbill
9
6
3
2
1
Rufous-necked Hornbill
11
2
1
0
1
Plain-pouched Hornbill
8
3
3
0
0
TickelTs Brown Hornbill
10
6
2
1
3
Oriental Pied Hornbill
8
2
2
0
0
Total
46
19
11
3
5
Budo Sungai-Padi National Park
No.
nests
Female
imprisoned
Successes
Failures
No
data
Great Hornbill
62
26
21
3
0
Rhinoceros Hornbill
46
</figure>
<page confidence="0.634101" page_id="56293382"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
13
11
</page>
<figure confidence="0.987310363636364" page_id="56293382"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
2
0
Helmeted Hornbill
13
3
3
0
0
Wreathed Hornbill
16
9
8
1
0
Bushy-crested Hornbill
15
3
3
0
0
White-crowned Hornbill
8
0
0
0
0
Total
160
53
46
6
0
Dr Pilai Poonswad, Secretary-General of the Hornbill Research
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.925268666666667" page_id="56293382"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
Foundation, has written to thank the society for its support in helping
conserve hornbills in Thailand. It is an ongoing study and the foundation
continues to collect hornbill data at the above areas and needs and welcomes
the Avicultural Society's continued support. This we have given by again
this year adopting a pair of Rhinoceros Hornbills and a pair of Great
Hornbills.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998398" page_id="56293383"  page_num="39" year="" vol="">
39
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700099333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293383" page_num="39" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE GREEN-NAPED LORIKEET
Trichoglossus haematodus haematodus
IN A MIXED-SPECIES EXHIBIT AT OREGON ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.978242882352941" page_id="56293383"  page_num="39" year="" vol="">
by Rick Yazzolino, Shawn St. Michael and Charlie Rutkowski
Oregon Zoo's lorikeet exhibit houses 84 lories of 10 different species.
This multi-species flock environment presented a number of problems, which
needed to be overcome before a successful breeding programme could be
developed. We believe that many of the techniques used here can be
incorporated into other programmes and for other species to help improve
breeding success.
The lorikeet exhibit was opened in 1999. It consists of an outside walk-
through aviary and an off-exhibit indoor holding area. The L-shaped aviary
measures 75ft and 50ft (22.8m and 15.2m) at the sides and is framed by 20ft
(6m) tall fibreglass posts, draped with wire mesh which forms the walls and
roof. A covered walkway contains infrared heaters to provide supplementary
heat in inclement weather. A pool is provided to give the birds the opportunity
to bathe. The indoor area has a large 16ft x 8ft x 9ft (4.8m x 2.4m x 2.7m)
flight and two smaller holding cages. Each holding area can be connected
by opening a small hatchway between them.
The covered walkway.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.985622" page_id="56293384"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
40
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.758103" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293384" page_num="40" year="" vol="">
YAZZOLINO ET AL - GREEN-NAPED LORIKEET
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999228863636364" page_id="56293384"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
The feeding regime consisted of Cuttlefish Nectar (V4 cup powder to 6
cups water) in the morning and afternoon, with fruit put out in the middle of
the day. In addition, Bird of Paradise pellets are available ad-lib. The general
public is allowed to feed the birds small cups of apple juice. The feeding of
fruit in the exhibit proved problematic. The birds left as many little pieces
of fruit as they ate and these attracted rats. To reduce this problem all feeding
except that by the public was moved indoors.
In 2000 nest-boxes were placed in the exhibit. The boxes measure lOin
x 9in x lOin (approx. 25cm x 23cm x 25cm) with a 2in (5cm) diameter hole.
The floor of the nest-boxes was covered with fine wood chips. The birds
took to the boxes and produced nestlings. However, several problems
occurred. The nest-boxes were checked on a regular basis and the parents
became aggressive during these inspections. Also, when the nestlings fledged
they were mobbed by some of the more aggressive birds and this resulted in
the death of some of the fledglings. To help protect them one particularly
aggressive bird was removed from the flock. Another problem was that the
fledglings were mobbed by other birds whenever they 'food called'. These
problems resulted in a low 25% survival rate for fledglings.
Several steps were taken to resolve these problems. The first was to
train the birds to come into the holding area. Initial training consisted of
blowing a whistle when feeding the birds fresh nectar. The birds were given
The doorway into the holding area.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.466413" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293385" page_num="41" year="" vol="">
YAZZOLINO ET AL - GREEN-NAPED LORIKEET
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998273" page_id="56293385"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
41
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.994673608695652" page_id="56293385"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
a few minutes to come in, after which the door to the holding area was
closed. They quickly leamt to do this, in fact after a short time the whistle
was abandoned, as the birds come in as soon as they hear the sound of the
blender. This allows us to check and monitor all the nest -boxes. There are
two caveats to this, the first being that if a bird does not come in and there
are nestlings in boxes, the birds are shut in for only a few minutes. This
reduces the amount of time birds not shut in have to get up courage to go
into these nest-boxes. The second caveat is that when new birds are put out
in the exhibit, the door is left open and nectar is placed on the ledge, to give
the new birds an opportunity to find the nectar and learn to find their way
back into the holding area.
By checking and monitoring the nest-boxes, we know exactly when the
eggs were laid, when they hatched and when the nestlings are about to fledge.
We can also monitor other problems such as 'over grooming'. If the adults
break or pull out blood feathers when doing this, we know that the nestlings
will have a more difficult time fledging.
Another hurdle we had to overcome was developing protocols for hand-
rearing the nestlings. They are raised by their parents up to about day 50 or
just prior to fledging. They are then brought inside and placed in a Brinsea
TLC 4 brooder set at 28*C (82 4*F), As soon as possible the chicks have to
be taught how to feed themselves. Chicks receive nourishment from their
parents by holding their head up. We have to teach them to eat with their
Brinsea TLC 4 brooder.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997169" page_id="56293386"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
42
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.737656" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293386" page_num="42" year="" vol="">
YAZZOLINO ET AL - GREEN-NAPED LORIKEET
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997189086956522" page_id="56293386"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
head down. We do this by holding the syringe above the chicks' heads and
dribbling nectar down, which initiates the 'gobbling' response. The syringe
is then moved down towards the bowl of nectar. By repeatedly doing this
the chicks quickly learn to feed themselves.
We use a syringe to start teaching the chick to feed itself and work towards getting it to
feed from a bowl.
The chicks will eat much better if the nectar is warmed to about 32.2*C
(90*F). The nectar should not be allowed to sit for more than three hours, as
after this it begins to deteriorate. Removing the nectar after three hours and
replacing it with fresh nectar will also help prevent 'sour crop'. If the chicks
are removed from the nest before day 50, Exact(R) is added to their nectar. If
this is given to older chicks in small amounts, we have found that it has a
tendency to cause loose stools and if it is fed exclusively, it can bind them
up.
The chicks are first introduced to fruit by blending it into the nectar.
Then later fruit is placed in the flight. They are also provided with Bird of
Paradise pellets and fresh water. At about day 50, the chicks are moved to
one of the indoor flights. Here they have the opportunity to climb on the
wire mesh and on the branches. They also get to bond with chicks from
other nests and start to learn to fly. To further strengthen their breast muscles,
we give the chicks flight training. This is done by getting all of the other
birds to go out of the indoor flight and then closing the door. The chicks are
then placed on the floor of the flight and are encouraged to fly. Placing
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.466539" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293387" page_num="43" year="" vol="">
YAZZOLINO ET AL - GREEN-NAPED LORIKEET
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999761" page_id="56293387"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.98262185" page_id="56293387"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
them on the floor ensures that we know whether or not they are strong enough
to fly and eliminates the possibility of injury that could occur were they
encouraged to take off from a perch or were just tossed into the air.
Eventually they are encouraged to fly around the indoor flight. To do
this we use a feather duster. Once the birds are flying strongly they are
introduced into the flock. Observers ensure that the birds get along well. In
a number of instances we have seen the parent birds go back to feeding their
offspring.
The steps described above have in the past three years enabled the flock
of lorikeets here at Oregon Zoo to go from a 25% success rate to a 90%-
100% success rate in the number of young raised. We believe that our ability
to monitor the eggs and chicks, teaching them to feed themselves and, most
importantly, giving them flight training, have contributed greatly to this
success.
The importance of the fledglings being able to escape from the more
aggressive birds in the flock cannot be understated. We believe that the
steps we have taken can also be undertaken at other facilities where birds
are housed in flock situations and can also be applied to other species.
Charlie Rutkowski can be contacted at: 4550 NW 186th Ave., Portland,
Oregon 97229-2044, USA. Tel:(503) 645-9504. You can visit the Oregon
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.93920725" page_id="56293387"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
Zoo website at:www. oregonzoo.org
* * *
MARVIN L. JONES 1928-2006
Josef Lindholm has reported the death in California of Marvin L. Jones.
</table>
<reference confidence="0.848537333333333">
Marvin's, A History of the Genus Picathartes in Captivity, 1948-2002, was
published in the AviculturalMagazine VoL 109, No.3, pp. 125-129, Vol. 109,
No.4, pp. 167-173 (2003) &amp; Vol. 110, No. 1, pp.9-16 (2004). It was published,
Josef pointed out, 50 years after Marvin's first article, Birds of the Cologne
Zoological Gardens, appeared in the Avicultural Magazine Vol.60, No.l,
pp.26-30 (1954), when Marvin was stationed in Germany with the US Army.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.99787" page_id="56293388"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
44
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.98267" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293388" page_num="44" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
HORNBILLS OF AFRICA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9918413" page_id="56293388"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
A new aviary called Hombills of Africa, has been opened at the World of
Birds Wildlife Sanctuary, Hout Bay, Cape Town, the continent's largest bird
park. The aviary houses a number of species of African hombills, ranging
from several of the smaller Tockus spp. up to larger hombills such as the
Silvery-cheeked Bycanistes brevis , Black-and-white-casqued B.
subcylindricus and the Black-casqued Wattled Ceratogymna atrata.
Nine nooks with tables and chairs are spaced throughout the enclosure,
at which visitors can sit and relax and watch for the birds moving among the
dense foliage above. Tea, coffee and cold drinks and sandwiches can be
obtained at a nearby cafeteria and taken back to the tables and it is hoped
that the hombills will eventually become tmsting enough to come down to
them in search of titbits.
The World of Birds has also announced that it has lodged an application
with Cape Town City Council to lease and administer an adjoining public
open space, which has a large dam. It has many rescued gulls, Egyptian
Gees q Alopochen aegyptiacus , Hadada Ibis Bostrychia hagedash and other
waterbirds and desperately needs a release site along with a safe sanctuary
for permanently handicapped birds. It is envisioned that it will eventually
be populated by pelicans, cranes, storks, herons, egrets, ibises, spoonbills,
and ducks and geese.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.833322" page_id="56293388"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
* * *
NEARLY A HUNDRED IN CAPTIVITY
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.956671117647059" page_id="56293388"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
"There are now believed to be nearly 100 Spix's Macaws Cyanopsitta
spixii living in captivity", wrote Avicultural Society member Tony Pittman
in a letter in a letter published in Cage &amp; Aviary Birds , March 16th, p.6.
One was hatched on January 17th at Loro Parque, Tenerife, where two
Spix's Macaws were hatched in 2004. The egg laid on Christmas Day 2005,
was unexpected and outside the species' usual breeding period. The young
macaw, a female, will be paired with a young male hatched in 2004, which
with its parents, was imported into Germany from Switzerland last year.
In early May 2005, two young were hatched at Sheikh Saoud Al-Thani's
A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation in Qatar. Sadly, later there was an outbreak
of Proventricular Dilatation Disease (PDD) amongst the macaws kept there,
which resulted in at least three fatalities. In September, 15 Spix's Macaws
acquired from Roland Messer in Switzerland, were transferred from that
country to A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation in Qatar. Another Spix's Macaw,
a female, was hatched there towards the end of October. If you would like
to learn more and keep up to date with the latest developments regarding
Spix's Macaw, Tony has a website: www.bluemacaws.org
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700292" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293389" page_num="45" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99025" page_id="56293389"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
45
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.987062" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293389" page_num="45" year="" vol="">
SOUTH AFRICAN VULTURE UNIT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990915363636364" page_id="56293389"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
The De Wildt Vulture Unit (e-mail:vulture@dewildt.org.za) was
established in 1990 to serve as a rehabilitation and holding facility for injured,
poisoned and disabled vultures. The aim is to rehabilitate them to the point
where they can be successfully released back into the wild. Birds that recover,
but are no fit enough to be released, but can live good lives in captivity, are
accommodated at the unit on a permanent basis. Some of these birds are
utilised in the unit's educational and awareness programmes, aimed at
farming communities, schools and bird clubs. The unit also goes into urban
communities and out into rural communities to educate children about vulture
conservation The birds are also utilised in research programmes and are
encouraged to breed in captivity.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.724873" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293389" page_num="45" year="" vol="">
* t *
COMMON IN SOUTHERN SOUTH AMERICA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9790951" page_id="56293389"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
The Wilson Journal of Ornithology (formerly The Wilson Bulletin)
Vol.118, No.l, March 2006, includes a paper (pp.85-90) on the breeding
biology of the Double-collared Seedeater Sporophila caerulescens. Mercival
R. Francisco studied the reproductive biology of this common seedeater in
south-east Brazil, where during seven breeding seasons between 1997-2003,
41 nests were studied. Nesting occurred from December-May and all nests
contained two eggs, laid on consecutive days, with incubation commencing
the morning after the female laid the second egg. Incubation and nestling
periods were 12 days and 12-15 days, respectively. Only the female incubated
the eggs.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.64337625" page_id="56293389"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
* * *
ENDANGERED CONURE
Chester Zoo is thought to be one of only two zoos in Europe keeping the
Grey-breasted Conure Pyrrhura griseipectus , a Critically Endangered species
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.9906861" page_id="56293389"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
endemic to north-east Brazil This conure, only recently accorded species
status, was previously regarded as a subspecies of the White-eared Conure
P. leucotis.
After the zoo's pair of Red-billed Curassows Crax blumenhachii lost
the chick from it first clutch earlier in 2005, the pair unexpectedly nested
again later in the year and the egg was artificially incubated and the chick
was reared by a domestic hen.
The zoo, which last year bred a spectacular 51 Java Sparrows Padda
oryzivora , has established a breeding flock of these birds in its Dragons in
Danger exhibit, home to its Komodo Dragons Varanus komodoensis.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996827" page_id="56293390"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
46
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9825835" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293390" page_num="46" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
AFRICAN HAPPENINGS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.979947333333333" page_id="56293390"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
The latest Bulletin of the African Bird Club Vol. 13, No. 1, March 2006,
includes several records likely to be of interesting to aviculturists. Among
them is the record of 23 Grey Parrots Psittacus erithacus seen on October
8th last year in the Kakamega Forest, western Kenya, 10 years after this
species was thought to be extinct at that locality (p. 102). Elsewhere (pp.84-
85), Victor Mamonekene and Frederic Lambert Bokanza-Paco report the
sighting of Grey-necked Picathartes Picathartes oreas in Congo-Brazzaville,
the first record for that country and the southernmost locality at which this
species has been recorded.
There is also the first record of the Rose-coloured Starling Sturnus roseus
for Ethiopia and sub-Saharan Africa (p.75). A single bird was seen on the
ground with a group of Wattled Starlings Creatophora cinerea. Other records
include the first Desert Eagle Owl Bubo ascalaphus for Burkina Faso (pp.78-
79), the first record of the Blackcap Sylvia atricapilla in Mozambique (pp.
80-81) and the first sightings of Pink-backed Pelicans Pelecanus rufescens
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.8967884" page_id="56293390"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
in Madagascar since 1960 (pp.86-87).
* * *
THE FLAMINGO SPECIALIST GROUP (FSG)
This group was established in 1978 at Tour du Valat in France, under the
leadership of Dr Alan Johnson, who coordinated the group until 2004.
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.910808235294118" page_id="56293390"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
Currently, it is coordinated from the Wildfowl &amp; Wetlands Trust at
Slimbridge, here in the UK, as part of the IUCN-SSC/W etlands International
Waterbird Network.
The FSG is a global network of flamingo specialists (both scientists and
non-scientists) concerned with the study, monitoring, management and
conservation of the world's flamingos. Its role is to actively promote flamingo
research and conservation worldwide by encouraging the exchange of
information and cooperation amongst these specialists and those of other
relevant organisations, particularly IUCN-SSC, Ramsar, WWF International
and BirdLife International.
FSG members are working with both wild and captive flamingos. They
are undertaking field surveys, tracking flamingo movements, studying their
breeding biology and diseases, and are involved in data management. Further
information about the FSG can be obtained from Dr Brooks Childress,
Wildfowl &amp; Wetlands Trust, Slimbridge, Glos. GL2 7BT, UK. Tel:+44
(0)1453 860437/Fax:+44 (0)1453 860437/E-mail: Brooks.Childress
@wwt. org.uk
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700615" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293391" page_num="47" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994427" page_id="56293391"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
47
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996689" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293391" page_num="47" year="" vol="">
HAVEN OF TRANQUILITY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.965034916666667" page_id="56293391"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
During the latter part of last year, Brian A. G. Hill - who is now back in
Greece - visited Brazil and while in Belen, made frequent visits to the
zoological-botanical garden, less than a V 2 -hour walk from where he was
staying. It occupies only one block of the city, he wrote, but it is such a
representative "jungly" last remnant of forest near the city centre, that not
only offers some tranquility from the bustle and noise of the city, but also a
most prestigious institution, Museu Emilio Goeldi, dating from about 1894.
Brian provided the following list of the live birds exhibited there: Maguari
Stork Ciconia maguari , Wood Stork Mycteria americana. Harpy Eagle
Harpia harpyja , Snowy Egret Egretta thula , Great Egret Ardea alba , Scarlet
Ibis Eudocimus ruber , Black-bellied Whistling Duck Dendrocygna
autumnalis, White-faced Whistling Duck D. viduata , Rufescent Tiger Heron
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.7388075" page_id="56293391"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
Trigrisoma lineatum , Striated Heron Butorides striatus , White-necked Heron
A. cocoi , Buff-browed Chachalaca Ortalis superciliaris , Cock-of-the-Rock
Rupicola rupicola, Sunbittem Eurypyga helias , Chestnut-fronted Macaw
Ara severa, White-crested Guan Penelopepileata , Rusty-margined Guan P.
superciliaris , Bare-faced Curassow Crax fasciolata, Ariel Toucan
Ramphastos vitellinus ariel and White-throated Toucan R. tucanus.
* * *
NEW AT WHIPSNADE
Whipsnade Wild Animal Park has received a pair of Sulawesi Tarictic
Hombills Penelopides exarhatus sanfordi from San Diego Wild Animal Park.
Curator John Ellis describes the male hombill as looking "stunning". Now
that Whipsnade's two American Bald Eagles Haliaeetus leucocephalus are
adult, they have been withdrawn from the bird shows and housed in a new
18ft (approx. 5.4m) high aviary in the Bird Garden, in which it is hoped the
pair will breed.
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.922843" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293391" page_num="47" year="" vol="">
TOUCAN BREEDING CENTRE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9727312" page_id="56293391"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
A breeding centre to house 16 pairs of toucans, namely eight pairs of
Toco Toucans Ramphastos toco and two pairs each of Channel-billed Toucans
R. v. vitellinus , Red-billed or White-throated Toucans R. tucanus , Choco
Toucans R. brevis and Plate-billed Mountain Toucans Andigena laminirostris,
is being established at the Dutch Parrot Sanctuary, Oerle, the Netherlands.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.362027" page_id="56293391"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.564991" genericHeader="method" page_id="56293391" page_num="47" year="" vol="">
ESSEX SUCCESSES
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.835333666666667">
Last year, Colchester Zoo, bred three Hamerkop Scopus umbretta. The
trio hatched in early July and fledged in late August. Two pairs of Ruppell's
Griffon Vultures Gyps ruepellii each reared a chick.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.997788" page_id="56293392"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
48
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9829275" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293392" page_num="48" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
SAVING THE GOULDIAN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99411608" page_id="56293392"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
Mike Fidler, who with Tasmanian finch breeder Marcus Pollard, has set
up the Save the Gouldian Fund - website:www.savethegouldian.org - is
appealing to aviculturists to help save this iconic species. A few years ago,
Mike retired and with his wife Elisabeth, moved from the UK to Australia,
where in 2003, he gave A$600,000 (approx. #250,000 or US$450,000) to
the Australian Wildlife Conservancy (AWC) to fund research on the Gouldian
Finch Erythrura gouldiae in Mornington Wildlife Sanctuary, formerly
Momington Station, in northern Western Australia's Kimberley region. Mike
is also funding University of New South Wales researchers and allowing
them unfettered use of his state-of-the-art aviary facilities and the birds
housed in them.
There are perhaps some 2,000 or so Gouldians living in small isolated
groups in Western Australia and the Northern Territory, wrote Karen McGhee
in an article entitled - The exquisite Gouldian Finch is one of the world's
most prized caged birds. But can a multi-million dollar rescue mission save
it in the wild? (. Australian Geographic , July-September 2005, pp.39-45).
They are, she wrote, fragmented remnants of a population that may once
have numbered tens of thousands, or even hundreds of thousands, that
inhabited vast areas of savannah woodland across tropical northern Australia.
Now, the biggest flocks found in the Northern Territory and the
Kimberley, number little more than a few hundred birds. The decline was
first noted about 30 years ago in Queensland, then in the Northern Territory
and most recently in Western Australia. The Gouldian is just one of several
species of native Australian birds fast disappearing due to habitat changes
brought about, it is believed, by altered fire regimes and the spread of cattle.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.324063" page_id="56293392"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
* * *
THE MAN WHO BRED THE GRENADA DOVE
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.864878555555555" page_id="56293392"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
Recently the society was contacted by a lady who has in her possession
the Avicultural Society medal awarded to H. E. Bright for the first breeding
of Leptotila wellsi. Could we, she wondered, tell her anything about H. E.
Bright and the award of the medal?
It was reasonably easy to discover that H. E. Bright was Herbert Bright
and that the medal was awarded to him in 1926 for the first breeding of the
Grenada Dove. According to Dave Coles's First Breeding Records of Birds
Reared to Independence under Controlled Conditions in the United Kingdom ,
Herbert Bright was also credited with the first breeding in the UK of the
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.75613675">
Namaqua Dove Oena capensis (1915), Gold-billed Saltator Saltator
aurantirostris (1921), White-breasted or Jobi Ground Dove Gallicolumba
jobiensis (1922), Marquesas Ground Dove G. rubescens and Soccoro or
Grayson's Dove Zenaida graysoni (both 1926).
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99816" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56293393" page_num="" year="" vol="">
LATEST FBF BREEDING REGISTER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.915390024390244" page_id="56293393"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Foreign Bird Federation Register of Birds Bred in the UK under
Controlled Conditions for the Years 2001-2004 has recently been published.
It lists information provided by many (though not all) private aviculturists
and public collections in the UK. It reveals that in 2004, 15,104 birds, of
494 species, were reported as having been bred. The figures for 2003 were
roughly the same, while the number reported as having been bred in 2002
was higher (18,415) and, in 2001, was considerably lower (6,499).
This attractively presented, 32-page publication, the twenty-first in the
series, dating back to 1984, provides a fascinating 'snapshot' of which species
are currently being kept and bred in the UK - and how many. It is gratifying
to see the growing number of species being bred, but of concern to see that
others are it seems no longer being bred or are being bred in smaller numbers
than before, e.g. no Elliot's Syrmaticus ellioti, Mikado S. mikado or Reeves's
Pheasants S. reevesii are listed as having been bred in 2004. Twenty-eight
species of pigeons and doves, including the Pheasant Pigeon Otidiphaps
nobilis aruensis and Victoria Crowned Pigeon Goura victoria , were bred in
2004. Among the parrots, 110 Blue-and-Yellow Macaws Ara ararauna were
bred in 2004 and 389 Grey Parrots Psittacus e. erithacus (compared with
523 in 2003 and 732 in 2002).
Eight Green Aracaris Pterglossus viridis were bred in 2004 and five in
2003. Turaco and hombill numbers are lower than might be expected and
the only barbet listed as having been bred during 2001-2004 is the Red-and-
Yellow Trachyphonus erythrocephalus. Seven species of laughingthrushes
Garrulax spp. were bred during the same period. Ten White-naped Yuhinas
Yuhina bakeri and 10 Emerald Starlings Lamprotornis iris were bred in 2004,
but just eight Bali Starlings Leucopsar rothschildi are listed for that year,
against 17 the previous year.
Fifty Black-crowned Waxbills Estrilda nonnula are listed as having been
bred in 2004, but just five Lavender Waxbills E. caerulescens and six
Crimson-rumped Waxbills E. rhodopygia. Eight Western Bluebills
Spermophaga haematina and eight Dybowski's Twinspots Euschistospiza
dybowskii were bred in 2004. Australian finches and parrot finches Erythrura
spp. generally bred well, as did all three silverbills Lonchura spp. and the
Java Sparrow Padda oryzivora. However, only four Bronze-winged
Mannikins L. cucullata are listed as having been bred in 2004 and no Timor
Sparrows P.fuscata. Twenty-six Cuban Finches Tiaris canora were bred in
2004, 54 in 2003 and 52 the year before.
Copies, price #5 (post free), are available from the FBF Registrar, Reuben
B. Girling, 11 Deramore Drive, Badger Hill, York YO10 5HW, UK. A few
copies of earlier Breeding Registers remain available price #2. Cheques
(sterling only) should be made payable to the Foreign Bird Federation.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.792253740740741" page_id="56293394"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
3 9088 01174 3747
CONTENTS
The Avicultural Society
1
Further success with the Brown Twinspot Clytospiza monteiri ,
including the first parent-reared young
by Andy Chaney. 2
Breeding the Sooty-headed Bulbul Pycnonotus aurigaster
by Jim Jerrard.4
The Autumn Social Meeting - 2005
by Paul Boulden.5
Cotswold Wildlife Park Review of 2005
by Louise Peat.6
The Chestnut-bellied Seed-Finch Oryzoborus angolensis
in the wild and in aviculture
by Robin Restall. 10
Hand-rearing a Spangled Cotinga Cotinga cayana
by John E. R. Francis. 19
Breeding the St Vincent Parrot Amazona guildingii
by Henry Quinque. 24
Hombills in Thailand - 2005 . 34
Breeding the Green-naped Lorikeet Trichoglossus haematodus
haematodus in a mixed-species exhibit at Oregon Zoo
by Rick Yazzolino, Shawn St. Michael and Charlie Rutkowski .. 39
News &amp; Views.44
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</table>
</algorithms>
