<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<equation confidence="0.764165666666667" page_id="56253596"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
?/
Z 7 AVICULTURAL
\T\
MAGAZINE ( a V
VOLUME 117
No. 4
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990762" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253597" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.96460475" page_id="56253597"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2011: British Isles #21.00:
Overseas #24.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the
Society later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of
the AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.687655" page_id="56253597"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, SHERATON LODGE, STATION ROAD, SOUTHMINSTER,
ESSEX CM0 7EW, UK.
</construct>
<bodyText confidence="0.94756275" page_id="56253597"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Barclays Bank, Bumham-on-Crouch Branch. Please
quote Account No. 13296954, Sort Code 20 54 30, and ensure you send your
name as the account reference, or else we cannot match payments. In case
of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and Treasurer at the address
above, or e-mail: otusscops@talktalk.net
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have not
been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of a
particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history. Articles
should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the scientific
names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given. References
cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line drawings,
black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular point in
the article will be used where possible and should be clearly captioned. If
authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when submitting the
article and write their name on the back of each photograph. Tables and
graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be aware of
the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of the page
which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997594" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56253597" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982475333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.878263" genericHeader="method" page_id="56253598" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.921563" page_id="56253598"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 117-No. 4 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2011
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.970266333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56253598" page_num="" year="" vol="">
NEW STUDIES FIND CHALLENGES AND
OPPORTUNITIES FOR THE CONSERVATION OF
PRINCE RUSPOLI'S TURACO Tauraco ruspolii
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.951684896551724" page_id="56253598"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Alazar Daka, Tolera Kurnsa, Luca Borghesio,
Jean-Marc Lemould and Afework Bekele
The Ethiopian highlands are home to two endemic species of turaco,
the widespread White-cheeked Turaco Tauraco leucotis and the globally-
threatened Prince Ruspoli's Turaco I ruspolii. The two turacos co-occur
only in a small region of southern Ethiopia, where T. leucotis lives mainly
in forest and T. ruspolii mainly in more open woodland vegetation. Natural
hybrids of the two species were reported in 2002, which may pose a further
threat to the survival of T. ruspolii. Field work was carried out between
November 2007-June 2010 to evaluate the abundance and distribution of
the turaco hybrids and the impact of human-caused habitat change on Prince
Ruspoli's Turaco. We obtained 342 records of T. leucotis , 231 of T. ruspolii
and nine of hybrids. Hybrids were observed in the overlap zone between
the ranges of the two parent species, suggesting that they are widespread in
the region. Turaco hybrids are difficult to recognise and can only be safely
distinguished from pure individuals at close range, therefore, we believe
that the abundance of hybrids may have been underestimated. All of the
hybrids were observed in anthropized habitats (i.e. habitats transformed or
adapted either to meet the needs of humans, or by human activity), suggesting
that habitat change may be one of the causes of hybridization. Recorded
frequencies of T. ruspolii were quite high, especially in the Sede and Lela
Lemu area, where human presence was limited. Recorded rates of turacos
decreased in more anthropized habitats.
Five species of birds are endemic to the highlands of southern Ethiopia,
an area of only 37,000sq km (approx. 14,285sq miles) and, therefore, smaller
than the size of Denmark. Besides being biologically rich, the region is also
densely populated and the impact of the human population continues to
grow: satellite images show a 40% reduction in natural habitats in the past
40 years. It is not surprising, therefore, that two of the endemic species of
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999519" page_id="56253599"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
146
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.455481" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253599" page_num="146" year="" vol="">
DAKA ET AL - PRINCE RUSPOLI'S TURACO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.992615219512195" page_id="56253599"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
birds - the Ethiopian Bush Crow Zavattariornis stresemanni and the Liben
Lark Heteromirafra sidamoensis - have been moved to higher categories
of threat in the latest versions of the IUCN Red List. Little is known about
another of the endemic birds of southern Ethiopia, the charismatic Prince
Ruspoli's Turaco, a bird which figures prominently in many of the best
known books on African birds, but which not many people have had the
pleasure to see.
The range of Prince Ruspoli's Turaco extends over an area of only
7,000sq km (approx. 2,700sq miles), in which agriculture, towns, mines and
roads are expanding at a fast pace. Add to this the menace of hybridization
with the White-cheeked Turaco, which is much more widespread in the
Ethiopian highlands and extends into Eritrea and Sudan and, moreover, also
occurs on the edge of the range of Prince Ruspoli's Turaco. Observations of
natural hybrids of the two species, first reported in 2002, have multiplied in
recent years, raising concerns that the genetic integrity of this rare species
may be at risk. Many authors have, in fact, proposed that environments
disturbed by human activity are conducive to hybridization.
There are a number of questions which require answers, these include:
What is the current conservation status of Prince Ruspoli's Turaco?
What is the impact of habitat change on Prince Ruspoli's Turaco and
which are the most important sites for its conservation?
Is habitat change a cause of the hybridization between the White-cheeked
and Prince Ruspoli's Turaco?
How numerous are hybrid turacos compared with pure-bred
individuals?
In an attempt to answer these questions, a survey was undertaken in the
northern part of its range, where it co-occurs with the White-cheeked Turaco.
This area is a broad ecotone (transitional) belt, which includes dense forests
on its northern edge, shading towards progressively drier and more open
woodland, with a mix of trees and open habitats. Finally, the habitat at the
most southerly edge of the area becomes dry bushland.
Between November 2007-June 2010, two of the authors (Alazar Daka and
Tolera Kumsa, who are students at the University of Addis Ababa), combed
the study area and used recordings of the calls of the two species of turaco
in an attempt to determine their exact numbers and distribution. A total of
more than 900 sites were visited and 342 records were obtained of I leucotis ,
231 of I ruspolii and nine of hybrids. The results show that the two turacos
have different habitat preferences, with the White-cheeked being a largely
forest species, while Prince Ruspoli's Turaco becomes progressively less
abundant as the forest becomes more dense. Prince Ruspoli's Turaco tends
to be more abundant where there is more abundant open woodland with
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.503976" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253600" page_num="147" year="" vol="">
DAK A ET AL - PRINCE RUSPOLI'S TURACO
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999196" page_id="56253600"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
147
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999402195121951" page_id="56253600"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
tall trees mixed with a matrix of shrubs and open spaces. Thus, it is at the
edge of the forest that the two turacos come in contact with each other and
have more chances to hybridize. The original division of habitat between
the White-cheeked Turaco and Prince RuspolEs Turaco can be seen very
clearly around Sede and Lela Lemu, where some of the best preserved forests
survive. This area remains relatively uninhabited by people and scarcely
modified by agriculture. In Sede and Lela Lemu, the White-cheeked Turaco
occurs only in forest, whereas Prince Ruspoli's Turaco is found at the edge
and outside of the forest. No turaco hybrids were observed in Sede and Lela
Lemu, though the coverage of these sites remains insufficient to conclude
that absolutely no hybrids occur there.
To answer the question of what are the effects of habitat degradation on
the hybridization of these two Ethiopian turacos, we focused our attention
on the area between Shakiso and Kebre Mengist, the largest towns in the
region. There, deforestation has been intense and natural forest has been
eroded and thinned by the removal of large trees for their timber. Open
habitats have been observed in what was formerly dense forest and, where
forest persists, its structure is much more open and discontinuous due to
illegal logging and the removal of firewood, as well as other forms of human
disturbance. In partly deforested regions, the White-cheeked Turaco may
remain in small patches of remnant forest, along rivers and in plantations of
exotic trees such as Eucalyptus spp. and Cupressus lusitanica , which have
greatly expanded in the area over the past 20 years. At the same time, at
partly deforested sites, Prince Ruspoli's Turaco may be able to move into
forests which have been made more open and discontinuous by the selective
felling of trees. Therefore, in landscapes modified by human activity, the
two species may come in contact with each other far more frequently and
the chances of hybridization may be increased. Our results support this
hypothesis, as observations in Shakiso and Kebre Mengist suggest that the
distribution of the two species overlaps far more frequently than it does in
Sede and Lela Lemu. The division of habitat in Shakiso and Kebre Mengist
is much less clearly defined than it is in Sede and Lela Lemu and, indeed,
the area of contact between the two turacos may be much larger in Shakiso
and Kebre Mengist. As suspected, turaco hybrids were observed in this area
on several occasions. Therefore, our study provides initial support to the
hypothesis that habitat degradation can trigger hybridization between species.
Our data, however, remain limited, with observations of only nine turaco
hybrids having been recorded and, therefore, the sample size on which we
base our hypothesis is insufficient to draw definitive conclusions.
On the question of how abundant hybrid turacos are in the highlands of
southern Ethiopia, raw numbers suggest that hybrids make up only 1.6%
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999083" page_id="56253601"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
148
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.475732" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253601" page_num="148" year="" vol="">
DAKA ET AL - PRINCE RUSPOLFS TURACO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999285365853658" page_id="56253601"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
of the total number of observations recorded during field work. However,
we fear that this relatively low figure may be an underestimate, as hybrid
turacos are not easy to distinguish from pure-bred birds. Only birds of which
a good view is obtained at close range can safely be identified as hybrids
or pure-bred individuals. Moreover, we cannot exclude the possibility that
the external appearance of some hybrids may be so similar to that of either
one of the two parent species, that accurate identification in the field may,
in some cases, be impossible. Genetic tests on laboratory samples may be
the only means of establishing the true prevalence of turaco hybrids.
We do not know whether or not hybrid turacos are fertile and therefore
capable of reproduction with either of their parent species, Neither do we
know much about the behaviour of hybrid turacos. We know that hybrids
usually occur in mixed flocks in which both pure Prince Ruspoli's and White-
cheeked Turacos occur. However, a flock observed in July 2003 by Mike
Pennington, a professional tour guide, was composed of five hybrids with no
pure-bred individuals amongst them, which suggests that hybrid turacos can
at times occur independent of the parent species. Further research is required
to accurately evaluate the impact of hybridization on Prince Ruspoli's Turaco.
Current results suggest that as human-caused habitat degradation escalates,
reports of hybrid turacos may become increasingly more widespread.
Fortunately, Prince Ruspoli's Turaco remains abundant where appropriate
habitat occurs. Although more accurate estimates of the population density
will require further detailed analysis, it is reassuring to know that, where
woodland makes up 50% or more of the habitat, the recorded frequency of
Prince Ruspoli's Turaco is 0.3 or even higher (i.e. three or more observations
for each 10 points sampled). This suggests that it is present in satisfactory
numbers, especially when one considers that Prince Ruspoli's Turaco often
goes unrecorded due to its shy and silent behaviour. However, the frequency
of sightings decreases rapidly as the amount of agriculture increases, which
shows - if there was any need - that increased human activity will certainly
have a negative impact on the population of Prince Ruspoli's Turaco.
The results of our study also show the importance of the forests of Sede
and Lela Lemu for the conservation of Prince Ruspoli's Turaco. The large
expanses of woodland surrounding these forests are where Prince Ruspoli's
Turaco was most frequently observed and, the forests themselves, are among
the few remaining examples of largely intact montane forest in Ethiopia and
are important not only for the White-cheeked Turaco, but probably also for
many other birds, mammals and plants. These forests should be afforded
greater protection to save them from rapidly growing human disturbance,
which is bound to escalate, as large mining sites (gold has been found in the
area) and new roads are being opened close to them.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.307989" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253602" page_num="149" year="" vol="">
DAKA ET AL - PRINCE RUSPOLFS TURACO
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998187" page_id="56253602"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
149
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.813806" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56253602" page_num="149" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.44050825" page_id="56253602"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
Our research was funded by Conservation des Especes et des Populations
Animates (CEPA), France, Zoologische Gesellschaft fur Arten- und
Populationsschutz (ZGAP), Germany, Chester Zoo, International Turaco
Society (ITS) and The Avicultural Society, UK, Zoo Zlin, Czech Republic,
A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation (AWWP), Qatar and Addis Ababa University.
The support of these sponsors is very much appreciated. We also wish to
thank Dr Almaz Kebede and W/ro Erkeselam G/Tsadik for the administration
and for facilitating the funding through the Wildlife Conservation and
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.423093">
Environment Development Association of Ethiopia (WildCODE) and, Mike
</subsectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.9047676" page_id="56253602"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
Pennington and Ato Akale Yemane, for the assistance and information they
provided.
Alazar Daka, Tolera Kumsa and Afework Bekele, Biology Department,
Addis Ababa University, PO Box 1176, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia.
Luca Borghesio, Dept. Biological Sciences, University of Illinois at
Chigaco, Chicago, IL 60607, USA.
Jean-Marc Lemould, CEPA - Conservation des Especes et des Populations
Animales - 17 rue de I'etang, 68440 Schlierbach, France.
* * *
A FINAL REMINDER
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.70821525" page_id="56253602"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
Those of you who have not yet paid your 2012 subscription will not
receive any further issues of the magazine until your subscription for
2012 has been received, i.e. #21 for UK membership and #24 for overseas
membership, plus #6 if air mail is required. Cheques should be made payable
to The Avicultural Society and sent to: Peter Stocks, The Hon. Secretary
and Treasurer, The Avicultural Society, Sheraton Lodge, Station Road,
Southminster, Essex CM0 7EW. E-mail:otusscops@talktalk.net/ Tel:01621
772427.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.972001" page_id="56253603"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
150
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.775146" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253603" page_num="150" year="" vol="">
THE BEAUTIFUL BLUE-BELLIED ROLLER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.963608842105263" page_id="56253603"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
Coracias cyanogaster
by Gary Bralsford
I have never tired of the beauty of the Blue-bellied Roller Coracias
cyanogaster. I have had several pairs over the past six years or so, but now
concentrate on keeping just two pairs. I have a 2008-bred pair and a 2009-
bred pair. Both pairs were bred by my good friend Bob Jewiss in Kent and
are unrelated to one another and this year (2011), I succeeded in breeding
this species for the first time. Two young were reared, which have proved
to be a male and a female. Only one brood was raised, which is unusual as
they usually have two clutches.
This species was probably first brought to the UK from The Gambia by
Dr Emilius Hopkinson in 1925 and a colour plate of it from a painting by
Roland Green, illustrating an article about it by David Seth-Smith, was the
frontispiece in the magazine in February 1927.
The Blue-bellied Roller measures about 28cm-30cm (approx. 11 in-12in)
in length, plus an additional 6cm (approx. 2%in) which is accounted for by
the tail streamers. The entire head, neck, breast and upper mantle are pale
buffy or chalky white and the belly and under tail-coverts are dark ultramarine
blue, as are the wings and rump. There is a patch of light blue on the wings
and the tail is also shades of light blue. The back is brownish-black. When
it flies the wings have a pale blue bar or band running along the base of the
flight feathers. The sexes look alike. The juvenile is described later.
It is found in West Africa, in Senegal and The Gambia and in countries
including Guinea, Mali, northern Sierra Leone, Ghana, Nigeria and northern
Cameroon, eastwards to Chad, the Central African Republic, extreme
southern Sudan and the north-east of the Democratic Republic of Congo
(Zaire). It is most abundant in the west of its range and becomes increasingly
scarce further east. This lovely roller is both a resident species and an intra-
African migrant which undertakes a partial north-south migration linked to
the rains. It is a resident in the south of its range and these birds are joined
by birds from other areas in the dry season. They often migrate in small
flocks, with movements occurring in the months of October-January.
Its preferred habitat seems to be savannah woodland dominated by
Isoberlinia trees. It can, however, also be found in the rainforest zone,
plantations and burnt clearings where it hunts insects fleeing the area, as well
as being found in galley forest (forest bordering rivers in otherwise open
country) and dense woodland in which it searches for hollows in which to
nest. It is also said to occur in damp areas with scattered Borassus palms.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.641504" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253604" page_num="151" year="" vol="">
BRALSFORD - BLUE-BELLIED ROLLER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999108" page_id="56253604"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
151
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.98422743902439" page_id="56253604"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
It feeds mainly on grasshoppers, beetles, termites and large ants and also
take wasps, millipedes, earthworms, small skinks and snakes and has been
seen taking the fruits of the Oil Palm Elaeis guineensis. When it spots prey
on the ground, it swoops down and glides straight onto its prey. Most of its
food is taken on the ground but quite a lot is also taken on the wing. Its large
head, neck and bill, mean that once it has seized its prey, it seldom manages
to escape. These rollers make short work of a small mouse if it manages to
get into their aviary and are equally adept at dealing with dead day old chicks,
so should have no difficulty dealing with a small snake or lizard.
The Blue-bellied Roller is not as solitary as some of the other rollers and
often occurs in pairs, and groups of as many as six to 20 birds have been
recorded. They interact socially with one another - as my birds do at times
- and have mock chases and call to one another and may roost together. They
choose an exposed perch at the top of a tree and in my aviaries choose a
high perch on which to roost. Their flight is direct and due to their shallow
wing-beats has a laid-back look about it.
They can be territorial and males often outnumber females. Courtship in
the wild and in aviaries involves fast chases on the wing, which in aviaries
can occasionally result in injuries. In the wild, the bird often plummets
earthward, rolling from side to side and calling all the time as it rolls through
the air. Not all pairs or groups of birds attempt to nest during any one year.
This can cause those attempting to breed this species to think that their birds
may not be compatible or perhaps may not be a true pair. My birds made
little attempt to breed in 2010 because, I think, they were too young, but
one pair bred successfully this year.
The eggs are white and roundish in shape like owls' eggs (those of the
European Roller C. garrulus measure 35.4mm x 28.4mm and those of the
Indian Roller C. henghalensis 34.3mm x 28.1mm). In the wild, egg laying
has been recorded from February through to September. It breeds during the
rains and in the northern part of its range, in countries such as The Gambia,
for example, the resident birds are joined by additional birds which arrive
about May to breed, whereas in Cote d'Ivoire egg laying has been recorded
from February-September.
The Blue-bellied Roller (and other rollers) should, as a general rule, be
housed in the largest flight you can manage to provide for them, you will
then have the chance to see them perform their rolling display flights. These
are not, however, always strictly necessary, as they will breed, or attempt to
breed, in smaller enclosures. The flights in which my birds are housed are
1 Oft x 4ft x 6ft high (approx. 3m x 1.2m x 1.8m high).
My friends have no problems breeding the Blue-bellied Roller in 12ft
(3.6m) long flights. A few years ago, Rob Monks bred these rollers in one of
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999164" page_id="56253605"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
152
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.902463" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253605" page_num="152" year="" vol="">
BRALSFORD - BLUE-BELLIED ROLLER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.988306902439024" page_id="56253605"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
his flights and on that occasion the pair nested quite late in the yean Other
breeders, such as Richard Green and Harry Sissens, who have much larger
gardens than I have, have bred them in correspondingly larger aviaries.
When it comes to sexing Blue-bellied Rollers, I pay particular attention
to the shape of the head. Males seem to have a more domed or rounded
skull, whereas that of the female is flat on top. This is, of course, not a
foolproof method and DNA sexing is the most reliable way of ensuring that
you have a true pair. There can be some aggression between the male and
female and it is a good idea to have an area where the female can escape
the attention of the male.
My birds have access to a nest log approximately 1ft in diameter x
1ft 6in high (30cm in diameter x 46cm high) with a Tin (10cm) entrance
hole. The perches in the flights are as high as possible and as far apart as
possible. My birds' diet consists of an insectile mix, mixed with minced
(ground) beef. I also give them chopped day old chicks, as well as morio
worms, mealworms, waxworms and locusts or crickets, depending on which
of these I have available at the time. My birds love pachnoda grabs (fruit
beetle larvae), which are quite large and full of protein.
Bob Jewiss, who has had considerable success breeding the Blue-bellied
Roller, said that following an 18 days incubation period, the chicks spend
quite a long time in the nest - 34 days or more and it is even longer before
they are weaned. So, it can be a lengthy process of about three months from
the time the eggs are laid until the young become independent.
After the young have fledged, the nest log needs a good clean out, as
it is full of droppings and is quite smelly The Blue-bellied Roller usually
produces at least two clutches a year and is, therefore, a good bird to establish
in aviculture. My only concern is that as I mentioned earlier, in captivity,
as in the wild, a pair may breed one year and then take a break of a year or
more before breeding again. There could be a number of reasons for this,
particularly in captivity, while in the wild it is likely to be due to unsuitable
weather conditions resulting in a lack of food, or the right sort of food, on
which to rear the young.
When the young rollers fledge they look like duller versions of their
parents and it may be five to six months before they moult into adult plumage
and get their tail streamers.
I have found that Blue-bellied Rollers become quite tame and often
chatter away and greet me and seem to know when it is feeding time. Their
voice is not loud and their dry, clicking t6 ga-ga-gaa-gaa" uttered at three to
five second intervals, does not trouble my neighbours. I have sometimes
witnessed my rollers gorging themselves with food and then being unable
to fly back up onto the perch. Some individuals are more prone to this than
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.641465" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253606" page_num="153" year="" vol="">
BRALSFORD - BLUE-BELLIED ROLLER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999598" page_id="56253606"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
153
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9942159375" page_id="56253606"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
others. Therefore, I find it best not to give them too much food at one time,
but to feed them 'a little and often.' For such relatively large birds, Blue-
bellied Rollers have very small feet and it is essential to provide them with
suitable sized perching, as well as a frost-proof shelter during the winter, to
guard against them getting frost-bitten toes.
Quite a few European-bred birds have been appearing on dealers' lists.
These are being offered for sale at around #400 (approx. US$600) each,
which is quite a high price, but they are well worth it if you have the money
to spare.
I know of at least six other aviculturists in the UK who are breeding this
species and, with new birds being brought in from Europe, there are signs
that it could become established in UK aviculture. It can be kept with other
species in a large flight or in a tropical house, like I have seen it housed at
the Cotswold Wildlife Park, so long as the other birds are of a similar size
to the roller.
I am delighted to have at last bred the Blue-bellied Roller and hope for
further success with this species in 2012. Rollers are beautiful and colourful
birds and have personalties to match - they are truly tropical birds.
Another of the species kept in the UK is the Lilac-breasted Roller C.
caudatus , while others such as the Rufous-crowned C. naevius , Abyssinian
C. ahyssinicus and Racket-tailed C. spatulatus have appeared occasionally.
The Racket-tailed Roller was bred by Roger Cattermole in 1991 (see Vol.98,
No.l, pp.22-26 (1992)) and the once familiar Indian Roller was bred at
Blackpool Zoo in 1984. Surprisingly perhaps, the European species was
bred by W. H. St. Quintin way back in 1901 and the Lilac-breasted was first
bred by Herbert Whitley at Paignton in 1929. I believe Whitley bred the
subspecies C. c. lorti, which has the lilac confined to the throat.
Gary Bralsford has been keeping birds for more than 20 years. He keeps
mostly softbills, but also keeps a few other species and wrote recently about
breeding the Oriental Greenfinch Carduelis sinica (Vol.117, No. 2, pp.49-
50 (2011)) and his next article will be about the Burrowing Owl Athene
cunicularia. E-mail: gary.bralsford@hotmail-co.uk
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999704" page_id="56253607"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
154
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7367065" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253607" page_num="154" year="" vol="">
PELICANS OF THE WORLD
by Christopher Marler
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995446333333333" page_id="56253607"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
There are either seven or eight species of pelicans, depending on the
opinion of the different experts, Clements (2007) lists eight species (see list
below). Pelicans have always been a prominent species in my zoological park
in Buckinghamshire, here in the UK, which has housed all eight species.
The species most commonly kept in zoological collections here in Europe
is the Great White Pelican Pelecanus onocrotalus, a large and colourful
species and therefore a great attraction to the visiting public. Over the past
50 years or so that I have kept pelicans I have always found them most
appealing. All of the species are quite different in character and all remain
friendly and enjoy the human company of those who look after them - and
not only for the food that they provide.
The eight species of pelican
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.829679666666666" page_id="56253607"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
American White Pelican Pelecanus erythrorhynchos
Great White Pelican Pelecanus onocrotalus
Dalmatian Pelican Pelecanus crispus
Australian Pelican Pelecanus conspicillatus
Spot-billed Pelican Pelecanus philippensis
Pink-backed Pelican Pelecanus rufescens
Brown Pelican Pelecanus occidentalis
Chilean Pelican Pelecanus thagus
Not only was it a challenge to obtain all eight species - in fact it took
nearly 40 years to eventually obtain the eighth species - a lovely pair of
Australian Pelicans P. conspicillatus , courtesy of my good friends at Tierpark
Berlin (in exchange for rare waterfowl). They are the tamest two pelicans
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.998131454545454" page_id="56253607"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
in my collection and always come to be greeted and caress the hand. The
pair has settled in here so well and is so well paired that I hope, with time,
the pair will provide us with our first breeding of this species which is
seldom kept in captivity which, sadly, reflects the difficulty of obtaining
such Australian birds.
I count myself fortunate to have kept all eight species of these magnificent
birds in my collection and have also been fortunate enough to have observed
all eight species in the marvellous areas of the world in which they live.
The Great White and Dalmatian Pelican P crispus I have seen in the wild
in the state of Gujarat in north-west India, on a large reservoir which at the
time was only about half full of water. This required wading out into the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.597446" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253608" page_num="155" year="" vol="">
MARLER - PELICANS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99822" page_id="56253608"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
155
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.898912" page_id="56253608"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
A splendid example of the Great White Pelican.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999547" page_id="56253609"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
156
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.898602" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253609" page_num="156" year="" vol="">
MARLER - PELICANS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998055739130435" page_id="56253609"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
The Great White Pelican has proved to be a difficult species to breed in captivity.
water to get a closer view of the birds - five Dalmatian and seven Great
White Pelicans. It was in the month of February and they would have been
on migration, so were in adult plumage, probably on their way back to their
breeding grounds on the Danube Delta.
While attending a Whooping Crane Convention at Wood Buffalo Park
near Fort Smith in the Canadian north, the American White Pelican P
erythrorhynchos was seen on a rapid flowing river with islands on which there
were several nests. The journey to Wood Buffalo Park to view Whooping
Cranes Grus americana on their nesting grounds was probably the most
exciting birdwatching trip I have ever been on. Seeing the Whooping
Cranes with their chicks from the air from a float plane (an aircraft capable
of landing on water) was a truly memorable experience.
The Australian Pelican P. conspicillatus with its spectacular black and
white plumage I have seen on numerous occasions during my visits to that
great continent. I have been fortunate to have judged at cattle shows in
various parts of Australia and have always taken the opportunity to fit in
some birdwatching en route. On Kangaroo Island, off South Australia, many
Australian Pelicans can be seen and on the occasion of one of my visits
several hundred were coming to a feeding station each day to be fed.
On my only visit to Sri Lanka I witnessed the magnificent spectacle of
a large flock of Spot-billed Pelicans P philippensis in Yala National Park in
the south-east of the country. I also saw this species during another trip to
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.59811" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253610" page_num="157" year="" vol="">
MARLER - PELICANS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999183" page_id="56253610"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
157
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997893078947368" page_id="56253610"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
India, when visiting the breeding area called Vedanthangel, south of Madras,
where it breeds in tall trees alongside Asian Openbills Anastomus oscitans
and Painted Storks Mycteria leucocephala. I have now visited this area twice
and the density of breeding birds is quite unique and reflects the abundance
there of fish which is, of course, dependent on good rainfall at the vital time
of the year when the chicks are being reared.
The Pink-backed species P rufescens I first saw on Lake Naivasha, one
of the Rift Valley lakes in Kenya. It is another tree-nesting species which is
often found in great numbers. The Great White Pelican can also be seen in
many parts of Kenya. I particularly remember seeing about 1,000 of these
magnificent birds resting on the shore of Lake Nakuru early one morning
when we were the only visitors in the park. They were a lovely pink colour
so it was possibly just before the breeding season. Seeing the pelicans, as
well as thousands of Lesser Flamingos Phoeniconaias minor and Greater
Flamingos Phoenicopterus roseus on the same lake, was a sight that was so
memorable and vivid that I will never forget it.
The Brown Pelican P. occidentalis and the Chilean Pelican P. thagus are
now considered to be two separate species, due to the size difference (the
latter is the larger of the two) and differences in the coloration of the bill, face
and head and the heavily streaked underparts of the Chilean species. I have
observed these two species: the first in the USA in Florida and California
and the Chilean off the coasts of Pern and its adjacent islands. Both dive
for their food like the Gannet Morus bassanus does, and it is great to watch
them when they see a shoal of fish and dive dart-like into the water after
them with their wings outstretched behind them.
Keeping pelicans in captivity is relatively straightforward, but breeding
them presents an entirely different challenge. We have had eggs from five
of the eight species but the successful breeding of any of these species has
so far eluded us. Earlier this year our six Great White Pelicans were very
active; they gathered nesting material and their plumage and facial coloration
were stunning and we witnessed attempted matings, which have given us
hope for the future. Freshwater fish are fed to them daily, following the
feeding pattern practised by our colleagues at Tierpark Berlin, and lots of
nesting material is provided.
The bird collection of Avicultural Society Chairman Christopher Marler
FLS, at Flamingo Gardens and Zoological Park, Weston Underwood, Olney,
Buckinghamshire is no longer open to the public, but is maintained now
purely as a private collection.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999108" page_id="56253611"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
158
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7241775" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253611" page_num="158" year="" vol="">
THE LEMON-BREASTED CANARY Serinus citrinpectus
by John Santegoeds
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.901663" page_id="56253611"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
This 12cm (approx. 4%in) long Serinus spp. (which may also be found
listed in the genus Ochrospiza or Crithagra ) remained undescribed until as
recently as 1960. Clancey and Lawson (1960) wrote that in October 1959,
C. H. (Jack) Scheepers of Bela Vista, Maputo, Mozambique, trapped about
40 examples of what was then an unknown species belonging to the genus
Serinus. Most of the birds remained in his aviaries until towards the end of
August I960, when many of them were studied closely by members of the
Male Lemon-breasted Canary.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.582566" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253612" page_num="159" year="" vol="">
SANTEGOEDS - LEMON-BREASTED CANARY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998947" page_id="56253612"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
159
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.940504" page_id="56253612"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
Courtesy of Hugh Chittenden
Nest containing three eggs in Lala Palm.
staff of Durban Museum, during the course of its ornithological expedition to
Mozambique, Clancey and Lawson wrote that while the duty of describing
this new species to science had fallen to them, foil credit for the initial
discovery must go to "Mr Scheepers,"
The male and female can readily be distinguished from each other by
their different coloured plumage. The male has a pale lemon yellow chin,
throat and upper breast, with the sides of the breast and flanks washed peachy
buff, lightly streaked with grey and with the lower breast and belly white.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.991532" page_id="56253613"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
160
</page>
<author confidence="0.269626">
SANTEGOEDS - LEMON-BREASTED CANARY
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.675466">
Courtesy of Hugh Chittenden
</affiliation>
<bodyText confidence="0.984029636363636" page_id="56253613"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
Typical habitat of Lemon-breasted Canary,
The female (whose upperparts are similar to those of the male) lacks yellow
on the face and underparts and has a dull white stripe above the eye. Her
underparts are buff, with the breast and flanks lightly streaked with darker
brown (see photo p.162). The juvenile resembles the female, but is more
huffy on the upperparts, especially on the head and has fine streaking on
the chest and flanks (see photo p.. 163). which is lost after the first moult.
Following the moult, some of the nice lemon yellow feathers begin to show
through on the chest of young males, but it is another year before they acquire
their full colour. In my experience, very young males have a fine lemon
yellow 'glow' before the moult, but this is not easy to see.
The Lemon-breasted Canary is a monotypic species with no known
subspecies. However, I used to own an imported pair that was a fraction
larger and more brightly marked than my other Lemon-breasted Canaries.
Unfortunately, I failed in my attempts to persuade the pair to breed. Although
I have no record of where this particular pair was caught, I suspect that the
slight variation can be put down to so-called "geographical differences."
This species is confined to south-east Africa, where it is now known to
occur not only in southern Mozambique, but also in southern Malawi, south-
east Zimbabwe and eastern Transvaal and north-east KwaZulu-Natal in South
Africa. Its preferred habitat is Lala Palm Hyphaene coricea (inatalensis )
savannah and mixed Lala Palm and dry woodland as well as, in Zimbabwe,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.582788" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253614" page_num="161" year="" vol="">
SANTEGOEDS - LEMON-BREASTED CANARY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998724" page_id="56253614"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
161
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999126317073171" page_id="56253614"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
low-lying Mo pane Colophospermum mopane woodland; it is also said to
be attracted to cultivation and settlements. It usually occurs in pairs when
breeding and in small to large flocks when not breeding, often in the company
ofYellow-fronted Canaries (Green Singing Finches) S. mozambicus. Winter
flocks occasionally number up to 250 birds.
I contacted Hugh Chittenden, an enthusiastic birder in South Africa, who
has written about the Lemon-breasted Canary. Hugh is one of the founding
members of Birdinfo, a website - www.birdinfo.co.za - which is well worth
visiting. It was on this site that we found the report on the research Hugh
has done on the breeding habits of the Lemon-breasted Canary and are
grateful to him for allowing us to use his photographs, including those that
are reproduced here.
Large parts of the Lala Palm savannah in southern Mozambique and South
Africa are now occupied by farming communities that tap the palms in order
to made palm wine, coupled with which, palm fronds are increasingly used
these days in basket making for the craft and curio trades. As a result of
this, nests are often disturbed and many of them are unsuccessful. Research
conducted in KwaZulu-Natal in 2007, revealed that of the 22 nests examined,
only eight showed signs that young had fledged from them.
Another concern is the alarming number of birds that are trapped annually
in southern Mozambique for the cage bird trade. The Lemon-breasted Canary
is, or was, frequently offered for sale at bird markets in Maputo and Beira
in Mozambique, with up to 2,000 being exported annually (Hockey et al.
2005, who cite Clancey, 1971 and Parker, 1999, respectively).
Although up to 2,000 were said to have been exported annually from
Mozambique, it was never imported in large numbers into Europe. Following
the ban on the importation of wild birds into the EU (European Union),
aviculturists here in Europe have had to make do with those imported prior
to the ban. I have no idea how many Lemon-breasted Canaries are at present
kept in European aviculture. Contact with other breeders/keepers suggests
that, although it is often stated in avicultural literature that it is not a difficult
species to breed, this is not always the case.
In KwaZulu-Natal it lays in December-February and in January in
Zimbabwe. Recently imported birds, in particular, stuck to this time frame,
which contributed to the fact that it was and, continues to be, seldom bred
here in Europe. As often happens with African seedeaters, recently acquired
birds were frequently housed in outside aviaries in which, with a bit of luck,
they may have attempted to breed. However, because they often nested
during the winter months, there were generally few successes. There were
exceptions, of course, but more often than not, those keeping them indoors
were more successful. However, this is not to say that it was easy - that
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998468" page_id="56253615"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
162
</page>
<author confidence="0.263521">
SANTEGOEDS - LEMON-BREASTED CANARY
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.657663">
Courtesy of Hugh Chittenden
</affiliation>
<bodyText confidence="0.991407666666667" page_id="56253615"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
Female and well-grown nestlings.
would be stretching it a bit.
The birds that are being bred nowadays are often those that enthusiasts
have been establishing in cages for one or more generations, although here
and there an imported bird may be found. This has contributed to the fact
that the breeding period here in Europe is gradually changing. In an aviary,
they are peaceful birds that are not too set in their ways, which can be the
case with some other Serinus spp. They have a nice song which is heard
regularly.
I give my birds a good seed mixture formulated for European species,
along with a tropical seed mixture and, sometimes, a small quantity of niger
seed and spray millet. I supply some chicory or a piece of apple every now
and then, but little of these are eaten. Chickweed fairs better, as do buds
of dandelions, barnyard grass, mug won and evening primrose. I also, of
course, provide fresh water and grit.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.582714" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253616" page_num="163" year="" vol="">
SANTEGOEDS - LEMON-BREASTED CANARY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999374" page_id="56253616"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
163
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.987012666666667" page_id="56253616"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
Juvenile.
When they have young, I give them a simple homemade eggfood
made using three Dutch rusks to one boiled egg (well heated and ground
down), mixed together with eggshell, a little honey and a good protein/
vitamin/mineral supplement, following the quantities recommended by the
manufacturer. I divide this into small portions which I freeze and each day
take the required amount out of the freezer and defrost it. I mix it with frozen
maggots which I have also defrosted and add a small quantity of niger seed
to it and then give it to the birds.
My breeding cages measure 80cm x 60cm x 60cm (approx. 2ft l l A in x
2ft x 2ft) (see photo p. 164) When the birds begin to come into breeding
condition, the frequent singing of the male often becomes noticeable, as
he puts in a real effort to impress the female with his beautiful song. The
birds follow each other and wherever the females flies, the male follows
her. Often, but not always, the female begins pecking her breast feathers
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999565" page_id="56253617"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
164
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.883342" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253617" page_num="164" year="" vol="">
SANTEGOEDS - LEMON-BREASTED CANARY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999188818181818" page_id="56253617"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
and this becomes clearly visible after a few days. Now and then I place a
small piece of cotton wool between the cage wires and this increases the
tension even more.
One of the breeding cages used by the author.
The nest-box is in the back left-hand corner.
As soon as the nest box is provided (I use the type illustrated in Vol. 117,
No. 1, p.38 (2011)), construction of the nest does not take long. Before putting
the nest box in place, I securely fasten a coconut fibre insert in the bottom
of the box. If it is not secured properly the birds will persist in tugging
and pulling at it and will not stop until it has been removed and is lying
on the floor of the cage. I supply plenty of a popular brand of European
bird nesting material and white cotton wool, as it has been noticed that this
species has a preference for light coloured/white nesting material. Some
males take a full part in assisting to build the nest, and all males assist in
some way. On completion of the nest, the site is fiercely protected from
possible trespassers.
The Lemon-breasted Canary usually lays three or sometimes four white
eggs, which I remove and replace with plastic eggs (used by canary breeders)
until the full clutch is laid. Some females sit so tightly that I have to push
them off the nest in order to inspect it. After approximately five days, I
check the eggs to ensure that they are fertile. If possible, I leave the male
in the breeding cage with the female as, luckily, most males prove to be
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.582782" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253618" page_num="165" year="" vol="">
SANTEGOEDS - LEMON-BREASTED CANARY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999152" page_id="56253618"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
165
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9985353" page_id="56253618"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
concerned husbands and excellent fathers, who feed the female on the nest
and also feed the chicks.
The eggs hatch after an incubation period of 13 days. The shells are
removed from the nest and neatly deposited on the floor of the cage or in one
of the food containers. After approximately five to six days the chicks are
ringed with 2.5mm size rings. I used to use 2.3mm size rings, which meant
I could ring the chicks a little earlier, but this proved to be quite a hassle and
1 now ring them a little later and use a slightly larger sized ring.
About 20 days after hatching the young leave the nest, but return to it
during the first few days and roost in the nest at night for at least the first
week. About 10=12 days after they have left the nest, I catch the young and
place them in a 'baby cage' attached to the front of the breeding cage, in
which they continue to be fed by the male for quite some time.
The female usually begins her next round quite quickly. I am very
careful though not to remove the young from their parents too soon and
often leave them in the 'baby cage' for a further three weeks or so, until I
am sure they are feeding independently. In the past I have lost young birds
because I thought they were independent before they were feeding entirely
by themselves.
A good, well bonded/compatible pair, together with good care is, I
believe, the key to success. As I stated earlier, this species has never been
imported into Europe in large numbers and has never been widely bred.
There are, however, several breeders in Europe who are reasonably successful
with this species. It is to be hoped that by working with one another, the
number of young bred each year can be increased and this species can find
a permanent place in European aviculture.
There are some 600 breeders of Serinus spp. throughout Europe and
several breeders of the Lemon-breasted Canary have registered on our
website. Through this initiative breeders can contact each other to exchange
birds and knowledge about the keeping and breeding of this species.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.955071" genericHeader="references" page_id="56253618" page_num="165" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.995318454545455">
Clancey, R A. and Lawson, W. J. 1960. A new species of Canary from southern Portuguese
East Africa. Durban Museum Novit., Vol. 6, Pt. 4, 61-64.
Clancey,P.A. 1971. A Handlist of the Birds of Southern Mozambique. Institute de Investigacao
Cientifica de Mozambique, Lourenzo Marques.
Hockey, P. A. R., Dean, W. R. J. and Ryan, P. G. (eds.). 2005. Roberts - Birds of Southern
Africa Seventh Edition. The Trustees of the John Voelcker Bird Book Fund, Cape Town.
Parker, V. 1999. The Atlas of the Birds of Sul do Save, Southern Mozambique. Avian
Demography Unit &amp; Endangered Wildlife Trust, Cape Town and Johannesburg.
John Santegoeds, who lives in Lierop in the Netherlands, is a founder
member of the European Society ofSerinus Breeders (ESSB). Website :www.
Serinus-Society. eu/E-mail:fam_santegoeds@hotmail. com
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999413" page_id="56253619"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
166
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.860297" genericHeader="method" page_id="56253619" page_num="166" year="" vol="">
ACTION FOR THE CONSERVATION OF THE
ENDANGERED SWIFT PARROT Lathamus discolor
by David Waugh
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.965486909090909" page_id="56253619"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
In 2010, a team began conducting research into the breeding biology
and migratory behaviour of the Swift Parrot Lathamus discolor , in order to
obtain information essential for the effective conservation of this endangered
species. The project is supported by the Loro Parque Fundacion (LPF) and
the Australian Research Council and is being undertaken by Prof. Robert
Heinsohn of the Fenner School of Environment and Society, the Australian
National University, and team members Dr Debra Saunders and Dejan
Stojanovic. The project's objectives include documenting critical aspects
of the breeding biology and ecology of the Swift Parrot in relation to land
management and, especially, forestry practises.
Swift Parrot at nest entrance.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.945808">
Dejan Stojanovic
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99895725" page_id="56253619"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
A lot of important data was obtained during the past breeding season,
which generated substantial interest amongst key stakeholders in the
conservation of the Swift Parrot. Work on its breeding requirements,
including its choice of nesting hollows and food sources, was especially
successful, with 21 nests being found. During the past breeding season,
due to the widespread occurrence of flowering trees throughout the region,
Swift Parrots nested across a large area of south-eastern Tasmania. Because
of the extent of the flowering and the small size of the parrot population,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.592638" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253620" page_num="167" year="" vol="">
WAUGH - SWIFT PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996036" page_id="56253620"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
167
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.5243655">
Dejan Stojanovic
Juvenile Swift Parrot.
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99986465" page_id="56253620"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
nest densities were low and nests took time to locate. The 21 nests were
found across an area stretching over 300km (approx. 186 miles). The team
monitored the growth of the 53 nestlings and found that 96% of the chicks
fledged. The results show that the nestling period is approximately 35 days
and the average clutch consists three to four chicks. Crop samples collected
from nestlings revealed that, contrary to the assumption that the Swift Parrot
is mainly nectarivorous, the parents feed a high proportion of invertebrates
to the nestlings.
All of the nests were in cavities with specific characteristics and a
comparison was made between the trees and tree cavities used for nesting
and those that were not used by the birds. The results suggest that the
parrots significantly prefer to use large, old trees for nesting, and that these
trees have more hollows. Furthermore, the parrots prefer to nest in hollows
which are deep and wide, but have a small entrance. The researchers found
that survey techniques used to search for tree cavities in Tasmanian forests
are prone to error and are planning improvements which will help in the
conservation of the Swift Parrot.
Blood samples were collected from the 53 nestlings and screened for
psittacine beak and feather disease (PBFD). The results showed that one
chick had been exposed to the virus (circovirus). This chick had been
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998843" page_id="56253621"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
168
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.844355" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253621" page_num="168" year="" vol="">
WAUGH - SWIFT PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.982366206896552" page_id="56253621"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
exposed to a strain of the virus typically carried by the Sulphur-crested
Cockatoo Cacatua galerita and the nest in which the chick was found had
been subjected to severe flooding due to rain. The low rate of exposure
to PBFD during the past breeding season will be compared to successive
seasons for a better interpretation of the dynamics of disease in this species.
During the next breeding season the researchers will, for example, collect
samples of substrate from Swift Parrot nests as part of an investigation into
the possible transmission of PBFD between parrot species which use the
same tree cavity successively over the course of a breeding season.
Another important objective of the project is to develop techniques for
tracking Swift Parrots, in order to determine better how they locate their
food sources and other resources. To this end, the researchers successfully
undertook the first trial of transmitters, which they attached to Swift Parrots
living in aviaries at Adelaide Zoo.
The aim of the trial was to identify a tracking device which can be safely
deployed on breeding adult Swift Parrots, to obtain accurate data from which
to interpret the behaviour of breeding birds. Three transmitter designs, each
using ultra-lightweight materials - one collar and two backpacks of different
weights - were tested on different groups and there was a control group, the
birds of which did not have a transmitter attached. No differences were
observed in the bodyweight or the condition of the birds in any of the groups
- either those with transmitters attached or those of the control group. These
trials clearly showed, however, that the collar is more suitable than either of
the backpacks. It can be attached in only one minute and, furthermore, the
bird does not bite the transmitter and there Is very little risk of it becoming
entangled in vegetation. Further modifications to the design will reduce the
overall weight of the transmitter, in readiness for tracking Swift Parrots in
the wild using this highly innovative technology.
Dr David Waugh is Director of the Loro Parque Fundacion, Loro Parque,
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.836879">
Tenerife, Canary Islands, Spain. Websiteiwww.loroparque-fimdacion.org
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.989487" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253622" page_num="169" year="" vol="">
SUCCESSFULLY BREEDING THE
LILAC-BREASTED ROLLER Coracias caudatus
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998391" page_id="56253622"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
169
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.985281108108108" page_id="56253622"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
by Dick Jaquest
For more than 25 years we have been breeding waterfowl with some
degree of success in our back garden. However, several years ago during a
storm the power went off and so did our electric fence. The family of foxes
living next door had a field day killing some 20 of our birds, including one
of the best breeding pairs of New Zealand Brown Teal Anas aucklandica
we had ever had.
As a result, we realised that we had to rethink how we house our
collection. Those of you who have seen it, will know how difficult this was
for us, as we live in a very congested residential neighbourhood, where we
are surrounded by six other houses.
The first thing we did was to invest in a very expensive Gallagher
PowerPIus MR2500 energizer (to provide electric current) and, just to be on
the safe side, we bought a second one in case the first should fail. Our next
step was to house some of our birds, such as the African White-backed Ducks
Thalassornis leuconotus , New Zealand Brown Teal, full-winged Hottentot
Teal A. hottentota and whistling ducks Dendrocygna spp. in aviaries.
In a small garden such as we have, space is at a premium, so in order
to make the best use of as much of the space as possible, we decided to
keep some smaller birds in the aviary, and chose a species which would
nest high up. Hoopoes Upupa epops were our first choice, but following a
few accidents, it soon became clear that it was not a good idea to keep such
long-beaked birds in this aviary. It was 24ft x 8ft x 10ft (approx. 7.3m x
2.4m x 3m), but we have Herring Gulls Larus argentatus living on the roof
of our house and, they scared the Hoopoes so much, that on two occasions
they flew into the wire and broke their beaks.
The next birds we obtained were some full-winged Madagascar Teal A.
bernieri , which proved to be a bad decision, because after living with African
Pygmy Geese Nettapus auritus at their original home, on arrival here they
promptly killed our pygmy geese.
We then decided to try Lilac-breasted Rollers Coracias caudatus. The
first two birds settled in very quickly and got on well together and were
fun to watch, but failed to produce any eggs. We had no idea how old they
were and, to be honest, were not absolutely certain that they were a true pair,
although they had been seen feeding each other with mealworms, etc., and
we were pleased to have them.
We had been toying with the idea of getting a second pair, but before we
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.992223" page_id="56253623"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
170
</page>
<table confidence="0.767765" page_id="56253623"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
JAQUEST - LILAC-BREASTED ROLLER
Brooding two small chicks and an unhatched egg.
Dick Jaquest
The chicks seem unaware that the parent has arrived back at the nest with food.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.468118" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253624" page_num="171" year="" vol="">
JAQUEST - LILAC-BREASTED ROLLER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995648" page_id="56253624"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
171
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.949371" page_id="56253624"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
Watched by the photographer, the parent feeds one of the rapidly growing chicks.
Taking a mealworm from the hand, watched by three African White-backed Ducks.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998602" page_id="56253625"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
172
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.820593" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253625" page_num="172" year="" vol="">
JAQUEST - LILAC-BREASTED ROLLER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999652365853659" page_id="56253625"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
had got any further with this idea, we woke one morning to find one of the
first pair dead in the pond. We found that the dead bird was a female and
began to look for a replacement. A company in the Netherlands had a female
available, so we made arrangements to bring her over to the UK.
It was not difficult to divide the aviary into two, and we housed the new
female on one side and the male on the other side for about a week and
allowed them to get used to each other. At the weekend we removed the
partition separating them and both of us took turns to watch them and see
that nothing went wrong. Sadly, however, a couple of weeks later the male
killed the female.
A few weeks passed and after advertising everywhere we could think of
for another female, we were offered a pair which we were told was old and
had been together for some time but had never laid any eggs. The pair was
housed in the second of our aviaries. I tried splitting them up and putting
the female with our original male, but it soon become very obvious that this
was not going to work and so I reunited the old pair. To our great surprise,
shortly afterwards the first eggs were laid and we were even more surprised
to discover that they were fertile. The very first youngster to be hatched was
a male. Although we were obviously delighted, we would have preferred it
to have been a female, which was what we needed.
We continued to search for another female for three years. Then, we
were given hope, when we received a phone call from Birdland, which
had a female and was looking for a male in order to make up an unrelated
pair. It was a three-hour drive to Birdland, but proved to be well worth it.
The new female and our original male were housed in separate aviaries for
approximately two to three weeks to get used to each other and were then
put together in the original aviary. Within six months of being introduced to
each other, the first eggs were laid. The pair later produced a second clutch
of eggs and the other pair also produced a second clutch of eggs, which
resulted in us being able to set up further unrelated pairs.
Only a quarter of the roof of our aviaries is covered, but the sides facing
the sea are screened to shelter the birds from the wind. The aviaries have
two heated boxes, but the birds never use these even during the cold weather.
The nest boxes are placed as high as I can get them and the birds have a
choice of at least four boxes. Our pairs move from one nest box to another
each time they nest. For perching I use hemp rope and natural branches and
give the birds plenty of space in which to fly around.
When we believe the young are old enough, we remove them from
the nest box and take samples for DNA sexing and place two sets of rings
(bands) on each bird. This saves us from catching up related birds when we
are trying to pair them up. At the same time, we clean out the nest box and
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.469423" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253626" page_num="173" year="" vol="">
JAQUEST - LILAC-BREASTED ROLLER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999461" page_id="56253626"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
173
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997783272727273" page_id="56253626"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
refill it with fresh, clean material and clean it out again a few weeks later.
This does not worry the parents or the young.
As the accompanying photos show, the parents appear happy for us to
watch them feeding their young. I feel that this is important, as it helps us
check that all of the chicks are being fed and there are no problems. In the
past, if I felt a chick was being neglected, I have fed it whilst the parent was
feeding the other chicks.
The diet fed to our birds consists of Whiskas cat food in jelly (with the
jelly removed), soaked puppy and small bite mixture pellets, mixed with
Witte Molen insectivorous food, with the jelly from the Whiskas added and
then topped with large and small mealworms. Each day during the summer
each roller also gets a pinkie mouse. If one of the birds is not quick enough,
this will be stolen by its partner, so we have to make sure that the birds get
just one each.
Up until now (2011) we have bred nine Li lac-breasted Rollers, one of
which was killed, we believe, by a Sparrowhawk Accipiter nisus , when the
young female roller was perched close to the roof of the aviary and, sadly,
the very old male died whilst in the nest box with chicks. The female is
now paired with an unrelated young male (a toy boy!) and the two seem
quite happy together.
Dick and Kay currently have some spare males which they would consider
swapping for one or even two new females to make up further unrelatedpairs.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.476493" page_id="56253626"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
E-mail :d-jaquest@toucansurf com/Website: www. ornamentalwaterfowluk.
co.uk/Tel:01273 584737/Mobile:0785 1190176.
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.733297" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56253626" page_num="173" year="" vol="">
CZECH VISIT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.89077925" page_id="56253626"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
The society has arranged a trip to the Czech Republic. The departure
date is Friday, September 14th 2012, followed by a visit to Prague Zoo on
Saturday, September 15th, Plzen (Pilsen) Zoo on Sunday, September 16th
and to a private collection on Monday, September 17th, before returning
home later that day. Further information about the collections to be visited
can be obtained from Mike Curzon. E mai I : nK:urzonmbe@h.otrnail.co.uk/
Tel:01373 824077. Details of the travel arrangements, accommodation, costs
and booking information are available from Karli Lisiecki, Howard Travel,
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.615842">
12/13 Church Walk, Trowbridge, Wiltshire BA14 8DX. E-mail:karli@
ho wardtravel. com/Tel: 01225 777227.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999771" page_id="56253627"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
174
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.851989375" page_id="56253627"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
A BIRD EXTRAVAGANZA WITH A FRENCH ACCENT
by Pierre de Chabannes
Most French zoos and animal parks rarely have more than 50 species
of birds and these consist mostly of common species such as ostriches,
rheas, macaws, pheasants and ducks. Having a park devoted entirely to
the wonderful world of birds seemed at first fairly unusual, but the Parc
des Oiseaux de Villars les Dombes - Villar des Dombes birdpark - created
in 1970 and located a few kilometres (miles) from Lyon (France's second
largest city) was up to the challenge and within a few years became one of
the most beautiful and interesting animal parks in France. Today, it houses
more than 2,000 birds of 400 different species on a 35 hectares (approx. 86
acres) site located in the centre of a legally protected area of natural marshes
and lakes known as Les Dombes.
Pierre de Chabannes
Australian Shoveller.
The tour of the park begins by a pond surrounded by aquatic vegetation,
which is home to a large breeding group of Caribbean Flamingos
Phoenicopterus ruber. The flamingos share this with a number of other
species which occur in the Caribbean and South America, such as White-
faced Whistling Ducks Dendrocygna viduata, Fulvous Whistling Ducks D.
bicolor , Bahama Pintails Anas bahamensis, Chiloe Wigeon A. sibilatrix ,
Ruddy Ducks Oxyura jamaicensis and the most prolific breeding group
of Argentine Ruddy Ducks or Lake Ducks O. vittata in any zoological
collection in France.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.766576" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253628" page_num="175" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - VILLAR DES DOMBES BI PDF'ARK
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.991626" page_id="56253628"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
175
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.278487">
Philippine Cockatoo,
</subsectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999294" page_id="56253629"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
176
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.759609" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253629" page_num="176" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - VILLAR DES DOMBES BIRDPARK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.698400882352941" page_id="56253629"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
Pierre de Chabannes
Interior of tropical house.
A wooded walkway takes visitors past the pond to La Maison des
Oiseaux - the House of Birds. This is a tropical house with a dozen (12)
nicely landscaped aviaries housing various tropical birds, including some
rarely seen species. The first of these aviaries houses a group of Blue-
bellied Rollers Coracias cyanogaster and a pair of d'Amaud's Barbets
Trachyphonus darnaudii. A female Black-tailed Trogon Trogon melanurus
- a species not kept anywhere else in Europe - a Blue-crowned Motmot
Momotus m. momota, some Blacksmith Plovers Vane Hus armatus and a
pair of Red-flanked Lorikeets Charmosyna placentis occupy the second
aviary. Living in the third aviary are Stella's Lorikeets C. papou stellae,
some Pekin Robins or Red-billed Leiothrix Leiothrix lutea, Blue or Western
Crowned Pigeons Goura cristata , some Orange-cheeked Waxbills Estrilda
melpoda and a group of Timor Sparrows Padda fuscata , the last named a
species kept in fewer than 10 zoos around the world. The fourth aviary
houses a pair of Black-naped Fruit Doves Ptilinopus melanospila, some
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.689183714285714">
Crested Wood Partridges Rollulus rouloul, a group of Painted Quail Coturnix
chinensis , Heck's Grassfinches Poephila acuticauda hecki, Gouldian Finches
Erythrura gouldiae , a few Red-headed Parrotfinches E. psittacea, some
Diamond Firetails Stagonopleura guttata, Diamond Doves Geopelia cuneata
and Pacific Parrotlets Forpus coelestis. In the fifth aviary visitors can see
Black-necked Stilts Himantopus mexicanus, African Montane or Broad-
ringed White-eyes Zosterops poliogastrus eurycricotus (misidentified as
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.759328" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253630" page_num="177" year="" vol="">
DE CHABAMMES - VILLAR DES DOMBES BIRDPARK
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.97975" page_id="56253630"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
177
</page>
<table confidence="0.6284224" page_id="56253630"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
Pierre de Chabannes
Caribbean Flamingo enclosure.
Kikuyu White-eyes), a large breeding flock of Black-and-white Mannikins
Spermestes ( Lonchura ) bicolor , Namaqua Doves Oena capensis , Speckled
Mousebirds Colius striatus and the only Black Crakes Amaurornis flavirostris
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.962105894736842" page_id="56253630"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
displayed in a French collection.
On the other side of the house there are three larger aviaries showcasing
other tropical birds such as Collared Warbling Finches Poospiza
hispaniolensis , Red Bishops Euplectes orix , Red-billed Queleas Quelea
quelea , the Sahel Paradise Whydah Vidua orientalis - which in the wild
parasitises the Green-winged Pytilia or Melba Finch Pytilia melba, Lilac-
breasted Roller C. c. caudata , White-headed Buffalo Weaver Dinemellia
dinemelli , Cut-throat Finch Amadina fasciata , Fischer's Turaco Tauraco
fischeri , Cape Thick-knee Burhinus capensis , African Olive Pigeons
Columba aquatrix , Pheasant Pigeons Otidiphaps nobilis. Blue-grey Tanagers
Thraupis episcopus , Croaking Ground Doves Columbina cruziana , Red-
cowled or Pope Cardinal Paroaria dominicana , Silver-beaked Tanager
Ramphocelus carbo , Red-crested Turacos I,' erythrolophus , Golden Tanager
Tangara arthus , Pileated Finches Coryphospingus pileatus , Hoopoe Upupa
epops and many more.
In 2009, a new building was opened housing the largest collection of
toucans, toucanets and araqaris seen in France since the Jardin d'Oiseaux
Tropicaux at La Londe Les Maures in southern France decided to no longer
keep most of its toucans, toucanets and araqaris and instead began breeding
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.9969" page_id="56253631"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
178
</page>
<table confidence="0.867656333333333" page_id="56253631"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - VILLAR DES DOMBES BIRDPARK
Pierre de Chabannes
Australian Thick-knee.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.770257" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253632" page_num="179" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - VILLAR DES DOMBES BIRDPARK
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997378" page_id="56253632"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
179
</page>
<author confidence="0.362811">
Dalmation Pelican.
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.324625">
Pierre de Chabannes
</affiliation>
<bodyText confidence="0.990734181818182" page_id="56253632"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
hombills in the late 1990s. Breeding pairs of several species are kept in
nicely landscaped medium-sized indoor aviaries. These include the only
pair of Guianan Toucanets Selenidera culik to be seen in a French collection,
which shares the aviary with some Small-billed Tinamous Crypturellus
parvirostris , another species which cannot be seen anywhere else in France.
Non-breeding pairs of Channel-billed Toucans Ramphastos v. vitellinus and
Toco Toucans R. toco are also displayed, living with Chaco Chachalacas
Ortalis canicollis. There are a pair of Red-billed Toucans R. tucanus , a pair
of Green Ara 9 aris Pteroglossus viridis and a pair of Keel-billed Toucans
R. sulfuratus brevicarinatus, the last two species of which are breeding.
Living behind the scenes is the last known Crimson-ramped Toucanet
Aulacorhynchus haematopygus in France and one of the last remaining
representatives of this species in Europe. It is living in a large aviary and,
the hope is, that a mate can be found for it. This species was bred repeatedly
in the past in this collection.
After leaving the house, visitors arrive at one of the most impressive
exhibits in the park - the gigantic Pantanal walk-through aviary - housing
several South American species which move freely around the aviary and
often come into direct contact with the public. The first species to be
spotted is usually the Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber , followed by the Puna
Ibis Plegadis ridgway and White Ibis E. albus , all of which breed regularly.
Visitors can also see Southern Lapwings V chilenensis cayennensis. Roseate
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.993465" page_id="56253633"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
180
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.893753" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253633" page_num="180" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - VILLAR DES DOMBES BIRDPARK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985400258064516" page_id="56253633"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
Spoonbills Platalea ajaja , a breeding group of Blue-winged Teal A. discors ,
Ringed Teal Calonetta leucophrys , Chilean Flamingos P. chilenesis and
two species of parrot, the Lilac-crowned Amazon Amazona fins chi and
Hyacinth Macaw Anodorhynchus hyacinthinus , both of which breed fairly
well in the park.
The next stop for most visitors is La Cite des perroquets - Parrot's city.
This begins with a walk-through aviary housing a large breeding group
of Australian Thick-knees B. grallarius - a species rarely seen anywhere
else in France - living with Eclectus Parrots Eclectus roratus polychloros ,
Rainbow Lorikeets Trichoglossus haematodus and a large flock of Java
Sparrows P. oryzivora. There is then a series of large and nicely landscaped
aviaries housing mostly parrots, along with a few other tropical birds. Most
of the species are kept in breeding pairs or groups and this includes some
of the park's most valuable birds. The pair of Blue-throated Macaws Ara
glaucogularis used to be the only pair of this species on public exhibition
in France, but is now housed behind the scenes. One of the most interesting
species currently on display in this section is the Critically Endangered
Philippine or Red-vented Cockatoo Cacatua haematuropygia. The park
was until 2008 responsible for the European Breeding Programme for this
species and continues to house a breeding group. There is also a breeding
pair of Hyacinth Macaws, a group of Ecuadorian or Lilacine Amazons
A. autumnalis lilacina, one of the only known breeding groups of Lilac-
crowned Amazons in France, and a breeding pair of Long-billed Corellas C.
tenuirostris . Other species living in these aviaries include Greater Vasa Parrot
Coracopsis vasa, Black-capped Lory Lorius lory ery thro thorax. Sharp-tailed
Conure A. acuticauda, Green-cheeked Amazon A. viridigenalis , Peach-
fronted Conure A. aurea , Grey Parrot Psittacus erithacus , African Ring-
necked Parakeet Psittacula k. krameri , Yellow-collared Macaw Primolius
auricollis and Military Macaw A. militaris mexicanus. These aviaries also
house a breeding pair of Australian Magpies Gymnorhina hypoleuca , a
breeding pair of Laughing Kookaburras Dacelo novaeguineae, Black-headed
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.8482807">
Caiques Pionites melanocephalus , Galahs Eolophus roseicapillus, Barraband
Parakeets Polytelis swainsonii, Red-headed or Jardine's Parrots Poicephalus
gulielmi , Monk or Quaker Parakeets Myiopsitta monachus , Azure-winged
Magpies Cyanopica cyana. Noble Macaws Diopsittaca n. nobilis , Grey-
winged Trumpeters Psophia crepitans , Greater Necklaced Laughingthrushes
Garrulaxpectoralis, Black-necked Starlings Gracupica nigricollis. Scarlet
Macaws A. macao , Laughing Doves Streptopelia senegalensis , Wattled
Starlings Creatophora cinerea and a huge breeding group of Fischer's
Lovebirds Agapornis fischeri.
In 2008, an area behind the parrot aviaries was designed where in late
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.771104" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253634" page_num="181" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - VILLAR DES DOMBES BIRDPARK
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99862" page_id="56253634"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
181
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9920574" page_id="56253634"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
spring and summmer bird shows are held up to three times a day. These
feature several exotic birds, ranging from parrots to ibises, geese and pelicans,
flying free. Also in 2008, a new area of the park was opened dedicated to
birds from the temperate and cold regions of South America. After walking
through an area reminiscent of volcanic landscape in Argentina, visitors
come to a fairly large enclosure housing Upland Geese Chloephaga picta
and some Lesser or Darwin's Rheas Rhea (. Pterocnemia ) pennata bred at
Parc Zoologique et Botanique de Mulhouse (Mulhouse Zoo). Then there
is a huge exhibit with a large pool housing the park's breeding colony of
about 60 Humboldt Penguins Spheniscus humboldti, which began breeding
the first year that the exhibit opened. As is customary with most penguin
exhibits these days, the pool has a side window through which the birds can
be seen swimming underwater. At the end of this area there is a huge aviary
occupied by a breeding pair of Andean Condors Vultur gryphus and a group
of Harris's Hawks Parabuteo unicinctus karrisi.
After returning to the main pathway, visitors arrive at a group of very long
enclosures with pools in them, and in these enclosures live most of the park's
cranes along with various species of waterfowl. The most recent addition
to the collection in this specific area is a pair of Wattled Cranes Bugeranus
carunculatus sharing an enclosure with Cape Teal A capensis. Other species
to be found in these enclosures include Saras Cranes Grus a. antigone ,
Greater Rheas R. americana, Southern Pochard Netta erythrophthalma
brunnea - a duck which is rare in Europe - Laysan Teal A . laysanensis ,
Whooper Swans Cygnus cygnus and Andean Geese C. melanoptera.
At the far end of the park is an Australian section with, in the first
enclosure, Emus Dromaius novaehollandiae, Australian Shelduck Tadorna
tadornoides , Radjah Shelduck I radjah , Chestnut Teal A. castanea , some
Cape Barren or Cereopsis Geese Cereopsis novaehollandiae , a breeding
pair of Black Swans C. atratus and some Maned Ducks Chenonetta jubata.
The other, and most interesting part of the Australian area, consists of a very
large walk-through aviary housing a diverse collection of birds, including
a breeding group of Australian Shoveler A rhynchotis variegata - a species
which is very rare in European collections - Maned Ducks, a breeding
group of Little Pied Cormorants Phalacrocorax melanoleucos - probably
the only specimens in France - a group of Pennant's Parakeets Platycerus
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.647705166666667">
elegans , Emerald Doves Chalcophaps indica, Common Bronzewings Phaps
chalcoptera , Diamond Doves Geopelia cuneata , Masked Lapwings V m.
miles, Ey ton 's or Plumed Whistling Ducks D. eytoni and a group of Straw-
necked Ibis Threskiornis spinicollis. Also living in the aviary are Garganey
A, querquedula - a northern migrant that occasionally reaches Australia
- Eurasian Teal A c. crecca and some Grey Partridges Perdix perdix.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998658" page_id="56253635"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
182
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.92399" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253635" page_num="182" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - VILLAR DES DOMBES BIRDPARK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997323176470588" page_id="56253635"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
On leaving the Australian zone, visitors find themselves a short distance
from an observation deck from which it is possible to spend hours watching
the local wild birds, especially waterbirds such as herons, ducks and grebe,
roaming about, feeding and breeding on and around a lake and marsh known
as - La petite Dombes. It is part of a large area of protected natural habitat
which is a stronghold for many wild birds, including Red-crested Pochard N.
rufina , Common Pochard Aythya ferina , Tufted Duck A.fuligula, Northern
Pintail Anas acuta , Great Crested Grebe Podiceps cristatus , the rarely seen
Black-necked Grebe P. nigricollis , and the European White Stork Ciconia
ciconia. The Parc des Oiseaux is currently the only public animal park in
France in which visitors can see such a wide variety of the local wildlife in
its natural environment.
The main path leading out of La petite Dombes takes visitors to the birds
of prey. A few large aviaries are visible from inside a building which has
many posters, panels and other pedagogical (teaching/educational) devices.
These aviaries are occupied by Great Grey Owls Strix nebulosa lapponica ,
Kestrels Falco tinnunculus , Himalayan Griffon Gyps himalayensis and
Great Eagle-Owls Bubo b. bubo. Then there is a huge walk-through aviary
in which several diurnal birds of prey are flying free and in which many of
them breed. Birds in this aviary include Red Kites Milvus milvus , Black Kites
M. migrans, Eurasian Black Vultures Aegypius monachus, Eurasian Griffon
G.f fulvus , Short-toed Eagles Circaetus gallicus. Common Buzzard Buteo
buteo , Long-legged Buzzards B. rufinus and Egyptian Vultures Neophron
p. percnopterus .
Almost half of the park's surface is occupied by a huge lake on which
many wild birds can be seen, including Great Crested Grebe, Common
Pochard and many other local species of duck, as well as Grey Herons
Ardea cinerea and White Storks. This fantastic lake can be seen from
almost everywhere in the park and the wild birds have become used to the
presence of humans and are often very tame. Flower and fruit gardens have
been created in which the wild birds come and forage. The park's efforts
to promote and protect local wildlife are among the best of any of the large
zoological collections in France.
There are a few walk-in enclosures in which there are some more
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.701859142857143">
waterfowl, many of which breed in these enclosures. Visitors can see
Pink-footed Geese Anser brachyrhynchus, a species which cannot be
seen in any of the French zoos, Philippine Ducks A. luzonica, Gadwall A.
strepera, Carolina or American Wood Ducks Aix sponsa , Mandarin Ducks
A. galericulata , Lesser White-fronted Geese A. erythropus, Red-breasted
Geese B. ruficollis , Lesser Canada or Cackling Geese B. hutchinsii minima ,
Ross's Geese A. rossii. Spot-billed Ducks A. p. poecilorhyncha, Marbled
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.771031" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253636" page_num="183" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - VILLAR DES DOMBES BIRDPARK
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999335" page_id="56253636"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
183
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99357287804878" page_id="56253636"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
Teal Marmaronetta angutirostris , Brazilian Teal Amazonetta brasiliensis.
Ferruginous Ducks Aythya nyroca , Common Goldeneye Bucephala clangula,
Common Eider Somateria molissima. Common Shelduck T. tadorna and
many other species.
On the other side of the main path is a large enclosure which is
landscaped, in which a female Southern or Double-wattled Cassowary
Casuarius casuarius used to live until mid-2011, when she was transferred
to the zoo at Mulhouse, to be paired with its lone male. The design of the
enclosure, which currently houses Parma Wallabies Macropus parma , has
been changed to accommodate Abyssinian Ground Hombills Bucorvus
abyssininicus.
The Jardin des oiseaux - Garden of birds - shows different ways of
attracting and feeding local birds and encourages the public to care for and
protect local wildlife.
The park's latest creation is an area called Terres de calaos - Lands of
hombills - consisting of a large enclosure which has been landscaped with
artificial termite mounds, etc., to resemble an African savannah, along with
two rows of medium-sized aviaries, each with a heated house. Living in
the enclosure is an adult pair of Southern Ground Hombills B. leadbeateri,
a species which is now common in zoos and breeds well. While housed in
the aviaries are African Grey Hombills Tockus n. nasutus , Von der Decken's
Hombill T. deckeni, the Tmmpeter Hombill Bycanistes ( Ceratogymna )
bucinator , Silvery-cheeked Hombills B. (C.) brevis , Blyth's or Plicated
Hombills Rhyticeros plicatus , Great Hornbill Buceros bicornis, Javan
Rhinoceros Hombill B. rhinoceros silvestris , Wrinkled Hombills Aceros
( Rhyticeros ) corrugatus and Malayan Black Hombills Anthracoceros
malayanus , the last two being kept in France only here and at the Jardin
d'oiseaux tropicaux. Red-crested Turacos and White-cheeked Turacos T.
leucotis are also displayed in the hombill aviaries. The park has France's
second largest collection of hombills - the largest collection being that of
the Jardin d'oiseaux tropicaux at La Londe les Maures on the Mediterranean
coast.
Parc des Oiseaux de Villars les Dombes is currently financing two in-situ
conservation programmes, one for the Abyssinian Ground Hombill and the
other for the reintroduction and management of the population of Oriental
Pied Hombills A. albirostris convexus on Pulan Ubin, an island off the
north-east of Singapore.
Another highlight of the park's conservation work is its successful
breeding colony of Dalmatian Pelicans Pelecanus crispus , which breeds
each year on islands in the lake on which it lives. The Parc des Oiseaux
currently houses the largest captive breeding colony of this species and it is
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999561" page_id="56253637"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
184
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.923078" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253637" page_num="184" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - VILLAR DES DOMBES BIRDPARK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.973253148148148" page_id="56253637"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
among the most productive, annually producing young birds from which to
develop a breeding programme for this species.
The next destination for visitors is a group of three aviaries housing
Ocellated Laughingthrushes G. ocellatus artemisiae living with a pair of
the rare Salvadori's Pheasant Lophura inornata , a pair of White-throated
Laughingthrushes G. albogularis which are currently the only specimens on
display in France, a pair of Edwards's Pheasants L. edwardsii, a group of Pied
Imperial Pigeons Ducula b. bicolor and Black-throated Laughingthrushes
G. c. chinensis.
The final exhibit and one of the most impressive is the huge and
beautifully landscaped walk-through aviary called - Krabi - in which one finds
a variety of waterbirds and some pheasants from Africa, Asia and Europe.
The main theme of this exhibit is the protection of wetlands around the
world. The list of species showcased in this amazing aviary includes: Great
White Egret Casmerodius a. albus , Little Egret Egretta g. garzetta , Cattle
Egret Bubulcus ibis , Himalayan Monal Lophophorus impejanus, Eurasian
Spoonbill P. leucorodia , Carolina or American Wood Duck, Mandarin Duck,
Mallard A. platyrhynchos, Grey Heron, Northern Bald Ibis or Waldrapp
Geronticus eremita , Falcated Teal A. falcata , Madagascar Teal A. bernieri
and Yellow-billed Stork Mycteria ibis.
This bird park - 'Made in France' - has not only the best avian collection
in France, but is among the most beautiful bird parks in Europe, set as
it is in an amazing landscape that includes a large nature reserve which
gives the public the opportunity to observe many different species of wild
birds, including some locally endangered species. The conservation and
pedagogical (educational) work of the park's employees is certainly among
the best known of any of the public animal collections in France.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.86945" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56253637" page_num="184" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986631083333333" page_id="56253637"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
I would like to thank the Curator Eric Bureau and Mme Julie Toque for
allowing me to visit the park during the winter months and for being so
helpful during the writing of the above article. I also wish to thank all of
the keepers and my friend Sergio (a former keeper) for the information they
provided me with and the warm welcome they gave me during my visits
in 2009 and 2010. Finally, I wish to thank my dear friend Josef Lindholm,
who was recently appointed Curator of Birds at Tulsa Zoo, for his help and
encouragement.
The author, who lives at Le Chesnay in France, was the recipient of
the 2010 Dulcie Cooke Award for the excellent photographs illustrating
his articles about the bird collections at Parc de Cleres, Taipei Zoo and
Weltvogelpark Walsrode. E-mail: pedroyayadrums@yahoo.com
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998779" page_id="56253638"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
185
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.969469" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253638" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
NEW SPECIES OF TURACO ADDED TO COLLECTION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.873335166666667" page_id="56253638"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
The World of Birds Wildlife Sanctuary, Hout Bay, near Cape Town, has
added Ross's Turaco Musophaga rossae to its collection. Visitors to Africa's
largest bird park can now see 10 members of the turaco family - the others
being the Violet M violacea, Knysna Tauraco corythaix, Purple-crested T.
( Gallirex)porphyreolophus , Green-crested or Guinea T. persa, Fischer's T.
fischeri and Hartlaub's T. hartlauhi , along with the Bare-faced Go-away Bird
Corythaixoidespersonatus. White-bellied Go-away Bird C. leucogaster and
Eastern Plantain-eater Crinifer zonurus.
To learn more about the World of Birds, which has more than 3,000 birds
and other animals belonging to some 400 different species housed in more
than 100 spacious walk-through aviaries in a tropical garden setting, you
can visit its website: www.worldofbirds.org.za
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.3492885" page_id="56253638"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
* * *
ENDING ON A HIGH
By early October, a total of 1,223 parrots had been bred this year by the
Loro Parque Fundacion, Tenerife. A number of important species of lories
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.980797045454546" page_id="56253638"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
were bred during the year, including four Violet-necked Eos squamata , a
Red Lory E. bornea, a Red-and-blue Lory E. histrio , two Blue-eared Lories
E. semilavata and, after a break of several years, two Blue-streaked Lories
E. reticulata. The ringing (banding) of a further two young Purple-bellied
Lories Lorius hypoinochrous devittatus brought the number of young reared
this year to 10. These will further help the fundacion in its attempt to build
up a self-sustaining captive-breeding population, which is presently being
hampered by a significant excess of males.
Six Hyacinth Macaws Anodorhynchus hyacinthus were continuing to
be reared either by their parents of were being hand-reared and a Moluccan
Cockatoo Cacatua moluccensis was also being hand-reared and another
was being reared by its parents. When the latter becomes independent it
will, it is hoped, be integrated into the fundacion's small flock of Moluccan
Cockatoos.
In the spring, customs officials at Vienna Airport seized 74 Amazon parrot
eggs, which a Slovakian was attempting to smuggle into the country from
Jamaica. The eggs were taken to Tierpark Schonbrunn (Vienna Zoo) and
placed in incubators and 54 chicks hatched, of which 45 - 23 Yellow-billed
Amazons Amazona collaria and 22 Black-billed Amazons A. agilis - were
reared to independence. Following Loro Parque Fundacion's collaboration
with its Austrian colleagues and in appreciation of its advice and practical
help, Curator Simone Haderthauer and keeper Petra Stefan took to Loro
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99932" page_id="56253639"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
186
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.923658" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253639" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997291" page_id="56253639"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
Parque in October, three pairs of Yellow-billed Amazons and three pairs
of Black-billed Amazons, as part of a breeding programme which is being
managed within the zoo community.
As part of a two-week internship, 20 veterinary students from Giessen
University in Germany visited the fundacion, where they attended lectures
and acquired practical experience of zoo medicine.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.8751175" page_id="56253639"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
* * *
NEW CURATOR MAKES A START
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.988991787878788" page_id="56253639"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
Josef Lindholm commenced his duties as the new Curator of Birds at
Tulsa Zoo on November 9th 2011, and expressed himself "delighted to be
working with a team of seven enthusiastic and knowledgeable aviculturists."
The zoo was recently transferred from the direct management of the City
of Tulsa to a newly incorporated non-profit making body which has plans
to expand the collection. Arrangements are already being made to acquire
a number of interesting native birds to coincide with the remodelling of
the zoo's famous North American Living Museum, which was opened in
1978.
There are presently 69 taxa of birds in the zoo collection. Josef was
delighted to find that the pair of Scissor-tailed Flycatchers Tyrannus forficatus
- The State Bird of Oklahoma - had produced a chick in 2010. It was sent
to Oklahoma City Zoo and then onto the National Aviary in Pittsburgh.
Josef believes that Tulsa Zoo, which in 1980 was the first zoo to breed the
OrmgQquit Euneonis campestris , a species which is endemic to the Caribbean
island of Jamaica, is the only zoo to have succeeded in breeding the Scissor-
tailed Flycatcher in captivity.
Tulsa's first Red-fronted Macaw Ara rubrogenys chick appears (according
to ISIS) to be the only one produced in an American zoo in 2011, as do the
two Plush-capped or Plush-crested Jays Cyanocorax chrysops. Josef said
that Tulsa Zoo has a long history of success with the Plush-capped or Plush-
crested Jay. He can clearly remember seeing two young with their parents in
an indoor exhibit when he first visited Tulsa Zoo in 1984. Also, (according
to ISIS) the Bali Starling Leucopsar rothschildi was one of only five hatched
in US zoos in 2011 (the others were hatched at Toledo and Minnesota).
With the arrival of a pair of Madagascar Teal Anas bernieri from Great
Plains Zoo, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, Tulsa Zoo became one of a dozen
or so US collections exhibiting this species. The birds, which remain the
property of the Republic of Madagascar, are descendants of those imported
in 2005 by Mike Lubbock's Sylvan Heights Waterfowl Park &amp; Eco-Center
in North Carolina.
At Dallas World Aquarium (where Josef was Senior Aviculturist prior
to taking up his appointment at Tulsa) the forty-first Andean Cock-of-the-
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.699546" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253640" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997637" page_id="56253640"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
187
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.966762" page_id="56253640"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
Rock Rupicola peruviana chick hatched in November and at the time Josef
wrote (December 4th 2011), several more eggs were being incubated.
Guianan Cocks-of-the-Rock R. rupicola and Capuchinbirds Perissocephalus
tricolor were also hatched in 2011, as well as the aquarium's first troupials
- presumably the Moriche Icterus chrysocephalus. Capuchinbirds were sent
to San Diego Zoo and in return the aquarium received Raggiana Birds-of-
Paradise Paradisaea raggiana, A pair of White-winged Trumpeters Psophia
leucoptera arrived at the aquarium from Peru some months before Josef's
departure and is a species he had not previously seen in captivity.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.87276" page_id="56253640"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.506104" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56253640" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
THE USUAL ROLLER COASTER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8061092" page_id="56253640"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
The 2011 breeding season was, writes Bernard Sayers, the "usual roller
coaster of plentiful disasters and occasional successes", before adding that
on the positive side the following were all successfully reared: three Black-
winged Lories Eos cyanogenia , five Black-cheeked Lovebirds Agapornis
nigrigenis, many wild-type grey Java Sparrows Padda oryzivora , two
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.963645" page_id="56253640"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
Lemon Doves Aplopelia larvata , four Sulawesi Ground Doves Gallicolumba
tristigmata , 13 Triangular-spotted or Speckled Pigeons Columba guinea ,
two Chaco Owls Strix chacoensis , two Boobook Owls Ninox boobook ,
four Burrowing Owls Athene cunicularia , three White-faced Owls Ptilopsis
leucotis, two Indian Scops Owls Otus bakkamoena and seven Tropical
Screech Owls Megascops choliba.
* * *
NATURAL HISTORY COURSES
The Field Studies Council (FSC), an environmental charity with over
</table>
<footnote confidence="0.440262">
65 years' experience of providing courses and fieldwork opportunities for
people of all ages, has in 2012 a number of natural history courses available
at different levels and all with expert tuition throughout. These will be
available at its network of UK centres, which are all in stunning locations,
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.88293025" page_id="56253640"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
often with unique wildlife.
The bird courses available can be viewed online by clicking onto the
following link: http://tinyurl.com/bm48elg or alternatively you can
view its e-brochure at: http://view.digipage.net/?userpath=00000645/
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.69174" page_id="56253640"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
00015144/00070991
</page>
<reference confidence="0.7825512">
Hard copies of the brochure and further information are available
from: Mel Cousins, Field Studies Council, Head Office, Montford Bridge,
Shrewsbury, SY4 1HW. Tel:01743 852118/E-mail: mel@field-studies-
council.org/Website:www.field-studies-council.org/Twitter:www. twitter.
com/fsc_news
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998775" page_id="56253641"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
188
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.76475" genericHeader="method" page_id="56253641" page_num="188" year="" vol="">
MY PAL STEWART PYPER
MEMORIES OF A FRIENDSHIP
by Mike Curzon
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.978211529411765" page_id="56253641"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
I first met Stewart in the early 1970s at a talk given by George Anderdon
to Frome Cage Bird Society. It was the beginning of a firm friendship which,
sadly, ended with Stewart's death in October.
In the early days of our friendship, Stewart came to Rode Tropical Bird
Garden every Saturday after shopping with his mother. He would pick-
up day-old chicks and bananas (always on the look-out for a bargain was
Stewart) and any snippets of news and gossip - or, better still, scandal. He
then began coming on the occasional zoo visit with me, when I went to
collect or deliver birds. Also, we used to go, together with Martin Greene, to
the Avicultural Society talks and wine and cheese evenings at the Linnaean
Society in London. It was great to travel there with Stewart, because he
knew his way around London - in fact he always seemed to know his was
around everywhere. Stewart must surely have been the prototype for the
first satnav. Whenever we went anywhere together, such as to an Avicultural
Society day out, he always knew unerringly which road to take and invariably
we arrived half-an-hour early, as Stewart liked to ensure that we had time
for coffee and biscuits before the meeting began.
On the society's European trips, Stewart always kept everyone together,
apart from Colin Jackson, who he used to give up on about halfway around.
Without Stewart, I doubt that Colin will make it past the first aviary. I used
to call Stewart, Shep, because of his sheepdog-like efforts to keep us all
together. I miss being able to phone Stewart and bounce ideas off him, and
miss his calls to me asking what I thought about various things. I also miss
his evening visits after he had been to his Uncle John's for dinner and then
came around to us for cheese and biscuits - always complaining if there were
no digestive biscuits. Then we would share a glass of red wine or port before
he dashed back home to Nunney. I will really miss my pal Stewart.
WE WILL MISS HIS LAUGTHER
Stewart was a well-known and popular figure at The Bear Inn at
Holwell. He supported a number of charities and among his many loves
was real ale and the pub provided two barrels of Funky Monkey, one of
Stewart's favourites, for a "farewell party." For every pint sold, #1 (approx.
US$1.50) was donated to the Church Roof Fund. This raised #150 (approx.
US$225).
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999181" page_id="56253642"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
189
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.7417444" page_id="56253642"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
Contributors to Volume 117 - 2011
Bertagnolio, Paolo
Visually sexing the Hawk-headed Parrot Deroptyus accipitrinus ...........51
Visually sexing the Senegal Parrot Poicephalus senegalus together
with an example of social breeding behaviour by his species .................97
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.790027533333333" page_id="56253642"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
Bralsford, Gary
Breeding the Oriental Greenfinch Carduelis sinica................................ A9
Breeding the White-crowned Robin-Chat Cossypha albicapilla............... 1
The beautiful Blue-bellied Roller Coracias cyanogaster...................... 150
The Chestnut-backed Thrash Zoothera dohertyi..................................AQ2
Braslurul Simon and Bretschek, Lech
The Southern Crested Caracara Caracara plancus, including its
breeding at Weltvogelpark Walsrode .....................................................122
Bnxslund, Simon and Gaede, Martin
News of parrots at Weltvogelpark Walsrode............................................32
Bra si end, Simon, Magnus, Wolfgang and Scheres, Geer
Notes on tinamous currently found in aviculture.75
Cohere Rose, McCulloch, Bronwyn, Butler, David and Holland, Glen
Captive care of the Friendly Ground Dove Gallicolurnba stairi ........... 105
de Chabanees, Pierre
A bird extravaganza with a French accent.............................................174
The Dallas World Aquarium ....................................................................59
Daka, Alazar, Kumsa, To! era, Borghesio, Luca, Lemould, Jean-Marc
and Bekele, Afework
New studies find challenges and opportunities for the conservation
of Prince Ruspoli's Turaco Tauraco ruspolii......................................... 145
Dunn, Christopher
The care and breeding of the Pekin Robin Leiothrix lutea .13
Edmans, Ian
The 2010 breeding season at Waddesdon Manor................................23
Ellis, Malcolm
The society's Special Interest Groups....................................................131
Girling, Reuben, B.
On some UK bird breedings by members of the
Avicultural Society in 2009.
</table>
<page confidence="0.866193" page_id="56253642"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
,52
</page>
<page confidence="0.98911" page_id="56253643"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
190
</page>
<table confidence="0.893101166666667" page_id="56253643"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
Contributors to Volume 117 - 2011 (cont'd)
Jaquest, Dick
Successfully breeding the Lilac-breasted Roller Coracias caudatus ....169
Low, Rosemary
Lorikeet exhibits in UK zoos...99
Marler, Christopher
Breeding Bewick's Swan Cygnus columbianus bewickii
at Flamingo Gardens and Zoological Park........ 11
Pelicans of the world.. 154
Matthews, Simon
The importance of record keeping in aviculture.. 135
Pryke, Sarah R.
Saving the Gouldian Finch Erythrura gouldiae ... 2
Santegoeds, John, Vervest, Huub and Vicentini, Gaetan
The Grey Singing Finch Serinus leucopygius .35
Santegoeds, John
The Lemon-breasted Canary Serinus citrinpectus .158
Sierra, Miguel and Gallego, Rosana
Breeding the Green Jay Cyanocoraxyncas at Barcelona Zoo.. 39
Smallbones, Peter
Breeding the Black-necked Weaver Ploceus nigricollis melanoxanthus
at Paignton Zoo Environmental Park.....28
Stocks, Peter
The Malay or Buffy Fish Owl Ketupa ketupu .128
</table>
<figure confidence="0.84984175" page_id="56253643"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
Waite, Rebecca
Hand-rearing a Great Blue Turaco Corythaeola cistata
at Paradise Park, Hayle, Cornwall...Ill
Waugh, David
Action on the conservation of the endangered Swift Parrot
Lathamus discolor .166
Wust, Rene
Conserving parrots around the world........87
</figure>
<page confidence="0.998802" page_id="56253644"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
191
</page>
<table confidence="0.696485419354839" page_id="56253644"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
Index to Volume 117 - 2011
bird breedings, by UK members of the Avicultural Society in 2009 .......52
Book Reviews
Babbling Birds: An Anthology of Poems about Parrots...90
Extremadura, Spain.........92
Rescued from the Brink of Extinction: Kakapo ...91
Canary, Lemon-breasted, its care and breeding.....158
Caracara plancus , including its breeding at Walsrode .....122
Caracara, Southern Crested, including its breeding at Walsrode...122
Carduelis sinica , its care and breeding.........49
Coracias caudatus, successfully breeding..........169
Coracias cyanogaster , with some notes on its breeding.150
Corythaeola cristata , hand-reared at Paradise Park, Cornwall.111
Cossypha albicapilla , breeding.7
Cyanocoraxyncas, breeding at Barcelona Zoo..........39
Cygnus columbianus bewickii, bred by our chairman ...11
Dallas World Aquarium, its fantastic collection of birds..59
Deroptyus accipitrinus , visual sexing. .51
Dove, Ground, Friendly, its captive care in Samoa......105
Erythrura gcwldiae, saving this iconic species......2
Finch, Gouldian, saving his iconic species.2
Finch, Grey Singing, its care and breeding.35
Gallicolumba stairi , its captive care in Samoa...105
Greenfinch, Oriental, its care and breeding ........49
Jay, Green, breeding at Barcelona Zoo.39
Ketupa ketupu .. 128
Lathamus discolor , action for its conservation...166
Leiothrix lutea , its care and breeding. 13
lorikeets, a critical look at their care in UK zoos... 99
My Pal Stewart Pyper - Memories of a Friendship....188
News &amp; Views.......44,94,138,185
</table>
<page confidence="0.998239" page_id="56253645"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
192
</page>
<table confidence="0.875489142857143" page_id="56253645"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
Index to Volume 117 - 2011 (cont'd)
Obituaries
Don Merton............48
Stewart Pyper............144
Owl, Fish, Malay or Buffy..........128
Parc des Oiseaux de Villars les Dombes, near Lyon, France......174
Parrot, Hawk-headed, visual sexing........51
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.866155714285714" page_id="56253645"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
Parrot, Senegal, visual sexing, social breeding behaviour........... 97
Parrot, Swift, action for its conservation.......166
parrots, conserving these birds around the world...87
parrots, news of these birds at Walsrode.....32
Ploceus nigricollis melanoxanthus , UK first breeding.......28
Poicephalus senegalus, visual sexing, social breeding behaviour........... 97
record keeping, its importance in aviculture... 135
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.495267555555556" page_id="56253645"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
Robin-Chat, White-crowned, breeding.....7
Robin, Pekin, its care and breeding.......13
Roller, Blue-bellied, with notes on its breeding....... 150
Roller, Lilac-breasted, successfully breeding........ 169
Serinus citrinpectus , its care and breeding .....158
Serinus leucopygius , its care and breeding.....35
Special Interest Groups, species and coordinators...130,131
Swan, Bewick's, bred by our chairman ......11
Tauraco ruspolii, challenges and opportunities..........145
</table>
<reference confidence="0.704488714285714">
Thrush, Chestnut-backed, breeding his species........ 102
tinamous, notes on species currently found in aviculture...... 75
Turaco, Great Blue, hand-reared at Paradise Park, Cornwall..Ill
Turaco, Prince Ruspoli's, challenges and opportunities.145
Waddesdon Manor, 2010 breeding season.....23
Weaver, Black-necked, UK first breeding.......28
Zoothera dohertyi , breeding this species .... 102
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.984553" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253646" page_num="" year="" vol="">
SANDPIPER MARATHON
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986675458333333" page_id="56253646"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Council member Nigel Hewston will be running the Virgin London
Marathon on April 22nd 2012, to raise funds for the Spoon-billed Sandpiper
Eurynorhynchuspygmeus conservation breeding programme. An expedition
to Chukotka in eastern Siberia by the Wildfowl &amp; Wetlands Trust (WWT)
and its Russian partners succeeded in collecting eggs and rearing 13 birds,
which are now housed in a purpose-built facility at Slimbridge and should
reach breeding age in 2013.
This critically endangered migratory wader is hurtling towards extinction
perhaps faster than any other bird. In a decade its population has crashed
from thousands to possibly as few as 200 birds. It is suffering from industrial
development on the mudflats which it uses as staging posts on its 8,000km
(approx. 5,000 miles) migration route between Siberia and Thailand,
Burma (Myanmar) and Bangladesh, where it spends the winter and may be
trapped for food. The breeding project is one of a number of conservation
measures involving several organisations, aimed at addressing these issues.
If successful, it will buy time for other measures to have an effect and,
potentially, provide birds for a reintroduction programme. Nigel says, "This
is a unique bird which will become extinct very soon without our help." The
WWT project is an example of the vital contribution that aviculture can
make to conservation and, Nigel very much hopes, that Avicultural Society
members will generously support the Sandpiper Marathon fund.
Please visit the website: www.justgiving.com/sandpiper to donate or
send cheques payable to the WWT to: Sandpiper Marathon, Fundraising
Department, WWT, Slimbridge, Glos. GL2 7BT, UK.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.550154" page_id="56253646"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.905708" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56253646" page_num="" year="" vol="">
LORY MEETING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.961294818181818" page_id="56253646"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The annual lory meeting organised by Rosemary Low will take place
on May 20th and this year will be held in conjunction with the parrot event
being staged by Parrots magazine. Entitled - Think Parrots 2012 - it will be
held at Woking Leisure Centre in Surrey, which is easily accessible from the
M25, M3 and A3. Advanced tickets for the event cost #6. However, there
will be no charge to attend the lory meeting, but those planning to attend
should advise Rosemary beforehand. As usual, the meeting will start at
1.00pm and close at about 4.00pm. There will be speakers and, by popular
request, this year one hour will be set aside for a questions and answers
session and discussion. For further information please telephone: 01623
846430 or e-mail: rosemary.low@virgin.net
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.869675" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56253647" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.94433584" page_id="56253647"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
New studies find challenges and opportunities for the
conservation of Prince Ruspoli's Turaco Tauraco ruspolii
by Alazar Daka, Tolera Kumsa, Luca Borghesio,
Jean-Marc Lemould and Afework Bekele.145
The beautiful Blue-bellied Roller Coracias cyanogaster
by Gary Bralsford.150
Pelicans of the world
by Christopher Marler.154
The Lemon-breasted Canary Serinus citrinpectus
by John Santegoeds.158
Action for the conservation of the endangered
Swift Parrot Lathamus discolor
by David Waugh.166
Successfully breeding the Lilac-breasted Roller Coracias caudatus
by Dick Jaquest.169
A bird extravaganza with a French accent
by Pierre de Chabannes. 174
News &amp; Views.185
My Pal Stewart Pyper: Memories of a Friendship
by Mike Curzon. 188
Contributors to Volume 117-2011.189
Index to Volume 117-2011.191
SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION LIBRARIES
3 9088 01657 3875
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
</table>
</algorithms>
