<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.837751" page_id="56259636"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 114
No. 2
2008
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259637" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.984827516129033" page_id="56259637"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2008 as for 2007: British
Isles #18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please).
The subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the
Society later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of
the AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, ARCADIA, THE MOUNTS, TOTNES, DEVON TQ9 7QJ,
UK.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TNI3 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail: Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have not
been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of a
particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history. Articles
should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the scientific
names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given. References
cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line drawings,
black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular point in
the article will be used where possible and should be clearly captioned. If
authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when submitting the
article and write their name on the back of each photograph. Tables and
graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be aware of
the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of the page
which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997594" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259637" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982475333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.80561" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259638" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.302961" page_id="56259638"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 114 - No. 2 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2008
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9614075" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259638" page_num="" year="" vol="">
NOTES ON THE IV INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM ON
BREEDING BIRDS IN CAPTIVITY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97122" page_id="56259638"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Josef Lindholm
All living Guam Rails Rallus owstoni and Guam Micronesian Kingfishers
Halcyon c. cinnamomina (Todiramphus cinnamominus cinnamominus in
Clements, 2007) are descendents of birds brought into aviculture in the late
1980s, before the last wild specimens were exterminated by the invasive
Brown Tree Snake Boiga irregularis .
In his book And No Birds Sing , science journalist Mark Jaffe (1994),
described the beginnings of the programmes that resulted in the establishment
of captive breeding populations of these two taxa. A pivotal development
was the meeting of Bob Beck of the Guam Division of Aquatic and Wildlife
Resources and Guy Greenwell, Larry Shelton and Don Bmnning, the
Curators of Birds at the National Zoological Park, Philadelphia Zoo and
Bronx Zoo, respectively. The meeting took place in 1983, in Los Angeles,
California, at the Jean Delacour/IFCB Symposium on Breeding Birds in
Captivity.
Although, at the time, few people, if anyone, were aware that the future
existence of two taxa of birds would be determined by the above meeting
at this symposium, it was certainly apparent to everyone present that a
remarkable assemblage of zoo people, private aviculturists, ornithologists
and other research workers had been brought together - in the words of the
Wizard of Oz - "to confer, converse, and otherwise hobnob."
The same could be said of the symposium that preceded it, in Seattle,
in 1978 (Anon., 1978), and of the one that followed in 1987, also in Los
Angeles. The proceedings of all three remain important reference points
(Risser et al. 1981; IFCB, 1983; IFCB, 1987). It was hoped by all those
involved that further symposiums would be held at regular intervals, but this
was not to be. Mark Jaffe (1994) chronicled the sudden and unexpected
downfall, in 1988, of the International Foundation for the Conservation of
Birds, the organisation which had funded the second and third symposiums,
as well as the publication of the proceedings of all three.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.98098" page_id="56259639"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
50
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.724155" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259639" page_num="50" year="" vol="">
LINDHOLM - IV INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986040756097561" page_id="56259639"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
There was much excitement when it was announced that a fourth
symposium, hosted by a major American zoo, would be held in 2000.
Speakers were recruited and the preparation of papers began, but for reasons
I am not aware of, these plans eventually came to nothing. Therefore, at the
end of 2005, when I learned that there were again plans afoot for a fourth
symposium, this time in Toronto, Canada, in 2007,1 was somewhat skeptical.
So were many others and, up until several months before the scheduled time,
rumours were rife that, again, nothing would come of this.
The symposium was planned originally for October 2007, but it became
necessary to move it forward to September. This was unfortunate, as it
meant it coincided not only with the Annual Conference of the (American)
Association of Zoos and Aquariums (AZA) but also that of the European
Association of Zoos and Aquaria (EAZA). Attendance at the symposium
was further affected by anxiety caused by unanticipated delays by the US
Government in granting passports to its citizens, who prior to the sudden
change of policy, had not had to concern themselves with such documents
when travelling to southern Canada.
Nonetheless, approximately 120 delegates gathered in Toronto, from
September 12th-September 16th 2007. They came from over 22 countries,
including Cuba, Brazil, Sweden, Latvia, Morocco, United Arab Emirates and
Saudi Arabia. Papers and poster sessions were presented by 43 speakers from
15 countries. In addition, there were spirited round table discussions on the
European bird import ban and the potential for collaboration between private
and institutional aviculture. A commercial exhibitors' room provided
participants with the opportunity to learn about the latest publications,
nursery apparatus, diets and medical procedures. The closing banquet
afforded the opportunity to recognise avicultural achievements, with the
Conservation Award to Jurong Bird Park, Singapore, for its Pied Hombill
reintroduction programme and the ISBBC Avicultural Award to Martine
van Havere for her work with Threskiomithidae (Ibises), as well as Lifetime
Achievement Awards to Lynn Hall, Mike Lubbock and Robert J. Berry.
It was not immediately apparent to most of the speakers and delegates
that the staging of the symposium was the achievement of two men - Myles
Lament and David Longo. Myles Lamont, Avian Manager at the Hancock
Wildlife Center in British Columbia, as well as an editor at Hancock House
Publishers, arranged the programme and recruited the speakers. Myles
was all of three years old in 1987 when the third symposium was held.
David Longo, who appeared to be not much older than Myles, is an Ontario
professional aviculturist specialising in conservation significant parrots.
He was responsible for logistics and finance, arranging the conference
hotel and international transportation of the speakers, and a myriad of other
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.321733" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259640" page_num="51" year="" vol="">
LINDHOLM - IV INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997367" page_id="56259640"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
51
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.970089658536585" page_id="56259640"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
practical considerations. Both men were in constant motion throughout
the conference and, if by the end, they appeared exhausted, it was only to
be expected. It was only after all was said and done, that the scale of their
endeavour could be truly appreciated.
During the symposium heavy emphasis was placed on aviculture as
a means of preventing the extinction of critically endangered taxa. In
some cases, the outcome remains uncertain. Although a robust self-
sustaining captive population of Northern Bald Ibis or Waldrapp Geronticus
eremita has existed for several year, the establishment of reintroduced wild
populations has so far met with only limited success. In his paper entitled
- Why is reietroduction of the Northern Bald Ibis so complicated? - Chris
Bowden, International Species Recovery Officer for the UK-based Royal
Society for the Protection of Birds (RSPB), presented an overview of the
challenges involved. A similar situation exists with Attwater's Prairie
Chicken Tympanuchus cupido attwateri. Molly Coym of Houston Zoo
discussed the methods by which a captive population has been maintained for
over a decade. Despite the frequent release of captive-bred birds, however,
the wild population barely persists in two small Texas preserves. Thus, the
captive flocks, distributed among six institutions, represent the most certain
likelihood of the continued existence of this subspecies.
A paper on the plight of a species that exists now only in captivity and
is clearly exhibiting the effects of a very small founder population, was
presented by Richard Switzer who, in May 2007, in his capacity as the new
Curator of Birds at A1 Wabra Preservation, Qatar, assumed responsibility
for the majority of living specimens of Spix's Macaw Cyanopsitta spixii.
Among this population are birds exhibiting "almost all the known diseases
which affect parrots." Furthermore, the lack of genetic diversity has resulted
in "infertility, late maturing, embryonic mortality and chick deformities." In
the face of these challenges, staff at A1 Wabra developed "what is arguably
the most thorough and extensive health management programme for any
bird species in the world." At the time the manuscript of his paper was
submitted, there were 47 Spix's Macaws in Qatar. The number had, through
the successful rearing of chicks, risen to 51 by the end of 2007.
Genetic swamping of one species by another, due to habitat degradation,
is an increasing problem. A species that may in the future cease to exist
in its pure form is the Madagascar Pond-Heron Ardeola idae , threatened
by the recent invasion of the Squacco Heron or African Pond-Heron A.
ralloides. Simon Braslund Jensen, now (2008) Zoological Director of
Walsrode Birdpark, discussed his institution's work with the Madagascar
Pond-Heron, both in establishing a captive population and in preserving its
remaining habitat, and presented a general overview of Walsrode 5 s extensive
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99243" page_id="56259641"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
52
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.722448" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259641" page_num="52" year="" vol="">
LINDHOLM - IV INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998404585365853" page_id="56259641"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
programmes in Madagascar.
Taxonomic revisions can complicate conservation programmes. The
total population of the Northern Brown Kiwi Apteryx mantelli has declined
by more than a third in the past decade, due to habitat loss and predation
by alien predators, with the situation rendered even more drastic by recent
molecular research which indicates that this species - only recently 'split'
from the other 'Brown Kiwis' - is itself comprised of distinct 'races', yet
to be given scientific names. Martin Bell of the Kiwi and Birdlife Park
at Queenstown, discussed Auckland Zoo's attempts to augment the much
reduced population of the Northland 'race' by collecting eggs from the
wild and releasing the resulting offspring into, hopefully, safe habitats. As
the founders of the current captive population of the North Island Brown
Kiwi outside of New Zealand were imported before any of the 'races' were
recognised, their taxonomic situation appears unclear. Kathleen Brader,
Senior Bird Keeper at the Smithsonian National Zoological Park, presented
a poster session discussing the history of kiwis in the UK, continental
European, Asian and American collections, and the implications for the
future. The first kiwi hatched outside of New Zealand was hatched at the
National Zoo in 1975 and is still alive and well. The overall survival of
captive-bred offspring has, however, been disappointing. Only five of the
22 hatched at San Diego Zoo between 1983-1999 were still alive in 2007.
Somewhat better results have been achieved at Frankfurt Zoo, with 16 of
the 32 hatched there since 1986 still alive in 2007. Kathleen told me she
hopes that kiwis of unclear provenance, rescued following dog attacks, may
eventually find their way into the overseas zoo population.
Martin Bell also presented a paper on recent promising developments
regarding the aviculture and reintroduction of the spectacular Takahe
Porphyria mantelli. For years results appeared tenuous, but recently birds
reared using hand-puppets have been confirmed to be breeding in the wild at
several locations. (A Takahe hatched from the first clutch of eggs collected
from the wild is still alive 25 years later.)
Chris Bowden's second paper concerned the plight of three species of
south Asian vultures - the White-rumped or Oriental White-backed Gyps
hengalensis, Indian G. indicus and Slender-billed G. tenuirostris - which
were once abundant but are now near extinction, due to secondary ingestion
of the cattle analgesic diclofenac. Along with efforts to remove diclofenac
from the environment, a captive breeding programme is in its early stages.
As of early 2007, 165 vultures representing all three species in roughly equal
numbers, had been brought into captivity in India. Within the next two years
it is hoped that the breeding programme will have at least 75 pairs of each
species. A similar programme planned for the White-rumped or Oriental
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.321613" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259642" page_num="53" year="" vol="">
LINDHOLM - IV INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998055" page_id="56259642"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
53
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.942195780487805" page_id="56259642"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
White-backed Vulture in Pakistan's Punjab Province was presented in poster
form, authored by Campbell Mum and Uzma Khan.
Papers were presented on two South African projects which are likewise
at early stages of development. William Horsfield, who has achieved
remarkable breeding results with parrots and toucans at his Amazona
breeding facility in KwaZulu-Natal, discussed the deteriorating status of
the Cape Parrot Poicephalus robustus and the attempts to establish a stable
captive population. There are at present fewer than 100 specimens listed
in the International Studbook. The only registered birds outside of South
Africa are at Mulhouse Zoo in France. They are descendents of the famous
breeding pair at Basel, augmented with birds from an importation in the
1980s. Jeanne Marie Pittman, Hospital Supervisor at Johannesburg Zoo,
dealt primarily with the medical aspects of the Wattled Crane Recovery
Programme. Recent research has shown that the South African population
of the Wattled Crane Bugeranus carunculatus is genetically unique and
is best managed separately from birds descended from founders from the
Botswana population. It is hoped that a captive population may eventually
be used to augment wild populations.
Africam Safari at Puebla, Mexico, has in recent years worked on
propagating a number of conservation significant birds endemic to Mexico
and Meso-America (Central America). Curator of Birds Juan Cornejo,
spoke briefly on its projects with the Maroon-fronted Parrot Rhynchopsitta
terrisi, Socorro Conure Aratinga brevipes, Tuxtla Quail-Dove Geotrygon
carrikeri and Bearded Wood-Partridge Dendrortyx barbatus. His main
focus though was on the Homed Guan Oreophasis derbianus. Always
rare, the Endangered Homed Guan appears not to have been brought into
captivity until the 1970s. As far as is documented, a successful full captive
breeding did not occur until 1994. Africam Safari acquired seven wild-
caught specimens and six captive-bred birds in 2000 and has achieved the
best captive breeding results. Juan is the International Studbook Keeper for
this species and is Mexican coordinator of the International Committee for
the Conservation of Oreophasis derbianus and its Habitat. He presented a
detailed account of the aviculture of this species of which he hopes a self-
sustaining captive population will be established. The first Homed Guans
kept alive outside of Mexico were those sent from Africam Safari to St
Louis Zoo in 2006.
A memorable feature of the second symposium was the showing of slides
documenting the development of Homed Guan chicks hatched from eggs
collected from the wild in 1982. The slides were included in a presentation
by Dr Jesus Estudillo Lopez (1983). Dr Estudillo has for well over 30
years been renowned for his magnificent aviaries and particularly for his
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994466" page_id="56259643"  page_num="54" year="" vol="">
54
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.724913" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259643" page_num="54" year="" vol="">
LINDHOLM - IV INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985009926829268" page_id="56259643"  page_num="54" year="" vol="">
work with cracids. In the Avicultural Magazine Vol.83, No.l, pp. 50-53
(1977), the then 86 year old Jean Delacour, wrote an enthusiastic account
of his first visit to Dr Estudillo's collection. With approximately 500 taxa
of birds, it may now be the largest collection in the Western Hemisphere.
Dr Estudillo's presentation in Toronto focused on his unique success
propagating the Northern Resplendent Quetzal Pharomachrus m. moccino
and the conservation status of this glorious bird, but was also an elegiac
summary of his years of field work in the Neotropics.
As might be expected, with the emphasis being on threatened birds,
the conservation of island endemics occupied a substantial part of the
programme. Dylan Kesler of the University of Missouri presented his
research on Pacific island kingfishers. This focused on the beginnings
of conservation projects for the Critically Endangered Niau Kingfisher
Halcyon gambieri gertrudae , as well as a study of the Pohnpei Kingfisher
H. cinnamomina reichenbachii (Todiramphus gambieri gertrudae &amp; T.
cinnamominus reichenbachii in Clements, 2007), to help better understand
the needs of the Guam Micronesian Kingfisher.
The extinction in the wild of the Guam Micronesian Kingfisher and the
Guam Rail occurred in the 1980s, whereas the Aga or Mariana Crow Corvus
kubaryi did not die out on that island until 2002 or 2003. At present there
are fewer than 200 on the nearby island of Rota and a few were reintroduced
from there to Guam. A few birds were sent to US zoos in the 1990s, but a
captive population was not established. At Toronto there was a poster session
on the efforts to stabilise the Rota population and re-establish this crow
back on the island of Guam. Despite the continued presence of the Brown
Tree Snake, chicks have in recent years been reared by birds translocated
there from Rota.
Other poster sessions dealt with two of the myriad of bird species
restricted to the Philippines. Three authors discussed the first captive
breeding of the Philippine Eagle-Owl Bubo p. philippensis and eight
authors presented a report on the first survey of the Critically Endangered
Negros Bleeding-heart Gallicolumba keayi. It was observed at multiple
locations and it is reassuring to learn that populations may tolerate low-
level agriculture. An avicultural programme has begun at the S. Y. Reyes
Zoological and Botanical Garden.
Gary Ward, responsible for the softbills and pigeons at the Durrell
Wildlife Conservation Trust, discussed the logistics of the so far successful
project to establish a captive population of the Critically Endangered
Montserrat Oriole Icterus obei. The initial decline of this species was
due to much of its mid-elevation forest habitat on the West Indian island
of Monserrat being cleared for agricultural use. The main threat to the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.321557" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259644" page_num="55" year="" vol="">
LINDHOLM - IV INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994204" page_id="56259644"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
55
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.982030048780488" page_id="56259644"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
remaining population is from volcanic activity and hurricanes. It is entirely
possible that a future natural disaster could wipe out the remaining wild
population. Therefore, it is reassuring to know that this species has proved
"relatively easy to breed and seems well suited to life in captivity, so long
as certain requirements are met." Plans are afoot to establish further captive
populations.
A further encouraging report came from Richard Switzer, regarding the
in situ project to boost the population of the Mauritius Fody Foudia rubra
by "rescuing and harvesting" eggs and chicks from nests in the wild. After
having been hand-reared, the birds are released on an offshore island, on
which they are closely monitored. The overall population is estimated to
have grown by 60% since 2002.
Especially encouraging was the presentation by Peter McClelland,
Programme Manager for Outlying Islands for the New Zealand Department
of Conservation. The flightless Campbell Island Teal Anas aucklandica
nesiotis was feared extinct, but was then rediscovered in 1975 on tiny
Dent Island. At the time there was estimated to be no more than 50 birds.
Eleven were collected between 1984-1990, but captive propagation did
not commence until 1994. A population was successfully established on
a 'holding island', while far grander plans were afoot. In 2001, the largest
rat eradication programme ever attempted, began on Campbell Island, on
which rats had been resident since 1812. It involved "four helicopters and
120 tonnes of bait" and was declared a success in 2003, when during an
exhaustive survey no remaining rats were discovered. After an absence of
more than a century, this teal is again living on Campbell Island, following
the introduction of 158 birds from breeding facilities and the 'holding
island,' that were introduced in phases, from 2004-2006. An expedition
in 2006 discovered not only that the teal was breeding freely, but the
'Campbell Island Snipe' (listed in Clements (2007) as an undescribed form
of the Subantarctic Snipe Coenocorypha aucklandica ssp.) had recolonised
the island and petrels were nesting there for the first time in decades.
Peter presented a second paper, which outlined the general principals of
island translocations, based on more than 20 years' experience of such
endeavours.
Alan Lieberman, who in various capacities has been employed for more
than 30 years by the Zoological Society of San Diego, gave an overview of
the Hawaii Endangered Bird Conservation Programme, administered by the
zoological society in collaboration with state and government agencies and
private corporations. Working with 22 endangered species, of course, entails
mixed results. On one hand, Alan described the depressing experience
of caring for the last Po'o-Uli Melamprosops phaeosoma , a species only
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.987418" page_id="56259645"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
56
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.718808" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259645" page_num="56" year="" vol="">
LINDHOLM - IV INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996812365853659" page_id="56259645"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
discovered in 1973, which "dying, and yet in Death alive" - in the words of P.
D. Q. Bach - has, in part, become an inmate of the 'Frozen Zoo' maintained
at the society's Center for the Reproduction of Endangered Species (CRES).
On the other hand, in eight years, 113 Critically Endangered Puaiohi
Myadestes palmeri, the smallest of Kaua'i's two thrushes and perhaps the
only extant one, have been reintroduced and, 10 other species of Hawaiian
passerines, some on the edge of extinction, have also been bred at the
programme's breeding centers.
Another island project launched by San Diego's Center for the
Reproduction of Endangered Species (CRES) and also administered
by Alan Lieberman, though funded by the US Navy, involves the San
Clemente Loggerhead Shrike Lanius ludovicianus mearnsi. Two posters
were presented by Susan Farabaugh, who co-authored them with seven
colleagues. One considered changes in the release protocol which has
resulted in a much improved survival rate among captive-bred birds over
a period of several years. None of the birds liberated between 1992-1999
survived to breed, whereas since then some of the birds released each year
have joined the breeding population and the number of birds has increased
substantially. As one might expect, parent-reared juveniles fare better than
hand-reared birds. The other poster dealt with the logistics involved in the
annual production of captive-bred birds for release, working with a captive
flock of approximately 60 birds.
The Loggerhead Shrike was also the subject of a paper presented
by Jessica Steiner, who coordinates the recovery effort for the eastern
subspecies L. 1. migrans in Ontario. By 1995 only 30 breeding pairs were
estimated to remain in Canada. Since 2001, however, 221 captive-bred
shrikes have been released, 129 of them in 2006. Reproduction by released
birds has now begun to be documented. There are at present 24 propagation
and release enclosures, located at field sites in southern Ontario.
Programmes for a number of other North American birds were also
profiled. Paul Williams, Animal Care Supervisor at the British Columbia
Wildlife Park, discussed the reintroduction of the Burrowing Owl Athene
cunicularia in British Columbia, from which this charming owl had almost
disappeared by the 1970s. Since 1989, roughly 600 of these owls have
been hatched at the park and others have been bred at Burrowing Owl
Conservation of BC, enabling more than 800 to have been released so far.
In addition, 700 artificial burrows have been installed.
By the close of the twentieth century, the population of the Light-footed
Clapper Rail Rallus longirostris levipes - a subspecies found only in southern
California - had declined to fewer than 600 individuals. Its decline was
almost entirely due to the extensive commercial development of its wetland
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.321729" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259646" page_num="57" year="" vol="">
LINDHOLM - IV INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997149" page_id="56259646"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
57
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.991963951219512" page_id="56259646"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
habitat, now fragmented into 23 disjunct locations. Laurie Conrad, Assistant
Curator of Birds at Sea World California, San Diego, discussed a programme
to augment these fragmented populations with captive-bred birds, to prevent
the effects of inbreeding. Pairs of wild-caught adults have been set up and
commenced breeding in 2001 and, 146 offspring, both parent-reared and
artificially incubated and the chicks hand-reared, have been released in five
areas. In the most recent census, 408 pairs were counted on 18 marshes, the
highest number of pairs for many years.
Steller's Eider Polysticta stelleri has proved the most difficult of the
eiders to establish and maintain in aviculture over long periods. A poster
session by Heidi Cline, who co-authored it with Tuula Hollmen and Nora
Rojek, explained the Alaskan Sea Life Center's experiments with the use
of artificial incubation to produce a captive flock at the centre and its role
in enhancing productivity in wild populations by safeguarding eggs from
predators.
An inspiration to all concerned, were the papers presented on two
famous species, the populations of which had plummeted to fewer than
30 living specimens of each and now number in the hundreds, thanks to
successful reintroduction programmes. Michael Wallace gave an overview
of his 28 years work with the California Condor Gymnogyps californianus
at Los Angeles Zoo and San Diego Wild Animal Park, describing the
challenges and disappointments that have attended efforts to re-establish
wild populations. Lead poisoning from bullet-ridden carcases remains a
major source of mortality and now that chicks are being parent-reared in
the wild, the ingestion of 'micro trash' proffered to them by their parents is
a serious cause of neonatal deaths. On the other hand, it was satisfying to
hear Dr Wallace's account (with pictures) of condors feasting on beached
Grey Whales Eschrichtius robustus - some of which had been dead for a
year! Joseph Duffs account of his innovative use of ultralight aircraft to
track the migratory routes of new populations of Whooping Cranes Grus
americana had a broad general appeal.
In the UK, several populations of the once extirpated Red Kite Milvus
milvus have been established in the past decade. Campbell Mum of the Hawk
Conservancy presented a poster, co-authored with three other researchers,
detailing the set backs and eventual successes in Hampshire, with birds of
various ages and backgrounds.
Two papers dealt with aviculture related to the ancient art of Arabic
falconry. In both cases French veterinarians are responsible for taxa of
bustards once regarded as forms of a single species, but each now considered a
separate (full) species in its own right. Since 1999, Frederic Lacroix has been
Manager of the Emirates Center for Wildlife Propagation in Missour, eastern
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994216" page_id="56259647"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
58
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.726374" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259647" page_num="58" year="" vol="">
LINDHOLM - IV INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997228717948718" page_id="56259647"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
Morocco, where more than 19,000 North African Houbara Chlamydotis u.
undulata have been produced since 1997; of which 8,146 were produced
in 2007. It was anticipated that nearly 6,000 would be released between
September 2007-March 2008. Previous releases have totalled 5,454 birds,
"with a survival rate of about 70% one year after release." In the near future
they hope to be rearing 5,000 Houbara a year. At the same time, efforts are
being made to conserve existing populations of Moroccan Houbara by the
creation of non-hunting zones.
Similar efforts are underway with the Asian Houbara or Macqueen's
Bustard C. macqueenii at the National Avian Research Centre in the United
Arab Emirates (UAE), where Olivier Leon is Manager of the Captive
Breeding Department. Dr Leon explained that unlike other bustard species,
the Houbara does not breed well under normal captive conditions and is
very sensitive to stress. Consequently, successful captive breeding of the
Houbara not only has to use and adapt techniques developed by the poultry
industry, such as artificial insemination and artificial incubation, but it is
also necessary to keep the birds "tamed from hatch to death," which is
extremely demanding in terms of manpower. While this may seem to lead
in the direction of some new sort of domestic fowl, careful attention is paid
to "maintaining the original genetic diversity of the founders."
The establishment of a population of American Kestrels Falco sparverius
as laboratory animals was examined by Dr David Bird, Director of the Avian
Science and Conservation Centre at McGill University. For 35 years he
has managed a research colony that has numbered as many as 500 birds at
a time. Propagation has been achieved through many generations and is
now formulaic. Emphasis has been placed on toxicology studies, but these
birds have also been the subject of research into "reproduction, physiology,
morphology, behaviour, veterinary medicine, nutrition and parasitology."
Several of the presentations were of a highly technical nature. The
paper entitled - A Medical Approach to the Atricial Chick - by Dr Michael
Taylor, Service Chief in Avian and Exotic Animal Medicine at Ontario
Veterinary College, was based primarily on work with parrots and placed
heavy emphasis on the development of the cloacal bursa. Coleen Lynch of
the Association of Zoos and Aquariums' Population Management Center
in Chicago discussed the principals of population biology, especially as
they apply to recovery plans for animals which have gone through genetic
bottlenecks. In a poster session, Austin and May Ann Hughes revealed their
hypothesis that many US migratory birds have comparatively little genetic
diversity, as a result of habitat restriction during the Ice Age.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.46482">
Phillip Seddon, Director of the Wildlife Management Programme at
the University of Otago, New Zealand, spoke of the risks imposed on birds
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.475109" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259648" page_num="59" year="" vol="">
LINDHOLM \0x25A0 IV INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996314" page_id="56259648"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
59
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997406048780488" page_id="56259648"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
stemming from their having been maintained in captivity. He said, candidates
for release programmes must be evaluated taking into account these potential
risks. "Each risk factor will have an associated risk function, the cumulative
probability of a deleterious effect with time spent in captivity, and each
will necessitate specific mitigation measures." Kate Mclnnes presented a
poster session, co-authored with three fellow New Zealanders, addressing
the disease issues faced by three New Zealand captive breeding and release
programmes and the strategies to deal with them. OMA-based tests for
psittacine beak and feather disease, Pacheco's virus, avian polyomavirus,
avian tuberculosis and other such afflictions have been developed by the
Health Gene Laboratory.
More traditional aviculture was not ignored. There were two papers on
traditionally difficult cockatoos. First, William Horsfield went into great
detail on the husbandry of the Palm Cockatoo Probosciger a. aterrimus ,
which he has consistently been successful with in South Africa; then
Australian aviculturist Neville Connors dispelled some longstanding
"avicultural myths" regarding cockatoos of the genus Calyptorhynchus , all
four members of which are thriving in private collections in Australia.
Peter Karsten, who following a long and distinguished career at Calgary
Zoo, has put much effort into establishing an aviary-bred strain of Pekin
Robins leiothrix lutea , presented two talks, as well as a poster session. His
paper on breeding livefood will be a valuable source of reference for others
wishing to do likewise. Each day Peter's so fibrils consume live insects, of
four species, worth roughly US$100 (#50) if he had to rely on purchasing
them from commercial suppliers. Instead, not counting an hour or so a day
of his own labour and the capital investment, Peter estimates that it costs
him just US$5 (approx. #2.50) to produce the 4,200 insects he feeds to his
birds each day. His poster session laid out the aviary conditions necessary
to successfully breed Pekin Robins and his key note speech, at the closing
banquet, emphasised the continued importance of collaboration between
private and institutional aviculturists.
A poster by Nebraska aviculturist Jason Beck, detailed his experiences
setting up six pairs of Piping Hombills Bycanistes fistulator , a species which
US zoos, already committed to programmes for other African hombills,
have little capacity for.
Kathy King, Chair of the Ciconiiformes and Phocn icoptcn formes Taxon
Advisory Group of the EAZA, reviewed the status of the 6,700 flamingos
in European zoos and discussed the challenges of maintaining the various
species into the future.
Mike Lubbock, with more than 40 years of work in major collections
of ducks, geese and swans, discussed the results of two 2004 surveys of the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.984898" page_id="56259649"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
60
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.719633" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259649" page_num="60" year="" vol="">
LINDHOLM - IV INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996893585365854" page_id="56259649"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
status of anatids in American aviculture. He foresees a rather depressing
outlook for the future of many of these species, as zoos follow the general
trend of reducing the number of taxon they exhibit and the number of private
waterfowl breeders appear to be on the decline. On a brighter note, Mike
elaborated on the transition of his Sylvian Heights Waterfowl Center from
a private facility to a public exhibit, that will continue to be a major and
reliable source of waterfowl for collections around the world.
Another master waterfowl breeder, Peter Kooij, who continues the
business his father started in the Netherlands many years ago, was a lively
participant in the above mentioned round table discussions, along with
Peter Karsten, Simon Bruslund Jensen and John Azua, Curator of Birds at
Denver Zoo, taking some thought provoking stands during discussions on
the future of European aviculture, and the realities involved in private and
institutional partnerships.
One hears practically nothing about birds in African zoos outside of
South Africa. Therefore, a poster presented by Jonathan Fayomi and
Olugbenga Eniola Bada of the zoo which is part of the University of Ibandan,
Nigeria, was of particular interest. After 30 years of benign neglect, the
aviary, once a proud feature of the zoo, had fallen into disrepair and housed
only the remnants of a collection. It has now though been renovated and
restocked and its inhabitants are "expected to breed and multiply in number
so that they can replenish the Earth."
My paper on the avicultural history of hummingbirds, ended up as a
more than 90 page manuscript, a development I had not anticipated, but one
gracefully received by Myles Lamont. My primary source of information
was the Avicultural Magazine. Jean Delacour, remembered most for his
achievements with pheasants and waterfowl, worked with hummingbirds for
at least seven of his nine-and-half decades, and I cited 42 of his publications
from 1922-1973. I found it appropriate, in that Dr Delacour was invoked
as a sort of'Patron Saint' of this symposium and was very much a presence
at the first two. (A poster session on his achievements at Bronx Zoo in the
1940s, which I presented at the 1983 symposium, eventually became an
article in the Avicultural Magazine (Lindholm, 1988)).
Although, for reasons noted earlier, the number of delegates was fewer
than had been hoped for, there was, as at previous symposiums, a wonderful
mix of people. I was especially delighted to meet Juan Soy, Head of
Conservation Programs for Cuba's Empresa Nacional para la Proteccion de
la Flora y la Fauna. Dr Soy, who is also on the faculty of the University of
Havana and has served as an Assistant Director of Havana Zoo, has worked
closely with researchers from other countries and has been featured in such
publications as the National Geographic. He has conducted field work on
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.321497" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259650" page_num="61" year="" vol="">
LINDHOLM - IV INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997469" page_id="56259650"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
61
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.956534764705882" page_id="56259650"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
the Critically Endangered Cuban Solenodon Solenodon cubanus (a large,
long-tailed, shrew-like, insectivore) and is presently working to establish a
captive population of the Endangered Blue-headed Quail-Dove Starnoenas
cyanocephala , the sole member of the genus found only in Cuba. The
proceeds of the symposium banquet auction were earmarked for the project
with the Blue-headed Quail-Dove.
I met people from several other countries, including Brazil and Saudi
Arabia, and two staff members from Jurong Bird Park, Singapore. Harald
Schmidt, Curator of Birds at Rotterdam Zoo, told me about the zoo's
breeding colony of European Bee-eaters Merops apiaster. It was a pleasure
to meet for the first time Jo Gregson, Senior Head Keeper of Birds at Paignton
Zoo, a long-time contributor to the Avicultural Magazine. It is always a
delight spend time with John Ellis, Senior Curator of Higher Vertebrates at
the Zoological Society of London (ZSL), who had taken time off from the
busy preparations for the re-opening of the renovated Bird House - renamed
the Blackburn Pavilion. Nancy Clum, Assistant Curator of Ornithology at
Bronx Zoo, my old friend Grenville Roles, in charge of the bird collection
at Disney's Animal Zoo Kingdom in Florida, John and I, served as the
Awards Committee for the symposium. Peter Kooij supplied us with much
needed advice.
Quite a number of American zoos were represented by delegates. There
was also a good turnout of those involved in one way or another with US
private aviculture, including a number well-known for their services to the
avicultural community: Walter Sturgeon, Lynn Hall, Ivo Lazzeroni (who
made an impassioned plea, during poster sessions, for private aviculturists
to focus greater attention on native birds), Natasha Schischakin, Dick
Schroeder, Luke Thirkhill and John Del Rio, among others.
I, and quite a few others, were indebted to Tom Mason, Curator of Birds
&amp; Invertebrates at Toronto Zoo, who was a wonderful host to those of us
who were able to visit the zoo, providing transport (not just to the zoo, but
also to other places of interest) and spending much time showing us around
the exhibits and explaining the zoo's extensive programs.
The general consensus was that the fourth symposium was a great success
and, the primary question was, when will the next one be?
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.987462" genericHeader="references" page_id="56259650" page_num="61" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.999063">
Anon. 1978. The First International Birds in Captivity Symposium (8th-12th March, 1978).
Avicultural Magazine 84,2:114-116.
Clements, J. F. 2007. The Clements Checklist of the Birds of the World, Sixth Edition. Cornell
University Press, USA &amp; Helm, London.
Delacour, J. 1977. Two collections of birds in Mexico. Avicultural Magazine 83,1:50-53.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.994874" page_id="56259651"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
62
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.669749" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259651" page_num="62" year="" vol="">
LINDHOLM - IV INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9093499" page_id="56259651"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
Estudillo Lopez, R. J. 1983. Considerations in regard to rare and endangered species of Cracids
both in nature and captivity. In: Proceedings - Jean Delacour/IFCB symposium on breeding
birds in captivity (pp.45-61).
IFCB. 1983. Proceedings - Jean Delacour/IFCB symposium on breeding birds in captivity.
IFCB.
IFCB. 1987. Proceedings - Jean Delacour/IFCB symposium on breeding birds in captivity.
IFCB.
Jaffe, M. 1994. And no birds sing. Simon &amp; Schuster.
Lindholm, J. H. 1988. Captain Delacour at the Bronx (1940-1947). Avicultural Magazine
94, 1 &amp; 2:31-56.
Risser, A. C., Baptista, L. F., Wylie, S. R. and Gale, N. B. 1981. Proceedings - First international
birds in captivity symposium. IFCB.
Josef Lindholm is Senior Aviculturist at The Dallas World Aquarium in
Texas. Website:www. dwazoo.com
The Proceedings of the IV International Symposium on Breeding Birds
in Captivity , which run to approximately 500 pages, can be purchased online
at:www.isbbc.org or by e-mail at:info@isbbc.org. Alternatively, copies
can be ordered by post from:I. S. B. B. C., 637316 St Vincent-Sydenham
Townline, Meaford, Ontario, Canada N411W5. Tel:+1 -604-866-2837. Price
Canada $64.99 (which is approx.#32.00).
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.5174885" page_id="56259651"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
* *
*
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.949998" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259651" page_num="62" year="" vol="">
SNIPPETS OF INFORMATION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9926318" page_id="56259651"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
Among "snippets of information" reported by a "correspondent" in
Seattle at the first symposium (Avicultural Magazine Vol.84, No.2, pp. 114-
116 (1978)), was that the Bali Starling Leucopsar rothschildi (at the time
called Rothschild's Myna or Crackle) can be sexed by the length of the crest
- that of the male being over 60cm (2'Ain) long whereas that of the female
is under 55mm (2 Ain) long.
The first item in News &amp; Views in the above issue of the magazine
(p.l 16), noted that Jersey Zoo had imported eight of these birds in 1971,
and from them some 70 young had been reared, 47 of which had been sent
to six different countries.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998403" page_id="56259652"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
63
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.770954" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259652" page_num="63" year="" vol="">
THE NESTING BEHAVIOUR OF THE MUSOPHAGIDAE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.979086473684211" page_id="56259652"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
(continued from Vol. 114, No. 1, pp.2-12)
Part 2
Further notes on the White-cheeked Turaco
Tauraco 1. leucotis
by Myles Lamont
In the summer of 2005 and again in 2006 one of the female White-
cheeked Turacos Tauraco /. leucotis at the Hancock Wildlife Research
Center constructed a nest of her own, on both occasions in a dense tangle of
English Ivy Hedera helix. In summer 2005, she was seen carrying nesting
material throughout a large mixed aviary (3.6m x 3.6m x 60m (approx. 12ft
x 12ft x 196ft)) whose occupants included some 10 other White-cheeked
Turacos, three Ross's Musophaga rossae, two Guinea T. persa and two
Red-crested Turacos T. erythrolophus. Despite the apparent competition
and potential rivals, she constructed a very secure nest and there were three
eggs, one of which was fertile; but she abandoned the nest approximately a
week after it was discovered.
In 2006, the same female constructed her nest in a different location,
again in the same mixed aviary shared with three other species of turaco and
some additional White-cheeked Turacos. Also present in the flight were
a female Red-billed Hombill Tockus erythrorhynchus and some ErckeTs
Francolins Francolinus erckelii. Both nests were sheltered from the rain
by a thick mat of ivy growing on the top of the aviary and extending about
0.5m (approx. 1ft 8in) above the nests; it is unknown whether or not this
had any bearing on her choice of nest sites. The thickest clumps of ivy
were growing on the west facing aviary wall, which was where she nested,
although there was probably the potential for her to have nested on the east
facing side. The nest consisted of approximately 87 items of nest material,
ranging from large sticks to smaller twigs, rootlets and leaves.
It should be noted that the female was only two years old at the time of
her first nesting attempt and it is possible that one of the eggs in her first
nest was laid by another female in the aviary.
In her second nest, the chick was first observed on July 7th, when it
was two or three days old. It began the fledging process on July 28th, but
returned to the nest for several days thereafter. It would spend the majority
of the day only 1m (3 ft 3 in) or so away from the next and returned to it at
various times throughout the day and, almost always, returned to it for the
night. About the fourth week, the chick left the nest and spent most of the
fifth week in a Red Alder Alnus rubra some 4m (approx. 13ft) from the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.972548" page_id="56259653"  page_num="64" year="" vol="">
64
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.316766" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259653" page_num="64" year="" vol="">
LAMONT - MUSOPHAGIDAE
</sectionHeader>
<figureCaption confidence="0.979483333333333">
Fig. 1. Length of individual pieces of nesting material.
Length of nest materials
Fig. 2. Diameters of individual pieces of nesting material.
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.992937333333333" page_id="56259653"  page_num="64" year="" vol="">
Diameter of nest materials
1 4 7 10 13 16 19 22 25 28 31 34 37 40 43 46 49 52 55 58 61 64 67 70 73 76 79 82 85
Number
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.478919" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259654" page_num="65" year="" vol="">
LAMONT - MUSOPHAGIDAE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.988682" page_id="56259654"  page_num="65" year="" vol="">
65
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.312768">
Female and well-grown nestling.
</tableCaption>
<page confidence="0.764615" page_id="56259655"  page_num="66" year="" vol="">
66
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.249337" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259655" page_num="66" year="" vol="">
LAMONT - MUSOPHAGIDAE
</sectionHeader>
<figureCaption confidence="0.990957">
Fig. 3. Composition of materials used for nesting.
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.7233545" page_id="56259655"  page_num="66" year="" vol="">
Nest Composition
5%
\0x25A1 Cottonwood Populusb trichocarpa
\0x25A1 Chinese Gooseberry Acfimdta cbinensis
\0x25A1 Red Elderberry Sambucus racemosa
El Red Alder A/ms rubra
\0x25A0 Red Cedar Thuja pficata
\0x25A0 English iw Hedera hehx
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.876224071428571" page_id="56259655"  page_num="66" year="" vol="">
nest site. The branches were between 2.8m-3.6m (approx. 9ft-12ft) above
the ground and the tree was quite mature, so provided heavy canopy cover
and some protection from the elements. The young turaco rarely ventured
outside of the tree and throughout the day was brought food by the female,
although they were very discrete about such feedings. Rather surprisingly, it
appeared not to be molested by other turacos in the aviary. No observations
were made of helpers at the nest, although we suspect that this may have
occurred.
By the sixth week, the young turaco was seen leaving the relative safety
of its 'nursery tree' and was occasionally observed scurrying along the aviary
floor. It was not often seen during the day and remained relatively inactive
until it had gained almost its full flight capability: nor, until it had achieved
full flight capability, did it show any attempt at kin socialisation.
On one occasion the young turaco was spooked when it was on a
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.483529" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259656" page_num="67" year="" vol="">
LAMONT - MUSOPHAGIDAE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998738" page_id="56259656"  page_num="67" year="" vol="">
67
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999859514285714" page_id="56259656"  page_num="67" year="" vol="">
Nest No. 1,2005. Size: approx. 22cm long x 17cm wide (8 3 /4in long
x 6 3 Ain wide). Location: 1.7m (approx. 5ft 6in) above the ground in
a dense tangle of ivy growing up the vertical netting beside an aviary
door. The nest faced westwards and would have received the majority
of sunlight after 1.00pm-2.00pm. Description: composed entirely of
dead, dry ivy twigs, most of which would have been broken off from the
creeper, rather than collected from the ground. They were interwoven
into a somewhat transparent, but nevertheless quite sturdy nest. Of the
three eggs that were in the nest, one disappeared shortly after the nest
was discovered, one was infertile and the chick in the other egg died
during the latter stages of incubation.
Nest No.2, 2006. Size: 33cm long x 17.8cm wide x 2.5cm deep
(approx. 1 ft long x 7in wide x lin deep). Location: 2.2m (approx. 6ft
6in) above the ground, above the aviary door, again in a dense clump of
ivy. The nest faced due west and was in sunlight from 1.00pm onwards.
Description: almost exactly the same as the first nest, except for being
slightly larger. Dry ivy twigs were again used for the majority of the
nest despite the availability of other nest materials. Two clutches of
eggs were successfully hatched in this nest
low perch and scuttled along the ground one and into a clump of grass.
The male Erckefs Francolin ran towards the clump of grass and began a
threatening posture towards the young turaco and, as it left the clump of
grass, the francolin chased after it. Without the young turaco having made
any vocalisations, a group of at least six adult turacos, seemingly led by
the mother of the young turaco, engaged the male francolin as it pursued
the young bird. The turacos dived at and bounced off the back of the male
francolin and emitted their typical alarm screeches. This worked amazingly
well and the francolin was immediately overwhelmed and left. The group
of turacos dispersed, except for the mother of the young turaco, which then
remained with it. The social support the turacos displayed further developed
our suspicion that there may be some co-parental behaviour on the part of
this species. We were unable to determine which bird was the father of the
young turaco, as the female was the only bird observed incubating and caring
for the chick. It may be important to mention that the majority of the adult
birds in the aviary were siblings and as a result there may have been some
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997887" page_id="56259657"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
68
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.87028" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259657" page_num="68" year="" vol="">
LAMONT - MUSOPHAGIDAE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994167" page_id="56259657"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
potential genetic reasoning for the aforementioned altruistic behaviour,
which was shown only by the other White-cheeked Turacos in the aviary.
A second clutch was laid, of two eggs, but only one hatched. The chick
remained in the same nest until it was two weeks of age, when all of the
birds were moved indoors for the winter.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.915226" genericHeader="references" page_id="56259657" page_num="68" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.87690225" page_id="56259657"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
Bannerman, D. A. 1933. The Birds of Tropical West Africa. Vol.3. Oliver &amp; Boyd, Edinburgh
and London.
Barnicoat, F. 1987. In: News &amp; Views, Avicultural Magazine 93,3:173-174.
Bates, G. L. 1909. Field-Notes on the Birds of southern Kamerun, West Africa. Ibis 9,3:1-
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.513853" page_id="56259657"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
74.
</page>
<reference confidence="0.870112621621622">
Bent, N. 1988. Breeding the Violet Turaco Musophaga violacea at Brookfield Zoo, Chicago,
USA. Avicultural Magazine 94,3:129-135
Berry, R. J. &amp; Todd, W. W. 1982. Breeding touracos at the Houston Zoological Gardens, Texas,
USA. Avicultural Magazine 88,4:205-209.
Boehm, E. M. 1967. Successful breedings at the Edward Marshall Boehm Aviaries in 1966.
Avicultural Magazine 73,4:116-120.
Britton, P L. and Britton, H. A. 1976. The nest and eggs of Tauraco fischeri. Bulletin of the
British Ornithological Club, 96,4:134-136.
Brown, P. B. 1971. In: News &amp; Views, Avicultural Magazine 77,6:227-228.
Candy, M. 1984. Habits and breeding biology of the Great Blue Turaco Corythaeola cristata.
Journal of the East African Natural History Society 180:1-19.
Chapin, J. P. 1963. The touracos: an African bird family. The Living Bird 2:57-67.
Chapin, J. P. 1939. The Birds of the Belgian Congo Vol.II. Bulletin of the American Museum
of Natural History 75:215-238.
Courtenay-Latimer, M. 1942. Knysna Lourie ( Turacus corythaix corythaix). Ostrich 13:1-9.
Congdon, S. and Heller, L. 2000. Raising Lady Ross' Turacos at Disney's Animal Kingdom.
AFA Watchbird 21, 5:48-50.
Ellis, M. 1979. Notes from a Kenyan collection. Avicultural Magazine 85,2:95-96.
Everitt, C. 1965a. Breeding the White-cheeked Touraco. Avicultural Magazine 71,4:24-27.
Everitt, C. 1965b. The year 1964 at the Boehm Aviaries. Avicultural Magazine 71,4:116-
120 .
Foxall, I. and Burton, P. J. K. 1975. Notes on the nesting of the White-cheek Touraco Tauraco
leucotis. Bulletin of the British Ornithologists' Club 95,1:27-29.
Friedman, H. 1930. Birds collected by the Childs-Frick Expedition to Ethiopia and Kenya
Colony. Part 1. United States National Museum Bulletin 153:248-259.
Fry, C. H., Keith, S. and. Urban E.K. (eds.). 1988. The Birds of Africa Vol. III. Academic
Press, London.
Garsee, S. 1992. Strange breeding behaviour of the Livingstone's Touraco. American Cage-
Bird Magazine 64 ,8:43-45.
Heston, J. 1987. Captive propagation and management of the Guinea Turaco. AFA Watchbird
13,6:46-51.
Hick, U. 1964. Breeding Knysna Turacos Tauraco corythaix at Cologne Zoo. International
Zoo Yearbook 5:131-132.
Horne, S. C. 1991. Breeding the Buffon's Touraco. Avicultural Magazine 97,1:35-36.
Isenberg, A. H. 1993. Successful breeding of the white breasted touraco. ASA Avicultural
Bulletin March 1993:10-12 (reprinted from 1936).
Jarvis, M. J. F. and Currie, M. H. 1974. Breeding the Purple-crested Touraco. Avicultural
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.482358" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259658" page_num="69" year="" vol="">
LAMONT - MUSOPHAGIDAE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995429" page_id="56259658"  page_num="69" year="" vol="">
69
</page>
<reference confidence="0.9751018125">
Magazine 80,6:217-219.
Lament, M. M. 2006a. Some notes on the occurrence of hybridization in turacos. International
Turaco Society Newsletter 26,2:12-15.
Lament, M. M. 2006b. The Magnificient Musophagidae. Proc. 32nd Annual American
Federation of Aviculture Conference 2006 (pp. 67-69). Dallas, Texas.
Lamont, M. M. 2005. Some observations of captive Musophagidae. AFA Watchbird 31,4 &amp;
33,1:52-56.
Mackworth-Praed, C. W. and Grant, C. H. B. 1957. Birds of Eastern and North Eastern Africa.
Series 1, Vol.2. Longmans Green, London.
McLachlan,G. R. and Liversidge, R. 1976. Roberts' Birds of South Africa (pp.231-232). Cape
&amp; Transvaal Printers, Ltd., Cape Town.
McLean, G. L. 1985. Roberts' Birds of South Africa , (pp.322-325) John Yoelcker Bird Book
Fund, Cape Town.
Milne, K. 1991. First breeding of the Fischer's Touraco. AFA Watchbird 18,5:41-42.
Milne, K. 1990. Breeding the Lady Ross's Touraco. AFA Watchbird 17,4:39-40.
Paterson, L. 1993. Breeding of Fischer's Touraco at Leeds Castle. Avicultural Magazine
99,4:168-170.
Payne, C. .M. 1963. Breeding the Knysna Touraco. Avicultural Magazine 69,1:25-29.
Payne, R. B. 1997. Family Cuculidae (Cuckoos) (pp.508-607). In: del Hoyo, L, Elliot, A.
and Sargatal, I. (eds.). Handbook of the Birds of the World. Vol.4. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona,
Spain.
Raison, F. 1992. Captive breeding of the Purple-crested Touraco Avicultural Magazine
98,3:111-114.
Risdon, D. H. S. 1954. Notes on Hartlaub's Touracos. Avicultural Magazine 60,3:86-89.
Roles, G. 1973. Breeding the Schalow's Turacos at the Jersey Wildlife Preservation Trust.
Avicultural Magazine 79,3:75-78.
Roles, G. 1970. Breeding the Grey Touraco at the Jersey Zoological Park. Avicultural Magazine
76,6:232-233.
Rowan, M. K. 1983. The Doves, Parrots, Louries and Cuckoos of Southern Africa. David
Philip, Cape Town.
Royston, A. 1974. In: News &amp; Views, Avicultural Magazine 80,5:196.
Rutgers, A. and Norris, K. A. (eds.). 1972. Encyclopedia of Aviculture. Vol.II. Blandford
Press, Poole, Dorset.
Stannard, J. 1971. Nesting louries. Bokmakierie 23,4:77-79.
Steel, N. R. 1973. Breeding Ross's Touraco. Avicultural Magazine 79,1:30-34.
Thompson, D. R. 1991. Touracos: an overview. ASA Avicultural Bulletin 20,8:7-8.
Todd, W., Grubbs, D. C. and Lahera, H. 1985. A successful breeding of the White-bellied
Touraco Corythaixoides leucogaster at the Houston Zoo. Avicultural Magazine 91,3:121-
123.
van Someren, V. G. L. 1956. Days with birds: studies of habits of some east African species.
Fieldiana Zoology 38:164-174.
Young, R. 1975. Second generation breeding of grey turaco at Busch Bird Park - Houston,
Texas. Avicultural World 1,5:3-6.
The author, Myles Lamont, Avian Manager, Hancock Wildlife Research
Center, 19313 Zero Avenue, Surrey, British Columbia V3S 9R9, Canada,
would like to hear from those aware of other reports of turaco nesting
behaviour, eitherpublishedor unpublished. E-mail :myles@hancockwildlife.
org
</reference>
<page confidence="0.965001" page_id="56259659"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
70
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.846715" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259659" page_num="70" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE BLACK-AND-WHITE
LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.933128878787879" page_id="56259659"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
Garrulax bicolor
by Andrew Owen
Garrulax bicolor is endemic to the montane and hill forests of Sumatra
from 750m-2,000m (approx. 2,500ft-6,560ft) above sea level.
It was previously considered to be a subspecies of the more familiar
White-crested Laughingthrush G. leucolophus , but as a result of taxonomic
changes was recently accorded full species status and given the English name
Sumatran Laughingthrush, later changed to Black-and-white Laughing-
thrush (Collar, 2006).
There is considerable concern about the status of this species in the wild.
Until recently it was considered to have been common and widespread in
suitable habitat, but appears to have been trapped so extensively in its forest
haunts, that in 2006 it was known at only a single site. Nigel Collar stated
that some birds could still be found in bird markets in northern Sumatra,
but they are now very rare and greatly outnumbered by the White-crested
species, imported from continental Asia.
Following its apparent rapid decline, this species' status in the wild on
the island of Sumatra, needs urgent re-evaluation.
This laughingthrush has apparently always been rare in western aviculture
with very few birds in the UK and Europe. During a recent search of the ISIS
database I could not find any listed in North American zoological collections.
The assumption must be that the majority of birds trapped for the bird trade,
remain in Indonesia and other parts of south-east Asia.
Description
It is a large laughingthrush approximately 30cm (11 %in) in length. It has
a white head, throat, neck and breast. The black feathers at the base of the
bill extend upwards onto the forehead and the black also extends from the
bill, around and behind the eyes and forms a narrow 'teardrop' shape (see
photo p.76 to see how different and unusual the markings are compared to
the bold black face mask of the White-crested species). Except for a faint
pale grey wash at the base of the nape, the remainder of the plumage is a
uniform blackish-brown. The eyes are dark reddish-brown, the bill is black
and the legs and feet are blackish-grey.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.49854" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259660" page_num="71" year="" vol="">
OWEN - BLACK-AND-WHITE LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996945" page_id="56259660"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
71
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.8799855">
Table 1. Biometric measurements and weights of four adult males and
one female.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.984694333333333" page_id="56259660"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
Bill
Skull
Tarsus
Wing
Tail
Weight
</figure>
<footnote confidence="0.9441554">
31.5mm
57.9mm
49.1mm
137mm
132mm
120g
31.0mm
57.6mm
49.2mm
134mm
130mm
137g
30.7mm
56.9mm
48.9mm
134mm
129mm
132g
32.1mm
57.7mm
48.8mm
136mm
131mm
129g
28.6mm
54.2mm
49.0mm
122mm
127mm
HOg
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.979069428571429" page_id="56259660"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
Acquisition and pairing of the birds
In 2001 my brother Neil purchased two of these laughingthrushes from
bird importer Phil Cleeton. DNA sexing revealed that they were both males.
After a lot of searching, Phil Cleeton managed to find another two, which
my brother purchased, but these too turned out to be males. Unable to find
any females, Neil decided in 2004 to sell the birds to us here at Waddesdon
Manor aviaries.
Although the chances of us finding any females appeared slim, we felt
that these loud, showy birds would make a wonderful exhibit and hoped
that in time we might find one or two females. Within weeks of the four
birds arriving here, Phil Cleeton managed to find another bird, this time in
the collection of a private aviculturist. We purchased this bird, which was
DNA sexed and found to be a female.
Following a 30 day quarantine period it was paired with one of the males
in an on-show aviary. However, following constant calling between the pair
and the remaining bachelor group housed nearby, it was decided to move
the pair to an off-show aviary. This was 6m long x 4m wide x 2.5m high
(approx. 20ft long x 13ft wide x 8ft 3in high) and planted with box bushes
and a 2.5m (approx. 8ft 3in) high leylandii tree. The floor was covered with
bark chips, mulch and leaf litter. The aviary was furnished with natural
perches and mossy logs, that provided the birds with additional enrichment.
Almost as soon as the logs were placed in the aviary, the birds stripped off
the moss, as they searched for insects and other small invertebrates.
The laughingthrushes received an insectivorous mix consisting of a
universal and low iron softbill food, to which was added grated carrot, finely
diced apple, soaked raisins and, on alternative days, either grated hard-boiled
egg or grated cheddar cheese. In addition, a variety of diced fruit was offered
to them in the same dish, along with a daily ration of livefood in the form
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.498934" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259661" page_num="72" year="" vol="">
OWEN - BLACK-AND-WHITE LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996237" page_id="56259661"  page_num="72" year="" vol="">
72
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.956592652173913" page_id="56259661"  page_num="72" year="" vol="">
of mealworms, crickets and waxmoth larvae. Every other day the food was
dusted with Nutrobal multivitamin powder. For birds of their size, we find
that they eat a relatively small amount of food.
Reproduction
The first sign of nesting activity was observed on March 28th 2005,
when both birds were seen carrying nesting material. Within a few days,
in a small wicker basket placed about 1.5m (5ft) above the ground in the
aviary shelter, a nest was built exclusively of coconut fibres. One white egg
was seen in the nest on April 19th, followed over the next two days by two
more. Incubation started after the second egg was laid. Both birds shared
Andrew Owen
Two chicks on day of hatching with third egg pipping.
incubation duties, alternating throughout the day. The eggs were seldom
left unattended and these normally very vocal birds fell silent. After 13
days, they were offered increasing amounts of livefood, consisting of small,
white-skinned mealworms, waxmoth larvae and crickets. The first two
eggs hatched on May 4th, indicating a 15 day incubation period. The third
egg hatched a day later. The pair was seen taking several white-skinned
mealworms or waxmoth larvae at a time to the nest during this period, when
we kept disturbance to a minimum. On May 8th the male was very quiet
and subdued and, although he appeared unwell, it was decided to leave him
in the aviary and place the birds on a course of antibiotics, given in their
drinking water.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.438405" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259662" page_num="73" year="" vol="">
OWEN - BLACK-AND-WHITE LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.866948" page_id="56259662"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
73
</page>
<table confidence="0.3349035" page_id="56259662"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
Eight days old.
Andrew Owen
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.499123" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259663" page_num="74" year="" vol="">
OWEN - BLACK-AND-WHITE LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997912" page_id="56259663"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
74
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.996738024390244" page_id="56259663"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
After seven days it was clear that all was not well. On first arriving at
the aviary, the birds were unusually vocal and neither of them was brooding
the young; furthermore, the livefood provided was eaten by them, rather than
taken to the nest. A check revealed the three well-developed chicks were
dead. All appeared to have abnormally swollen stomachs. Post mortem
examinations revealed a possible unidentified bacterial infection. The male
was removed from the aviary and placed in our hospital facility, where he
made a full recovery.
After an introductory period in an adjoining aviary, a replacement male
was introduced to the female on May 18th and both birds appeared very
compatible. Although we were disheartened by the earlier loss of the chicks,
the new pair soon showed signs of nesting and by May 28th was incubating a
clutch of three eggs in the original nest in the aviary shelter. The incubation
and nesting behaviour followed the same pattern as before, however, on this
occasion the chicks were abandoned at about four or five days old. The
weather was warmer and post mortem examinations were not possible, as
the chicks' bodies had started to decompose*. They did though, once again,
all show signs of having very swollen stomachs.
We were concerned that perhaps indigestible food being fed to the chicks
by the parents was becoming compacted in their stomachs. In the past I have
found that the hard, almost plastic-like stomachs parts of large, commercially
produced waxmoth larvae, can occasionally become compacted in the
stomachs of small and often unhealthy chicks. We decided, therefore, that
if the birds nested again, we would not offer them commercially produced
waxmoth larvae, but only home-grown tiny larvae, along with other soft-
bodied insects, to see if this resolved the problem.
With Waddesdon Manor having possibly the only female in the UK, we
felt we could not afford to risk losing any more young, so also decided that
should there be a third nesting attempt, we would remove the chicks and
attempt to hand-rear them.
There was a third nesting attempt and, on June 19th, three more chicks
had hatched.
Hand-rearing
On June 22nd the three chicks were taken from the nest and placed in a
brooder set at 32*C (89.6*F). One chick weighed 14. lg, another 12.6g and
the smaller chick, which was probably a day younger, weighed 9.6g.
The hand-rearing food consisted of a mixture of 50% pinkie mice and
50% papaya, with an added pinch of Nutrobal multivitamin powder, pureed
to a runny consistency and fed using tweezers. It is a diet we have used with
much success hand-rearing other passerine chicks, including those of other
species of laughingthrush.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.499006" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259664" page_num="75" year="" vol="">
OWEN - BLACK-AND-WHITE LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995869" page_id="56259664"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
75
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999637414634146" page_id="56259664"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
The chicks were fed at two hourly intervals. The two larger chicks fed
well, but as the smaller chick was rather lethargic, the temperature was
increased to 34*C (93.2*F). The chick's condition improved initially, but
then deteriorated and it refused to feed over the next few hours and died
the following day.
The remaining two chicks were strong and fed vigorously for the next
two days, then the slightly smaller of the two began to regurgitate its food.
It was given a slightly runnier mixture of 70% papaya and 30% pinkie mice.
By mid-morning on June 24th, both chicks were refusing food and passing
only very small droppings, rather than the large faecal sacs they usually
produced, also both were developing very swollen abdomens.
Drastic measures were needed if the two chicks were to survive. Over the
following 24 hours, they were fed only pureed papaya, mixed with a small
quantity of olive oil and a dilution of Avipro-Plus probiotics, in an attempt
to flush out any compacted food.
By June 25th, one of the chicks had died, but the other appeared to be
thriving. It appeared to be very hungry and in an attempt to improve the
nutritional value of the food, without causing further compaction, a few
soaked T16 low iron softbill pellets were fed to the chick. These were very
soft and spongy and appeared digestible, as the chick continued to produce
large faeces.
The brooder temperature was reduced by 0.5*C a day and by day seven
small blueberries and cricket abdomens were added to the diet. Although
this diet was not ideal, the chick continued to develop well, with dark pin-
feathers erupting on its back and white pin-feathers protruding on its head.
As the chick grew, increasing amounts of insects in the form of more white-
skinned mealworms, crickets and small waxmoth larvae, were added to the
diet. The chick fledged from its nest pot at 15 days old. It was provided
initially with some sticks to perch on and was heard for the first time making
adult type chuckling calls. At 17 days old it was placed in a small fledging
cage, in which it remained for the next five days.
After a few days in the fledging cage, the young laughingthrush was
observed pecking at insects and bits of fruit. Following this it was moved
to a larger cage measuring approximately 1m long x 0.5m wide x 0.5m high
(3ft 3in long x 1 ft 8in wide x 1 ft 8in high). It was offered food from tweezers
only twice at day, at 7.00am and 7.00pm (07.00hrs and 19.00hrs). The young
laughingthrush was feeding itself by the time it was 25 days old. It was
taking mostly insects and also eating fruit and T1 6 softbill pellets, therefore,
we discontinued using tweezers to feed it. Once it was fully independent,
we removed the dividing wall, thereby doubling the size of the cage.
After two months, it was moved to an outdoor off-show aviary, which it
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.21999" page_id="56259665"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
OWEN - BLACK-AND-WHITE LAUGHINGTHRUSH
76
Andrew Owen
Adult Black-and-white Laughingthrush.
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.987391" page_id="56259665"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
shared with a number of hand-reared young Pekin Robins Leiothrix lutea and
Silver-eared Mesias L. argentauris. It settled down well with its new and
smaller cage mates and showed no sign of aggression. Some feathers were
removed and sent for DNA testing and revealed that it is another male.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.988844">
Table 2. Measurements of six eggs.
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.985971833333333" page_id="56259665"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
Clutch 1 - laid 25.09.06-27.09.06
28.7mm x 22.6mm 29.4mm x 22.6mm
29.0mm x 23.1mm
Clutch 2-laid 17.10.06-19.10.06
28.6mm x 22.8mm 28.7mm x 22.9mm
28.6mm x 22.9mm
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.990283666666667" page_id="56259665"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
During 2006 the breeding pair was moved to a different off-show aviary
and took some time to settle down again. After several eggs were laid from
perches and lost, the pair finally nested in August and three chicks were
hand-reared from hatching. Again problems occurred when the chicks were
three to four days old and the diet had to be modified. They were reared on
papaya, soaked T16 pellets and small soft-bodied insects. One died shortly
after fledging, but the remaining two survived and were DNA sexed and
found to be females. The pair attempted to nest again late in the year (in
October), but the eggs were abandoned before they were due to hatch.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.497561" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259666" page_num="77" year="" vol="">
OWEN - BLACK-AND-WHITE LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.989233" page_id="56259666"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
77
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.470388" genericHeader="conclusions" page_id="56259666" page_num="77" year="" vol="">
Conclusion
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999164142857143" page_id="56259666"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
While we were trying to set up our breeding birds at Waddesdon Manor,
I searched for other collections keeping this species and discovered that the
Paultons Park collection in Hampshire had two of these laughingthrushes.
Curator Geoff Masson had them DNA sexed and luckily they turned out to
be a pair. During 2006 Geoff moved the pair to a larger; quieter aviary, and
succeeded in hand-rearing a single bird - a female. Like us, Geoff found
that breeding this species is not without problems and, he too, lost chicks
while they were being reared by the parents, before deciding to hand-rear
the chick he was successful with.
Although, with only two breeding pairs the sample size is very small,
it appears that this species' breeding requirements or rearing diet may be
different to that of other laughingthrushes. There is a need for research
into why parent-reared chicks are being lost at an early age and why chicks
are proving so difficult to hand-rear, when those of other closely related
species are straightforward to hand-rear. It is hoped that we can perfect the
breeding requirements of this charismatic and rare species and, ideally, be
able to produce parent-reared young in the future.
There has been an exchange of birds between our two collections and
we are planning to establish additional pairs. We hope to be able to produce
enough birds to set up a viable captive breeding population, involving other
zoological collections.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.498626" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259667" page_num="78" year="" vol="">
OWEN - BLACK-AND-WHITE LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995362" page_id="56259667"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
78
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.901594666666667" page_id="56259667"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
Products mentioned in the text
Avipro-Plus soluble probiotic: Vetark Animal Health, PO. Box 60, Winchester, Hampshire
S023 9XN, UK.
Nutribird T16 low iron pellets: Versele-Laga NV, Kappellestraat 70, B-9800, Deinze,
Belgium.
Nutrobal multivitamin powder: Vetark Animal Health, PO. Box 60, Winchester, Hampshire
S023 9XN, UK.
Reference
Collar, N. J. 2006. A partial revision of the Asian babblers (Timiliidae). Forktail 22:85-112.
Andrew Owen is Senior Aviary Keeper at Waddesdon Manor Aviaries,
near Aylesbury, Buckinghamshire HP 18 OJH, UK. Email:Andrew. Owen@
nationaltrust. org. uk/Webs ite: www. waddesdon. org. uk
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.823691" page_id="56259667"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.769113" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259667" page_num="78" year="" vol="">
ENCOURAGING NEWS FROM CHINA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996545590909091" page_id="56259667"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
Following field work in Wuyuan during April-May 2008, Prof. He Fen-
qi was for the first time able to announce the presence there of over 200
Blue-crowned Laughingthrushes Dryonastes courtoisi , some 60 or so of
which were discovered at a previously unknown breeding site. He cannot
say with certainty that it is an entirely new site. During the previous two
years (2006 &amp; 2007), two colonies of laughingthrushes vanished from their
breeding sites. It seems quite possible that some of the birds had moved
from an abandoned site to the newly discovered site and may have already
been breeding there in 2006 and/or 2007, as one of the nests appeared to
have been built earlier than the other nests in the colony.
The recently discovered breeding site is by a large river in a rather large
village, with plenty of birds in and around it. There are small vegetable
gardens and fruit trees here and there in the village and the laughinghrushes
are often found feeding in gardens and in the fruit trees. It makes an
interesting scene, with these rare laughingthrushes being no more than
common garden birds and playing quite an active role in the local bird
community.
Following further taxonomic changes the Blue-crowned Laughingthrush
is now recognised as a separate monotypic species (i.e. a species with no
subspecies) in the genus Dryonastes (rather than Garrulax), along with the
Yellow-throated Laughingthrush D. galbanus, which is also recognised as
a monotypic species in the genus Dryonastes (rather than Garrulax).
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.3312005" page_id="56259668"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
THE MADAGASCAR BUTTONQUAIL Turnix nigricollis
by Fred Bamicoat
</figure>
<page confidence="0.998175" page_id="56259668"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
79
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.994811324324324" page_id="56259668"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
In the distant past * aviculturally speaking - Madagascar provided several
beautiful and unique species to grace the aviaries of bird enthusiasts in
Europe and elsewhere. Two that immediately come to mind are the Grey-
headed or Madagascar Lovebird Agapornis cana, so different from all the
other members of the genus Agapornis , and the spectacular Madagascar
Fody Foudia madagascariensis, a bird now firmly established in Australian
aviaries, where aviculturists continue to refer to it as the Madagascar Weaver.
Another unique and beautiful Madagascan species is the Madagascar
Partridge Margaroperdix Madagascarensis.
Because of Madagascar's relatively close proximity to us here in South
Africa, I suppose that over the years a few more of its wonderful birds have
been available to South African aviculturists than to those elsewhere In the
world. Such importations have nevertheless been few and far between.
Of the 14 species of buttonquail or hemipodes, the Madagascar or
Black-necked Turnix nigricollis , seems to be the most colourful As well as
having kept and bred the Little or Common Buttonquail T, sylvatica , which
is by far the most widely distributed and has a subspecies T. s. lepurana
which occurs widely in southern Africa, where it is usually referred to
as the Kurrichane Buttonquail, I have seen several others of the genus
Turnix in Australian aviaries. Only the coloration of the Black-breasted
species T. melanogaster can rival that of the Madagascar Buttonquail.
The accompanying photographs, especially that of the female Madagascar
Buttonquail, which is, as in all buttonquail or hemipodes, larger than the
male and has more spectacular coloration, give an idea of the striking beauty
of this species.
The Madagascar Buttonquail has seldom figured in aviculture. I think
one has to go back about a century in UK avicultural literature to find
any record of it, A very detailed account can be found in the Avicultural
Magazine for April 1905. Written by Dr A. G, Butler, it records not only its
probable first arrival in England, but also provides an English translation of
the writings of Dr Karl Russ on the far more extensive experience of keeping
this species in Germany during the 1890s. In the Avicultural Magazine
for December 1912 there is an account of the successful breeding of it in
Yorkshire by W. H. St Quintin. St Quintin was particularly interested in
gamebirds and highly successful at breeding an extraordinary diversity of
this type of bird. He attributed his success to the use of the light of a large
garden frame, as a way of keeping a piece of ground dry, where the male
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.960756" page_id="56259669"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
80
</page>
<table confidence="0.9051688" page_id="56259669"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
BARNICOAT - MADAGASCAR BUTTONQUAIL
Male Madagascar Buttonquail.
Eelco Meyjes
Eelco Meyjes
The female Madagascar Buttonquail is larger than the male and more boldly coloured.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.469235" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259670" page_num="81" year="" vol="">
BARNICOAT - MADAGASCAR BUTTONQUAIL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997934" page_id="56259670"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
81
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997932073170732" page_id="56259670"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
could keep the chicks together.
As Madagascar became a French possession, I imagine this particularly
striking buttonquail was probably first taken to France. Certainly sometime
before 1890 small consignments began to reach German dealers and it
continued to arrive in increasing numbers. By 1895, a consignment of no
fewer than 40 pairs was reported in Cologne. It seems to have proved quite
easy to breed, with success being attained by Hauth, Langheins, Behrens,
Kemper, Krohm and others, as recorded by Dr Russ.
Dr Butler temporarily housed three for W. R. Ogilvie-Grant, his colleague
at the British Museum (Natural History), who was lucky enough to obtain
them from the well respected naturalist and importer of birds, Joseph
Abrahams. Butler "became thoroughly enamoured of them and with the
deepest regret had to restore them after some weeks to their owner on
completion of their aviary."
The Madagascar Buttonquail did not figure in aviculture again for most
of the remainder of the twentieth century. In 1991, as I gazed longingly at
the superb coloured plate of this species in Paul A. Johnsgard's Bustards,
Hemipodes and Sandgrouse: Birds of Dry Places (Oxford University Press,
1991), I never imagined I would ever see a living specimen, let alone
possess and breed this species. However, amazing birds turn up sometimes
in aviculture and, in September 1999, a small consignment reached South
Africa and I was able to obtain a pair. A few months later a second pair
became available.
I first succeeded in rearing young in March 2000. On that occasion
three young were raised and I have subsequently bred another 18 in all. I
have been able to swap or buy a few others and have managed to reach the
third generation. Virtually everyone who obtained pairs from the two small
importations has found the Madagascar Buttonquail quite willing to go to
nest, with a good chance of the chicks being reared. They generally lay more
clutches of eggs than they will successfully incubate, and in order to rear
their chicks, need a regular supply of termites for at least the first week.
Being so rare in aviculture, the Madagascar Buttonquail would be an
ideal species to build up aviary-bred stocks of, but because the genetic pool
available in South Africa was so small from the start and the species is
vulnerable to losses, I doubt this will happen without further importations
of additional stock.
My own aviaries are far from ideal for breeding buttonquail. I think
they would respond more positively in aviaries specially designed to suit
their needs. Buttonquail or hemipodes are birds of dry places and probably
flourish best in entirely covered aviaries in which the sandy floor is kept
permanently dry. They need clumps of grass or even just a simple heap
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995013" page_id="56259671"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
82
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.774466" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259671" page_num="82" year="" vol="">
BARNICOAT - MADAGASCAR BUTTONQUAIL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998375707317073" page_id="56259671"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
of hay, into which they can retreat, and enjoy bare patches of dry sand in
which they can make hollows and dust themselves. Their aviaries should
be located in reasonably sheltered and warm sites, as chicks are never reared
when the ground is cold. I have only succeeded in our warmer months, viz.
December-March.
If their aviaries can be designed so that they can be fed from outside,
for example from a covered passageway adjoining their shelter, thereby
removing the necessity of having to enter their enclosure, so much the better.
We have all found that they remain extremely nervous and flighty, even when
aviary bred. They have the irritating habit of flying towards you, even into
your face, whenever you enter their aviary, and I have even had them escape
through the door as I was opening it. Their habit of flying straight towards
the perceived point of threat is probably an inborn defensive mechanism in
this group of birds, the opposite of escaping by retreating and hiding.
All the buttonquail or hemipodes are polyandrous, the larger and more
brightly coloured female mating with a number of the more insignificant
looking males and leaving each of them to incubate a clutch of eggs and
raise the chicks single-handed. However, with the two species I have bred,
the Common or Kurrichane and the Madagascar Buttonquail, I have always
found them able to manage well enough in single pairs in relatively small
aviaries, without having to remove the female.
My observations coincide with the reported observations of Hauth in
1905, that in effect, while the male is incubating, the female keeps guard
over the nesting area. As a rule the male at first leads, warms and feeds
the chicks entirely on his own, but I have the impression that quite soon
the female starts sharing the responsibility of looking after the chicks to a
greater extent with T. nigricollis than with T. s. lepurana.
Madagascar Buttonquail seem enthusiastic nest builders. Mine have
always made fairly well-woven, over-arched nests, quite deep in a pile of
hay and usually accessed through a short tunnel. There is always a neatly
rounded saucer-shaped hollow for the eggs. Both birds participate in the nest
building, with the female playing the greater role, I think. In my experience
the clutch of eggs can number between three and five. However, unless the
birds are fully satisfied with the conditions, they will not begin to incubate
them.
The chicks cannot at first pick up food from the ground; the male needs to
hold a termite or other morsel of food in his beak and call them to come and
take it. Otherwise they just perish. I have found a supply of termites to be
necessary for stimulating this process. The chicks, however, are precocious
and quite soon begin to pick up some of their food for themselves. Their
development is surprisingly rapid, especially the development of the wings.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.469187" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259672" page_num="83" year="" vol="">
BARNICOAT - MADAGASCAR BUTTONQUAIL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998763" page_id="56259672"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
83
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997191666666667" page_id="56259672"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
I have found it fascinating to see them flying around like big bumblebees
high in the aviary, when startled by me entering the aviary with food, They
are fully capable of flight at about 10 days.
Feeding these birds is quite easy. They are perfectly capable of existing
on only the usual small seeds, but it is advisable to also supply gamebird
starter crumbs or something similar. I provide a dry insectile mixture
and think that they also benefit from a small, daily supply of soaked and
sprouted seeds, with a little slightly moistened rearing food of the type used
for canary rearing. Breeding activity is certainly stimulated by a regular
supply of livefood, but this is not essential throughout the year. Termites
are particularly attractive to them, but mealworms and/or maggots could
be used.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.964529" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56259672" page_num="83" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.860525333333333">
Butler, A. G. 1905. On breeding Turnix nigrieollis in German bird-rooms. Avicultural Magazine
(New Series) Vol.ffl, 6:195-203.
Johnsgard, P. A. 1991. Bustards, Hemipodes, and Sandgrouse: birds of dry places. Oxford
University Press, Oxford, New York, Tokyo.
St Quintin, W. H. 1912. Breeding notes for 1912. Avicultural Magazine (Third Series) Vol.
IV, 2:54-55.
</reference>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.414257">
Avicultural Society Vice President Fred Barnicoat lives in South Africa.
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.743646" page_id="56259672"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
He has an almost complete set of Avicultural Magazines and an encyclopedic
knowledge of the history of the society.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.578449" page_id="56259672"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
* *
*
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.841711" genericHeader="introduction" page_id="56259672" page_num="83" year="" vol="">
THIRTY-THIRD AGM AND UK CONVENTION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.842971363636364" page_id="56259672"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
The 33rd World Pheasant Association AGM and UK Convention will
be held from Friday, October lOth-Sunday, October 12th 2008 at St John
the Evangelist Church, Hills Road, Cambridge CB2 8RN. The speakers will
include Iain Grahame and Francois Bemar, who will talk about keeping
and breeding the Blood Pheasant Ithaginis cruentus in the 1970s and 2000s
and, John Sherlock, who will talk about Sudeley Castle&apos;s pheasants - past
and present. There will be a visit to a new zoo being developed and due to
open shortly at Cromer, Norfolk. It will be ran by the owners of Thrigby
Hall Wildlife Gardens and the Director will be Jim Irwin-Bavis, formerly
Curator at Harewood Bird Gardens in Yorkshire. There will also be a visit
to Pensthorpe Nature Reserve and Gardens.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996597" page_id="56259673"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
84
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.833473666666667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259673" page_num="84" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE BARE FACED CURASSOW Craxfasciolata
AT EXMOOR ZOO
by Derek Gibson
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97337375" page_id="56259673"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
Exmoor Zoo has had its current pair of Bare-faced Curassows Crax
fasciolata since 2003, when a female was acquired to pair with our male
that had been obtained from Beale Park in 2002. Both birds saw out 2003
and the beginning of2004 in harmony together in an aviary measuring 6m x
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.6568485">
3m x 6m (approx. 20ft x 1 Oft x 20ft). On September 30th 2004 the first egg
was laid on a pile of twigs and leaves, that could loosely be described as a
nest. It was about 3m (1 Oft) above the ground in a wooden box measuring
1m x lm (approx. 3ft 3in x 3ft 3in). The egg was incubated by the female
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.989671821428571" page_id="56259673"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
and after a period of 32 days, a chick could be seen putting its head over the
side of the box. Unfortunately, the following morning the chick was found
dead on the floor. We are not sure what went wrong, but put it down to
the parents' lack of experience and hoped that next time a more successful
outcome would ensue. No further breeding activity was recorded during
the remainder of 2004.
During the early months of 2005, there was a lot of activity: the male's
low-pitched booming; food being passed from the male to the female; the
choosing of titbits for food passing (in nearly all instances mealworms); and
the female making a nest from willow twigs and straw. While nest building
was in progress, the male perched close by, seemingly standing guard, but
unwilling to help construct the nest. Both birds exhibited the head-flicking
motion that all curassows seem to exhibit from an early age.
On June 12th 2005, the female was observed to be spending more and
more time in and around the nesting area and, on June 6th 2005, was noted
to be looking noticeably heavy. The male was spending a considerable
amount of time following her every move. An egg was laid on June 28th
2005. The decision was taken to remove the egg and replace it with a dummy
egg. No further egg was laid and the artificially incubated egg was found to
be clear. A further egg was laid on July 24th 2005, that was removed and
placed in an incubator. A dummy egg was left in the nest. A second egg
was laid three days later. It was laid from a perch and hit the only hard piece
of wood on the aviary floor. Again the first egg proved to be infertile. On
July 29th 2005 it was noticed that the female was limping on her left leg.
A closer inspection revealed no obvious injury, but it did seem to bring the
2005 season to an abrupt end.
Throughout the early months of 2006, booming and food passing again
occurred and finally, on May 15th 2006, mating was observed. An egg was
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.503768" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259674" page_num="85" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - BARE-FACED CURASSOW
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99643" page_id="56259674"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
85
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.996461" page_id="56259674"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
laid on May 27th 2006 and was transferred to an incubator. This egg proved
to be fertile and the chick hatched from it was successfully hand-reared by the
bird staff. A further egg was laid on August 17th 2006. It was removed for
artificial incubation and the chick hatched from it was reared successfully.
On December 20th 2006 the birds were moved to another aviary so that
we could accommodate a pair of Pied Crows Corvus albus. The aviary they
were moved to is much larger, it measures 6m x 6m x 8m (approx. 20ft x
20ft x 26ft), and has a small stream with running water and leylandii conifers
planted to provide cover. Half of the aviary is grassed and the other half
is covered with bark chips. The grass is left to grow and set seed and the
curassows seem to enjoy searching for whatever insects they can find. A
nest basket is provided at floor level, hidden from view by a conifer, but
they have made no attempt to use it.
The female was noted to look heavy on May 6th 2007 and an egg was
laid on May 9th 2007. A further egg was laid on May 11 th 2007. Both eggs
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.993727" page_id="56259675"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
86
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.880673" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259675" page_num="86" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - BARE-FACED CURASSOW
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.954332" page_id="56259675"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
were removed and proved to be fertile. Both were hatched in an incubator
and the chicks were successfully hand-reared.
Adult management
The adults are wormed with Panacur 10% solution twice a year on
March 1st and October 1st. A faecal sample is taken in February. To date,
no worms or eggs have been found in the samples. The female still tends
to limp occasionally. The curassows seem to be relatively hardy and no
heating is provided for them through our rather long winters. As long as
they have a snug shelter, they seem more than capable of toughing out the
most inclement weather.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.532949083333333" page_id="56259675"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
Adult diet
Maintenance diet fed to adults November Ist-February 13th.
8.30am feed
50g Seasonal fruits (cut into 1cm cubes)
1 Slice of brown bread (crumbled)
4 2cm Balls of minced (ground) meat
lOOg Waterfowl maintenance pellets
20-30 Soaked Zoo A pellets
1 Og Insectivorous mix
4.00pm feed
15-20 Mealworms (scattered)
200g Oystershell grit is added to the food once a month
Breeding diet fed to adults February 14th-October 31st.
8.30am feed
50g Seasonal fruits (cut into 1cm cubes)
1 Slice of brown bread (crumbled)
6 2cm Balls of minced (ground) meat
1 OOg Waterfowl maintenance pellets
20-30 Soaked Zoo A pellets
20g Insectivorous mix
4.00pm Feed
15-20 Mealworms (scattered)
2-4 Locusts
5-10 Waxmoth larvae
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.503119" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259676" page_num="87" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - BARE-FACED CURASSOW
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995488" page_id="56259676"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
87
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.496228">
Egg management
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.973428153846154" page_id="56259676"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
The eggs were incubated in Brinsea Octagon Pro 20 incubators at a
temperature of 37.4*C/37.6*C (99.3*F/99.7*F) with relative humidity of
about 55%. Upon external pip the eggs are transferred to a hatcher, with
greatly increased humidity to prevent the membranes from drying.
Chick management
Once the chick has hatched, it is first weighed, then transferred to a
Brinsea Octagon TLC-4 brooder, in which it remains for 24 hours. No food
is offered during this time in order to allow the yolk sac to be fully absorbed.
Only water is available in a small dish with pebbles on the bottom to prevent
drowning. The chick is later transferred to a rearing pen, heated from above
at one end to a temperature of 31*C (87.8*F). The heat is decreased by 1*C
each day until only background heat is available.
Chicks are fed the following diet:
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.73519275" page_id="56259676"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
Chick crumbs
Insectivorous food
Soaked Zoo A pellets
Fruit cut into 0.5cm cubes
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.9907176" page_id="56259676"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
Waxmoth larvae are offered, also crickets, locusts and mealworms, but
although livefood is available at all times, it is very rarely taken. Food
is offered from tweezers for the first two days. A dish of fresh water is
always available. A perch is provided from day five and is used almost
immediately.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.986106053097345" page_id="56259677"  page_num="88" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - BARE-FACED CURASSOW
Hand-rearing
record - Chick No.l.
Date
Observations
Weight
26.06.06
Given silky bantam chick for company.
116g
27.06.06
Observed drinking.
107g
28.06.06
108g
29.06.06
110g
30.06.06
Eating food from food pot.
116g
01.07.06
119g
02.07.06
124g
03.07.06
127g
04.07.06
Perching.
135g
05.07.06
139g
06.07.06
Middle toe measures 26.61mm.
143g
07.07.06
Feeding from hand.
148g
08.07.06
154g
09.07.06
Bird very nervous.
163g
10.07.06
174g
11.07.06
IBlg
12.07.06
193g
13.07.06
21 Ig
14.07.06
Silkie removed because of bullying
by curassow.
229g
15.07.06
236g
16.07.06
240g
17.07.06
246g
Data collected at 8.00am.
Hand-rearing record - Chick No.2.
Date
Observations
Weight
17.08.06
Given guineafowl for company.
118g
18.08.06
Observed drinking,
lllg
19.08.06
113g
20.08.06
119g
21.08.06
126g
22.08.06
Follows guineafowl everywhere.
130g
23.08.06
Perching.
137g
24.08.06
139g
25.08.06
144g
26.08.06
150g
27.08.06
157g
28.08.06
165g
29.08.06
Tarsus measures 29.77mm.
171 g
30.08.06
174g
31.08.06
180g
01.09.06
187g
02.09.06
193g
03.09.06
200g
04.09.06
209g
05.09.06
Beak measures 21.12mm.
22 lg
06.09.06
238g
Data collected at 8.00am.
</figure>
<figure confidence="0.971654123966942" page_id="56259678"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - BARE-FACED CURASSOW
89
Hand-rearing record - Chick No.3.
Date
Observations
Weight
09.06.07
Placed in dryer (10.00am).
120g
10.06.07
Transferred to rearing pen.
108g
11.06.07
Fed six waxmoth larvae by hand.
112g
12.06.07
Joined by sibling. No problems.
114g
13.06.07
Head-flicking.
117g
14.06.07
Provided with a perch.
122g
15.06.07
Beak 17.26mm.
126g
16.06.07
Visually sexed as probable male.
13 lg
17.06.07
Tarsus 29.78mm.
134g
18.06.07
140g
19.06.07
Bird nervous.
144g
20.06.07
155g
21.06.07
160g
22.06.07
169g
23.06.07
176g
24.06.07
Turned away when offered food.
180g
25.06.07
188g
26.06.07
199g
27.06.07
207g
28.06.07
A small crest was observed.
220g
29.06.07
229g
30.06.07
236g
01.07.07
243g
Data collected 7.15am-8.00am unless otherwise stated.
Hand-rearing
record - Chick No.4.
Date
Observations
Weight
11.06.07
Placed in brooder (8.45am).
119g
12.06.07
Placed in brooder with sibling.
105g
13.06.07
107g
14.06.07
Observed drinking and head-flicking.
HOg
15.06.07
117g
16.06.07
Probably a female.
123g
17.06.07
Perching.
128g
18.06.07
Feeding from hand.
130g
19.06.07
138g
20.06.07
144g
21.06.07
149g
22.06.07
156g
23.06.07
164g
24.06.07
168g
25.06.07
Beak 15.94mm, tarsus 29.50mm.
176g
26.06.07
186g
27.06.07
194g
28.06.07
201g
29.06.07
Crest noticed.
210g
30.06.07
225g
01.07.07
237g
Data collected 7.30am-8.00am unless otherwise stated.
</figure>
<page confidence="0.987386" page_id="56259679"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
90
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.781799" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259679" page_num="90" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
INTERNATIONAL ZOO YEARBOOK
VOLUME 41 &amp; VOLUME 42
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9548676875" page_id="56259679"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
The International Zoo Yearbook Vol.41 (2007) &amp; Vol.42 (2008) are
rather low on avicultural content. The special subject or main theme of
Vol.41 is animal health and conservation. The articles likely to be of
greatest interest to aviculturists are those on West Nile virus and avian
influenza H5N1, both of which can infect wild and captive birds (and
humans). From 1999-2005, West Nile virus had been isolated from over
284 dead bird species. In areas of North America, mortality approached
100% in American Crows Corvus brachyrhynchos and Loggerhead Shrikes
Lanius ludovicianus migrans. Raptors were also thought to be extremely
susceptible. H5N1 had, at the time the paper was written, been reported in
over 30 wild bird species and a similar number of captive bird species. The
majority of those infected, both wild and captive, had been ducks, geese and
swans. Others on the list of captive species infected (Table 2), include the
Greater Flamingo Phoenicopterus ruber , Hill Mynah Gracula religiosa,
Black-naped Oriole Oriolus chinensis and Red-billed Leiothrix or Pekin
Robin Leiothrix lutea (though somewhat confusingly in the text the author
refers to "Mesias Leiothrix sp.").
The second section of Vol.41, the zoo section, includes an account of
the first three years of the Masoala Rainforest ecosystem at Zurich Zoo.
Opened to the public in 2003, it is a 120m x 90m x 30m high (approx. 395ft
x 295ft x 98ft high) greenhouse-type structure, featuring plants and animals
of Madagascar's Masoala National Park. The exhibit aims to raise awareness
of the threatened biodiversity in rainforests and, through visitor donations
and a percentage of the takings of the shop and restaurant, generates more
than US$100,000 or #50,000 per annum towards the costs of running the
Masoala National Park which, in 2006, amounted to 25% of its annual
budget. It also promotes tourism to this, so far, not widely known national
park on the east coast of Madagascar.
In November 2006, when the account was written, the Masoala
Rainforest ecosystem housed 478 plant, six mammal, 22 bird, seven reptile,
two amphibian, three fish and more than 50 invertebrate species. The
22 species of birds included the Madagascar Partridge Margaroperdix
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.9904334">
madagascarensis, Madagascar Turtle Dove Streptopelia picturata , Lesser
Vasa Parrot Coracopsis nigra , Crested Coua Coua cristata, Red-fronted
Coua C. reynaudii, Madagascar Magpie Robin Copsychus albospecularis
and Madagascar Fody Foudia madagascariensis. The first parent-reared
Madagascar Crested Ibis Lophotibis cristata outside of Madagascar was
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909782" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259680" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996305" page_id="56259680"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
91
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9906225" page_id="56259680"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
raised there in 2004 and the first captive breeding of the Pitta-like Ground-
Roller Atelornis pittoides was recorded in 2006.
Vo1.42 (2008) has even less avicultural content than Vo1.41 (2007). The
main theme is amphibian conservation and the first 19 articles (pp.1-171)
are amphibian related. To find any avicultural content one has to turn to
the reference section. Listed there are the officially endorsed international
studbooks for species such as the Homed Guan Oreophasis derbianus,
Vietnamese Pheasant Lophura hatinhensis , Spix's Macaw Cyanopsitta
spixii , Blue-throated Macaw Ara glaucogularis , Maroon-fronted Parrot
Rhynchopsitta terrisi , Lesser Bird of Paradise Paradisaea minor and Red
Bird of Paradise P. rubra. Most data covers the period only up until the
end of December 2006. The reader can leam, for example, that in 2006, 10
Spix's Macaws were hatched and brought the total in the studbook (which
has a new keeper, Ryan Watson of A1 Wabra) up to 74. There were 69.63.16
Blue -throated Macaws and 22.22.12 Maroon-fronted Parrots, the latter all
in five institutions in Mexico.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.706239166666667" page_id="56259680"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
The International Zoo Yearbook Vol.41 was published on behalf of
the Zoological Society of London (ZSL) by Blackwell Publishing Ltd.,
Vol.42 is published on its behalf by Wiley-Blackwell Ltd., 9600 Garsington
Road, Oxford 0X4 2DQ, UK. Visitwww.blackwellpublishing.com/izy for
prices.
Malcolm Ellis
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.898342" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259680" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
PARROTS OF AFRICA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99936394117647" page_id="56259680"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
The avicultural literature relating to African parrots includes a couple of
publications (paperbacks) on the genus Poicephalus and, of course, many
titles on the Grey Parrot. The Parrots of Africa (in English) by German
author Dr Stefan Luft covers very different ground to the avicultural titles,
thereby filling a gaping hole in the literature.
Its basis is science not birdkeeping. The first chapter is a general
introduction covering phylogeny (including the lovebirds), the design of
African parrots, flight silhouettes and language use, and a table that extends
over six pages of lengths (overall, tail, tarsus, etc.) of all species and
subspecies. This could be of assistance in identifying some subspecies. The
second chapter covers research and conservation and such problems as how
to translate conservation research into practical action. An interesting map
shows the rate of deforestation in Africa per year. The damage caused by the
capture of wild African parrots for the pet trade is discussed and the different
stakeholders in the trade in Grey Parrots in Cameroon is explained in detail
(government, licensed dealers, middlemen, trappers and local people who
take part by, for example, transporting the parrots). There is a short and
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995869" page_id="56259681"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
92
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.971572" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259681" page_num="92" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987149304347826" page_id="56259681"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
largely theoretical discussion on captive breeding (studbooks, population
management, software, etc.).
Chapter 3 describes the types of habitats in which African parrots are
found and the following chapter focuses on non-breeding biology and
behaviour, including feeding, communication and roosting. The chapter on
feeding ecology includes information on diet and the following description
of drinking: "African parrots ladle water with the tip of the tongue, which
is then pressed into the palate to move the water back."
The chapter on breeding biology concludes the first part of the book
which covers 105 pages, with the following 40 pages devoted to the species
accounts, starting with the lovebirds. For each species there is a description
of plumage, subspecies, voice, range, habitat and status, general habits and
reproduction, plus a distribution map. This information is fairly brief, that
for the Senegal Parrot, for example, covers one and a half pages, including a
half-page map. Chapter 8(13 pages) is about keeping and breeding African
parrots. Twenty pages of small type, list the references cited. This section
is of enormous value to the serious student of African and other parrots.
There are some helpful line drawings but no photographs. The book
would perhaps have benefited from colour illustrations of the various
species, apart from the three shown on the front cover and the one on the
back cover. Nevertheless, overall the book contains a great deal of valuable
information.
Parrots of Africa is available from Dr Stefan Luft, Pistoriusstrasse 85,
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.620457">
13086 Berlin, Germany. Price [euro]17.00 or US$24.99. Postage is an extra
[euro]6.00, or, it can, apparently, be purchased post-free from Amazon.co.uk.
Any other enquries should be addressed to:stefan_luft@yahoo.com
Rosemary Low
</footnote>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.759185" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259681" page_num="92" year="" vol="">
WHERE TO WATCH BIRDS IN WALES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999670090909091" page_id="56259681"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
When asked to review a book, my first thought is, "Where do I start?"
"At the beginning" is not necessarily the right answer because you do not
review a book in the same way as you read it.
With a reference book it can be quite difficult - and this one covers an
entire country in a localised way. So, for instance, if you live in Glamorgan,
you might not be too fussed about the best birdwatching places Denbighshire,
but then, on the other hand, you might be going there on holiday and not want
to waste precious holiday time on fruitless searches. This is exactly where
this book kicks in - as a guide to key birdwatching haunts in Wales, it has
stood the test of time (this is the fourth edition, fully revised and updated,
with 40 new sites added) and is a masterful summation. That is not to say
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909761" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259682" page_num="93" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99734" page_id="56259682"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
93
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.993120552631579" page_id="56259682"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
it is faultless, to be able to say that with certainty you would need to know
the whole of Wales intimately. Not having had that pleasure, I looked at the
regions and birds I know best, then cross-referenced the two.
I was brought up in North Wales (Flintshire) and later did field work
on the Chough in West Wales in Pembrokeshire and Ceredigion. So it was
the Chough that I checked out first, then some of those species I used to see
whilst Choughs decided to be somewhere different from where I thought they
ought to be! The first snag I hit in the index is a common one. You look
up an entry only to be confronted with a whole series of page numbers - or
in this case site numbers - which convey no idea as to which are principal
references and which are merely 'honorary' mentions. In the case of the
Chough, which is not a common bird, there are 22 site references to follow
up; some of these, but not all, are important for the species. To enable faster
location of key sites, would it not have been simple to have put the more
important ones in bold type?
You have to search through 47 sites if you want to find the best places
to see a winter visiting Fieldfare, 51 for the Merlin and 28 for the Ring
Ouzel. If commoner species were treated in the same way it would be
ludicrous. There is an obvious weighting in favour of rarer birds. A process
of selection has gone on which might have been handled better: perhaps
excluding the 'everyday birds' from the main index while of course leaving
their references, where appropriate, in the site descriptions. The index could
then concentrate on the rarer or more 'distinctive species,' with their prime
sites identified.
A general map in the prelims locates each site by number, making it easy
to go quickly to a locality of choice. Each site description has a location
map and a good description of the habitat with principal species noted. This
includes taxa other than birds. Additional information on the best times
to visit, access, parking, etc. is very useful. One map I particularly like is
for site 51 - the Horseshoe Pass and World's End in Denbighshire, which
actually marks on the map where Black Grouse lek and where you can see
or hear Wood Warblers, Crossbills, Dippers and Ring Ouzels.
Numerous beautiful line drawings of noteworthy species decorate the
pages of this altogether beautifully produced book.
Where to watch birds in Wales by David Saunders and Jon Green, 352
pages, paperback, with many maps by Brian Southern and line drawings by
various artists, is published by Christopher Helm, an imprint of A&amp;C Black
(website:www.acblack.com). Price #16.99.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.178053">
Dr Richard Meyer
</subsectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99826" page_id="56259683"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
94
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9820465" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259683" page_num="94" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
BARBETS BRED FOR THE FIRST TIME
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.975808818181818" page_id="56259683"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
Two Brown-breasted Barbets Lybius melanopterus have been bred at
Waddesdon Manor aviaries, near Aylesbury, Bucks., here in the UK. The
first young barbet left the nest on June 21 st, followed the next day by the
second. Both were well developed and only slightly smaller than their
parents (which measure about 19cm (7V#in) in length), with orange faces,
rather than the bright red head of the adults.
It is believed to be the first time that this barbet, found on the eastern
side of Africa, from southern Somalia southwards to Malawi and northern
Mozambique, has been bred in the UK. Colin Scott, who recorded an
incubation period of 16 days, unfortunately failed in his attempt to hand-rear
a chick hatched by his pair of Brown-breasted Barbets.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.648456" page_id="56259683"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.559367" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259683" page_num="94" year="" vol="">
HONEYEATERS RELEASED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.883539" page_id="56259683"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
Thanks to the efforts of seven Australian zoos which participate in
the Australasian Regional Association of Zoological Parks and Aquaria
(ARAZPA) Captive Management Program for the threatened Regent
Honeyeater Xanthomyza phrygia, 28 of these honeyeaters were bred for
release into the wild earlier this year. Following quarantine at Taronga
Zoo, during which the birds were housed in a flock and accustomed to
feeding on native blossoms, they were transported to Victoria for release.
Once common there in box-ironbark woodlands, their numbers suffered a
serious decline due to widespread habitat loss and changes brought about
by activities such as gold mining and agriculture.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.656456" page_id="56259683"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.977242" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259683" page_num="94" year="" vol="">
AFRICAN PARROT STUDY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997902166666667" page_id="56259683"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
Meyer's or the Brown Parrot Poicephalus meyeri is the most widely
distributed of the African parrots, being found from Sudan to South Africa.
Despite this, it has never been studied and next to nothing is known about
its habits in the wild, hence the need for the Meyer's Parrot Project.
In Wingspan Vol.18, No.2, pp.40-43, June 2008, Steve Boyes a PhD
zoology student at the University of KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa, describes
early findings of the study of this parrot in an area of pristine wilderness in
the Okavango Delta in Botswana, southern Africa.
Of over 530 bird species that occur there, it is the only parrot. Ninety
percent of breeding occurs during March-April. It waits for Burchell's
Starling Lamprotornis australis to finish breeding before it commences
nesting, thereby avoiding competition with this larger, aggressive, cavity-
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.947875" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259684" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp;VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994161" page_id="56259684"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
95
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.988891454545454" page_id="56259684"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
nesting species. The parrot's breeding appears to be synchonised with
the period when its main food sources - the Manila fruit Sclerocarya
birrea, Terminalia sericea pods, Bushwillow pods Combretum hereonse
and Mopane pods Colophospermum mopane - are heavily infested with
insect larvae (grubs), that are thought to form a significant part of the diet
during breeding.
A Large-spotted Genet Genetta tigrina managed to enter one pair's nest
hole and ate the female and a chick, followed by two unhatched eggs. The
parrots showed interest in only eight of the 105 nest boxes that were put
up, and the boxes were eventually taken over by barbets, woodpeckers, tits
and hombills.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.1741886" page_id="56259684"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
The Meyer's Parrot Project is supported by the School of Biological and
Conservation Sciences, University of KwaZulu-Natal, British Ecological
Society, Cape Parrot Working Group and the World Parrot Trust, whose
magazine Psittascene (February 2008, pp.6-10) also included an account
of the study and several photographs.
Volunteers are required for 2009 and donations are invited. Further
information is available from Steve Boyes, Research Centre for African
Parrot Conservation, University of KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa. E-mail:
boyes@africaskyblue.org
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.662503" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259684" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
OTHER LONG-LIVED STARLINGS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993629105263158" page_id="56259684"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
In a note about a visit to London Zoo in June 1943 (Avicultural Magazine
Fifth Series, Vol. 111, No.4, p. 112 (July-August 1943)), Dr Emilius
Hopkinson wrote that he looked up, as usual, the two Amethyst (or Violet-
backed) Starlings Cinnyricinclus leucogaster , which he had brought to the
zoo many years previously from The Gambia, West Africa. One, a female,
had arrived at the zoo in 1922, the other, a male, had arrived in 1928, so they
had lived there for 21 years and 15 years respectively in perfect health and
plumage, though he added, perhaps the female was beginning to look a little
"passe". In the following issue (No.5, p. 129 (September-October 1943)),
David Seth-Smith wrote that the female was believed to be the first of her
kind to have arrived in the UK. Since the early days of the war, there had been
no fruit available to feed the birds in the Bird House. The birds of paradise
had succumbed, but the toucans, turacos and five species of hombills had
not only survived but were in "first rate condition" - presumably being fed
mainly on boiled carrots and boiled potatoes. During the Blitz in 1941, part
of the roof of the Bird House was demolished by an incendiary bomb. As a
result of this, the last of the hummingbirds had escaped through a hole made
in the aviary netting and the heating system had been put out of action for
two weeks during cold weather.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995259" page_id="56259685"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
96
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9806045" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259685" page_num="96" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
HORNBILL CONFERENCE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.980614" page_id="56259685"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
The 5th International Hombill Conference will take place from March
22nd-March 25th 2009 at Singapore Botanic Gardens. The theme of the
conference, sponsored by the National Parks Board, Singapore and Hombill
Research Foundation, will be - Hombills and the Challenges of the Future.
There will be sessions on: Behaviour and Ecology; Research Techniques;
Local, Regional and Global Threats to Hombills; In Situ Conservation
Strategies and Habitat Restoration; Outreach, Education and Community-
based Conservation; and Ex Situ Conservation and the Future of Hombills.
Keynote speakers will be Prof. Dr Pilai Poonswad and Dr Alan Kemp.
The conference will be followed by visits to the hombill breeding research
projects at Jurong Bird Park and the related wild site in Singapore, along
with field trips to view wild hombills in Borneo.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.763262" page_id="56259685"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.804335" genericHeader="method" page_id="56259685" page_num="96" year="" vol="">
NEWS FROM LORO PARQUE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997467347826087" page_id="56259685"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
Earlier this year a Lear's Macaw Anodorhynchus leari was hand-reared.
It developed magnificently and on day 41 weighed almost 718g. After a
break of several years, three (Lichtenstein's Noble or) Red-shouldered
Macaws Diopsittaca nobilis cumanensis had hatched and were being reared
in the 'baby station. ' A second clutch of eggs laid by the St Vincent Amazons
Amazona guildingii , like the first, proved to be infertile. An egg from a
pair of Orange-winged Amazons A. amazonica was added to the clutch and
was hatched by the St Vincent Amazons, which reared the chick without
difficulty.
A group of five young Chilean Burrowing Parrots Cyanoliseus patagonus
bloxami, three males and two females, were placed in a communal aviary
containing four nest holes. Both females were hand-reared at the Loro
Parque Breeding Centre and the males were bred two years ago at another
bird park. Already they had hatched three chicks that were growing well
and about to become independent.
In May, Loro Parque Fundacion biologist Rafael Zamora undertook an
extensive search on Gran Canaria (one of the Canary Islands), in an attempt to
establish whether the Blue Chaffinch Fringilla teydeapolatzeki had survived
last year's disasterous forest fires that had destroyed much of its habitat.
He was able to report that a small population of this endemic subspecies
appeared to have survived the disaster and, Rafael and his colleagues,
managed to find some nests. It is hoped that the population will slowly build
up again and help ensure the long-term survival of this subspecies.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.994823" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259686" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTINENTAL INFLUENCE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994136863636364" page_id="56259686"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Two possible UK first breedings, that of the American Goldfinch
Carduelis tristis and the Grey-capped Social Weaver Pseudonigrita arnaudi ,
were reported in Cage &amp; Aviary Birds July 31st 2008, p.3 &amp; pp. 14-15.
Stephen Abbott was unsuccessful in his attempts to breed the American
Goldfinch until he visited Germany, where he found another two pairs and
talked to aviculturists there who have successfully bred this species. Having
observed their methods and copied them back here in the UK, he succeeded
in breeding three young and is hopeful of further success.
John Robinson, who bred a total of five Grey-capped Social Weavers in
2007, put his eventual success down to the inclusion in the diet of the home-
made eggfood mixture recommended by Belgian breeder Paul de Nil. Both
sexes incubated the eggs, which hatched after 14 days. The young left the
nest after about 20 days. John, who has also bred the Black-capped Social
Weaver P. cabanisi, believes that rather than trying to breed them in a colony,
it is best to keep just one pair per aviary, so that the breeding pair does not
have to compete for livefood with the other birds in the colony.
In the absence of any previously published record of the American
Goldfinch having been bred in the UK, it appeared to be the first UK breeding
of the species. However, a few weeks later in the letters pages (August 14th
2008, p.7), Peter German wrote to say that several of these birds were bred
by different breeders in the 1970s. Apparently, no account was published,
hence no previous breeding record existed.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.859606" page_id="56259686"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.688629" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56259686" page_num="" year="" vol="">
BREEDING INITIATIVE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9808944" page_id="56259686"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Having recently obtained three pairs of Black Crakes Amaurornis
(formerly Limnocorax ) flavirostris, a species absent from the collection
since the 1970s, Walsrode Birdpark in Germany has set up an initiative
with Copenhagen Zoo and Antwerp Zoo, in an effort to establish several
unrelated pairs and develop a long-term captive breeding plan for this
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.590111125" page_id="56259686"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
attractive African crake.
* * *
SEED-EATING PIGEONS AND DOVES
Philip Schofield has volunteered to act as the contact for a Special
Interest Group devoted to seed-eating pigeons and doves. He hopes shortly
to have an operational e-mail address, but in the meantime can be contacted
- Tel:01305 264361 - if you are interested in participating in this group.
Rosemary Wiseman - e-mail:ro.wiseman@virgin.net - will continue to be
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.666373" page_id="56259686"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
the contact for fruit doves, ground doves and bleeding-hearts.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.808189" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56259687" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.95871755" page_id="56259687"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
. SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION LIBRARIES
3 9088 01463 1501
Notes on the IV International Symposium on Breeding Birds in
Captivity
by Josef Lindholm.49
The nesting behaviour of the Musophagidae - Part 2
by Myles Lamont...63
Breeding the Black-and-white Laughingthrush Garrulax bicolor
by Andrew Owen.70
The Madagascar Buttonquail Turnix nigricollis
by Fred Bamicoat. 79
Breeding the Bare-faced Curassow Crax fasciolata at Exmoor Zoo
by Derek Gibson.84
Book Reviews
International Zoo Yearbook Volume 41 &amp; Volume 42.90
Parrots of Africa.91
Where to Watch Birds in Wales.92
News &amp; Views .94
Published by the Avicultural Society , England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</table>
</algorithms>
