<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.7373446" page_id="56264459"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 112
No. 3
2006
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264460" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990837" page_id="56264460"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2006 as for 2005: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.5855" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264460" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.972357" page_id="56264460"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, ARCADIA, THE MOUNTS, TOTNES, DEVON TQ9 7QJ, UK.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TNI3 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail: Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998476" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264460" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982477333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7999255" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264461" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.292167" page_id="56264461"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 112 - No. 3 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2006
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.972598" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264461" page_num="" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE BLACK-FACED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.968497870967742" page_id="56264461"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Garrulax affinis
by Nigel Hewston
The Black-faced Laughingthrush is one of many of its congeners with a
wide distribution in the Himalayas, ranging from Nepal through Myanmar
to western China and Taiwan. Birds present in the UK are of Chinese origin.
Rutgers (1969) stated that it is found at higher altitudes than other
laughingthrushes, up to 9,000ft (approx. 2,745m) or even 11,000ft (approx.
3,350m), so it is not surprising that it has proved to be hardy in European
aviaries. According to Grewal, Harvey &amp; Pfister (2002), in India, it is a
common breeding resident in the northern mountains, wintering lower in
the foothills. It inhabits forest undergrowth and montane scrub, feeding in
pairs or small parties on invertebrates and fruits and nesting in low growth.
It is apparently more confiding than other laughingthrushes, running rather
than flying from disturbances. Grimmett, Inskipp &amp; Inskipp (1999) described
its habitat as forest and shrubberies above the treeline.
It is a predominately brown, but very attractive, medium-sized
laughingthrush. The head is blackish brown with broad white moustachial
markings and a partial white ring behind the eyes. The breast, mantle and
scapulars appear scaled, as the feathers have dark brown margins and paler,
greyer centres. In a good light the scapulars and parts of the mantle are also
glossed with olive. The rump and vent are a rich chestnut and the flight and
tail feathers are golden-olive at the base changing to slaty blue-grey at the
tips. The eyes and beak are black and the legs a brownish pink. Western
birds have prominent white patches on the sides of the neck, but these are
less pronounced in Chinese birds. In the pair which bred these were
completely absent in one bird and apparent as silvery-grey smudges in the
other. Dave Coles (2000) listed six subspecies, Howard &amp; Moore (1984)
seven, of which five are present in The Natural History Museum at Tring
(Coles, 2000). I have not examined these skins, so have not identified which
subspecies my birds belong to.
The male has a clear, but not very loud or interesting whistled song
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999384" page_id="56264462"  page_num="98" year="" vol="">
98
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.856057" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264462" page_num="98" year="" vol="">
HEWSTON - BLACK-FACED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998921166666667" page_id="56264462"  page_num="98" year="" vol="">
usually of only four notes, described by Grewal, Harvey &amp; Pfister (2002) as
"wheet wheeoo woo". The female has a more plaintive whistle analogous
to that made by female Pekin Robins Leiothrix lute a and Omei Shan
Liocichlas Liocichla omeiensis which are unpaired or separated from their
mates, except that with the laughingthrushes I have occasionally heard this
while the male is present. It is similar particularly to the liocichla call, but
often contains three or even four notes, as opposed to the two of the liocichla.
There is also a metallic chattering or whirring call which may be used as a
scolding or alarm call, but which is also used in a duetting display,
accompanied by wing flicking. There is another harsh, loud call which I
have heard from the juvenile bird and, I think, from the adults, the function
of which is not clear to me.
I received a pair of these birds early in April 2005 on loan from Andrew
Blyth. This pair, plus another pair and a single female, had previously been
here from May 2001-March 2002, while Andrew was rebuilding some of
his aviaries. They would have stayed longer, but one pair came into breeding
condition in January 2002 and became dangerous to smaller birds (Hewston,
2002). At that time I had no suitable breeding aviary which the pair could
have to itself, so the pair was returned to Andrew, along with the other three
birds, though these had not caused any problems in mixed aviaries. By
2005 three of the five birds survived, including the pair which had shown
no signs of breeding during its last stay, and this was the pair which was
returned to me. All the birds were imported in 1997, so the pair was at least
eight years old at the time of breeding.
On arrival the pair was housed on its own in a 24ft x 12ft (approx. 7.3m
x 3.6m) planted aviary with a shelter 8ft x 4ft (approx. 2.4m x 1.2m) in a
shed which also contained the shelter for a pair of Omei Shan Liocichlas
which arrived at the same time and was housed in an adjacent aviary. The
aviary had been empty for two years and had become rather overgrown.
The front was fairly open, with a wire roof and sides and a tall, narrow
conifer, a low Lonicera bush, some young bamboo, a large Kniphofia in a
pot and a grassed area, but a Hebe in the centre had grown up to and through
the roof and almost filled the whole width of the aviary. Together with a
Cotoneaster at one side, a leylandii at the other and a hornbeam Carpinus
sp. also in the middle, they virtually blocked off the back of the aviary,
which was enclosed by fence panels at the back and on one side, and the
shed on the other, with opaque sheeting on the roof There was also a large
honeysuckle growing up a central roof support behind the Hebe. The aviary
was furnished with natural perches and had a large log in the middle. The
back had been used as a log store while empty, and logs were left stacked
about 3 ft (lm) high along the back wall. The top was cut off the cotoneaster
to allow the birds to fly the length of one side of the aviary. A universal
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.571259" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264463" page_num="99" year="" vol="">
HEWSTON - BLACK-FACED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99773" page_id="56264463"  page_num="99" year="" vol="">
99
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999331452380952" page_id="56264463"  page_num="99" year="" vol="">
food, soaked softbill pellets and sultanas, fresh fruit (mainly chopped pear)
and mealworms were provided in the shelter.
The birds settled quickly and after about a week a few pieces of nesting
material were found dropped on the shelter floor, often the first indication
that breeding activity has begun. On April 22nd a nest in the early stages of
construction was found about 5ft (1.5m) above the ground near the top of
the leylandii. A certain amount of dead grass and growing moss were
available on the aviary floor, along with bamboo leaves, which were
supplemented with tough grass stems, softer grass, moss (provided growing
on rocks) and coconut fibre. All these materials were used to make a deep
cup, which appeared quite advanced by April 25th, though the first egg was
not laid until the 30th. There were two eggs in the first clutch, which were
not actually seen until May 16th, the first time since laying that both adults
were seen away from the nest. The eggs were incubated until May 21st,
when they were candled and found to be clear, so were removed. They
were bright blue with a few small dark spots at the large end.
On May 24th the nest was being re-lined, mainly with coconut fibre, and
the first egg of the second clutch was laid on May 28th. There were two
eggs again and this time they were candled after about six days and were
both fertile. Nest inspection was difficult as the sitting bird needed to be
flushed from the nest and a mirror used to see inside. The nest with its new
lining was now very deep, and the bird trying to leave in a hurry found its
way blocked by branches, so inspections were kept to a minimum to avoid
stress and possible injury to the sitting bird and damage to the eggs.
On June 12th there were still two eggs in the morning, in the evening
one of the birds was seen apparently eating aphids from hornbeam leaves.
The next morning there was one chick in the nest, and two by the evening,
giving an incubation period of 14-15 days. Mini mealworms were provided
ad-lib, with white-skinned ones provided at least three times daily, along
with small brown crickets (fed dead, thawed from frozen). After a couple of
days waxworms and larger white-skinned mealworms were added, with larger
crickets and regular mealworms replacing the smaller ones as the chicks
grew.
All appeared to be going well until one chick was found dead below the
nest on June 26th. Its body plumage appeared uniformly dark brown and
had not spread out from the tracts to cover the whole body. The dark grey
flight feathers were only just longer than the coverts. Its skin was pink, it
had a prominent yellow gape and its legs were pale flesh coloured. The
other chick was still alive but could not be persuaded to raise its head.
However, the second chick did survive and I consulted Dave Coles's
excellent handbook to find out when I might expect it to fledge. The youngest
fledging age given is 12 days, with the most likely age being 14-16 days. I
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.969503" page_id="56264464"  page_num="100" year="" vol="">
100
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.860993" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264464" page_num="100" year="" vol="">
HEWSTON - BLACK-FACED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999353875" page_id="56264464"  page_num="100" year="" vol="">
was not too alarmed when the chick failed to fledge at 16 days, as Dave
states that some chicks take as long as 18 days, but when the chick had not
fledged by the morning of July 3rd I thought it must have a problem.
However, by the next morning it had fledged and was looking healthy and
behaving normally despite having stayed in the nest for at least 20 days or
probably 21 days. It had the usual short tail and was duller coloured than its
parents, but was a good size and was perching in honeysuckle the following
day. It found its way into the shelter at 32 days old, by which time the
Juvenile at 32 days old.
parents were building another nest in the honeysuckle. Three eggs were
laid and I made the mistake of assuming that they would be fertile, but when
one was found broken below the nest after 10 days' incubation, I candled
the others and found they were infertile. There were no further nesting
attempts in 2005. The young bird which continued to develop well was still
begging, and being fed, on August 24th, though I am sure it was also feeding
itself long before then. It was DNA-sexed and found to be a male. I removed
it from its parents in late September to be paired with Andrew's other,
surviving bird, which fortunately is a female and which he kindly let me
have on loan.
This year (2006), the original pair nested three times. The first egg was
laid on April 23rd. This year there were two eggs in each clutch, one of
which hatched from each of the first two clutches, but both chicks died at
five days old. At least one of the eggs in the third clutch was fertile but
failed to hatch. Following a winter trim, the conifer that the birds had used
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.571274" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264465" page_num="101" year="" vol="">
HEWSTON - BLACK-FACED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999259" page_id="56264465"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
101
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999451923076923" page_id="56264465"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
the previous year was not quite the nest site it had been and the birds initially
struggled to build a nest in it. However, they took readily to a basket wired
to the tree at their chosen site. All three clutches were laid in a nest built,
and subsequently re-lined, in this basket.
The new pair, in a smaller (15ft x 6ft (approx. 4.5m x 1.8m)) aviary, was
given a dead conifer to nest in which the pair chose in preference to a large
clump of bamboo. The pair had the same problem as the first pair and
accepted the same solution and had a good nest in the basket by mid-May.
No eggs appeared and I eventually noticed that a large lump had appeared
on the female's abdomen. I assumed that attempting to breed for the first
time at an advanced age had caused a problem in her reproductive tract.
She showed no discomfort and was removed to another aviary, to be replaced
in early July by another female kindly loaned by Birdworld, near Famham,
Surrey. This bird settled well with the male but no serious attempt was
made to nest.
The new female had been in the collection at Birdworld since 1998. I
can find no other record of the breeding of the Black-faced Laughingthrush
and I am concerned that in 2007, the 2005 male will be the only bird in the
UK less than 10 years old, and without very good luck it may be too late to
establish this species in captivity, at a time when it seems very unlikely that
further stock will become available from Asia in the near future, if ever. I
would be very interested to hear from anyone else who keeps this species in
the UK or elsewhere. There is a real danger that most species of
laughingthrushes now present in aviaries in the UK and elsewhere will be
lost unless a concerted effort is made to breed from them in the very near
future.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.952601" genericHeader="references" page_id="56264465" page_num="101" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.987681454545455">
Coles, D. 2000. Management of Laughingthrushes in Captivity. DC Books, UK.
Grewal, B., Harvey, B. and Pfister, O. 2002. A Photographic Guide to the Birds of India.
Christopher Helm, London.
Grimmett, R., Inskipp, K. and Inskipp, T. 1999. Pocket Guide to Birds of the Indian Sub-
Continent. Christopher Helm, London.
Hewston, N. R. 2002. Letters to the Editor. Avicultural Magazine, 108,2:85-86.
Howard, R. and Moore, A. 1984. A Complete Checklist of the Birds of the World. Macmillan,
London.
Rutgers, A. and Gould, J. 1969. Birds of Asia. Methuen, London.
Nigel Hewston is an Avicultural Society Council Member. He lives at
Stonehouse, Glos., UK. E-mail:nigelhewston@supanet.com
</reference>
<bodyText confidence="0.99827825" page_id="56264465"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
As described above, the Black-faced Laughingthrush Garrulax affinis ,
has been bred by Nigel Hewston. It is believed to be the first breeding of
this species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who knows of a previous
breeding is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99927" page_id="56264466"  page_num="102" year="" vol="">
102
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.820757" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264466" page_num="102" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL SUPPORT FOR THE ECHO PARAKEET
PROGRAMME ON MAURITIUS
by Roger Wilkinson
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989627194444444" page_id="56264466"  page_num="102" year="" vol="">
This is a short account of the Echo Parakeet Psittacula eques conservation
programme that is run by the Mauritius Wildlife Conservation Foundation
(MWF) in partnership with the National Parks and Conservation Service,
Mauritius. In particular it highlights the support from Chester Zoo and other
conservation organisations in assisting this programme, both through staff
involvement and financial support. This account expands and updates an
article previously published by the European Association of Zoos and Aquaria
(EAZA) in Proceedings of the EAZA Conference 2004.
Chester Zoo is also assisting other conservation initiatives on Mauritius,
including providing technical and financial support for the Mauritius Fody
Foudia rubra and the Olive White-eye Zosterops olivacea recovery
programmes and has assisted with financial support for veterinary research
on the Pink Pigeon Columba (. Nesoenas) mayeri. More recently financial
and staff support has been provided for projects on the conservation of
threatened endemic plants. In the Mascarenes, Chester Zoo continues to
support research on the Rodrigues Fruit Bat Pteropus rodricensis and through
Shoals Rodrigues also helps to finance both marine conservation and
community initiatives.
Chester Zoo is one of several organisations supporting the Echo Parakeet
conservation project. The Durrell Wildlife Conservation Trust (Jersey Zoo)
is the major sponsor of the Mauritius Wildlife Foundation and significant
investments in the Echo Parakeet programme have been made by the World
Parrot Trust (WPT), The Parrot Society and the Loro Parque Fundacion.
I was able to visit Mauritius and Rodrigues in November 2003 when,
staying as a house guest of Carl Jones, I learned so much more about these
projects through meeting the MWF staff at the field sites. This was especially
the case regarding the conservation programme for the Echo Parakeet. I
had several enjoyable days accompanying members of the Echo Parakeet
team in the field at the most critical time during that year's Echo Parakeet
breeding season.
Conservation history
The Echo Parakeet, which is Critically Endangered, occurs only on
Mauritius. In 1986 only eight to 12 birds were known, and only two or
three of these were females, although a few other birds may have been
overlooked. These were restricted to the Black River gorges and surrounding
forests, an area that in 1993 was designated the countiy's first national park.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.71224" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264467" page_num="103" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - ECHO PARAKEET
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999692" page_id="56264467"  page_num="103" year="" vol="">
103
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.990281414634146" page_id="56264467"  page_num="103" year="" vol="">
It was set up to conserve the Mauritius Kestrel Falco punctatus , Echo
Parakeet, Pink Pigeon and other native wildlife. Further research in 1994
and 1995 gave an estimate of 30 Echo Parakeets in the wild. Although a
considerable improvement on the previous estimate, this larger estimate still
suggested that extinction was imminent unless immediate conservation
attention was focused on this species. Under the guidance of Carl Jones, the
Scientific Director of the MWF, and with integrated wild and captive
management, the Echo Parakeet recovery has been extremely successful.
Through a combination of the release of captive-bred birds and active
management of the wild population, by April 2006 the number of birds in
the wild had increased to 300-320 individuals.
Conservation management
Conservation management is focused on the Echo Parakeets living in
the wild, with back-up captive breeding and captive rearing facilities for
young birds rescued/harvested from the wild. The field work is coordinated
by Jason Malham, a New Zealander, and the Echo Parakeet programme has
close interactions with staff of the New Zealand Department of Conservation,
with benefits to both as a result of sharing experiences and ideas for recovery
programmes for island birds. The captive facilities are managed by
Frederique Koenig, a Mauritian trained at Jersey Zoo, who has run the captive
facilities for several years. During my visit the hand-rearing of both captive-
bred and rescued wild-hatched chicks was managed by Ryan Watson, from
Adelaide Zoo, Australia. Ryan is one of a number of staff members from
Adelaide Zoo, who over the years have assisted the MWF conservation
programmes. In the 2004-2005 breeding season, for example, Heidi Groffen
and Pat Hodgens from Adelaide Zoo assisted with releases and hand-raised
birds respectively. Prior to this, between 1997-1998, Paradise Park, Cornwall,
home of the World Parrot Trust, seconded Kirsty Jenkin, Nick Reynolds,
Dale Jackson and Pete Haverson to assist with the Echo Parakeet programme
on Mauritius.
Management in the wild, includes checking nest site activities, the
provision of artificial nest cavities, nest monitoring and clutch and brood
manipulations, supplementary feeding and monitoring of released birds and
predator control. Echo Parakeet nest cavities may be taken over by other
birds including the White-tailed Tropicbird Phaethon lepturns. The latter is
discouraged by fixing branches across the entrance to nest cavities, thereby
making access to them difficult for this species. Unusual nest predators
include the large African srmlAchatina that has on several occasions 'slimed'
young chicks to death in the nest. Areas of the tree trunk above and below
the nest entrance are covered in wrap around plastic sheeting that is greased
to discourage nest predators, such as monkeys and rats, that may climb up
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999632" page_id="56264468"  page_num="104" year="" vol="">
104
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.81703" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264468" page_num="104" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - ECHO PARAKEET
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9973685" page_id="56264468"  page_num="104" year="" vol="">
to the nests. The Black Rat Rattus rattus is kept under control by poisoning
and trapping in areas close to active nest sites.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.707675" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264469" page_num="105" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - ECHO PARAKEET
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.990976" page_id="56264469"  page_num="105" year="" vol="">
105
</page>
<table confidence="0.33078" page_id="56264469"  page_num="105" year="" vol="">
Roger Wilkinson
Pair of wild Echo Parakeets.
</table>
<page confidence="0.999224" page_id="56264470"  page_num="106" year="" vol="">
106
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.906212" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264470" page_num="106" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - ECHO PARAKEET
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993726642857143" page_id="56264470"  page_num="106" year="" vol="">
Artificial nests of several different designs are also provided, as the
number of suitable natural nest sites is limited and competition for these
may limit the number of breeding pairs in an area. The nests are inspected
daily and records kept of egg-laying, hatch dates and chick development.
This necessitates tree climbing and both Jason and the rest of the field team
are skilled climbers. Chicks are weighed and any that weigh less than 20%
of the average weight for chicks of their age are removed for hand-rearing.
Rescued chicks are transported to the Gerald Durrell Endemic Wildlife
Sanctuary (GDEWS) and after being hand-reared there are released back
into the wild.
Supplementary feeding is through pole-mounted hoppers containing
commercially manufactured parrot pellets. The Echo Parakeets learn to lift
up the lids of these hoppers so as to feed. The lids prevent the pellets being
taken by other birds and mammals.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.498101">
Chester Zoo
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.974562961538461" page_id="56264470"  page_num="106" year="" vol="">
Conservation support and staff involvement
Direct financial support to MWF in terms of grants between 2000-2005
for Echo Parakeet programme support, including the construction of release
aviaries, amounted to over #29,000 (approx. US$54,000). Costs related to
Chester Zoo staff working on Mauritius (but excluding their salaries), whilst
seconded from Chester Zoo, take these costs to well over #40,000
(approx.US$75,000) over the six years we have been supporting this
programme. Most of these costs have previously been met from our
conservation budget, that is itself derived from visitor revenue to the zoo.
This allows us to inform our zoo visitors that their visit directly supports
field conservation. In 2004 and 2005 the funds for the keeper assistance
and day to day cover in their absence came from the hugely successful Keeper
for a Day scheme (in which members of the public pay to be a keeper for a
day) run by the Chester Zoo keeping staff. This financial and staff investment
has provided significant benefits to this programme and directly links to the
zoo's conservation mission. This support is perhaps unusual in that much
of Chester Zoo's conservation outreach focuses on threatened species we
hold in the zoo. We do not presently hold any Echo Parakeets, although we
hope that we may in the future. Through the Echo Parakeet work we support
a Critically Endangered species that we do not currently hold and export
our staff expertise to assist this conservation programme.
Anne Morris was our first staff member to work on Mauritius and spent
three months in 2000-2001 at the Black River Aviaries (now the Gerald
Durrell Endemic Wildlife Sanctuary), where her main task was hand-rearing
Echo Parakeets. Anne and her husband Paul have many years' experience
of parrot husbandry and of hand-rearing parrots at Chester Zoo, and this
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.712247" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264471" page_num="107" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - ECHO PARAKEET
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999583" page_id="56264471"  page_num="107" year="" vol="">
107
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998943944444445" page_id="56264471"  page_num="107" year="" vol="">
was a real opportunity for those skills to be directly applied to parrot
conservation in the wild. The facilities and protocols for hand-rearing parrots
at the GDEWS are excellent and gave Anne new insights into best practise
for parrot rearing. Anne then stayed on longer at Black River and worked
with the team releasing the birds she had reared. This greatly assisted the
release process and generated real personal satisfaction for her in seeing the
birds she had reared being successfully released.
In 2003, two more of our bird keepers, Paul Morris and Clare Daniel,
were seconded to MWF for a combined period of over three months and
worked with staff releasing hand-reared birds. The release process involves
a soft release that requires a combination of keeper skills and knowledge of
how the birds behave. After having been hand-reared, the parakeets are
first accustomed to their release aviaries and then the behaviour of the
released birds is carefully monitored. Again this is an area in which our
staff members' experience and skills are uniquely appropriate to assist this
most important parrot conservation programme. Paul returned to Mauritius
to assist with field work on the Echo Parakeets during the 2004-2005 breeding
season.
Chester Zoo staff involvement in this project has been beneficial to Echo
Parakeet conservation, the MWF and Chester Zoo. This involvement has
benefited our staff in terms of their personal experience in working with a
team of wildlife conservationists abroad and applying and developing their
skills in a new situation. It has also given them the new experience of
working field conservation and benefits Chester Zoo through their increased
experience that can be communicated to other staff members and our public.
The conservation mission of Chester Zoo then becomes real to our keepers
and not abstract. They can really say that they have helped save the Echo
Parakeet from extinction.
The Mauritius Wildlife Foundation is very happy with the close
relationship that has developed with Chester Zoo and the other collections
in developing this project. In the 1980s the Echo Parakeet was regarded by
many as a hopeless case, but due to the international effort described above
and the close involvement of the National Parks and Conservation Services
on Mauritius, this has become one of the most successful parrot restoration
programmes in the world and provides an important example for the
conservation of other endangered parrots.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.967543" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56264471" page_num="107" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgments
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9388016" page_id="56264471"  page_num="107" year="" vol="">
I am grateful to Carl Jones, who has been instrumental in saving many
Mauritian species from extinction, for correcting and adding to a previous
version of this article. I also wish to thank Paul Morris, Anne Moms and
Clare Daniel for information on their experiences whilst seconded on
Mauritius. The whole Echo Parakeet team, past and present, deserve our
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99953" page_id="56264472"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
108
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.765669" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264472" page_num="108" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - ECHO PARAKEET
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.682131">
Roger Wilkinson
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9982085" page_id="56264472"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
Male at pole-mounted hopper containing commercially
manufactured parrot pellets.
thanks for working against all odds and under often arduous conditions, to
ensure the survival of the Echo Parakeet in the forests of Mauritius. Finally
thanks to the Durrell Wildlife Conservation Trust, Chester Zoo, Paradise
Park, Adelaide Zoo, the World Parrot Trust, Loro Parque Fundacion and the
many other supporters, with apologies to those not named, that have enabled
this conservation work to proceed.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.704877" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264473" page_num="109" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - ECHO PARAKEET
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.984955" page_id="56264473"  page_num="109" year="" vol="">
109
</page>
<figure confidence="0.83981225" page_id="56264473"  page_num="109" year="" vol="">
Roger Wilkinson
One and four-day-old Echo Parakeet chicks.
Roger Wilkinson
Paul Morris radio-tracking released Echo Parakeets.
</figure>
<page confidence="0.995616" page_id="56264474"  page_num="110" year="" vol="">
110
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.6090575" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264474" page_num="110" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - ECHO PARAKEET
Bibliography
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.929960407407407">
BirdLife International. 2000. Threatened Birds of the World. Lynx Edicions and BirdLife
International, Barcelona and Cambridge, UK.
Jones, C. G. 2004. Conservation and Management of Endangered Birds. In: Sutherland, W. J.,
Newton, I and Green, R. E. Bird Ecology and Conservation. A Handbook of Techniques,
Chapter 12, pp.269-301. Oxford University Press, Oxford, UK.
Malham, J., Reuleaux, A., Buckland, S., van de Wetering, J., Sawmy, S. and Bowkett, R. 2004.
Management of Echo Parakeets in the Wild 2003/2004. In: Echo Parakeet Management Report
2004. Unpublished report to Durrell Wildlife Conservation Trust, World Parrot Trust, Chester
Zoo and Conservation Service of Mauritius and Mauritius Wildlife Foundation.
Plant, A., Groffen, H. and Hodgens, P. 2005. The Release of Echo Parakeets in the Wild 2004/
2005. In: Echo Parakeet Management Report 2005. Unpublished report to the Durrell Wildlife
Conservation Trust, Chester Zoo, World Parrot Trust, IBL Limited, General Construction,
National Parks and Conservation Service of Mauritius and Mauritian Wildlife Foundation.
Reuleaux, A., Malham, J., Morris, P., Daniel, C., van de Wetering, J., Buckland, S., Sawmy, S.
and Bowkett, R. 2004. The release of Echo Parakeets at Bel Ombre 2003/2004. In: Echo
Parakeet Management Report 2004. Unpublished report to Durrell Wildlife Conservation
Trust, World Parrot Trust, Chester Zoo and Conservation Service of Mauritius and Mauritius
Wildlife Foundation.
Wilkinson, R. 2005. The Mauritius Wildlife Foundation echo parakeet programme and zoo
conservation support. In: Hiddinga, B. (ed.) Proceedings of the EAZA Conference 2004,
Kolmarden, pp.200-202. EAZA Executive Office, Amsterdam.
Dr Roger Wilkinson is Head of Science and Conservation, Chester Zoo,
Upton-by-Chester, Chester CH2 ILH, UK. Roger is an Avicultural Society
Vice President.
SPRING SOCIAL MEETING 2007
Saturday, March 31st, the Avicultural Society will visit Waddesdon
Manor, near Aylesbury, Buckinghamshire HP 18 0JH.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990544" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264475" page_num="111" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE ELEGANT CRESTED TINAMOU
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987834" page_id="56264475"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
Eudromia e. elegans
in
by Bryan Andrews
Living in West Wales, just a few miles (kilometres) from Phil Cleeton of
C&amp;J Bird Brokers, enables me to call in on a regular basis to see his fresh
imports. These are mainly softbills, but on one such visit I saw and purchased
two juvenile Elegant Crested Tinamou, that had been captive-bred in Europe.
The Elegant Crested Tinamou is found throughout Argentina and Chile. It
is one of 46 species of these ground-dwelling, omnivorous species, that
range in size from that of a quail to that of a guineafowl. They inhabit arid
and semi-arid grassland, dry savannah and open woodland, favouring open
sites. Thought of as a primitive group of birds, they appear to be closely
related to the ratites, the tinamous having strong legs and feet that lack a
hind toe (Davies, 2002).
The half-grown birds I had purchased grew well and turned out to be a
true pair. They were housed in a well planted aviary, that they shared with
pairs of Crested Wood Partridge Rollulus roulroul , Schalow's Wheatear
Oenanthe schalowi and a group of six White-headed Mousebirds Colitis
leucocephalus. The tinamous never roosted in the sleeping quarters, which
had heating and lighting, but instead slept in a shallow scrape in the only
uncovered part of the aviary. They roosted there even during the worst
weather.
Over the Christmas 2005 period, four eggs were laid in a deep scrape.
Because of the poor weather they were removed for artificial incubation
and were measured, weighed and photographed. On the 10th day they were
candled and all four proved to be infertile.
Both tinamous came through the winter without any ills, enjoying a diet
of diced mixed fruits, Beapher softfood and Puik wild birdseed with added
chopped peanuts. A couple of buckets of sand mixed with crushed oystershell
provided them with a play area into which a number of mealworms were
thrown each morning, and both the tinamous and the partridges spent time
hunting for them.
The tinamous started the 2006 laying season on April 6th, using the
same scrape as before. This is at the base of a very large Japonica shrub.
As no attempt was made to conceal the eggs, I was able to keep a close
check on them and remove each fresh egg as it was laid and replace it with
one of the eggs from the earlier infertile clutch, hoping as I did so that the
female could not count beyond four! I used Brinsea Octogon 20 incubators
run at a temperature of 37.6*C (99.7*F) and a wet bulb reading of 60%-65%
for the first 16 days, which was raised to 70%-75% for the remainder of the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998514" page_id="56264476"  page_num="112" year="" vol="">
112
</page>
<table confidence="0.930014666666667" page_id="56264476"  page_num="112" year="" vol="">
ANDREWS - ELEGANT CRESTED TINAMOU
Sarah Lewis &amp; Bryan Andrews
Elegant Crested Tinamou.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.625638" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264477" page_num="113" year="" vol="">
ANDREWS - ELEGANT CRESTED TINAMOU
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997272" page_id="56264477"  page_num="113" year="" vol="">
113
</page>
<table confidence="0.927511" page_id="56264477"  page_num="113" year="" vol="">
Sarah Lewis &amp; Bryan Andrews
Distinctively coloured eggs of the Elegant Crested Tinamou.
Sarah Lewis &amp; Bryan Andrews
This photo gives an idea of the size of the chick .
</table>
<page confidence="0.999693" page_id="56264478"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
114
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.615926" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264478" page_num="114" year="" vol="">
ANDREWS - ELEGANT CRESTED TINAMOU
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.329436">
Sarah Lewis &amp; Bryan Andrews
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998492913043478" page_id="56264478"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
Taking mealworms from the hand.
hatching period. The incubation time varied from 18-21 days, with the
heavier chicks being the earliest to hatch (see Table 1). The egg colour, as
seen in the photograph (p. 113 ), never varied, but there was a slight variation
in both the dimensions and the weight of the eggs, although these differences
did not correlate with the hatching weights of the chicks.
The chicks hatch fully feathered and with the crest already visible (see
photo p.l 13). As can be seen in Table I, all did not go well at the start of
rearing, which was due to the reluctance on the part of the chicks to take any
of the foods offered, which included micro crickets and skinned mealworms.
The breakthrough came when I started to force-feed the chicks at two-hourly
intervals with soaked trout pellets. These seemed to do the trick and by day
five the chicks were playing with compound crumbs that had been dressed
with livefood. The preferred dry food was a pin-head sized compound that
I had purchased in Singapore. Made by a company called 3 Coins, it is used
by bird keepers there to feed their white-eyes Zosterops spp. This tiny
compound is made from green peas, soya beans, black beans, unpolished
rice, sugar, proteins and vitamins. So far I have been unable to find it here
in the UK.
By the second week, the chicks were hunting down medium-sized crickets
and eating a few mealworms each day. I think I may have overdone the
amount of protein provided for two of the chicks as both suffered from
slight angel wing. This was easily corrected using micropore tape left on
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.626942" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264479" page_num="115" year="" vol="">
ANDREWS - ELEGANT CRESTED TINAMOU
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99887" page_id="56264479"  page_num="115" year="" vol="">
115
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.996963">
Table 1. Eggs and chicks hatched in incubator.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.988746083333333" page_id="56264479"  page_num="115" year="" vol="">
Egg
Set
Hatched
Weight
Remarks
1
8.4.06
-
-
Infertile
2
8.4.06
26.4.06
31g
Hand-reared
3
12.4.06
30.4.06
32g
Died at seven days
4
14.4.06
3.5.06
30g
Died at five days
5
17.4.06
5.5.06
32g
Hand-reared
6
26.4.06
15.5.06
30g
Angel wing
7
26.4.06
17.5.06
28g
Hand-reared
8
26.4.06
15.5.06
30g
Angel wing
9
30.4.06
21.5.06
27g
Hand-reared
10
4.5.06
25.5.06
27g
Hand-reared
11
4.5.06
24.5.06
30g
Hand-reared
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.9872203" page_id="56264479"  page_num="115" year="" vol="">
the wings for seven days. A second school of thought suggests that rearing
chicks under a white light contributes to this problem. So, perhaps it was
more than coincidence that these were the only two chicks reared under a
white light.
All of the chicks were by then eating softfood and a mixture of finely
diced soft fruits, along with seed.
Having reared enough chicks for my purpose, I now plan to leave the
male to incubate any further eggs, and hope to report that he managed to
hatch and rear the chicks, assisted perhaps by the female (as is the way with
tinamous).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.522051" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56264479" page_num="115" year="" vol="">
Reference
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.839715">
Davies, S. I. J. F. 2002. Ratites and Tinamous. Oxford University Press, Oxford, UK.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.9996" page_id="56264480"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
116
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.994414" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264480" page_num="116" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE WHITE-HEADED MOUSEBIRD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.955706545454546" page_id="56264480"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
Colius leucocephalus
by Bryan Andrews
In February 2005, Phil Cleeton of C&amp;J Bird Brokers imported, amongst
a number of other birds, some White-headed Mousebirds, six of which were
obtained by me. They arrived in fine condition, with full tails; these being
twice the length of the body are not always so complete.
Sarah Lewis &amp; Bryan Andrews
Two females sitting on the same nest.
I housed them indoors, keeping them at a temperature of 73*F (22.8*C),
in an all-wire suspended cage. In the spring of that year they were moved to
a 9ft x 3ft x 6ft (approx. 2.7m x lm x 1.8m) planted aviary with a sleeping
box, with heating and lighting in it. The box was rarely used, the birds
preferring instead to spend the nights hanging in a cluster from the roof
netting, until the morning sun brought them out of their torpid state.
Housed on their own, they were offered and ate the same softbill diet as
my other birds. This consisted of diced fruit, Bogena Universal and chopped
greens, with sliced papaya (pawpaw). I should add here that since January
2006, following constant nagging by Phil Cleeton, I now feed all fruits and
vegetables halved not diced.
At the beginning of June, all six mousebirds were seen feeding each
other and showing great interest in the canary wicker nest pans placed
amongst fir cuttings and bamboos. They would add to and take away fresh
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.520102" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264481" page_num="117" year="" vol="">
ANDREWS - WHITE-HEADED MOUSEBIRD
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.992137" page_id="56264481"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
117
</page>
<table confidence="0.504418666666667" page_id="56264481"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
Sarah Lewis &amp; Bryan Andrews
Chicks and eggs in nest built in fine-leaved bamboo.
Sarah Lewis &amp; Bryan Andrews
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.979412" page_id="56264481"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
The length of the young mousebird's tail is still only approximately two-thirds the
length of the adult birds' tails.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999194" page_id="56264482"  page_num="118" year="" vol="">
118
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.885637" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264482" page_num="118" year="" vol="">
ANDREWS - WHITE-HEADED MOUSEBIRD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997977690476191" page_id="56264482"  page_num="118" year="" vol="">
greenery they had placed in the pans daily. With no visual way of sexing the
six birds, I just let them get on with it. They would feed and groom each
other and I would find them sitting in different nests each time I looked.
On making a closer inspection in mid-July, I found that two of the nests
each contained two eggs. Prior to leaving for a month-long stay in Indonesia
with my partner, young were being fed by the adults. However, while in
Singapore, we received a phone call to say that the birds in the aviaries back
home in Wales were being bothered by a Sparrowhawk Accipiter nisus and
that the commotion it had caused had resulted in the loss of the young
mousebirds.
No further nesting attempt was made and on our return I moved the
mousebirds into an unheated indoor flight for the winter.
At the start of April 2006 the mousebirds were moved to an outdoor
aviary that was densely planted with bamboo and a number of large shrubs.
They shared the aviary with Elegant Crested Tinamou Eudromia elegans
and Gambel's Quail Lophortyx gambellii. The planting of the aviary made
viewing of the nests extremely difficult. However, on June 5th, I was able
to see two mousebirds sitting tightly on separate nests, one was in a canary-
type nest pan and the other was on a beautifully woven nest that the birds
had made themselves. It was approximately 5ft (1.5m) above the ground in
the centre of a fine-leaved bamboo. This is the nest shown in the photo on
p. 117. The photos were taken after I finally plucked up enough courage,
and against all the rules, ventured into the undergrowth and photographed
the two nests, which between them contained a total of three eggs and four
chicks. I had no way of knowing which bird had laid which eggs in which
nest. Plus, I understand that females will share nests and both birds will sit
on the eggs, as can be seen in the photo on p. 116, taken during the 2005
breeding season.
I can vouch for the fact that all the adult group take part in the feeding and
preening of the young, as the four fully-fledged young could be viewed in
food-passing sessions. With their body size now, at the time of writing (July
2006), not so different from that of the parent birds, it is only by looking at the
length of their tails that I can tell them apart, the length of the young birds'
tails being approximately two-thirds of the length of the tails of the adults.
I realise that this is a poorly documented study of these birds, given that
it may well be the first breeding of this species in the UK. However, at least
two of the adults have gone down again and next year, following my
retirement, I will have time to make a more detailed study.
As described above, the White-headed Mousebird Colitis leucocephalus ,
has been bred by Bryan Andrews. This is believed to be the first breeding of
this species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who knows of a previous
breeding is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.966861" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264483" page_num="119" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE BLACK-CAPPED SOCIAL WEAVER
</sectionHeader>
<keyword confidence="0.324429">
Pseudonigrita cabanisi
</keyword>
<page confidence="0.998069" page_id="56264483"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
119
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.96857865" page_id="56264483"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
by Martin Davies
I acquired eight Black-capped Social Weavers in April 2006, with the
aim of trying to establish a breeding colony, given that we are unlikely to
see this species imported again. Within days I had sadly lost two of them.
The remaining six seemed robust and soon settled into a planted flight
measuring 11ft x 10ft x 8ft (approx. 3.5m x 3m x 2.4m). I noticed the birds
beginning to establish a pecking order with the alpha pair soon heading up
my potential breeding colony. As I had never seen this species before I
found the behaviour of the birds fascinating. They communicated with each
other using a wide variety of calls, consisting mostly of loud squawks and
chattering. They would greet each other en masse with head bobbing, tail
quivering and a great deal of excitement. Much of their time was spent
together, perching and following each other in flight, and only separating
when they foraged on the aviary floor. Although they are coloured black,
white and brown, they are quite striking looking birds and for weavers,
became very steady once settled into their surroundings. Plumage-wise the
sexes look alike but males and females do differ slightly in size and when
observed for some time, behaviourally the differences are more apparent,
with the males being much more confident and 'pushy', especially where
livefood is concerned.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.577114">
Feeding
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.976918066666666" page_id="56264483"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
I fed the birds a good quality seed mixture for finches, with a high millet
content, together with mealworms, waxworms and various fruits (all of the
latter were ignored, except for the apple) and a commercially available softbill
mixture. Grated cheese, carrot and the usual softbill fare were steadfastly
ignored.
Breeding
In early May, with the colony well settled in, I started to provide various
types of nesting material such as hemp teasings, dry hay, small twigs and
coconut fibre, but to my great disappointment, the birds made only half-
hearted attempts at nest building. I remembered that when I had been in
South Africa most of the weavers that I saw had started building individual
nests using green material and not the dry material that I had provided up
until then. So, I supplied them with some long stems of grass. These got
them going with a little more enthusiasm, but again they soon gave up. In
despair, I phoned Mike Curzon, to ask if he could offer me any advice? He
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.97985" page_id="56264484"  page_num="120" year="" vol="">
120
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.849122" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264484" page_num="120" year="" vol="">
DAVIES - BLACK-CAPPED SOCIAL WEAVER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997648045454545" page_id="56264484"  page_num="120" year="" vol="">
Nest built by Black-capped Social Weavers.
consulted a reliable field guide and confirmed that they make individual
nests rather than a single colonial nest. Despite the advice, however, it
occurred to me that they might build colonial nests just for roosting purposes
when not breeding and that this might bond the colony together and make it
feel more settled. So, I placed in the flight, two hanging baskets stuffed
with hay. These produced an almost immediate result. The birds became
very excited and chattered away to each other, using calls I had not heard
them use before. They began to fashion tunnels into the mass of hay and
over time, they built individual compartments in it. I provided more hay
and they just kept adding to the structure until it became quite substantial. I
kept disturbance to a minimum and only entered the flight to feed the birds.
Therefore, I had no real idea whether or not they were breeding. Furthermore,
my work commitments at the time meant that I had little leisure time to
observe them. I had though noticed copulation occurring.
In early June we had some very inclement weather and on visiting the
flight one morning to feed the birds, I found one of them dead. This reduced
the number of birds to five. As the weather improved and time moved on
the remaining birds became more interested in each other and began to
increase their consumption of any livefood in their flight - waxworms and
fruit flies being favourites. About this time I noticed one pair in particular
becoming very territorial over their area of the communal nest and my hopes
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.503588" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264485" page_num="121" year="" vol="">
DAVIES - BLACK-CAPPED SOCIAL WEAVER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.993132" page_id="56264485"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
121
</page>
<author confidence="0.449898">
Martin Davies
</author>
<bodyText confidence="0.9936832" page_id="56264485"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
Pair of adult Black-capped Social Weavers. The sexes differ slightly in size and the
male is much more confident than the female.
began to rise. The only concern I had was that I was due to go away on
holiday for two weeks and was worried that any extra care that might be
needed would not be fully catered for in my absence. I need not have worried,
as on my return I was greeted by the sound of a nestful of young social
weavers. I was sorely tempted to look into the nest, but resisted the
temptation. The youngsters' "chirping" was faint, so I thought they must
have hatched very recently. As the days passed, the "chirping" remained
faint and I started to worry that the chicks were not getting enough sustenance.
So I tried to reintroduce more variety into the diet, by providing grated
cheese, carrot and hard-boiled egg, but all were ignored again. My worries
proved to be unfounded, as on July 24th when visiting the flight, I found
two young fledglings getting used to their new home. They were smaller,
very pale versions of the adults and were very flighty, and were flying at the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997661" page_id="56264486"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
122
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.855341" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264486" page_num="122" year="" vol="">
DAVIES - BLACK-CAPPED SOCIAL WEAVER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99774268" page_id="56264486"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
wire. The parents and the unpaired adult bird fed the youngsters and at
night they all returned to the nest to roost. Shortly after their first outing,
they returned to the nest and remained there for several days before venturing
out again into the flight. The fledglings then began to investigate the feeding
pots and settled down over several days, becoming steadier as they
familiarised themselves with their surroundings.
At this time there was a change in the behaviour of the non-breeding
members of the colony. They left the colonial nest and started to make their
own nest, which is identical in shape and size to the image of the nest I
found on the internet and is like the nest described to me by Mike Curzon.
It is now, at the time of writing (August 2006), occupied by the other pair
and I assume there are eggs in it.
I will endeavour to establish links with other keepers of this fascinating
species - at present, I know of only one other. As we are unlikely to see the
import ban lifted, I feel that as bird keepers, we now have a responsibility to
specialise in such species, to ensure as wide a variety of species as possible
remain available for the future.
Martin later confirmed that there were a further three young, but they
were lost during a heavy rainstorm, after which the weather turned cooler
and the birds contented themselves by making nest repairs, but did little
else.
As described above, the Black-capped Social Weaver Pseudonigrita
cabanisi, has been bred by Martin Davies. This is thought to be the first
breeding of this species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who knows of
a previous breeding is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.6863202" page_id="56264486"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
Martin Davies is a UK member living in Wiltshire.
* * *
BREEDERS' REGISTER
Andrew Owen of Waddesdon Manor aviaries is setting up a Breeders '
Register of keepers (breeders) of the Chestnut-backed Thrush Zoothera
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.965538333333333" page_id="56264486"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
dohertyi, with the aim of trying to establish a self-sustaining population of
this Indonesian species found from Lombok to Timor. He would also like
to hear from anyone who keeps the distinctive Sumatran subspecies of the
White-crested Laughingthrush Garrulax leucolophus bicolor , which was
bred earlier this year at Waddesdon Manor. If you keep either of these
birds, or would like to know more, you are invited to contact Head Keeper
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.5660115">
Ian Hadgkiss or Andrew by telephone at: 01296 653286 or by e-mail:
Andrew. Owen@nationaltrust. org.uk
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998928" page_id="56264487"  page_num="123" year="" vol="">
123
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.978003" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264487" page_num="123" year="" vol="">
TOO RARE TO COLLECT
THE DISCOVERY OF A NEW SPECIES OF LIOCICHLA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.988715128205128" page_id="56264487"  page_num="123" year="" vol="">
A professional astronomer Ramana Athreya has found a new species of
liocichla in a remote part of north-eastern India. He first saw it at Eaglenest
Wildlife Sanctuary, Arunachal Pradesh, in 1995. Ramana and his colleagues
on the Eaglenest Biodiversity Project returned to the site in late January
2005 and again in May 2005 armed with mist nets, but failed to find the bird
again. It was not until May this year that two were eventually trapped.
Because of their great rarity, no scientific specimen was collected, instead
they were photographed, feather samples were taken and voice recordings
made, then the two birds were released.
The description of this new species, which has been named the Bugun
Liocichla Liocichla bugunorum (see photo on following page), and the story
of its discovery, were published in the journal Indian Birds. Its Editor,
Aasheesh Pittie, described the discovery of this new species in a part of the
world that has been visited by bird collectors for more than a century, as
"nothing short of miraculous."
Dr Nigel Collar of BirdLife International warmly congratulated Ramana
Athreya on his outstanding discovery and fully supports his decision not to
collect a specimen at this stage. Dr Collar said: "This species appears to be
very rare indeed, and from what we know at present the taking of even one
individual could jeopardise the Bugun Liocichla's future survival prospects."
The known population consists of only 14 individuals including three
breeding pairs. Apparently it is not particularly shy and because of this and
its very distinctive appearance, it must be very rare otherwise it would
certainly have been found earlier. "It is good news that it has been found in
a wildlife sanctuary where it is already protected", said Dr Collar, who added:
"A priority now is to find out if other populations of this remarkable species
exist elsewhere and what its habitat requirements are, so that appropriate
conservation measures can be put in place."
It is probably most closely related to the Omei Shan Liocichla L.
omeiensis, which is known from only a few mountains in central China,
more than 1,000km (600 miles or so) away, where it is found in the
undergrowth of primary and secondary forest between l,000m-2,400m
(approx. 3,280ft-5,870ft). It was first bred in the UK by Richard Cockerill
in 1993 and subsequently by Andrew Blyth in 1995 and by Nigel Hewston
in 1996. A census of known keepers conducted in March 1998 recorded 21
males and 20 females in 10 collections (see Avicultural Magazine Vol.107,
No.3, pp. 109-114 (2001)).
Detailed examination of the Eaglenest birds and comparison with
specimens and tape recordings of the Omei Shan Liocichla revealed many
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99929" page_id="56264488"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
124
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.970011" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264488" page_num="124" year="" vol="">
BUGUN LIGCICHLA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.947899" page_id="56264488"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
Bugun Liocichla Liocichla bugunorum.
plumage and vocal differences. Comparisons were made possible by
reference to skins in The Natural History Museum collection at Tring, which
were donated by Avicultural Society members who participate in the EAZA
ESB (European Association of Zoos and Aquaria European Studbook)
programme for the Omei Shan Liocichla.
There are two other species of liocichla, the Red-faced L. phoenicea and
Steere's Liocichla L steerii. The Red-faced was first bred in the UK at the
Tropical Bird Gardens, Rode (sec Avicultural Magazine Vol. 102, No. 1, pp.23"
24 (1996)) and by B Massey in 1991. Steere's Liocichla was first recorded
as having been bred in the UK in 1990.
The paper describing the Bugun Liocichla and more photographs of the
specimens trapped can be downloaded from: www.indianbirds.in
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9507535" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264489" page_num="125" year="" vol="">
AL WABRA WILDLIFE PRESERVATION, QATAR:
WORKING WITH TURACOS Musophagidae spp.
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997052" page_id="56264489"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
125
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.940745" page_id="56264489"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
by Simon Braslund Jensen
The turacos are a primitive, almost primeval-looking family of medium
to large-sized birds, most closely related to the cuckoos. The 23 species are
distributed exclusively in tropical African forests and savannahs. Most
species are beautifully coloured in shades of green, blue and red, and are
well known for their unique feather pigments, the so-called turacin and
turacoverin, found only in this family.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.590972666666667" page_id="56264489"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
Sven Hammer!AWWP
A Prince Ruspoli's Turaco Tauraco ruspolti approaching a waterhole close to Arero,
Ethiopia,
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.9974376" page_id="56264489"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
Due to their appealing appearance, many of the species have for many
years been popular in zoos and private collections. However, just a few
years back, captive breeding would never have been considered as an option
for the conservation management of turacos, as they had long been considered
as delicate and rather difficult to breed in captivity.
In recent years the methods used for keeping and breeding turacos have
improved a great deal, due largely to the systematic approach by dedicated
individuals and public collections such as the zoos in Cologne, Germany
and Houston, Texas, USA. Now for the first time, it seems possible to
establish self-sustainable captive populations, in particular within the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998936" page_id="56264490"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
126
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.899514" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264490" page_num="126" year="" vol="">
JENSEN - TURACOS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990560926829269" page_id="56264490"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
framework of regional and international cooperation, with studbooks being
maintained to ensure the necessary exchange of bloodlines.
This is in line with the identification of more and more threats to several
turaco species in the wild, especially to some of the unique subspecies with
limited distribution. A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation (AWWP), owned by
Sheikh Saoud Bin Mohammad Bin Ali Al-Thani, has had a long standing
interest in improving our knowledge of some of the lesser known species
and subspecies, and has decided to invest resources into the turacos as a
group, with initial emphasis on two species, one in situ and the other ex situ.
The goals of AWWP were to investigate the current status of the little
known Prince Ruspoli's Turaco Tauraco ruspolii in Ethiopia and
simultaneously develop captive management strategies for turacos using a
common species, the Violet Turaco Musophaga violacea of West Africa, as
a model.
Prince Ruspoli's Turaco (in situ )
AWWP has coordinated and funded research on Prince Ruspoli's in
Ethiopia, which has resulted in major publications on the ecology of its
habitat, the juniper forests, and some of the problems this species faces in
the wild.
Prince Ruspoli's Turaco, which has a very limited distribution in south-
central Ethiopia, remains one of the least known of the turacos. It appears
that it is strongly connected with the endemic juniper forest found in this
region. For a long time the limits of its distribution remained undefined, as
did its ability to adapt to other types of habitat. It was believed that the
juniper forests were subject to a number of threats, including from large
numbers of feral goats, along with humans cutting down trees for much
needed firewood. Furthermore, there had been sightings of possible hybrids
between Prince Ruspoli's Turaco and the more common White-cheeked
species T. leucotis, that normally occurs further north in Ethiopia, isolated
from the juniper forests.
In 2003 AWWP employed Italian biologist Luca Borghesio to answer
some of these questions and if possible investigate what could be done to
secure the future of Prince Ruspoli's Turaco and its habitat. He put together
a research team in order to undertake an expedition to Ethiopia, in cooperation
with the Ethiopian Wildlife Natural History Society and the Ethiopian
Wildlife Conservation Organisation.
One of Borghesio's first tasks was to identify the extent of the juniper
forests and the decline that had occurred in the past decades. This was done
with the help of satellite images taken by the US military. Images covering
the entire region were purchased and after visiting the forest the specific
signatory structure of the undisturbed juniper forest was compared to that
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.575572" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264491" page_num="127" year="" vol="">
JENSEN - TURACOS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998278" page_id="56264491"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
127
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998943071428571" page_id="56264491"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
of destroyed forest, as well as that of other types of forest cover. This data
was then correlated to their specific coordinates on the satellite maps. The
process revealed an exact picture of the juniper forests in the entire region,
as well as giving clues to their status. The field expeditions also wanted to
determine if the turacos did in fact occur only in specific habitats. Results
were a little inconclusive, as the field work was cut short by Ethiopian
bureaucracy and our research permit being revoked. However, it was possible
to determine that Prince Ruspolfs Turaco was present also on the fringes of
its preferred habitat. In addition, it was proved that hybrids between Prince
Ruspoli's Turaco and the White-cheeked species exist where the two meet.
Based on historical data on the distribution of the White-cheeked Turaco
and the fact that so far only a few hybrids have been observed, it is fairly
certain that this is a recent development.
Our studies proved that the density of Prince Ruspoli's Turaco was larger
than expected, especially in suitable habitat, but also that this habitat is
shrinking at an alarming rate. The massive loss of habitat may be what
causes Prince Ruspoli's Turaco to move into other habitat, where it comes
into contact with the White-cheeked species, with the result that hybrids
sometimes occur. Or, it may also be possible that the juniper forest is
changing due to human activity causing deforestation. Another reason may
be that the planting of non-native and taller trees is allowing the White-
cheeked Turaco to encroach into traditional Prince Ruspoli's Turaco habitat.
The long-term effects of hybridization are unknown and will need further
studies.
Our studies provided conclusive evidence to validate a recommendation
to the HJCN/BirdLife to re-evaluate the threat status of Prince Ruspoli's
Turaco and to consider elevating it from Vulnerable to Endangered status.
The field trips also gave us a better understanding of some of the
humanitarian problems in the region. The lack of firewood is a major problem
for the local people, as is the lack of surface water, which makes it difficult
to cultivate the same areas of cleared land over a number of years. Amongst
the local people there is little understanding of the uniqueness of their forests,
therefore they cut down the trees indiscriminately and replant with introduced
species, leaving little space and food for the endemic fauna. The feral goats
remain uncontrolled and destroy forest even in isolated places. In particular,
they apparently damage the ground by impacting the soil, making it difficult
for juniper trees to grow. Large scale erosion is evident in places where the
forest has been cleared.
The only way it will be possible to counter some of these problems, will
be to help the local people to develop the region and make better use of
available resources and at the same time improve their appreciation of their
unique forests. It may be possible to make better use of the farmland by
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997825" page_id="56264492"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
128
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.893706" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264492" page_num="128" year="" vol="">
JENSEN - TURACOS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993917666666667" page_id="56264492"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
LANDSAT satellite image of survey area January 2002. Yellow spots indicate the
known presence of Prince Ruspoli's Turaco and the yellow line bounds its estimated
range. Forested areas are coloured red and Acacia-Combretum-Terminalia woodland
blue-green. Transitional habitats between forest and woodland are selected by this
turaco.
pumping up underground water and by controlling the goats. More effective
ways of burning wood can also be introduced. There is, for example, a
simple metal stove that compared to the traditional open fireplace, reduces
by half the amount of wood needed to boil water.
North-eastern Africa, including large parts of Ethiopia, seem to be
inescapably affected by global climate change, that is directly influenced by
humans. In few regions of the world are the direct effects as visible as here,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.575386" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264493" page_num="129" year="" vol="">
JENSEN - TURACOS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999049" page_id="56264493"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
129
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99591975" page_id="56264493"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
Remnant forest near Negele, on the southern edge of its range, Mankubsa Forest has
been destroyed in less than 15 years and the presence of Prince Ruspoli's Turaco in the
area is severely threatened. It was still observed there in February 2003 in isolated
groves of trees which had been spared deforestation.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994303" page_id="56264494"  page_num="130" year="" vol="">
130
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.898827" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264494" page_num="130" year="" vol="">
JENSEN - TURACOS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997081634146341" page_id="56264494"  page_num="130" year="" vol="">
with ongoing droughts and failing rains, as well as increasing temperatures.
How this is affecting the region in which Prince Ruspoli's Turaco lives is
unknown, but it is certainly an additional factor that warrants ongoing
monitoring (Flannery, 2005).
Violet Turaco (ex situ )
AWWP is using the Violet Turaco as a model species to identify the
needs of turacos in captivity and to learn how they respond to the conditions
available. With this information we can then continuously develop better
captive management guidelines and determine if it is feasible to consider
captive management and 'conservation breeding' for endangered species of
turaco. The purpose of this is to develop self-sustainable captive populations
to ensure the survival of endangered species such as Prince Ruspoli's Turaco,
which is currently not being maintained in captivity. Should it become
necessary, such populations could function as an invaluable back-up and a
research resource.
The Violet Turaco is a typical bird of gallery forest, often found in the
more lush growth of trees along rivers and creeks, as well as the margins of
forests. Its general behaviour is similar to that of most other turaco species
including, at least so we expect, Prince Ruspoli's Turaco. It feeds mainly
on fruits especially figs and occasionally eats insects, having a particular
liking for swarming termites.
Turacos are most frequently observed in pairs, but may occasionally be
seen in small groups, especially around favoured feeding trees and water
sources. At other times turacos are territorial birds that loudly proclaim
their presence in their territory and perform visual displays that often involve
their vividly coloured wings. Their nests, which are mostly fragile platforms
of sticks often placed in thick foliage, are not unlike those of pigeons.
Typically one to two eggs are laid and are incubated by both birds. The
incubation period of the Violet Turaco is longer than that of most other
species, being 24-26 days, rather than the usual 18-21 days. The young of
all turacos leave the nest very early, at less than three weeks old and even
before they can fly. They climb around in the nesting tree using both their
claws and their wings to hold on. In the wild the Violet Turaco has been
known to occasionally be assisted at the nest by helpers, thought to be young
from previous clutches. Such behaviour has not been recorded among most
of the other turacos.
The captive population of Violet Turacos at AWWP is based on two
founder pairs. Between 2000-2005, 22 young were hatched of which 13
were parent-reared and nine were hand-reared. In total we had 12 mortalities
of birds less than six months old, equally distributed between hand-reared
and parent-reared birds.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.575551" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264495" page_num="131" year="" vol="">
JENSEN - TURACQS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998668" page_id="56264495"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
131
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998496238095238" page_id="56264495"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
The turacos have been kept in a number of different set-ups, leaving us
with a fairly good idea of their optimal housing requirements. Violet Turacos
are easily disturbed by other birds of different species when kept in a mixed
species aviary and are particularly disturbed by others of their own species,
even when kept in neighbouring aviaries. It is therefore advisable to keep
breeding pairs secluded from other turacos and preferably some distance
away to avoid stress caused by other turacos' loud territorial calls. Attempts
to keep non-breeding birds in groups for any length of time have consistently
failed, both in small aviaries and in very large free flight aviaries, even in
the case of relatively young birds. However, on one occasion an unrelated
trio, consisting of one male and two females, lived together in the large
free-flight aviary, with all three together attending and fiercely defending a
nest. So far they have failed to rear any offspring, which may very well be
related to the competition from other birds in the aviary. Normally attempts
to keep more than two birds together result in aggression at some point, but
two birds, even if they are the same sex, normally get on well together without
any problems. For breeding, largish aviaries 8m long x 5m wide x 4m high
(approx. 26ft long x 16ft wide x 13ft high), that are well-planted and provide
plenty of hiding places and shade, have proved most successful. The nest
baskets are placed high in the aviary and the birds are provided with artificial
rain several times a day.
Adult Violet Turacos seem to adapt well to the climatic conditions in
Qatar, both in the blazing heat of the summer when the temperature may
reach up to 55*C (131 *F) and in the winter when the night time temperature
drops to 5*C (41 *F). However, young birds, particularly nestlings, suffer in
the heat and the eggs do not hatch when it becomes too hot, so an air-
conditioned shelter is a big advantage.
The turacos are somewhat nervous in disposition and even tame, hand-
reared birds, are easily flushed and frightened. This is particularly true of
birds that are new to an aviary, and we have seen a few birds with injuries
and even fatalities as the result of flying against the mesh. By using mesh
that is flexible this risk is much reduced. Being careful and quiet around
cages and aviaries with recently transferred birds is also important. Turacos
are also nervous when being handled and holding them for too long,
particularly in hot weather, should be avoided. Attention should also be
paid to the fact that turacos are apt to struggle a lot when being held, and are
loose feathered, making them difficult to hold on to.
Turacos can be tough on each other and on several occasions we have
suspected aggression by the adult male towards fledglings. It can be an
advantage to remove the young early if aggression is suspected. The
fledglings can be placed in a neighbouring cage or in a small cage in the
aviary, and the parents will often continue to feed the young through the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997042" page_id="56264496"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
132
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.709244" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264496" page_num="132" year="" vol="">
JENSEN - TURACOS
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.43703">
Luca Borghesio
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99465975" page_id="56264496"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
Transitional habitat between Juniperus-Podocarpus forest and
Combretum-Terminalia woodland just south of Kibre Mengist. Up to 10-20 Prince
Ruspoli's Turacos can be seen in a day, but the habitat is changing rapidly, seemingly
in favour of the White-cheeked species.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.371122" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264496" page_num="132" year="" vol="">
Catrin Hammer/AWWP
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999664166666667" page_id="56264496"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
The largest holding facility for turacos at AWWP is 1,800 sq m (approx. 19,375 sq ft),
but can only hold three turacos without aggression occurring sooner or later.
mesh. With many turaco species, males have been known to kill their mates,
so care must be taken to provide plenty of potential hiding places, not just
low down but also at the higher levels of the aviary. It may be worth
mentioning that the courtship behaviour of turacos often includes a ritualized
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.572514" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264497" page_num="133" year="" vol="">
JENSEN - TURACOS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994008" page_id="56264497"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
133
</page>
<table confidence="0.904353" page_id="56264497"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
Simon Bruslund Jensen!AWWP
Five days old Violet Turaco being fed using a syringe.
Adult pair of Violet Turacos calling in duet.
</table>
<page confidence="0.999517" page_id="56264498"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
134
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.901625" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264498" page_num="134" year="" vol="">
JENSEN - TURACOS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999657142857142" page_id="56264498"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
chase, that may become aggressive if the birds are confined in too small an
aviary and if no hiding places are available. Sliding doors between adjacent
aviaries is a good idea, as it provides the option of separating birds for short
periods without causing too much disturbance; it is also useful when pairing
up or flocking birds.
At AWWP the turacos' diet consists mainly of fresh fruits. Banana, pear
and papaya (pawpaw) are fed daily, with apple, mango and grapes, as well
as a number of local seasonal fruits, being added to the diet to provide variety.
We also offer them greenfood in the form of parsley and occasionally
dandelion leaves. In addition the birds are offered small amounts of a dried
insectivore mix in the morning and Hill Mynah pellets (fed dry) in the
afternoon. A few mealworms are normally given once or twice a week only,
but can be offered a little more frequently when the birds are breeding.
Turacos have a high metabolism and eat large amounts of food and it is
important that the vast majority of their diet consists of fruit, of which they
will consume more than 1 OOg a day. Foods other than fruit must be restricted
otherwise they may cause obesity and other health problems.
During breeding the birds are fed the same diet as usual, except that
once chicks are in the nest, larger amounts of food are needed. It may be
necessary to feed them several times a day to ensure that fresh food is always
available. A breeding pair is very faithful to a successful nest site and will
use it over and over again. The nest itself is a very simple collection of a
few sticks and twigs and very little improvement is made to it between
clutches. Some pairs do not use nest material at all, instead the female lays
the eggs directly on the bottom of the nest basket provided. It is though
important to provide such birds with some nest material to support the eggs
and most importantly to give the chicks something to grip onto. Moving the
nest or transferring the birds to another aviary may very well disrupt the
entire breeding season. Pairs prefer to use nest baskets placed high in the
aviary, preferably in a dark comer. It is important that fine branches are
available close to the nest, as the chicks will leave the nest before they are
able to fly and will possibly even climb back onto the nest; large branches
seem to deter the parents from using the nest site. Most ordinary baskets
will be accepted by the birds. We have found that a good size is about 20cm
x 20 cm (approx. 8 in x 8 in) and have the impression that baskets with high
sides are preferred and birds using them are less sensitive to disturbance;
they also prefer to be able to see through the bottom of the basket. Wooden
frames 22cm x 22cm x 15cm high (approx. 8 V 2 in x 8 V 2 in x 6 in high) with
the bottom made of fine mesh are a good alternative. Violet Turacos are
able to breed in their second year; one female at AWWP produced her first
eggs when aged one year and five months old.
If eggs have to be removed for artificial incubation, a temperature of
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.574984" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264499" page_num="135" year="" vol="">
JENSEN - TURACOS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998376" page_id="56264499"  page_num="135" year="" vol="">
135
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.99833">
Table 1. Diet sheet.
</tableCaption>
<page confidence="0.998352" page_id="56264500"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
136
</page>
<table confidence="0.8030412" page_id="56264500"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
JENSEN - TURACOS
Simon Bruslund Jensen/AWWP
Immature Violet Turaco hand-reared at AWWP: note the position of the toes.
Simon Bruslund Jensen!AWWP
Adult Violet Turaco.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.575439" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264501" page_num="137" year="" vol="">
JENSEN - TURACOS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998568" page_id="56264501"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
137
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.996303695652174" page_id="56264501"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
37.5*C-37.8*C (99.5*F-100*F) and a relative humidity of45%-55% work
quite well. The eggs have to be turned five to 12 times a day. Turaco eggs
are pure white and very round almost entirely spherical in shape. We have
often found them to be relatively fragile without being thin-shelled.
Freshly hatched Violet Turacos chicks are, like those of most turacos,
covered with fluffy black down. They open their eyes on the first day and
after a week the first pin-feathers emerge on the wings. Chicks being hand-
reared are fed fruit pulp mixed with a commercial hand-rearing formula
made for parrots, which can be administered through a syringe. Gradually
more and more whole pieces of fruit and soaked pieces of Hill Mynah pellets
are added to the diet and can be offered using forceps at the side. Small
amounts of vitamins and minerals have to be added to the mix at all times to
avoid any problems with bone development. Young chicks are fed every
IV 2 hours during a 14-hour day period but are not fed at night when they
should be given the opportunity to rest. The feeding intervals are gradually
increased to every three hours by about day 20. At this point the chicks can
be offered some food in a small bowl placed in the brooder. It is an advantage
to wean the chicks early to avoid them becoming imprinted on humans.
Just after hatching, the temperature in the brooder should be about 37*C
(98.6*F) and then gradually lowered to about 30*C (86*F) by about day 20.
Hand-reared young turacos that have received minimum attention become
good parents themselves whereas Imprinted birds, when they are breeding,
often become very aggressive towards humans.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.610369">
Table 2. Average weight gain of three chicks from day one to day 26.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.267332" page_id="56264501"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
Weight gain of Violet Turaco chicks
Days
</figure>
<page confidence="0.998693" page_id="56264502"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
138
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.898962" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264502" page_num="138" year="" vol="">
JENSEN - TURACOS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.93789425" page_id="56264502"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
The average body weight of healthy male Violet Turacos kept at AWWP
is approximately 340g (range 315g~360g) and the average body weight of
females is 3Q5g (range 277g-354g).
Products mentioned in the text
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.408663111111111" page_id="56264502"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
Aleckwa Honigfutter grob (insectivore food with honey): supplied by Aleckwa Tiemahmng,
Germany (websiterwww.aleckwa.de).
Wittemolen Beo Care Plus Granulate (Hill Mynah pellets): supplied by Wittemolen, the
Netherlands (website:www.wittemolen.com).
Zeigler Bird of Paradise Pellet (low iron pellet): supplied by Zeigler Bros., Inc., USA
(website: w w w.zeiglerfeed. com).
Nekton-Tonic F, -S and -MSA (supplements): supplied by Guenter Enderle, Nekton Produkte,
Germany (website:www.nekton.de).
Bibliography
</table>
<reference confidence="0.775179235294118">
Borghesio, L., Giannetti, K. Ndang'ang'a, K., Shimelis, A., Borghesia, A., Rizzo, D. and Fufa,
K. 2004. A reassessment of the conservation status of Prince Ruspoli's Tauraco ruspolii.
African Bird Club Bulletin 11,2:104-111.
Borghesio, L., Giannetti, F., Ndang'ang'a, K. and Shimelis, A. 2004. The present conservation
status of Juniperus forests in the South Ethiopian Endemic Bird Area. African Journal of
Ecology, 42:137-143.
Borghesio, L. and Massa, R. 2000. Status and conservation of Prince Ruspoli's Turaco Tauraco
ruspolii. Ostrich 71:355-358.
Borghesio, L. 1997. Field observations on Prince Ruspoiks Turaco Tauraco ruspolii. Scopus
19:83-91.
del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A. and Sangatal. J. (eds.). 1997. Handbook of the Birds of the World.
Vol.4. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona.
Flannery, T. 2005. The Weather Makers, The history and future impact of climate change.
Penguin Books.
Forshaw, I. M. 2002. Turacos, A Natural History of the Musophagidae. Nokormis Editions,
Melbourne, Australia.
Habermehl, H. 1999. The Economics of Improved Stoves: Guide to Micro- and Macroeconomic
</reference>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.629361">
Analysis and Data Assessment. Eschbom, GTZ.
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.921846357142857" page_id="56264502"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
Lamount, M. 2004. Some observations of Captive Musophagidae. AFAWatchBird 32,1:52-
56.
Lemould, J-M. and Seitre, R. 2004. Does hybridisation with White-cheeked Turaco Tauraco
leucotis represent a threat for Prince Ruspoli's Turaco? African Bird Club Bulletin 11,2:112-
116.
Simon Bruslund Jensen is Curator of Birds at Al Wabra Wildlife
Preservation, PO Box 44069, Al Shahaniyah, State of Qatar. Website:
awwp. alwabra. com/E-maihawwp. bird@aiwa.bra. com
Al Wabra Wildlife Preservation (&amp;apos;AWWP) is a private institution owned
by HE Sheikh Saoud Bin Mohammad Bin AH Al-Thanl The breeding centre
for rare and endangered wildlife, which has state of the art facilities,
including climate control and artificial rainfall systems, is located in central
Qatar, and appears literally as a lush green oasis in the middle of a stony
desert.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999011" page_id="56264503"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
139
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.970639" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264503" page_num="139" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEW
INTERNATIONAL ZOO YEARBOOK
VOLUME 40
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994597486486487" page_id="56264503"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
Section 1 (pp. 1-217) of the latest International Zoo Yearbook is devoted
to elephants and rhinoceros, it is not until one gets to Section 2 (pp.221-
378), The Developing Zoo World, that one comes to three articles on birds.
The first of these concerns the breeding and hand-rearing of Storm's
Stork Ciconia stormi at the Zoological Society of San Diego. The breeding
pair housed off exhibit at San Diego Wild Animal Park (SDWAP), the subject
of the study, produced 34 eggs (two to four eggs per clutch) over the four
year period. Twelve young were hatched, eight of which survived. The
authors describe the husbandry techniques and courtship, incubation both
by the parents and in an incubator, and the growth and development of the
chicks. There are photos of chicks at one day, three days, seven to 10 days
and at 37 days, plus a growth curve graph.
The second article describes the hand-rearing of a group of Greater
Flamingos Phoenicopterus ruber roseus for translocation from The Wildfowl
&amp; Wetlands Trust (WWT), Slimbridge to Auckland Zoo, New Zealand.
WWT agreed to provide Auckland Zoo with 20 hand-reared Greater
Flamingos from the Slimbridge flock of 178 birds. The eggs were hatched
and the chicks were hand-reared in a pre-export isolation facility, as required
by the New Zealand Ministry of Agriculture and Forestry. The authors
describe the isolation facility, egg-laying, incubation, housing and
development of the chicks (with a graph plotting daily body-mass
measurements), feeding (Table 1 lists the ingredients of the diet and Table 2
the average quantities of food given), health monitoring, then the eventual
translocation when the chicks were aged an average 55 days (range 33-71
days) and quarantine in New Zealand. One hundred and one days after the
first chick had hatched at Slimbridge, 18 Greater Flamingos were transferred
to the zoo's African savannah exhibit (two died while in quarantine). It is
hoped that the 18 flamingos will become the founders of a self-sustaining
population of Greater Flamingos in the Australasian region.
Of greatest interest is likely to be the article describing the reproduction
of the Bali Starling Leucopsar rothschildi at the Durrell Wildlife Conservation
Trust, Jersey. To understand better the reproductive activity of this species,
cameras were placed in the nest boxes of six pairs. Details of egg-laying
and egg turning were recorded for 16 clutches and incubation data were
recorded for 14 clutches.
Forty-eight eggs were laid, resulting in a mean 2.8 eggs per clutch. The
mean incubation period was 15.5 days. Of the 23 chicks that hatched, only
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996083" page_id="56264504"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
140
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.951978" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264504" page_num="140" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEW
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9876125" page_id="56264504"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
five birds survived up to 30 days (a mortality rate of 78%). One pair reared
three chicks and two others were hand-reared. They fledged at approximately
28 days. The hatching success (23 of 34 fertile eggs, 68%) is said to be
consistent with other reports from captivity and the wild. In the wild the
average clutch size is three eggs, of which two hatch and usually one chick
is reared.
The authors suggest that Jersey's low success rate may have been because
the quality or quantity of food was not sufficient; the lack of food in the
early morning (the parents did not get their first feed of the day until 8.00am)
may also have had a deleterious effect. Food in captivity may lack sufficient
variety the authors suggest, and a more varied diet could lead to increased
parental interest in foraging and feeding and a decrease in the occurrence of
feather plucking.
The Reference Section, Section 3 (pp.381-516), includes a list of the
zoos and aquariums of the world and a list of international studbooks,
including those for several bird species.
For information on obtaining the latest International Zoo Yearbook
Volume 40, would-be subscribers are advised to go to the Blackwell
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.4936485">
Publishing website:www.blackwellpublishing.com/izy
Malcolm Ellis
</subsectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.979997" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264504" page_num="140" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.948752" page_id="56264504"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
The society has a large stock of back issues mostly from 1935 onwards
but there are also some earlier issues still available. They are priced #3.00
each (including p&amp;p). Please check availability before placing an order.
Overseas members may be able to pay by credit card through a Paypal
invoice, but this service is not available in all countries. All enquiries should
be addressed to: P. Boulden, Hon. Secretary/Treasurer, Avicultural Society,
Arcadia, The Mounts, East Allington, Totnes, Devon TQ9 7JQ, UK or
E-mail:admin@avisoc. co.uk
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998551" page_id="56264505"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
141
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9824365" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264505" page_num="141" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
LEAR'S MACAW BRED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.982726" page_id="56264505"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
Earlier this year, A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation (AWWP) in Qatar,
succeeded in hatching its first Lear's Macaw Anodorhynchus leari. AWWP
has four pairs of Lear's Macaws, which it has had on loan from the Brazilian
Government since 2004. This species has proved difficult to breed in captivity
and until this recent success, had not been bred successfully officially since
1984.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.499013">
Copyright AWWP
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.973772" page_id="56264505"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
Lear's Macaw chick aged 34 days.
AWWP's breeding pair laid a clutch of three eggs, two of which were
fertile. However, one of the chicks died very early during the incubation
period; the other hatched successfully on July 14th 2006. The breeding
programme is part of an international effort and is being undertaken in
cooperation with the Brazilian Government's Natural Heritage Department
(IB AM A). The aim is to establish a viable captive population, as part of a
conservation programme to secure the long-term future of this Critically
Endangered species.
AWWP's successful breeding of a Lear's Macaw represents the first
offspring bred as part of the official IBAMA-initiated captive-breeding
programme. This breakthrough has provided important breeding data that
will be helpful to other institutions participating in the breeding programme
and will hopefully contribute to further breeding success with this species.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998736" page_id="56264506"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
142
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.983016" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264506" page_num="142" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
BRED FOR THE FIRST TIME
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999018" page_id="56264506"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
The pair of Sulawesi Tarictic Hombills Penelopides exarhatus sanfordi
which arrived at Whipsnade Wild Animal Park from San Diego Wild Animal
Park in 2005 (see News &amp; Views Vol. 112, No. 1, p.47 (2006)) has bred. It is
the first time that the Sulawesi Tarictic Hombill has been bred in the UK
and may be a European first. The female broke out of the nest on September
20th, followed by a single young one.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.819185" page_id="56264506"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.795346" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264506" page_num="142" year="" vol="">
ARACARIS HATCHED IN DALLAS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.88485075" page_id="56264506"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
Josef Lindholm, Senior Aviculturist at The Dallas World Aquarium,
reports that so far in 2006, nine Green Aracaris Pteroglossus viridis have
been reared from four clutches of eggs (two were hatched by a female less
than a year old, and four were from a single clutch). The pair of Ivory(TM)
billed Aracaris P. flavirostris, which hatched two chicks last year (the first
hatched outside South America), has hatched three chicks this year. The
first Crimson-rumped Toucanet Aulacorhynchus haematopygus in almost
two years has also been hatched.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.332613" page_id="56264506"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.377972" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264506" page_num="142" year="" vol="">
CIRL BUNTINGS RELEASED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.862567090909091" page_id="56264506"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
More than 70 Cirl Buntings Emheriza cirlus have been released in south
Cornwall, here in south-west England, as part of an innovative project by
the RSPB (Royal Society for the Protection of Birds), Paignton Zoo
Environmental Park, Natural England (the enlarged organisation which has
replaced English Nature) and the National Trust.
Cirl Bunting chicks were collected under licence earlier this year by the
former English Nature from several sites in south Devon and hand-reared
by aviculturists from Paignton Zoo Enviromental Park, and it is these birds
that have been released in south Cornwall. It is said to be the first European
reintroduction of a small farmland bird.
The Cirl Bunting was once widespread in the UK, being found along the
south coast of England, north to the Midlands and Wales. It requires weedy
stubble fields on which it can feed on seeds and spilled grain during the
winter months and insect-rich land with hedges in which it can nest during
the summer months, but changes in farming practises led to a loss of such
habitat and its decline, until eventually it was restricted to a small area of
south Devon. Only 118 pairs remained in 1989, but since 1993 the RSPB
has worked with farmers, landowners and partner organisations to ensure
that the Cirl Bunting has suitable places to live, feed and breed. As a result
the population has increased to more than 700 pairs.
The reintroduction project will run for the next three years, so that enough
birds can be released to create a sustainable population.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.70008" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264507" page_num="143" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998145" page_id="56264507"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
143
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.973145" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264507" page_num="143" year="" vol="">
BRED FOR THE FOURTH TIME
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.7975" page_id="56264507"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
London Zoo has succeeded for the fourth time in breeding the Toco
Toucan Ramphastos toco. Earlier this year three young were fledged.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.559234" page_id="56264507"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.851689" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264507" page_num="143" year="" vol="">
MORE CONSERVATIONALLY RELEVANT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994017428571429" page_id="56264507"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
Last year Chester Zoo rationalised its bird collection to make it more
conservationally relevant. Additions to the collection included Chestnut-
backed Thrush Zoothera dohertyi , Orange-headed Ground Thrush Z. citrina ,
Chestnut Thrush Turdus rubrocanus, White-naped Yuhina Yuhina bakeri
and Timor Zebra Finch Taeniopygia g. guttata. It also acquired 10 Kikuyu
White-eyes Zosterops kikuyuensis, specifically to help build the skills of the
bird staff involved in the incubation and rearing in the field of the Critically
Endangered Olive White-eye Z. olivacea. The zoo also added to the
collection three pairs of Madagascan Fody Foudia madagascariensis, a
species very similar to the Critically Endangered Mauritius Fody F. rubra ,
which Chester Zoo staff travel to Mauritius each year to incubate, hand-rear
and reintroduce to the wild as part of its field support to Mauritius.
This year Chester Zoo had another exceptionally good breeding season
with more than 80 species laying eggs. The most noteworthy breeding was
of two Javan Rhinoceros Hombill Buceros rhinoceros silvestris chicks. The
parents have been together at the zoo for 11 years and the female is known
to be at least 26 years old. It is the first time that the Rhinoceros Hombill
has been bred in the UK.
The zoo has acquired a new female Great Hombill B. bicornis from
Alphen in the Netherlands. She is more than 37 years old and came originally
from the wild. She will be paired with the zoo's 27 year old male. The
Chestnut-backed Thrushes acquired in 2005 immediately settled in the zoo's
Tropical Realm and produced their first brood of three chicks. Elsewhere in
the zoo a pair of Northern Lapwing Vanellus vanellus, succeeded in rearing
a chick. The parents were hatched from eggs rescued from the mnway at
Hawarden Airport, where wild lapwings nest occasionally in areas that are
unsafe for birds and pose a potential hazard to aircraft.
A White-naped Crane Grus vipio chick hatched in late April. The egg
was artificially incubated, then returned to the pair at hatching. It is the first
offspring sired at the zoo by its new 17 year old male crane which was
hatched at Frankfurt Zoo. Chester's old male died in January 2005. It was
more than 60 years old. He was obtained by London Zoo from Alfred Ezra
in 1949 and was transferred from Whipsnade to Chester in 1997. Chester's
pair of Great Grey Owls Strix nebulosa lapponica successfully fledged four
chicks. Since being at the zoo the pair has produced a total of 18 young.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999595" page_id="56264508"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
144
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9717825" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264508" page_num="144" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
SECOND LESSER BIRD OF PARADISE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.739905333333333" page_id="56264508"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
Toledo Zoo, Ohio, USA, has bred a second Lesser Bird of Paradise
Paradisaea minor. The first chick was hand-reared, but this chick was
successfully reared by its parents.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.742912" page_id="56264508"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.871535" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264508" page_num="144" year="" vol="">
SAVING ENDANGERED PACIFIC PARROTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.975086" page_id="56264508"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
Last year's Birdfair (British Birdwatching Fair) raised a record #200,000
(approx. US$370,000) to support BirdLife International's work conserving
Gurney's Pitta Pitta gurneyi in Myanmar and Thailand (see Avicultural
Magazine Vol.Ill, No.4, p. 188 (2005)). This year's Birdfair raised funds
for BirdLife International's Pacific programme, which will focus on five
parrots, the New Caledonian Lorikeet Charmosyna diadema , Uvea Parakeet
Eunymphicus cornutus uvaeensis , Rimatara or Kuhl's Lorikeet Vini kuhlii,
Ultramarine Lorikeet V. ultramarina and Red-throated Lorikeet C. amabilis.
It is hoped to rediscover and conserve the New Caledonian Lorikeet,
thought to have last been seen in 1953 or 1954 and in 1976. A similar
search will be made for the Red-throated Lorikeet of Fiji. A recent three
month survey failed to find any trace of it. The Rimatara or Kuhl's Lorikeet
and the Ultramarine Lorikeet, along with the Uvea Parakeet, will benefit
from specifically targeted actions. Twenty Rimatara or Kuhl's Lorikeets
will be translocated to the island of Atiue, which is free of the Black Rat
Rattus rattus. The latter having arrived on Rimatara during the building of
an airport. Another species, the Blue or Tahitian Lorikeet V. peruviana , will
also benefit from the programme, as will many other Pacific birds on the
Cook Islands, Fiji, Samoa, New Caledonia and French Polynesia, the five
project countries.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.59462" page_id="56264508"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.959938" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264508" page_num="144" year="" vol="">
KILLED IN AN ENCOUNTER WITH AN ELEPHANT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9563246" page_id="56264508"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
Italian aristocrat and explorer Prince Eugenio Ruspoli (1866-1893), after
whom Prince Ruspoli's Turaco Tauraco ruspolii was named, travelled in
Ethiopia from 1891-1893. He was killed in an "encounter with an elephant"
which he had wounded, before he had got around to recording the locality
and date (in 1892 or 1893) that he collected the turaco which bears his name.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.943118" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264509" page_num="" year="" vol="">
DIANA HOLLOWAY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.988323866666667" page_id="56264509"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Aviculture lost one of its greatest practioners with the passing of Diana
Holloway on Sunday, July 16th 2006.
Blackbrook Zoological Park and Hillside Wildfowl contain so many avian
jewels, from penguins to pelicans, pheasants to waterfowl, ibis to crowned
pigeons, flamingos, cranes and storks, and so many other delights that it is
hard to imagine that it was all created by this remarkable lady, actively
supported by her son Mark.
Diana served as President of the British Waterfowl Association, a Director
of the International Wild Waterfowl Association and, of course, a Vice
President of the Avicultural Society.
Diana's modesty and easy nature endeared her to many and her passing
will be mourned by all who knew her. Our sincere condolences to Mark at
this very sad time and I know he will want to continue with this work and
build up the two collections to greater heights in the future as a living
memorial to a fine creative lady.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.770141333333333" page_id="56264509"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Christopher Marler
INTERNATIONAL
ZOO NEWS
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.9476565625" page_id="56264509"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
For more than half a century, International Zoo News
(/ZAO has provided the zoos and aquariums of the
world with a regular forum for the exchange of news,
information and ideas. Besides the latest news from
scores of animal collections, IZN regularly contains
original feature articles on the captive management of wild animals,
profiles of major collections, reviews of the latest zoological books,
and summaries of recent articles from other zoo publications around
the world. IZN also highlights the importance of captive breeding
for the survival of endangered animal species, and carries many
reports on reintroduction and other in situ conservation projects.
Annual subscription for 8 issues, post paid: U.K. #45.00; overseas
(surface mail) #48.00, [euro]75.00 or US$80.00; airmail #53.00, [euro]80.00
or US$90.00. For a free sample copy, contact the editorial office:
IZN, Fealquoy, Rousay, Orkney KW17 2PS, U.K. (E-mail:
ngouldizn@ aol.com)
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.804283" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264510" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.93759115" page_id="56264510"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Breeding the Black-faced Laughingthrush Garrulax affinis
by Nigel Hewston.97
Avicultural support for the Echo Parakeet Programme on Mauritius
by Roger Wilkinson ... 102
Breeding the Elegant Crested Tinamou Eudromia e. elegans
by Bryan Andrews &amp;apos;.:.Ill
Breeding the White-headed Mousebird Colius leucocephalus
by Bryan Andrews.116
Breeding the Black-capped Social Weaver Pseudonigrita cabanisi
by Martin Davies.119
Too rare to collect
The discovery of a new species of liocichla. 123
A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation, Qatar:
working with turacos Musophagidae spp.
by Simon Bruslund Jensen. 125
Book Review
International Zoo Yearbook. 139
News &amp; Views. 141
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</table>
</algorithms>
