<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.755166" page_id="56261214"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 112
No. 4
2006
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="method" page_id="56261215" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990837" page_id="56261215"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2006 as for 2005: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.5855" genericHeader="method" page_id="56261215" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.972357" page_id="56261215"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, ARCADIA, THE MOUNTS, TOTNES, DEVON TQ9 7QJ, UK.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TNI3 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail: Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998476" genericHeader="method" page_id="56261215" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982477333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.760148" genericHeader="method" page_id="56261216" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.268889" page_id="56261216"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 112 - No. 4 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2006
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.891703" genericHeader="method" page_id="56261216" page_num="" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE RED-BILLED BUFFALO-WEAVER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.87294390625" page_id="56261216"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Bulbalornis niger intermedius
by Carl Gamham
The Red-billed Buffalo-Weaver has three recognised subspecies - B. n.
niger, B. n. militaris and B. n. intermedius - the latter being a comparatively
recent classification change, as it was formerly believed to be a subspecies
of the White-billed Buffalo-Weaver 5. albirostris. The author has been unable
to trace identification details for the subspecies. (In the recently published
(2005) Roberts - Birds of Southern Africa, Seventh Edition, the geographical
variation is described as clinal and slight and largely down to the shade of
plumage coloration and mottling on the underparts of the female. Only B.
n. niger and B. n. intermedius are recognised, not B. n. militaris, described
by Clancey from the Luangwa Valley, Zambia. There are two populations in
Zambia (it also occurs in Zimbabwe and other neighbouring countries) and
both were considered to be of the nominate form by Benson et al. (The Birds
of Zambia, 1971), though it was noted that the Luangwa Valley birds were
smaller. Until there is further study to clarify whether or not the variation is
well-marked and consistent, the authors have taken a conservative approach
and consider B. n. militaris to be synonymous with the nominate form. -
Ed.).
Seen at a distance, the males appear to be black, but when held in the
hand, they are seen to be a very dark charcoal grey. They have variable
small patches of white on the sides of the breast (the largest usually just in
front of the wing butts) and on the flanks, and have white-edged primaries.
In breeding males the bill is deep waxy orange or reddish, tipped black, but
is yellowish-orange in birds out of breeding condition. The legs and feet are
greyish yellow, or pale orange to pinkish or reddish brown.
There is some disagreement in the sources available to me as to the
description of the females, not least perhaps because there is an almost total
lack of referral of comments to particular subspecies and also due ,to the
comparatively recent inclusion of B. n. intermedius as a subspecies of B.
niger. The females familiar to the author - originating probably, from Tanzania
and therefore B. n. intermedius - are charcoal grey above and white below,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999456" page_id="56261217"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
146
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.948051" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261217" page_num="146" year="" vol="">
GARNHAM - RED-BILLED BUFFALO-WEAVER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.992491119047619" page_id="56261217"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
with heavy dark mottling, which is less dense on the throat and belly. The
bill is horn-coloured, with a dark tip.
Both sexes are approximately 25cm (9in) long and weigh about 80g.
They are long, slim birds, with fairly long tails. Nestlings are probably
sexable while still in the nest. Males are probably darker and do not have
pale edges to the flight feathers. Information received also indicates that
male chicks get an orange tint to their horn-coloured bill approximately two
weeks after fledging, though this has not been confirmed.
This species is native to large parts of Africa. The nominate form occurs
from northern South Africa northwards. How far northwards it extends
depends on whether B.n.militaris is regarded as a valid subspecies or as
synonymous with the nominate form (see above). B. n. intermedius occurs
from central Tanzania, northwards through Kenya to southern Somalia,
southern Ethiopia and southern Sudan. The Red-billed Buffalo Weaver's
preference is for dry savannah and open woodland, particularly if there are
large trees - or man-made structures such as telegraph poles or electricity
pylons - which can provide nest sites.
A group of 11 birds was obtained during the winter of 2005-2006. The
group consisted of two adult males and nine other birds including some
which were believed to be immature males, based on the best guesses that
could be made from the conflicting accounts in the literature about the
appearance of the females.
The birds were initially housed in box cages in an unheated, but frost-
free, timber shed until they were seen to be eating adequate amounts of food
and a warm spell of weather allowed them to be transferred to an outside
aviary. They readily ate my standard softbill diet - soaked and finely crumbled
Purina Omega Tasty Original (a complete compound, dog food, containing
23% protein and 10% oil), but sampled very few seeds. When they eventually
started eating seed they proved to be extremely conservative in their choice
and currently receive a mix of approximately 75% canary seed, with millets,
wheat, sorghum, hemp and rape making up the remainder. Substantial
amounts of seed are eaten now, in contrast to the White-headed Buffalo
Weaver Dinemellia dinemelli , which seldom eats seed at all in captivity. As
would be expected the seed is de-husked before being swallowed. The birds
are fed seed ad-lib and eat approximately 6g dry weight of dog food per day.
The birds were transferred to an aviary 12ft x 6ft x 6ft tall (approx. 3.6m
x 1.8m x 1.8m tall) with one end forming a 4ft x 6ft (approx. 1.2m x 1.8m),
roofed and enclosed shelter, connected via a pop-hole to the remaining part
of the aviary, which was open on all sides. Within the shelter a 12mm (approx.
V 2 in) diameter dowel perch some 20cm (approx. 8in) from the aviary roof
was provided along the 6ft (approx. 1.8m) length, fitted on the underside of
which was an electric soil-warming cable set to come on when the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.775049" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261218" page_num="147" year="" vol="">
GARNHAM - RED-BILLED BUFFALO-WEAVER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999021" page_id="56261218"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
147
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999433904761905" page_id="56261218"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
temperature dropped to 5*C (41 *F). A nightlight was also provided.
The outside flight was provided with natural perching and a 50mm (2in)
mesh wire netting hammock strung from the roof to form an approximate
half-cylinder about 60cm (almost 2ft) in diameter x 90cm (3ft) long. This
was provided with a small number of twiggy branches to act as supports for
any nest or nests.
Early in May 2006 the colour of the bill of one of the males deepened
and he started construction of a stick nest on one side of the netting hammock.
Materials supplied consisted of beech and cupressus twigs 2mm-4mm in
diameter and 20cm-30cm (approx. 8in-1 ft) long. These were intentionally
supplied with few forks/as little branching as possible, as construction was
achieved by the male threading the twigs into any existing mass by pushing
the twig to his side, while held in his bill. If a new twig would not feed into
the existing mass, the male would turn it around and try to feed it in from
the opposite end.
The first nest was ignored by the females, even though the male frequently
displayed with dropped wings and fanned tail, and called loudly. In early
June, the same male moved the entire nest from one side of the wire netting
hammock, to the other - a distance of only some 40cm (1ft 4in) or so, which
took him one day. Two females immediately showed interest and started
building within the stick nest using fresh green grass approximately 60cm
(almost 2ft) long. Coconut fibre, hay, straw and raffia were all ignored.
Although a laurel bush in the flight was substantially stripped of leaves,
very few fragments of these leaves were found in the nests.
As more sticks were offered, the nest grew and the second male started
to construct a nest on the opposite side of the netting hammock, in the position
chosen originally by the first male. In total six grass nests were built, four
in the stick nest of the dominant male and two in the smaller stick nest of the
subordinate male. As more sticks were provided, and within the constraints
imposed by the available support, twig tunnels were constructed to the active
nests. They sloped slightly upwards into the nests and were noticeably curved
- neither orientation apparently being dictated by available support for the
tunnels. The longest measured approximately 60cm (almost 2ft) - sufficient
to make reaching the grass nest barely possible.
One clutch of two, three of three and one clutch of four eggs were laid.
The eggs, which measured approximately 25mm x 20mm, were off-white
and heavily marked with pale grey smudges. Incubation, very unusually
for a passerine, started after the first egg had been laid. The first chick
hatched June 25th - June 26th, after an incubation period of 11 days. On
hatching, the chicks were an intense, vivid pink-orange colour all over. The
females sat very tightly and often had to be lifted from the nests to enable
inspection to take place. The growth of the chicks, particularly the feet and
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998929" page_id="56261219"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
148
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.946343" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261219" page_num="148" year="" vol="">
GARNHAM - RED-BILLED BULLALO-WEAVER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998356690476191" page_id="56261219"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
legs, was initially very fast and they had to be close-ringed (banded) at
approximately seven days old. Closed rings size M (5mm) were used. The
nestling period was in the order of 20-22 days.
Due to the number of adults and the number of potential chicks involved,
along with the fact that frozen crickets, available in plentiful supply, were
ignored, the livefood offered for rearing was frozen blow-fly maggots
(pinkies). These were offered several times each day with the birds
consuming about [ /i pint (200ml-300ml) a day once there were several chicks
in the nests. Unfortunately, when the oldest chick was 14 days old, a batch
of maggots contaminated with botulism was provided. The subordinate
male and several chicks of various ages died and were found in the nests.
Thereafter the livefood was changed to mealworms.
A week later, livefood was not supplied for about six hours, although a
generous amount of mealworms had been supplied prior to this. Following
this break in the supply of livefood, four chicks were found dead and outside
of the nests. A few days later, when livefood was not supplied for
approximately three hours, the nests were inspected. The oldest chick, about
12 days old, from a nest of two, was found to be healthy and very much
alive, half-way down the tunnel entrance to the nest.
While I do not propose to conduct an experiment to confirm the theory,
perhaps this explains the second loss of chicks. It may be that if chicks are
very hungry, they leave the nest chamber to meet a returning parent and fall
from the nest. If so, this may also indicate why incubation starts following
the laying of the first egg. It may be that if there is a shortage of food the
strongest and healthiest will get preferential treatment by virtue of getting
to the food first.
From the first nests, two birds fledged from one nest, one on July 26th
and the other on July 27th. Both were females. Although the male continued
to maintain and modify the nest and display, no further eggs were laid until
fresh green grass was again supplied each day. Within three days of this, six
females had started new clutches.
These eggs hatched but the chicks were slowly lost. As the dead chicks
were not ejected from the nests, most were found later in an advanced state
of decay, making it impossible to determine the cause of death. All three
that could be examined were distended and had enlarged livers. In addition,
the remaining adult male was found dead in a nest, presumably having died
during the night (as this species roosts in the nest). Post mortem examination
revealed a grossly enlarged and congested ureter that had partially blocked
the cloaca. Although this was a major contribution to its death, the precise
cause was not determined.
Although a single chick fledged from the second breeding attempt, all
the others were lost and the single fledgling also died two days later, followed
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.775042" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261220" page_num="149" year="" vol="">
GARNHAM - RED-BILLED BUFFALO-WEAVER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999284" page_id="56261220"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
149
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9954359375" page_id="56261220"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
closely by the, now independent, fledglings from the first breeding attempt.
Post mortem examinations were carried out on several birds. All showed
enlarged livers and one older fledgling also had signs of infection in several
abdominal organs. Four birds were sent for laboratory examination and all
were found to have died from atoxaplasmosis. This is a protozoan disease
similar to coccidiosis in which the protozoan species tends to be very species-
specific in what it will infect. As such, it seems inevitable that the disease
was and is present in the adult birds. At the time of writing (October 2006),
no cure or prophylactic treatment has been identified.
Amongst the original group of birds, one in particular was initially thought
to be an immature male as it was substantially darker, but otherwise identical
to the remaining birds. The colour and pattern of that bird remain essentially
unchanged except that its beak has darkened considerably. With no
identification information available to me, it seems very likely that this bird
is a female White-billed Buffalo Weaver. This supposition is supported by
the fact that it was the only non-male that did not attempt to breed.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.812806" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56261220" page_num="149" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.6196756" page_id="56261220"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
Immeasurable thanks to Brian Stockdale at Meadow Lane Veterinary
Practice for his interest, time and efforts. Thanks also to Andrew Kruppa
and Mark Winterbottom for sharing their thoughts and information about
the Red-billed Buffalo Weaver.
Carl Garnham is a UK member who lives in Leicestershire.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.472368" page_id="56261220"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.928823" genericHeader="references" page_id="56261220" page_num="149" year="" vol="">
FOUND ON MOUNTAIN RANGE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.979458375" page_id="56261220"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
On a previously unexplored Colombian mountain range, a team of
biologists has discovered a new bird which has been named the Yariguies
Brush-Finch Atlapetes latinuchus yariguierum. The new bird has a black
bill, orangish-rufous crown, blackish face and upperparts and yellowish
underparts. It differs from its closest relative in lacking any white markings
on the wings.
The expedition which discovered it was funded by the BP (British
Petroleum) Conservation Programme, which this year has given 27 schemes
from 21 countries US$475,000 (approx. #250,000) to support research
projects aimed at tackling a range of global environmental issues.
The cutting about the discovery of the Yariguies Brush-Finch was sent
by Prof. J. R. (Bob) Hodges. Bob said that regrettably old age is catching
up with him and he now has virtually no opportunities to meet other
aviculturists. He occasionally visits the Cotswold Wildlife Park, where he
finds himself spending long periods watching the Scheepmaker's Crowned
Pigeons Goura scheepmakeri and Great Blue Turacos Corythaeola cristata.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995946" page_id="56261221"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
150
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.96107" genericHeader="method" page_id="56261221" page_num="150" year="" vol="">
THE FIRST HAND-REARING OF
MAURITIAN WHITE-EYES Zosterops spp.
</sectionHeader>
<title confidence="0.448279">
by Andrew Cristinacce, Amanda Ladkoo, Elise Kovac,
</title>
<author confidence="0.695756">
Lara Jordan, Anne Morris, Trace Williams, Frederique de Ravel
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.27256">
Koenig, Vikash Tatayah and Carl Jones
</affiliation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.960479" genericHeader="method" page_id="56261221" page_num="150" year="" vol="">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989637606060606" page_id="56261221"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
Island bird species threatened by introduced mammalian predators can
be safeguarded from extinction by introduction onto predator-free offshore
islands. To minimise the impact on existing populations, threatened nests
can be rescued from the wild and chicks hand-reared for release. Using a
closely related but common surrogate species can help to refine rearing
technique before trials on more endangered species. Four Mauritius Grey
White-eyes Zosterops borbonica mauritianus chicks were successfully hand-
reared to fledging before four Critically Endangered Mauritius Olive White-
eyes Z. chloronothos were reared, one from hatching. The potential for
further development of techniques and future conservation measures are
discussed.
Introduction
Island bird species have accounted for over 90% of bird extinctions over
the past 400 years and 39% of threatened bird species are restricted to islands
(Johnson &amp; Statterfield, 1990) but recently a number of island bird species
have been saved from extinction when appropriate conservation measures
were taken (Butchart et al., 2006). Mauritius, in the Indian Ocean, provides
well known examples of the problems afflicting remote islands following
human settlement. Although 52% of its original avifauna is now extinct
(Cheke, 1987a), Mauritius is recognised as part of a biodiversity hotspot in
the Indian Ocean (Myers et al., 2004) and intensive conservation management
has been used to increase the populations of some of the rarest birds in the
world (Jones et al., 1995; Swinnerton, 2001).
The Mauritius Olive White-eye is now possibly the rarest bird on
Mauritius and is the only endemic bird species to show a large population
decline in recent years. Its population size was estimated at 340-350 pairs
in 1974-1975 (Cheke, 1987), but this had fallen to 200 pairs by 1993 (Safford,
1997a). A further decrease-to 93-148 pairs by 2001 (Nichols et al., 2004)
led to the IUCN classification of Critically Endangered.
The Mauritius Olive White-eye likely faces the same threats from nest
predation by introduced mammals as other Mauritian birds (Safford, 1997b;
Carter &amp; Bright, 2002) and this has caused low productivity (Nichols et al.,
2005). One of the strategies suggested for increasing populations of
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.517303" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261222" page_num="151" year="" vol="">
CRISTINACCE ET AL - MAURITIAN WHITE-EYES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998617" page_id="56261222"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
151
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.993278" page_id="56261222"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
Mauritian birds is translocation to offshore islands free of mammalian
predators (Safford &amp; Jones, 1998). The most effective way to establish a
population of Olive White-eyes on an island is to rescue threatened nests
from the wild and hand-rear chicks for release.
Chicks from common but closely related species can be used to develop
techniques for the hand-rearing of more endangered species (Kuehler et al.,
1996). The Mauritius Grey White-eye is the only native terrestrial bird to
have adapted to the arrival of humans on Mauritius. It is widespread
throughout the island and the population was estimated at 34,000-68,000
pairs (Cheke, 1987; Safford, 1994). This makes it an ideal species to use as
a surrogate for its more endangered congener. This paper describes the first
nest rescues and hand-rearing to fledging of both Grey and Olive White-
eyes.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.782285">
Methods
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.978783555555555" page_id="56261222"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
Nest rescues
In the 2004-2005 breeding season a nest of two Grey White-eye chicks
about three days old was rescued from the wild. The nest was taken whole
when the parents were off the nest and was lowered to the ground in a
specially prepared tub. It was carried to the nearest road and then driven to
the Gerald Durrell Endemic Wildlife Sanctuary (GDEWS) for the chicks to
be hand-reared. The whole process took about one hour. The following
season a second brood of two Grey White-eyes was rescued at the same
stage from an area containing high densities of Olive White-eyes. As this
area was further away it was decided to feed the chicks on the journey. The
chicks were fed by tweezers immediately after the rescue and every hour
thereafter. They were given bee larvae until they stopped begging for
additional food.
Later in the 2005-2006 breeding season, following the successful rearing
of the Grey White-eye chicks, two threatened Olive White-eye nests were
rescued from the wild. The first nest contained two five-day old chicks.
These were rescued and fed in the same way as the second brood of Grey
White-eyes. The second nest was rescued early because introduced Crab-
eating Macaques Macaca fasicularis were seen in the area and the nesting
pair's previous two nests containing eggs were predated by monkeys. The
rescued nest contained a day-old chick and two eggs, one of which had died
under the parents. The viable egg was placed in foam in a portable incubator
set at 37*C (98.6*F). The chick was also placed in the incubator and fed
only one piece of bee larvae on the journey because it still had an obvious
yolk sac.
Hand-rearing
Both species were given the same hand-rearing diet shown in Table 1.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.989225" page_id="56261223"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
152
</page>
<figure confidence="0.981514674418605" page_id="56261223"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
CRISTINACCE ET AL - MAURITIAN WHITE-EYES
I g
3 I
s" b
5
CO
ft)
cs^
o
n
2-3
3
-- OQ 2 .
r, O
S" **
3 a
6 (T 9
V. 0 2
n v
xs U _
3 o a
.*\0x25A0*. r*T 20
&amp;lt; a^
ft !S O
^ 0 3
r 3 &amp;lt;2
&amp;lt;D C
?r tn
w *t?
r* os u&gt;
8S*
M + Ut
-- O&amp;apos;,
(c)wo
(c) c
r &amp;lt;* w
O w o
O C
-- as
(c) W
C C
+ ON
I s
</figure>
<tableCaption confidence="0.970174">
Table 1. Feeding schedule for Mauritius Olive White-eyes and Grey White-eyes.
</tableCaption>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.517456" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261224" page_num="153" year="" vol="">
CRISTINACCE ET AL - MAURITIAN WHITE-EYES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999505" page_id="56261224"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
153
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.984294135135135" page_id="56261224"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
The chicks were fed by tweezers, mainly on bee larvae, egg and papaya
(pawpaw). Young (&gt;one day old) laboratory-bred mic qMus musculus were
added to the diet from day six onwards. The chicks were fed every 40
minutes for the first three days after hatching and every hour from days
three to eight. The interval between feeds was increased to 90 minutes for
days eight to 13 and to two hours from day 13 to fledging.
The Olive White-eye egg was placed in an incubator at a temperature of
37.2*C (99*F) and 86% humidity. The chicks were placed in their original
nest after it had been treated with 5% Carbonyl powder to remove any mites.
The nest was lined with a textured mat and a thin layer of tissue to increase
the grip of the chicks and allow easy removal of waste. The two chicks
from each nest were reared together and kept in a Marsh brooder between
feeds. The temperature in the brooder was gradually decreased as the chicks
grew (see Table 1). The chicks were weighed every morning before the first
feed and observations on their development were recorded.
After chicks were found outside of the nest on the floor of the brooder,
they were considered fledged and were moved into a small cage measuring
about 60cm x 60cm x 25cm (approx. 2ft x 2ft x lOin) with a partly covered
wooden back and sides. Leafy branches were arranged in the cage to provide
a secure, sheltered environment for the birds. Perches of various widths
were placed around the nesting tub and at higher elevations in the cage.
The following day the fledglings were moved into a larger cage measuring
lm x lm x 0.3m (approx. 3ft 3in x 3ft 3in x 1ft). A tube of nectar, fruit on
perching branches and bowls of insect mix were placed in the cage. Over
the next few days the fledglings were fed less frequently as they began to
explore the available food and started to feed themselves. When the chicks
were fully weaned, the cage was put into an outside aviary for increasing
intervals of time each day until the juveniles were released into the aviary
by leaving the door to the cage open.
Sexing
All four Mauritius Olive White-eyes were sexed at approximately 10
weeks of age. Each bird was caught and two blood samples were taken
using a sterile needle to prick the birds' feet above a claw. A drop of blood
was collected on paper, sealed in a sterile container and sent for sexing to
Molecular Diagnostic Service, South Africa. Biometrics were taken of all
four birds including weight, wing chord, tarsus length and distance from
culmen to gape.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.859713">
Results
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.91827" page_id="56261224"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
All the Grey White-eyes and Olive White-eyes were successfully hand-
reared to independence. No major problems were encountered when the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999641" page_id="56261225"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
154
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.791875" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261225" page_num="154" year="" vol="">
CRISTINACCE ET AL - MAURITIAN WHITE-EYES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994667714285714" page_id="56261225"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
birds were reared from the chick stage. The defecation pattern was irregular
for the first few days after rescue and in some cases the chicks were straining
to pass faecal sacs. This was rectified by increasing the amount of papaya
in the diet and by feeding one chick at a time until full instead of feeding
them alternately. The sudden increase in pressure caused by a full crop
seemed to stimulate movement of the faecal sac. A clump of cricket eggs
was found in the faecal sac of one two-day old Olive White-eye chick. After
this only male crickets were fed to chicks.
The Olive White-eye egg weighed 0.994g and measured 1.57mm x
1.15mm when it was rescued from the wild. It hatched the following day at
a weight of 0.86g. At two days old the chick was put back in the nest with
its sibling, that had been rescued in the same nest at one day old. On day six
the youngest chick developed a slight gasp, which worsened after each feed
and subsided three to five minutes after each feed. Its begging had become
lethargic and its faecal sac became wet, loose and an opaque grey colour.
Occasionally the chick would simply hold food in its beak without
swallowing it.
The chick was separated from its older sibling in case of infection and
was fed smaller pieces of food. In case the chick had developed a bronchial
infection a hatcher was set up in which the humidity rings were filled with a
solution of F10 disinfectant (Health and Hygiene Ltd) and distilled water in
a ratio of 1:125. The chick was placed in the hatcher for 30 minutes three
times a day. Two new supplements were added to the feeds: Critical Care
Formula (Vetark Ltd) which was given at alternative feeds and Avipro (Vetark
Ltd) which was given after each session in the hatcher, as F10 destroys
beneficial gut fauna as well as harmful ones.
On day seven the gasping varied from light to severe hill body movements
and the feeding pattern remained the same as on the previous day. On day
eight the breathing of the chick had improved considerably. The beak of the
chick had grown quite a bit and the left nostril opening could be distinguished
for the first time. This eased the chick's breathing and treatment in the
hatcher was discontinued. The chick had fully recovered by day nine and
by day 12 was returned to the nest with its older sibling.
Development of white-eye chicks
The development of the Olive White-eyes is described in the Appendix.
The development of the Grey White-eyes was similar. The chicks of both
species grew very quickly and they spent just 13-14 days in the nest before
fledging. The eyes of the Grey White-eye chicks were open at day six,
while those of the Olive White-eye chicks did not open until day seven to
day eight. In the case of both species, feathers started emerging from day
five, breaking at the tips of the secondary pins. Fledging plumage was
obtained after 12 days.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.517468" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261226" page_num="155" year="" vol="">
CRISTINACCE ET AL - MAURITIAN WHITE-EYES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999247" page_id="56261226"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
155
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.994495454545455" page_id="56261226"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
The tails of both species were not fully feathered until day 12 and even
after fledging remained noticeably shorter than those of the adult birds. The
white feathers around the eyes of the Olive White-eye started to unfurl about
the fledging time or just after. The exact time varied from individual to
individual. The birds of the first clutch had eye rings by day 15 whilst those
of the second clutch did not obtain their eye rings until day 27 or day 28.
The daily weight gain was similar for both species (see Fig. 1 (p. 156) for
that of Mauritius Olive White-eyes). Chicks gained weight steadily until
about day 10. The weight then remained stable or decreased slightly just
before fledging. The chicks weighed about 7g at fledging. At about 11 days
old chicks started to perch on the edge of the nest. Their begging response
decreased and occasionally they would refuse food. Three Olive White-eye
chicks fledged at 13 days old and one at 14 days old. All Grey White-
eye chicks fledged at 13 days old. One clutch of two Olive White-eyes
was weaned by 21 days old, but the second clutch was not fully weaned
until day 28. Both clutches of Grey White-eyes were weaned by 20 days
old.
All the fledglings adapted well to aviary life. The Olive White-eyes fed
mainly on nectar and also on fruit spiked on branches and showed less interest
in the insect mix than the Grey White-eyes. All four Olive White-eyes were
sexed and found to be males. The biometrics at 10 weeks of age are shown
in Table 2 (below).
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.916355">
Table 2. Biometrics of captive Mauritius Olive White-eyes.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.975674764705882" page_id="56261226"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
Bird
Age
(days)
Weight
(g)
Wing-chord
(mm)
Tarsus
(mm)
Culmen-Gape
(mm)
GA78213
72
9.5
51
20.3
14.9
GA78214
70
9
50
18.6
15.3
GA78215
81
8.5
49.5
19.1
15.6
GA78216
81
9
52.5
19.5
</figure>
<page confidence="0.640148" page_id="56261226"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
16.4
</page>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.699452">
Discussion
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9975022" page_id="56261226"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
All the Olive and Grey White-eyes were successfully hand-reared to
independence. Rearing chicks from a common but closely related species
enabled us to develop techniques and gain experience with small chicks
before tackling a critically endangered species. Few problems were
encountered during the rearing and most of those were easily overcome.
The cause of the problem which affected one Olive White-eye chick between
the age of six and eight days is still not known. Although the chick was
given emergency care it remains unclear whether this resulted in its recovery.
With critically endangered birds, all possible measures should be taken to
ensure their survival.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999483" page_id="56261227"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
156
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.719442" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261227" page_num="156" year="" vol="">
CRISTINACCE ET AL - MAURITIAN WHITE-EYES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.983457380952381" page_id="56261227"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
Fig.l. Mean (=S.E) daily weights of Mauritius Olive White-eyes (n=l day 1
and 14, n=2 days 2-4, n=4 days 5-13).
Daily weights of Mauritius Olive White-eyes
The chicks of both species grew rapidly and fledged after approximately
13 days. At around fledging time all chicks weighed slightly less than adults,
but by 10 weeks old Olive White-eyes had reached the full adult weight. At
that stage, wing length was generally 2mm-3mm shorter than that of adult
Mauritius Olive White-eyes measured in the wild (Cheke &amp; Jones, 1987).
Weaning varied between white-eye species. Both clutches of Grey White-
eyes and one clutch of Olive White-eyes were feeding themselves about
eight days after fledging. The second clutch of Olive White-eyes took a
week longer to be completely weaned. The weaning period after fledging
was longer for both species than that recorded for hand-reared Mauritius
Fodies Foudia rubra (unpublished data) and white-eyes appear to take longer
to start exploring their surroundings after fledging (pers. obs.).
The development of the white eye-ring in Olive White-eyes also varied.
It appeared around fledging time in one brood, but up to two weeks after
fledging in others. Lack of an eye-ring confirms a recent fledgling, but the
presence of an eye-ring does not preclude recent fledging. Observations in
the wild suggest that tail length may be a better method of distinguishing
adults from recent fledglings (Powell et al. in prep.).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.517318" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261228" page_num="157" year="" vol="">
CRISTINACCE ET AL - MAURITIAN WHITE-EYES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998605" page_id="56261228"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
157
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.992119727272727" page_id="56261228"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
Conservation measures
In future it will be possible to rescue nests from the wild at the egg stage.
This will leave nests exposed to predation for a shorter time and the parents
will be able to recycle more quickly. Eggs can be safely removed when the
vein coverage is 100%. This occurs about two-thirds of the way through
the incubation period. The incubation period of the Mauritius Olive White-
eye is 13 days (Safford, 1994) so eggs can be taken after nine days. This has
already been carried out successfully with Mauritius Fodies (unpublished
data).
Juveniles hand-reared from eggs can be used for releases (Kuehler et ah,
1995). The optimum release site would be a predator-free offshore island
(Safford &amp; Jones, 1998). The island with the most potential for a release of
Mauritius Olive White-eyes is lie Aux Aigrettes, which has already undergone
20 years of habitat restoration. Olive White-eyes have already shown that
they can adapt to different environments. They have never been seen to eat
fruit in the wild (Safford, 1991; Cheke, 1987), but have readily taken it in
captivity.
The four Mauritius Olive White-eyes hand-reared in 2005-2006 will be
kept at GDEWS at Black River. This will give some indication of the
susceptibility of Olive White-eyes to lowland diseases which could be present
on lie Aux Aigrettes. All wild populations of Mauritius Olive White-eyes
are currently found in the uplands of Mauritius. Mauritius Grey White-
eyes, Mauritius Fodies and Mascarene Paradise Flycatchers Terpsiphone
bourbonnensis desolata in the lowlands are susceptible to avian pox and the
long-term impact of this pathogen on these species requires investigation
(Cheke, 1987; pers. obs.).
Although all the Mauritius Olive White-eyes reared so far are male, it
may still be possible to perform captive breeding trials by taking more
chicks into captivity. Any captive-bred fledglings can be used to increase
the number released in reintroduction programmes (Tweed et al., 2003). It
will also be useful to have captive breeding techniques in place as a safety
net in case of further declines in the wild population when direct intervention
may be more contentious (VanderWerf et al., 2006).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.944051" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56261228" page_num="157" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9785234" page_id="56261228"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
This work was funded by The Ruth Smart Foundation and Chester Zoo
and supported by the National Parks and Conservation Service of Mauritius.
We would like to thank Andrea Powell, Jessica Steiner, Ruth Cole, Jason
Malham and Anna Reauleaux for finding and rescuing white-eye nests. Dr
Diana Bell kindly commented on earlier versions of this manuscript.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999184" page_id="56261229"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
158
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.948032" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261229" page_num="158" year="" vol="">
CRISTINACCE ET AL - MAURITIAN WHITE-EYES
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.907453806451613" page_id="56261229"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
Butchart, S.H M., Stattersfield, A.J. and Collar, N.J. 2006. How many bird extinctions have
we prevented. Oryjc40: 266-278.
Carter, S. R and Bright, RW. 2002. Habitat refuges as alternatives to predator control for the
conservation of endangered Mauritian birds. In: Veitch, C. R. and Clout, M. N. (eds.) Turning
the tide: the eradication of invasive species 71-78. IUCN SSC Invasive Species Specialist
Group, IUCN Gland and Cambridge.
Cheke, A.S. (1987a). The legacy of the dodo-conservation in Mauritius. Oryx 21:29-36.
Cheke, A.S. (1987b). The ecology of the smaller land-birds of Mauritius. In: Diamond, A.W.
(ed.). Studies ofMascarene Island birds, pp. 151-207. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.
Cheke, A. S. and Jones, C. G. 1987. Measurements and weights of the surviving endemic
birds of the Mascarenes and their eggs. In: Diamond, A. W. (ed.). Studies ofMascarene Island
birds , pp. 151-207. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.
Johnson, T. H. and Statterfield, A.J. 1990. A global review of endemic birds. Ibis 132:167-
180.
Jones, C.G., Heck, W., Lewis, R.E., Mungroo, Y., Slade, G. and Cade, T. 1995. The restoration
of the Mauritius Kestrel Falco punctatus population. Ibis 137:S 173-180.
Kuehler, C, Kuhn, M., Kuhn, J.E., Lieberman, A., Harvey, N. and Rideout, B. 1996. Artificial
incubation, hand-rearing, behaviour, and release of common 'Amakihi (. Hemignathus virens
virens ): Surrogate research for restoration of endangered Hawaiian forest birds. Zoo Biology
15:541-553.
Kuehler, C, Harrity, P., Lieberman, A. and Kuhn, M. 1995. Reintroduction of hand-reared
alala Corvus hawaiiensis in Hawaii. Oryx 29:261-266.
Myers, N., Mittermeier, R.A., Mittermeier, C.G., da Fonseca, G.A.B. and Kent, J. 2000.
Biodiversity hotspots for conservation priorities. Nature 403:853-858.
Nichols, R.K., Woolaver, L.G. and Jones, C.G. 2004. Continued decline and conservation
needs of the Endangered Mauritius Olive White-eye Zosterops chloronothos. Bird Cons. Int.
15:297-302.
Powell, A.C., Steiner, J. and Jones, C.G. Nesting success and breeding biology of the Mauritius
Olive White-eye Zosterops chloronothos (in prep.).
Safford, R.J. 1991. Status and ecology of the Mauritius fody Foudia rubra and Mauritius
olive white-eye Zosterops chloronothos : Two passerines in danger. Dodo : Journal of the Jersey
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.918122111111111">
Wildlife Preservation Trust 27:113-138.
Safford, R.J. 1994. Conservation of the forest-living native birds of Mauritius. PhD thesis,
University of Kent, UK.
Safford, R.J. 1997a. Distribution studies on the forest-living native passerines of Mauritius.
Biological Conservation 80:189-198.
Safford, R.J. 1997b. Nesting success of the Mauritius Fody Foudia rubra in relation to its use
of exotic trees as nest sites. Ibis 139:555-559.
Safford, R.J. and Jones, C.G. 1998. Strategies for land-bird conservation on Mauritius.
Conservation Biology 12,1:169-176.
Swinnerton, K.J. 2001. The ecology and conservation of the Pink Pigeon Columba mayeri in
Mauritius. PhD thesis, University of Kent, Canterbury, UK.
Tweed, E.J., Foster, J.T., Woodworth, B.L., Oesterle, P., Kuehler, C, Lieberman, A.A., Powers,
A.T., Whitaker, K., Monahan, W.B., Kellerman, J. and Telfer, T. 2003. Survival, dispersal,
and home-range establishment of reintroduced captive-bred puaiohi, Myadestes palmeri.
Biological Conservation 111:1-9.
VanderWerf, E.A., Groombridge, J .J., Fretz, J.S. and Swinnerton, K.J. 2006. Decision analysis
to guide recovery of the po'ouli a critically endangered Hawaiian honeycreeper. Biological
Conservation 129:383-392.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.516663" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261230" page_num="159" year="" vol="">
CRISTINACCE ET AL - MAURITIAN WHITE-EYES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997118" page_id="56261230"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
159
</page>
<author confidence="0.60123">
Andrew Cristinacce, Amanda Ladkoo, Elise Kovac, Frederique de Ravel
</author>
<category confidence="0.375379">
Koenig and Vikash Tatayah, Mauritian Wildlife Foundation; Carl Jones,
Mauritian Wildlife Foundation and Durrell Wildlife Conservation Trust;
</category>
<author confidence="0.665471">
Lara Jordan, Anne Morris, Chester Zoo; Trace Williams, RSPB (Royal
</author>
<bodyText confidence="0.912190054054054" page_id="56261230"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
Society for the Protection of Birds).
Appendix
Development of Mauritius White-eye chicks day one to day 15.
Day 1. Eyes: Closed. Head and beak: Four down feathers. Pink/orange
beak, pink inside mouth. Yolk-coloured gape flanges. Body: Pink with grey
subcutaneous (s/c) pin-feathers on wings.
Day 2. Eyes: Closed. Head and beak: Four down feathers. Pink/orange
beak, pink inside mouth. Yolk-coloured gape flanges. Body: Pink with grey
s/c pin-feathers in lines on scapulars, flanks and breast. Barely visible pin-
feathers along the line of vertebrae. S/c pin-feathers of primaries and
secondaries.
Day 3. Eyes: Eye slits visible but eyes remain closed. Head and beak: Barely
visible s/c pin-feathers on forehead and and s/c pins on hindneck. Pink/
orange beak, pink inside mouth. Yolk-coloured gape flanges. Body: S/c pin-
feathers along the line of the vertebrae. S/c lines of pin-feathers on scapulars,
rump and from forehead to breast, belly and abdomen. S/c primary and
secondary pin-feathers and wing-coverts.
Day 4. Eyes: Eye slits visible but eyes remain closed. Head and beak: S/c
pin-feathers on forehead, crown, lateral crown, nape and hindneck. Pink/
orange beak, pink inside mouth. Yolk-coloured gape flanges. Body: Pin-
feathers emerging on back, scapulars, rump and flanks. Lines of s/c pin-
feathers from foreneck, down either side of the breast, belly and abdomen.
Primary and secondary pin-feathers and wing-coverts emerging. S/c pin-
feathers of tail and legs.
Day 5. Eyes: Eye slits visible but eyes remain closed. Head and beak: Pin-
feathers emerging on forehead, crown, lateral crown and hindneck. Pink/
orange beak, pink inside mouth. Yolk-coloured gape flanges. Body: Pin-
feathers emerging on back, scapulars, breast, belly, flanks, abdomen and of
the tail. The primary and secondary pin-feathers also emerging, along with
the wing-coverts. S/c pins on foreneck and at top of legs.
Day 6. Eyes: These remain closed. Head and beak: Pin-feathers emerging
on the forehead, lateral crown, nape and hindneck. S/c pin-feathers of ear-
coverts and sub-moustachial area. Beak orange, with darkening at tip. Gape
flanges remain yolk-coloured. Body: Pin-feathers emerging on back, of
scapulars, rump, flanks and at the top of the legs. The tail pin-feathers are
also emerging, as are those of the foreneck and feathers are beginning to
unfurl on the breast, belly and abdomen. The primary and secondary pin-
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998611" page_id="56261231"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
160
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998927255813954" page_id="56261231"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
feathers are also emerging, along with the wing-coverts.
Day 7. Eyes: Slits visible but eyes remain closed. Head and beak: Pin-
feathers emerging on the forehead, crown, lateral crown, nape, hindneck,
ear-coverts and moustachial area. Beak orange, with darkening at tip. Yolk-
coloured gape flanges. Body: Pin-feathers emerging on back, scapulars,
foreneck, flanks and legs. Primary, secondary and wing-covert pin-feathers
also emerging. Unfurled feathers in tail and on rump, breast, belly and
abdomen.
Day 8. Eyes: Semi-open. Head and beak: Pin-feathers continuing to emerge
on the forehead, crown, lateral crown, nape, ear-coverts and moustachial
area. Unfurling feathers on hindneck. Beak dark orange with grey tip,
extending towards forehead. Still retains yolk-coloured gape flanges. Body:
Pin-feathers emerging on back. Scapulars, rump and feathers at the tops of
the legs unfurling, as are those on the foreneck, breast, belly, flanks and
abdomen. Primary, secondary and tail feathers also unfurling. Down
developing around vent.
Day 9. Eyes: Open. Head and beak: Pin-feathers emerging on the forehead
and crown. Unfurled feathers on lateral crown, nape, hindneck, ear-coverts
and moustachial area. Beak dark orange with grey tip, extending towards
forehead. Yolk-coloured gape flanges. Body: Feathers unfurling on foreneck,
back, scapulars, rump and at top of legs. The tail feathers are also unfurling,
as are those of the primaries, secondaries and coverts. Unfurled feathers on
breast, belly, flanks and abdomen.
Day 10. Eyes: Open. Head and beak: Unfurling feathers with some sheaths
remaining on the forehead, crown, lateral crown, nape, ear-coverts, hindneck
and moustachial area. Beak deep pink with dark grey tip, extending towards
forehead. Yolk-coloured gape flanges. Body: Unfurled scapulars, wing-
coverts, foreneck, breast, belly, flanks, abdomen and rump feathers. Back
and tail feathers unfurling. Two-thirds of sheaths on primaries and
secondaries still retained.
Day 11. Head and beak: Unfurled feathers on the forehead, crown, lateral
crown, nape, ear-coverts, hindneck and moustachial area. Beak grey/black
with gape receding and pale yellow flanges. Body: Unfurled scapulars, wing-
coverts, foreneck, breast, belly, flanks, abdomen and rump feathers. Back
and tail feathers unfurling. One- to two-thirds of the primary and secondary
feather sheaths still retained.
Day 12. Head: All feathers unfurled. Body: Most feathers unfurled. A small
portion of the sheath remains on some of the primaries.
Day 13. Head: Feathers fully developed. Body: Feathers completely
unfurled, with fluffed-up appearance.
Days 14 &amp; 15. Head: White eye-ring pin-feathers beginning to emerge.
There is though variation from individual to individual. Body: Full fledgling
plumage.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9598845" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261232" page_num="161" year="" vol="">
NOTES ON THE CARE AND BREEDING OF THE
TURQUOISE TANAGER Tangara mexicana
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997679" page_id="56261232"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
161
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.96532325" page_id="56261232"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
by Mark Sproule
This article describes the successful breeding of the Turquoise Tanager
in an indoor birdroom in Canada. I was able to determine insect consumption
up until fledging and also observe that the female incubated from the time
the first egg was laid.
Description
The Turquoise Tanager has a wide distribution in South America east of
the Andes extending from Colombia, Ecuador and Pern in the west, Venezuela
and Trindad in the north, and throughout the Amazon Basin. There is a
separate population in eastern Brazil from Bahia to Rio de Janeiro that was
considered a separate species (see comment by Isler and Isler, p. 175 (1999)).
Curiously enough T. mexicana is not found anywhere near Mexico.
The head and throat and breast are metallic blue. This blue also occurs
on the rump and lesser wing-coverts. The rest of the back, wings and tail
are black. The centre of the breast, belly and under tail-coverts are a lemon
yellow colour. There are five subspecies. Four of these - T. m. mexicana , T.
m. boliviana, T. m. media and T. m. vieilloti - all have similar coloration and,
in particular, a yellow belly. T. m. brasiliensis , the subspecies from eastern
Brazil, is larger than the others and is distinguished from them by having a
white, instead of yellow, breast. A friend of mine who had T. m. brasiliensis
and T. m. mexicana , indicated that their contact calls are different.
Tanagers are rarely available to private aviculturists in Canada, so having
been trying for some time to obtain some Tangara tanagers, I jumped at the
chance when I was offered a 'pair' of T. mexicana in late October 2003.
Based on the descriptions in Norgaard-Olesen (1973) and plates in Isler &amp;
Isler (1999), I believe that my birds belong to the nominate form T. m.
mexicana.
Accommodation
All my birds are housed indoors year-round in a birdroom in the basement.
The area of Canada where I live regularly experiences winter temperatures
of -30*C (-22*F). The basement has in-floor heating so I can maintain a
year-round temperature of 22*C-24*C (71.6*F-75.2*F). There is an electronic
air filter running continuously to help clean and circulate the air. When the
weather is not too cold I open the windows for fresh air. Humidity hovers
around 50%-60%. I have tried using a humidifier to increase the humidity
but it did not make a significant difference so I no longer use it. I have a
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997924" page_id="56261233"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
162
</page>
<table confidence="0.9457708" page_id="56261233"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
SPROULE - TURQUOISE TANAGER
Mark Sproule
Adult showing head coloration.
Adult showing body coloration.
Mark Sproule
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.370657" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261234" page_num="163" year="" vol="">
SPROULE - TURQUOISE TANAGER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.985153" page_id="56261234"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
163
</page>
<table confidence="0.77982" page_id="56261234"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
Mark Sproule
Eggs laid in nest built in the box of nesting material.
Chick in nest 11 days.
Mark Sproule
</table>
<page confidence="0.999528" page_id="56261235"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
164
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.741517" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261235" page_num="164" year="" vol="">
SPROULE - TURQUOISE TANAGER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.981859976190476" page_id="56261235"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
separate area that is used to quarantine new birds.
When I first received the tanagers, they were housed in a large cage 4ft
x 2ft x 2ft high (approx. 1.2m x 0.6m x 0.6m high) for 60 days quarantine
before being moved into my birdroom. I had intended to move them into a
large flight that housed a pair of Zosterops chloris that over a period of
months had shown no signs of nesting, but, when I went to catch them I
discovered that they were sitting on three eggs. The only other flight I had
available at the time was 2ft wide x 4ft deep x 8ft high (approx. 0.6m wide
x 1.2m deep x 2.4m high), so I put the pair in that. The pair immediately
settled down. I find that birds seem to feel safer and are much calmer in tall
flights in which they can perch above my head height.
The flight has natural branches near the top. Artificial plants provide
cover. There is a feeding hatch 4ft (approx. 1.2m) off the ground so that I
can feed the birds without entering the flight. I placed an open box full of
nest material among the branches so the birds would not have to go down to
the ground to collect nest material. I also constructed two nest areas carefully
screened by artificial plants.
Diet
The tanagers are fed my standard softbill mixture twice daily. The mixture
is roughly one part diced tofu and three parts diced fruit. Ground up Mazuri
low iron softbill pellets are added to the mixture. If too much of this is
added to the mix it becomes a solid inedible mass. I have tried a number of
different pellets but have yet to find one that the birds will eat willingly.
The fruit normally consists of a base of ripe pear and apple, to which I try to
add a couple of the following: com, peas, grapes, blueberries, zucchini
(courgette), cucumber, peaches and papaya (pawpaw). Once a week I add a
scoop of Prime vitamins and a scoop of a calcium/vitamin Ds supplement -
more often when birds are breeding. In the morning they also receive
specially prepared sponge cake soaked in nectar. Boiled rice is added to the
afternoon feed.
As the birds are kept indoors, livefood is a challenge. I give waxworms,
mealworms and mealworm pupae. Some years ago I tried two week-old
crickets - the birds loved them but enough escaped and survived that we had
crickets singing for months afterwards. Fmit flies present similar problems.
I supply the tanagers with a few mealworms or waxworms daily but they
show little interest in these when they are not breeding.
Breeding
First attempt
In early March 2004 I noticed that there was nesting material scattered
about the floor of the flight. When I checked, I discovered that they had
completely ignored my carefully constmcted nest sites and instead built a
nest in the box of nesting material. The outside of the nest was constmcted
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.375725" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261236" page_num="165" year="" vol="">
SPROULE - TURQUOISE TANAGER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999158" page_id="56261236"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
165
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997605463414634" page_id="56261236"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
largely of burlap strands and the inside was lined with sisal twine. There
were two eggs in the nest, the normal sized clutch for tanagers. The eggs
were white with brown markings concentrated at the larger end. The eggs
measured 17mm x 11mm. I set up a wireless internet video camera, so that
I could observe what was happening. These cameras are great, as you can
hang them up anywhere and watch on your PC without disturbing the birds.
I also use a digital camera to photograph nests - this allows me to easily and
quickly examine at my leisure nests that are in difficult to reach locations.
When I checked the nest on March 19th, I discovered that it contained
two tiny chicks. They were pinkish with a small amount of pale greyish
down mostly on their heads and lower backs. I increased the livefood,
providing them with freshly moulted mealworms, mealworm pupae and
waxworms. The livefood was sprinkled with Prime vitamins and the calcium/
vitamin D 3 supplement. I was concerned because they were mainly taking
just a few waxworms and mostly ignoring the mealworms. However, I
checked the nest on the 21st, 24th and 28th and found that the young were
growing well and figured that the birds must know what they were doing.
Unfortunately, I had to go out of town for a couple of days at that point.
When I returned the young looked quite well feathered and appeared fine.
The next day though, April 4th, both young were dead.
I had been giving the birds commercially produced waxworms and had
been leaving them in the container they were sold to me in. I think that they
must have been contaminated. I now keep the waxworms on a waxworm
growing medium and have had no further problems.
Second attempt
In mid-April the birds tore apart the original nest and began building a
new nest in the same location. After watching hours of video, it appears
that only the female builds the nest. On April 22nd there was one egg in the
new nest and on the 23rd there were two eggs in the nest. On May 6th I
checked the nest again and found one chick and one egg. The following day
the second egg had hatched giving an incubation period of 14 days. This
pattern has been followed with subsequent nests, so I think that the female
starts incubation following the laying of the first egg. At least this seems
true of this species in captivity. I was again concerned by how few insects
were being consumed and decided to keep a record (see graphs). On May
11th I found the smaller (younger) of the two chicks dead on the floor. On
May 18th the remaining chick jumped out of the nest while I was changing
the food dishes. I replaced it in the nest twice and on the second occasion it
remained there. The following day it fledged at 13 days old. It was a dull
bluish-black on the back and under the chin, the belly was pale yellow and
there were some shiny blue feathers on the head. The rump was shiny blue
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999346" page_id="56261237"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
166
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.730999" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261237" page_num="166" year="" vol="">
SPROULE - TURQUOISE TANAGER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9801275" page_id="56261237"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
similar to that of the parents. At this point the next problem presented itself.
The chick could not fly vertically and wound up on the floor. The parents
refused to go down to the floor to feed it and each time I tried to put it back
Aged 15 days.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.591589">
Mark Sproule
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993233461538462" page_id="56261237"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
on a perch, it would immediately wind up on the floor again. I caught up the
parents and chick and placed them in a large cage raised about 4ft (1.2m) off
the ground. I placed a branch angled so that it touched the cage floor. This
seemed to solve the problem. I continued to supply insects but the parents
stopped feeding them to the young tanager as soon as it fledged.
Third attempt
At six weeks the young tanager was almost as large as its parents and
was feeding itself. I caught the parents and returned them to the same flight.
Within hours they were playing with nest material. This time they re-used
the old nest, adding to it just a small amount of new material. On June 26th
I checked the nest and found that it contained one egg. I checked again 14
days later, on July 10th, and found that the nest contained one chick and an
unhatched egg. On July 11 th the second egg had hatched. This supports my
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.348255" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261238" page_num="167" year="" vol="">
SPROULE - TURQUOISE TANAGER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.916276" page_id="56261238"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
167
</page>
<figure confidence="0.5525758" page_id="56261238"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
Insect consumption - Nest 3
\0x25A1 Mealworms
H Mealworm
Pupae
ffi Waxworms
</figure>
<page confidence="0.998729" page_id="56261239"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
168
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.742547" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261239" page_num="168" year="" vol="">
SPROULE - TURQUOISE TANAGER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.973559238095238" page_id="56261239"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
theory that the female begins incubation following the laying of the first
egg. On July 13th I found the smaller chick dead on the floor of the flight.
In the wild I think that these birds normally start incubation once the second
egg has been laid and as a result the two chicks hatch at the same time. By
beginning incubation following the laying of the first egg, the older chick
out competes the younger one. The remaining chick progressed well and
fledged on July 25th. Although it was able to fly better than the previous
fledgling, I again moved all three birds into a large cage.
At six months I had both offspring DNA feather sexed. The first is a
female and the second is a male. By eight months they were in foil adult
plumage. I was surprised to hear the young male singing, as I have never
heard the original male singing. The song is comprised of several contact
notes strung together and lasts about five seconds.
Conclusion
Breeding this species under controlled conditions in my birdroom allowed
me to make some observations that would have been difficult to have made
in an outdoor aviary or in the wild. I was surprised how few insects were
required to raise a tanager chick to fledging, compared to other softbills
which will consume as many insects as are provided. It also appears that
the female starts incubation following the laying of the first egg. I would be
interested to learn if other tanagers do the same thing.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.933478" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56261239" page_num="168" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.864211333333333">
Isler, M. L. and Isler, P. R. 1999. The Tanagers, Natural History, Distribution and Identification.
Smithsonian Institution Press, Washington, DC, USA.
N0rgaard-Olesen, E. 1973. Tanagers. Vol. 1, Skibby Books, Skibby, Denmark.
</reference>
<equation confidence="0.369416" page_id="56261239"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
* *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.599015" genericHeader="introduction" page_id="56261239" page_num="168" year="" vol="">
GREAT BLUE HATCHED IN JAPAN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.754687" page_id="56261239"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
A Great Blue Turaco Corythaeola cristata hatched at Inokashira Park
Zoo, Tokyo, on or about June 12th 2006. Copulation was noted in April and
the birds began to sit on May 13th. The pair arrived at the zoo on December
21 st 2000 and is housed in a huge walk-through greenhouse aviary.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.928155" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261240" page_num="169" year="" vol="">
COLLATED DATA ON THE MADAGASCAR FODY
</sectionHeader>
<keyword confidence="0.272115">
Foudia madagascariensis
</keyword>
<page confidence="0.998638" page_id="56261240"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
169
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.890413805555555" page_id="56261240"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
by Neville Brickell
Usually known now as the Madagascar or Madagascan Fody but
previously and sometimes, at least in aviculture, still known as the
Madagascar Weaver. Other names include Madagascar Red Fody, Cardinal,
Cardinal Fody, Madagascar Cardinal and, on St Helena, Robin.
Description
In breeding plumage the male is orange-red or crimson with a black eye-
stripe running from the base of the bill to behind the eyes and has black
streaking on the back. The wing-coverts have a white edge and the other
wing feathers and the tail feathers have yellowish or reddish edging. The
bill is black and the legs and feet are flesh-coloured. There is considerable
variation in the coloration of the plumage in the non-breeding season. The
female looks similar to the male in eclipse (non-breeding) plumage. Her
bill is yellowish-brown. The juvenile looks similar to the female, but is
paler overall.
Voice
A fairly vocal species. Has a drawn out, trilling, high-pitched rather
metallic "chett chett chett..." song, usually performed while perched at the
end of a reed stem or on a branch of a tree; alarm call a sort of shrill "tik tik"
(Langrand, 1990).
Distribution
Madagascar. Introduced successfully onto the Mascarene Islands
(Mauritius, Reunion and Rodrigues), the Seychelles (Cousin, Curieuse, Mahe
and Praslin), Comoro Islands (Aldabra, Anjouan, Grand Comoro, Mayotte
and Moheli), Amirante Islands, Diego Garcia and apparently also established
on St Helena, as a result of released or escaped captive birds (Crook, 1961;
Long, 1981).
Habitat
From sea-level up to 2,300m (approx. 7,500ft), in second growth, but
avoiding evergreen forest. Also occurs in parks, gardens, rice paddies and
timber plantations on Madagascar. On Moheli and Mayotte in the Comoro
Islands it occurs in thickets and shady trees (Benson, 1960; Langrand, 1990).
According to Penny (1992) it is very common in the lowlands, especially
around human habitations, where it obtains food. Haydock (1954) found it
in coastal regions and in thickly vegetated areas in the highlands, including
in gardens and cultivation.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996031" page_id="56261241"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
170
</page>
<table confidence="0.892977583333333" page_id="56261241"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - MADAGASCAR FODY
Some places it can be seen:
Madagascar Zoological &amp; Botanical Gardens.
Mauritius Gerald Durrell Endemic Wildlife Sanctuary (formerly
Black River Aviaries); Casela Bird Park; Sir Seewoosagur
Ramgoolam Botanical Garden (formerly the Royal
Botanical Gardens) and still known simply as
Pamplemousses; Natural History Museum.
Reunion Natural History Museum.
UK Chester Zoo recently acquired three pairs. These are
housed in its Tropical Realm exhibit.
Behaviour
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.9964273125" page_id="56261241"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
Found singly or in pairs during the breeding season, but at other times in
flocks numbering several hundred individuals in its natural range. Similarly,
it has been observed in twos, threes and singly on the Comoros, as well as in
larger numbers, e.g. flocks of over 50 have been recorded on Moheli and
Mayotte, and of 20 on Anjouan (Benson, 1960; Langrand, 1990).
On the subject of captive birds, Butler (1899) wrote: "I have indeed,
never, to my knowledge, lost any birds through the attacks of the Madagascar
Weaver, but I have seen a few of them badly scared at times." Bates &amp;
Busenbark (1970) wrote: "This is a beautiful though quarrelsome bird" and
Fitzpatrick (1989) suggested that any problems of this nature can be overcome
by supplying two females to one male, thereby diverting his aggression
towards them and relieving the pressure on other aviary inmates. However,
according to Kingston (1998), breeding males often accommodating several
females, may cause the latter to abandon their nests, due to their relentless
pursuit of the females. He achieved good results from a single male and
female housed together.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.563229">
Feeding
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993648384615385" page_id="56261241"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
Primarily eats seeds; mostly of various grasses. An examination of the
stomach contents of 42 individuals revealed 40 types of small seeds. The
stomach contents of nine of the birds also included insects; in four cases
relatively small quantities of beetles Coleoptera spp. On Mayotte in the
Comoro Islands, where this species has been introduced, with the exception
of one specimen, the stomach contents contained more livefood than seeds.
This survey also revealed that 16 individuals had consumed grit. Spiders,
caterpillars (in the breeding season) and occasionally nectar from unidentified
flowers have been recorded. On Madagascar and islands onto which it has
been introduced, it is a notorious pest where rice is grown. When it is
ripening, the Malagash erect small round huts on stilts, to enable them to get
a full view over the area under cultivation and use children to drive off the
birds (Benson, 1960; Langrand, 1990; Penny, 1992).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.503104" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261242" page_num="171" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - MADAGASCAR FODY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998613" page_id="56261242"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
171
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.966422125" page_id="56261242"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
Captive-birds can be offered a seed mixture of 10% yellow manna, 35%
red manna, 20% Japanese millet, 25% canary seed and 10% white millet.
Greenfood can include dandelion Taraxacum spp., Dock Rumex obtusifolius,
Gold-of-pleasure Camelina sativa, Milk Thistle Silybum marianum and
Shepherd's-purse Capsella bursa-pastoris. Softfood such as an egg and
biscuit mixture is acceptable. Recommended livefood can include crickets,
grasshoppers, fly larvae, maggots, mealworms, moths and spiders (Kingston,
1998).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.440032">
Neville Brickell
Male Madagascan Fody Foudia madagascariensis.
Housing
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8409409" page_id="56261242"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
Suitable accommodation to house a pair or a male and two females,
consists of a reasonably sized aviary measuring about 4m long x 3m wide x
3m high (13ft long x 9ft 9in wide x 9ft 9in high). About two-thirds of the
flight should be open and the shelter must be damp-free and provide
protection from strong winds and driving rain. Tall grass, bushes and small
trees can be provided, and the latter may be selected for building the nest in,
or they may prefer to nest under cover.
Breeding
Recorded breeding in September and May, as well as in December on
Madagascar; November-March or April on the Seychelles; May or June
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998275" page_id="56261243"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
172
</page>
<table confidence="0.4538105" page_id="56261243"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - MADAGASCAR FODY
Mohcli (Comoro Islands) and November Comoro Islands.
Evidently it breeds mainly during the rains. Built 1 m- 3rn (approx. 3ft
3 in-9ft 91 n) above the ground, the nest is spherical in shape and is loosely
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.97050754054054" page_id="56261243"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
twined and woven, using strips of grass and palm leaves. It is then lined
with kapok, the white woolly fibres used to stuff cushions and children's
toys, etc. These derive from the Kapok Tree Ceibapentandra, that is native
to tropical America, Africa and India. Near the top of the nest there is a side
entrance, with a short, wide, downward-curved access tunnel. Pollen (in
Butler, 1899) stated that nests are sited between two or four branches of
Acacia, Mimosa or Tamarisk trees, or at times in reed thickets (Madagascar);
it has been recorded nesting in conifers on St Helena.
The slightly glossy eggs are pale bluish-green. On Madagascar there
are usually three to five (or occasionally two to four) eggs in a clutch; on the
Mascarene Islands (Mauritius, Rodriques and Reunion) the recorded clutch
size is three to four eggs; on St Helena it is two; and in captivity it is two to
five eggs (Benson, 1960; Butler, 1899; Fitzpatrick, 1989; Haydock, 1954;
Langrand, 1990; Long, 1981; Penny, 1992). The incubation period is 14
days and the nestling period about 18-21 days. Up to three broods a year
are possible under suitable conditions (Kingston, 1998; Rutgers &amp; Norris,
1977).
Life expectancy
.May live to an age in excess of seven years (Fitzpatrick, 1989).
Hybrids and mutations
Benson (1960) suggested it may be that the Comoro Fody F.
eminentissima and the Madagascar Fody have different breeding seasons
and this assists in preventing hybridization in the field. However, in a report
on the African Bird Club Conservation Fund Awards for 2005, the writer
(Anon., 2006) referred to Hugh Doulton's interim report on the expedition
to the Comoro Islands and noted that on Grand Comore and Anjouan the
Madagascar Fody and the closely related Comoro Fody were not
distinguished in counts as they are known to interbreed frequently. Australian
aviculturist Russell Kingston (1998) stated that cross-breeding between the
two species is a serious concern in his country.
The first recorded breeding of the Madagascar Fody in the UK, was by
J.G. Leeming in 1850 (Coles, 1986). Robin Restall (1975) noted that it had
apparently been bred in Germany and France and that in Jean Delacour's
aviaries a male had mated with a female Half-masked (Vitelline Masked)
Weaver Ploceus vi tell inns in 1910 and 1911. They bred in a nest box and
reared three young, two of which were females and quite similar to the
female Madagascar Fody; the male, when two years old, developed a pale
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.503094" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261244" page_num="173" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - MADAGASCAR FODY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999407" page_id="56261244"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
173
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99833" page_id="56261244"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
orange creamy colour. Robin had noted earlier that xanthochroic specimens
of this species occasionally crop up in which the bright red is replaced by
bright yellow. In the yellow mutation the male and female are said to be
identical in breeding dress and to require surgical sexing or DNA testing in
order to be paired.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.915759" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56261244" page_num="173" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.850512111111111" page_id="56261244"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
Anon. 2006. African Bird Club Conservation Fund. Bulletin of the African Bird Club Vol.13,
No.2, p.127.
Bates, H. and Busenbark, R. 1970. Finches and soft-billed birds. T.F.H. Publishers, USA.
Benson, C.W. 1960. The Birds of the Comoro Islands: Results British Ornithological Union
Centennial Expedition 1958. Ibis 103b:5-196.
Butler, A.G. 1899. Foreign Birds for Cage &amp; Aviary , Part 1. "The Feathered World", UK.
Coles, D. 1986. First Breeding Records for Birds Reared to Independence under Controlled
Conditions in the United Kingdom. Published by the author.
Crook, J.H. 1961. The Fodies (Ploceinae) of the Seychelles Islands. Ibis 103a, Vol.l:517-548.
Fitzpatrick, E.L. 1989. The revised edition Finch Breeders Handbook , Vol.2. Queensland
Finch Society, Inc. Publications, Australia.
Haydock, E.L. 1954. A survey of the Birds of St. Helena. Ostrich 25, 2:62-75.
Kingston, R. 1998. Keeping and breeding Finches &amp; Seed-eaters. Indruss Productions, Australia.
Langrand, O. 1990. A Guide to the Birds of Madagascar. Yale University Press, USA.
Long, J.L. 1981. Introduced Birds of the World. David &amp; Charles, London.
Penny, M. 1991. Collins Field Guide - Birds of the Seychelles. Collins, London.
Restall, R.L. 1975. Finches and other seed-eating Birds. Faber and Faber, London.
Rutgers, A. and Norris, K. A. (eds.). 1977. Encyclopedia of Aviculture Vol. 1. Blandford Press,
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.810912714285714" page_id="56261244"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
UK.
Neville Brickell lives in Durban, KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa. He is a
life member of Natal Bird Breeders ' Society and a foundation member of
Natal Avicultural Society, the Wildlife Environmental Society (Photographic
Section) and the Indigenous Bird Breeders ' Research Group (Southern
African Region).
* * *
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.974673" genericHeader="introduction" page_id="56261244" page_num="173" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.950543" page_id="56261244"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
The society has a large stock of back issues mostly from 1935 onwards
but there are also some earlier issues still available. They are priced #3.00
each (including p&amp;p). Please check availability before placing an order.
Overseas members may be able to pay by credit card through a Paypal
invoice, but this service is not available in all countries. All enquiries should
be addressed to: P. Boulden, Hon. Secretary/Treasurer, Avicultural Society,
Arcadia, The Mounts, East Allington, Totnes, Devon TQ9 7JQ, UK. E-
</bodyText>
<email confidence="0.526507">
mail:admin@avisoc.co.uk
</email>
<page confidence="0.999583" page_id="56261245"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
174
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.713275333333333" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261245" page_num="174" year="" vol="">
MEMOIR, NOTES AND ANTHOLOGY ARISING FROM A
VISIT TO BRAZIL
Parti
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993681888888889" page_id="56261245"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
by Brian A. G. Hill
It was my first visit to Brazil, in fact my first visit to any South American
country. I was there from the first week of November 2005 to the third
week of February 2006.
Here I relate my observations of the visit chronologically, hence mixing
observations of aviary birds at zoos, with those of birds that, though not
confined, were living in close association with the human population, again
in zoos or in public parks, or the general environs of the cities and towns I
visited. Unless I qualify my observations by stating a bird or birds I watched
were in an aviary, or even that I watched them from within their aviary, it
should be assumed they were full-winged and at liberty to come and go as
they chose, or in the sort of intermediate state of having been pinioned to
confine them within the grounds, though not within an enclosure.
Apart from my journey by boat from Belem to Manaus, five days and
nights in total, but with a stop-over about mid-way for some days at Santarem
and its environs, I did not make any excursions to what might be considered
really wild countiy, i.e. remote from substantial human settlements.
Preparatory to my visit, I read that classic of natural history The Naturalist
on the River Amazons by Bates (1854), who will feature much in my narrative.
Bates started and finished his much more extensive visit to Brazil at Belem,
which at that time was known as Para, now the name of the Brazilian northern
frontier state in which Belem is situated. Besides Bates's classic, I also took
along the 1982 soft-cover edition of de Schauensee'srt Guide to the Birds of
South America , even though it is not really suitable for use in the field.
There are not even the briefest notes on how the birds appear and move (the
'jizz') or any description of the vocalizations. It is essentially a systematic
catalogue, as if done from museum skins. I would though refer members to
it for descriptions of the plumage/s of the birds mentioned in this report. I
have tried to breathe some life into his descriptions, by relating cameos of
their behaviour as I observed it.
Belem
Belem therefore was where I commenced my visit, and where I was for
all of November and December 2005, apart from a couple of excursions, for
a few days apiece, to no great distance away.
There were two locations I visited frequently, which had birds and other
animals in captivity, or at liberty in their grounds. The first, Mangal das
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.468759" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261246" page_num="175" year="" vol="">
HILL - VISIT TO BRAZIL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999118" page_id="56261246"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
175
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.991323761904762" page_id="56261246"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
Garqas (MDG), is an open site, almost devoid of trees of any size (yet). It
adjoins a military establishment, the grounds of which are park-like, i.e.
with close-mown lawns and sports pitches, and with a scattering of biggish
trees, some of which retain dead branches, so beneficial to many birds, as
perches uncluttered by foliage and therefore allowing an all-round view;
while those that are stout enough also offer nest sites. Mangal das Garzas is
meticulously maintained and policed. Even if this observation is not
reiterated, the reader can assume it to apply to all the other zoos and parks
generally that I visited in Brazil.
Mangal das Garqas features a number of diverse attractions for the general
visitor, but for the purposes of this report it is the birds which occur there
which are most relevant.
The management policy seemed to be to allow most of the birds which
were living wild in its environs to fly to and fro as they choose. Some other
birds were also allowed free-range in the grounds, but because they were
not of common occurrence in the municipal environment, at least some of
them, if not all, were pinioned. The third category of birds were those
confined in aviaries, which at Mangal das Garzas are big and can be entered
by the visitors.
As might be expected for a park adjacent to a river (the Rio Para), it has
a few small lakes. In the shallows of these lakes and on the surrounding
lawns at the time of my visit on November 5th, there were many Great
Egrets Casmerodius albus. They were more numerous there than anywhere
else I have seen them. They were especially concentrated at Mangal das
Garqas when fish and other food was being put out. They outnumbered the
also quite numerous pan-American Snowy Egret Egretta thula , which at a
glance is much like the Eurasian Little Egret E. garzetta and may be its
American ecological equivalent.
On another lake nearby - much of its surface densely covered with water
hyacinths - were a few Neotropic Cormorants Phalacrocorax brasilianus , a
species intermediate in size between the common Cormorant P. carbo and
the Pygmy Cormorant P. pygmeus of south-east Europe and Asia Minor,
though from its apparent liking for shallow, calm water in which to fish, it is
more akin ecologically to the latter.
The above egrets and cormorants were full-winged and free to come and
go. I was less sure about the flock of Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber , as I
never saw them in flight on any of my numerous midday visits, though if
they were full-winged, they may have flown early in the morning or in the
evening.
A quite different ambience attaches to the Museu Paraense Emilio Goeldi,
the other main location I frequently visited. A couple of miles (kilometres)
or so up river, it occupies only more or less one city block and contains, for
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999416" page_id="56261247"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
176
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.823409" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261247" page_num="176" year="" vol="">
HILL - VISIT TO BRAZIL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999069761904761" page_id="56261247"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
example, the type specimen of the tree, Guajara Chrysophyllum excelsum,
which was already adult by the late 1800s.
Bates returned to Para (Belem) on March 17th 1859, after an absence in
the interior of seven and a half years. In terms of organisation, efficiency
and amenities he found the city much improved. However "the expenses of
living had increased fourfold ..." and "the noble forest-trees had been cut
down, and their naked, half-burnt stems remained in the midst of ashes,
muddy puddles, and heaps of broken branches." Although Bates left Para
(Belem) for England on June 2nd 1859, never to return, his concern was
addressed by the naturalists Penna and Goeldi. As a result the city has "one
of the most important scientific research institutions in the Amazon.
Dedicated to studying Amazon man and his physical environment, it has a
zoological and botanical garden, in addition to a permanent exhibit of
ethnographic objects of various Amazonian Indian peoples" (Anon., 2005).
Going through the turnstile at the main entrance a visiting European,
such as myself, enters a sample of a novel environment - South American
equatorial rainforest. The luxuriant vegetation ranges from lowly herbs to
towering giant trees. It was mostly the diversity and density of the woody
plants which, after merely a few paces from the entrance, muffled the din
and extinguished the glare of the surrounding streets. So that entering this
natural edifice dedicated to nature, was like entering a cathedral.
Disporting themselves around a pool were one or two White-necked
Herons Ardea cocoi, one of which was standing near a Rufescent Tiger-
Heron Tigrisoma lineatum. The latter lived up to the notoriety popularly
attached to the 'Tiger Panthera tigris ' by posturing aggressively towards
the heron, which attempted to escape by flying up on to the apex of the
facade of a small neoclassical Greek-style building, where it was thereupon
pursued by the Rufescent Tiger-Heron. Sharing the same enclosure, but not
getting involved in the dispute, were some Black-bellied Whistling Ducks
Dendrocygna autumnalis. I am unsure whether or not they were pinioned.
They should not have been, because they were surrounded by, albeit a sample,
of the habitat they need. Unless, of course, it was feared that they might
stray out into a human environment that was dangerous for them, which I
doubt. I was impressed by the benign attitude which seemed to prevail
towards birds in Belem and other Brazilian cities.
On a visit on November 11th, whilst viewing some of what seemed to be
the comprehensive collection of tortoises and turtles, a Green Iguana Iguana
iguana fell from quite high overhead or threw itself off a branch, or else one
of these gave way whilst it was scrambling from bough to bough. It hit the
enclosure's iron balustrade railing I was leaning against and landed almost
at my feet. It appeared unharmed and I was able to take two photos of it
before it ambled away into cover.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.468814" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261248" page_num="177" year="" vol="">
HILL - VISIT TO BRAZIL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999044" page_id="56261248"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
177
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999049166666667" page_id="56261248"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
Another enclosure contained a pool in which were some Amazonian
Manatees Trichechus inunguis , which a little earlier had received their ration
of vegetation to munch, as if they were the aquatic equivalent of cows in a
stall. The agoutis Dasyprocta spp. were tame enough to be allowed free-
range within the bounds of the Museu Paraense Emilio Goeldi. Although
they allowed themselves to be photographed at close range, it seemed they
could become nervous and suddenly bolt. Even a heavy rain shower caused
them to do this during one of my visits, and they exhibited a remarkable
turn of speed.
One day I made a short excursion out of the city, downstream to the
nearby village of Icoaraci, another of the places visited by Bates. Even then
it had thriving saw-mills and today is known for its pottery. On the day of
my visit, November 14th, the local newspaper predicted a maximum
temperature of 34*C (93.2*F) and a minimum temperature of 24*C (75.2*F)
for Belem. Icoaraci though had the advantage of a pleasant breeze
accompanying the incoming tide at about 10.00am that day. At a bar
overlooking the small beach, I got into conversation with an expatriate
Caribbean fisherman, who seemed to know not only the local coast, but also
far beyond. Our conversation ranged over many topics, one of which was
the local birds, and inevitably the Black Vultures Coragyps atratus featured,
because there were some in view whilst we chatted, and they abound in
Belem. He thought the local birds nested "somewhere in the bush", but
even if they nest in thickets, these are presumably secluded enough for these
ground-nesting birds. He went on to say that when one of them dies its
corpse remains uneaten by animals (by which I suppose he meant higher
animals) and just desiccates and rots away, otherwise ignored. As to their
nesting, judging by their numbers and familiarity with people in Belem, I
think they may also nest within the city, perhaps in some of the uncompleted
and as yet unoccupied 20-30 storey high-rise buildings and perhaps also in
cavities in some of the big, old buildings.
Here I digress and jump ahead of my chronology to comment, I hope
interestingly, on his remarks about the American Black Vulture's
untouchability. When I got back to my home here in Greece, I turned up an
article on Western Hemisphere vultures in Purnell's Encyclopedia of Animal
Life. In Volume 6, pp.2502-2503, is a double-page spread showing vultures
resting on a sandy beach, adjacent to dense shrubby growth. The caption
states that the birds are Turkey Vultures Cathartes aura , but the bare skin
on their heads and necks is greyish black and they have short tails, meaning
of course that the caption was incorrect and the birds were in fact Black
Vultures. I took a similar photo of a flock resting on the wide sandy beach
at Caripy, near Belem, of which more later. The article included the
interesting statement that: "Turkey Vultures are immune to the deadly
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998835" page_id="56261249"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
178
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.812672" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261249" page_num="178" year="" vol="">
HILL - VISIT TO BRAZIL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994417071428571" page_id="56261249"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
botulinus toxin which must be a hazard to most carrion eaters." Assuming
this statement is also applicable to the Black Vulture, much of what the old
fisherman told me could be quite valid.
"An anaerobic bacterial organism, Clostridium botulinum Type C,
produces a very powerful exotoxin that is responsible for a serious type of
food-poisoning in many species of animals, including birds and man. The
toxin is formed outside the body of the bird when the anaerobe grows in
stagnant shallow ponds or pools. C. botulinum multiplies rapidly in water
containing decaying vegetation, dead fish, and particularly large quantities
of dead insect matter; slight alkalinity of the water and high temperatures
aid multiplication, so that outbreaks occur most frequently in the summer
months. Ducks are most frequently affected, so much so that the disease is
called k duck sickness'. The disease however is not confined to ducks, and
to date (1964) species of birds belonging to 21 families are known to be
affected with botulism. Under suitable conditions very large outbreaks of
botulism occur, and it has been estimated that in one outbreak in Oregon a
million birds died and that between one and three million birds died at Great
Salt Lake in 1929." (Jenings, 1964).
In recent years near my home here in Greece, it has occurred at a lake
which has expanses of shallow water overlying a deep accumulation of mud,
subject in usual summers to heat which in June-July can be as intense as
that in the tropics. Because of the usually cooler summers in the UK it is
rarer there. The antidote is to have less mud and decaying matter and deeper
water with enough flow to prevent stagnation.
In the Birds of Prey Issue of the Avicultural Magazine Vol. 87, No.4,
pp.212-215 (1981), there was an interesting article by Caryn Schrenzel on
breeding and hand-rearing the American Black Vulture at Lincoln Park Zoo,
Chicago, Illinois, U S A. Lincoln Park Zoo received an adult pair of American
Black Vultures in September 1962 and kept the pair in an open enclosure
during warm weather and transferred the pair to a closed, heated den 10ft x
6ft x 6ft (approx. 3m x 1.8m x 1.8m) during the winter. This procedure of
moving the birds twice a year continued until spring 1976 when it was decided
to open the den, giving the pair access to an open flight measuring 20ft x
20ft x 20ft (approx. 6m x 6m x 6m).
After almost 14 years and another winter had gone by, during which no
breeding ever occurred, an egg was found in a comer of the den on July 5th
1977. This egg was part incubated in an incubator and 41 days later the
chick was heard tapping inside the egg, but two days after that, no sound
could be heard coming from this or a second egg. Both were found to
contain fully-formed dead chicks. Another clutch of two eggs was laid in
late September. The first egg hatched 41 days after being discovered. A
few days later the chick disappeared and the second egg was found broken.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.4688" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261250" page_num="179" year="" vol="">
HILL - VISIT TO BRAZIL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999326" page_id="56261250"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
179
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.956316095238095" page_id="56261250"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
Eggs were found again the following year on February 25th and 26th but
these were found broken on March 11th. Eggs were found again on April
24th but one was broken and the other was infertile.
Later that spring two further eggs were laid, the smaller of which was
retrieved and placed in an incubator. That egg pipped on July 4th. The
chick was almost fully feathered at 10 weeks and on November 1 st, at about
four months, was put in an outside den. The article shows how the captive
breeding of a bird such as the American Black Vulture, which is so abundant
in many cities and towns of South America, can be quite tricky and by no
means straightforward. Much can be learned though trying to propagate
such species in captivity.
Mid-November visits to the Museu Paraense Emilio Goeldi were
memorable for offering close viewing of a few representatives of the
Ramphastidae family. I viewed a White-throated or Red-billed Toucan
Ramphastos tucanus in its aviary and also a Keel-billed Toucan R.
sulphuratus , both of which I photographed at close quarters, though separated
from them by the aviary mesh. Having nothing further to report from Museu
Paraense Emilio Goeldi and Mangal das Garqas for the week November
17th-November 23rd, I will move on and report on the pigeons, sparrows
and parrots of the city.
Feral Pigeons Columba livia dom. are not excessively numerous. The
most I ever saw together was 10 and that was on only a few occasions, more
often it was not as many as that. In appearance they were just like a
corresponding ensemble in a European city, being a similar mix of colour
varieties and about the same size. Even though the Portuguese had been at
Belem since its foundation in 1616 by Francisco Caleira Castelo Branco (its
strategic location at the mouth of the rivers Amazons enabled the Portuguese
to defend this vast and bountiful region from foreign invaders), Feral Pigeons
were not present before about 1860, otherwise Bates would surely have
mentioned them, for he was too broad-minded a naturalist not to have done
so. I think their introduction resulted with the coming of steamships, just
about the time Bates left to return to England, and with the greatly increased
rate of immigration, mostly from Portugal, Spain and Italy, which these
ships facilitated. The arrival of the Feral Pigeon in South America was an
inevitable consequence of its colonisation by Europeans, most of whom
must have wanted these birds in the cities they founded. Since then I think
the morphology of the Feral Pigeon has been maintained by recruits,
intentional or not, from Europe, facilitated by huge container-carrying ships
from places such as Hamburg in Germany, which is apparently the home
port of a big operator. They sail as far up river as Manaus, if not beyond.
One morning I got a brief view of a falcon which used the cover of the
Forte do Presepio to dash down to the fish dock, on which a few Feral
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994997" page_id="56261251"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
180
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.811863" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261251" page_num="180" year="" vol="">
HILL - VISIT TO BRAZIL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996009272727273" page_id="56261251"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
Pigeons habitually gathered. According to the book it could have been a
Peregrine Falco peregrinus. Similar remarks apply to the House Sparrows
Passer domesticus as to the Feral Pigeons. There were not many and I
never came across a mass roost as one can in many European countries.
Such roosts can be found in just about every city, town and village in Greece.
I strolled many times along the dockland road because it had less of the
bustle of the city centre and had enough free-standing fig trees offering
cover for birds and providing me with shade from the midday sun, but
disconcertingly it also provided cover for some individuals who were intent
on trying to steal from those they perceived to be easy victims, on a road
very little frequented by pedestrians. One such was the youth who came at
me with a knife, but whom, because I threatened retaliation, ran off.
There were some food processing factories nearby and there were several
Common Ground Doves Columbina passerina searching for food; as
sparrows might. I had actually seen this species earlier, just outside the
terminal buildings of Belem Airport. I had at the time though just landed
following a 10-hour flight from Frankfurt-am-Main, in what felt like a chilly,
over-refrigerated cabin, and emerged into the glare, heat and humidity of
equatorial Brazil, so will I hope be excused for not immediately recognising
this diminutive dove on that occasion.
There were lots of Brotogeris parakeets, even in the busiest parts of the
city. They were though hidden in the dense canopies of the massive mango
trees, which with some other equally, or even more massive, amenity trees,
are such a feature of the city. I never saw in this city, nor in any other city or
town I visited in Brazil, any evidence of the butchery of municipal trees,
which the tax-paying public in some European cities is conned into accepting,
because it is euphemistically passed off as "tree surgery". Massive trees are
appreciated, at least in the cities of Brazil, not only as cover for wildlife,
such as birds, but also because they provide much needed shade from the
midday equatorial sun. In the city centre I never got a view of the Brotogeris
parakeets, but their shrieking calls made passers-by aware of their presence,
as doubtless, they fed on ripe mangos and also perhaps on insects attracted
to the fruits.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998407" page_id="56261252"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
181
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9880765" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261252" page_num="181" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
TURACOS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995952526315789" page_id="56261252"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
Turacos - a natural history of the Musophagidae was published originally
in a large format and very expensive limited edition, now there is a smaller,
and hence more affordable edition of this major monograph from the Forshaw
and Cooper partnership. It contains the same combination of thorough,
informative text and superbly painted plates that we have come to expect
from this experienced and talented team.
The introduction provides a good overview of the relationships,
distribution and natural history of the turacos. This is followed by a chapter
on turacos in aviculture contributed by Robert Berry, who established, and
William Todd who continued, the successful turaco breeding programme at
Houston Zoo, Texas. The chapter begins with a brief account of early
breedings in the UK and France recorded in the Avicultural Magazine , and
goes on to summarize later successes in the USA, UK and Europe up to the
1970s, as various species became more available. Advice on general
husbandry, housing, breeding and feeding is sound, based as it is on the
authors' experiences at Houston Zoo. There is an interesting section on
captive status, but though this mentions the formation of the International
Turaco Society, it otherwise focuses largely on zoos, inevitably perhaps as
ISIS provides the only readily accessible and regularly updated source of
information on international captive populations.
The species accounts provide a detailed summary of published
information, very much in the Parrots of the World mould, and are
accompanied by William Cooper's accomplished plates which, again as in
previous titles, depict adults perching, displaying or feeding on and among
plants and landscapes typical of their habitats. The birds were painted from
individual museum skins, in addition to which the artist also travelled
extensively in Africa to study his subjects in life, and the text is liberally
illustrated with half-tone drawings showing birds engaged in a range of
natural behaviours, both in the wild and in captivity. The colour plates are
superb, not only in bringing the birds to life through naturalistic poses and
settings, but also in capturing accurately the range of metallic purples, blues
and greens which feature on the wing coverts and tails of many species. A
small criticism is that the Great Blue Turaco appears to have more delicate
legs than I remember. The text in the species accounts is organised under
the headings: Description, Distribution, Movements, Habits, Calls, Feeding,
Breeding and Eggs. For many species, the section on breeding draws heavily
on accounts of captive breedings, and the Avicultural Magazine features
prominently in the list of references.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998647" page_id="56261253"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
182
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.971545" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261253" page_num="182" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.898233428571429" page_id="56261253"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
All in all, this is a well-executed and produced book which will be enjoyed
by turaco enthusiasts and those who appreciate fine bird books. If I have a
reservation it is that the format makes it neither compact enough nor cheap
enough to find a home among the general run of bird books, yet it is not
large enough to have the same appeal as an impressive coffee table book.
Turacos - a natural history of the Musophagidae by Joseph M. Forshaw,
illustrated by William Cooper, 223 pages, is published by Nokomis Editons
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.745786" page_id="56261253"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
PTY Ltd., Victoria, Australia. Tel:+61 3 9486 1756/Fax:+61 3 9482 3573/
Website:www.nokomis.com.au /E-mail:nglavish@nokomis.com.au. Price
A$230.00 (approx. #92.25 or US$181.50, plus postage).
Nigel Hewston
THE PARROT COMPANION
The Parrot Companion by Rosemary Low provides new owners and
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.997198592592593" page_id="56261253"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
would-be owners of parrots with advice regarding what to look out for and
what to try to avoid. As Rosemary states, some parrots can live for a long
time and possibly outlive their owners, if looked after correctly.
The book is divided into nine chapters and has some really nice colour
photos, showing what the different parrot species look like. Rosemary offers
sound advice as to what to expect from different types of parrots, when it
comes to noise, suitability as pets, and size. The 192 pages cover just about
everything that one needs to know and answers a lot of questions regarding
owning parrots, rearing parrots, and suitable housing for these birds.
It then moves on to what one will need and what to buy in the way of
suitable toys, a good cage that will be its home, with cage bars and spacings
explained, as well as the various types of food containers, water drinkers
and perches etc. The next chapter explains how to introduce your parrot
and help it become a family member, with things to do and things that you
should not do explained. There is a chapter on how to avoid problems such
as biting, feather plucking, screaming, and possible ways to cure these
problems. Then there is a chapter on basic training, a must for any pet
parrot, with the author explaining how to go about this important aspect,
such as training the bird to step up and step down, plus explaining clicker
training and what you should not do.
In the chapter on feeding, Rosemary sets out to explain which foods are
good and which foods are bad for pet parrots. There is information on fat
content, protein, carbohydrates, calcium and much more about the types of
food that are available. A lot of detail is given on the various nuts suitable
for parrots, as well as fruits and vegetables and other foods.
Towards the end of the book there is a chapter on health and beauty,
which explains how to look after your bird's health and the early detection
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909704" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261254" page_num="183" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999313" page_id="56261254"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
183
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9972" page_id="56261254"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
of ill-health. It also points out the types of things birds should not be given
to play with so as to avoid problems such as metal poisoning. The final
chapter deals with re-homing parrots. I sometimes wish people would read
this chapter first, as it would possibly help some parrots to remain with their
owners.
This is a very good book for those about to embark on the road to
becoming a parrot keeper, as well as for those that want to try to improve
their parrot's life.
The Parrot Companion by Rosemary Low, which covers caring for
parrots, macaws, budgies, cockatiels and more, has 192 pages and numerous
colour photos and other illustrations. It is published by New Holland
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.776118653846154" page_id="56261254"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
Publishers (UK) Ltd., 86-88 Edgware Road, London W2 2EA. Price #12.99.
It is available from all good book shops, online booksellers and by mail
order from LBS on: 01903 828503.
Cliff Wright
The IV International Symposium On
Breeding Birds in Captivity
- l|e Intemtiowl Gatbrnny of tl?e World&amp;apos;s Finest Aviculturists -
Toronto, Ontario, Canada
Some of the benefits of attending this symposium include;
September 12-16, 2007
DoubleTree Int. Plaza
www. ISBBC. org
+ The opportunity to further the success and fecundity of
ESTABLISHED BREEDING PROGRAMS FOR BOTH IN AND EX-SITU
INITIATIVES.
-i- The opportunity to converse and engage with some of the
+ Experience one of the most culturally diverse cities and
COUNTRIES IN THE WORLD, MAKING IT THE PERFECT VENUE FOR
INTERNATIONAL COLLABORATION AND PARTICIPATION.
WORLD LEADERS IN THE FIELDS OF AVICULTURE, ZOOLOGY, ORNITHOLC
AND AVIAN CONSERVATION.
For More Information Please Visit Us Online At
WWW.ISBBC.ORG
Or Call
+1 416. 910. AVES
+L 604. 866. AVES
</table>
<page confidence="0.999551" page_id="56261255"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
184
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.844898" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261255" page_num="184" year="" vol="">
DO YOU KEEP EITHER OF THESE SMALL DOVES?
</sectionHeader>
<author confidence="0.405698">
Jerry Fisher
</author>
<bodyText confidence="0.998863342105263" page_id="56261255"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
Most aviculturists are familiar with the Diamond Dove Geopelia cuneata
which is now domesticated and of which almost inevitably colour varieties
have been established. Fortunately there exists a ring-fenced, small group
of pure normal-coloured Diamond Doves, and if anyone is interested in
helping to maintain this group, they should get in touch with us (see below).
The Namaqua or Cape Dove Oena capensis, which until recently was
still being imported into the UK, is a different proposition. Unless there is
a concerted effort by small dove enthusiasts, this delightful bird could be
lost to aviculture, if the current import restrictions remain. It is quieter and
even steadier than the Diamond Dove and its behaviour and care are very
similar. Surprisingly, both species will cohabit peacefully in a reasonable
sized aviary.
Losses of recently imported Namaqua or Cape Doves could be high and
they have a reputation for being delicate which, until last year, I regarded as
fully justified. Then, in January 2005, I saw two pairs and their offspring
living happily in outside aviaries, protected from the elements only by a
layer of bubble-wrap. Admittedly it was in Cornwall, but I later discovered
that Alan Ollerenshaw had been breeding them outdoors for a couple of
seasons in Nottinghamshire.
My own birds (acquired from Cornwall) have bred this year in a heated
shelter connected to a flight in which they spend most of their time and in
which I am sure they would breed if I let them. I have received information
from New Zealand that this dove has been bred there using a colony system.
Here in the UK we now have a nucleus of fully acclimatized captive-
bred birds and Alan and I are anxious to build upon this and assemble a
small group of aviculturists committed to establishing a captive-bred self-
sustaining population of Namaqua or Cape Doves in the UK. We are, of
course, also keen to hear from anyone who is already breeding this species.
We are seeking people who are prepared to make a simple but serious
commitment to keep accurate breeding records (the base population has
good genetic diversity) and to retain birds they have bred until the end of
the season for disposals and exchanges within the group. Only then will
any suplus birds be put on the open market and group members will, as far
as possible, be expected to keep track of them.
Colony breeding is a medium-term possibility, but only appears to work
successfully with proven bonded pairs - which is another reason to keep
track of as many pairs as possible.
There is another area with which assistance would be much appreciated.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999631" page_id="56261256"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
185
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.98504665" page_id="56261256"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
We do, of course, occasionally experience losses of adult birds and part-
grown chicks. Given that we are private aviculturists of modest means the
cost of detailed post mortem examinations of each bird lost would be
prohibitive. Nevertheless we are concerned that as a consequence we may
be missing clues that could help us improve our husbandry of these birds -
especially if trends develop over a number of deaths. Therefore, if anyone
can offer veterinary support in this area it would be greatly appreciated.
Should this embrace the involvement of a professionally managed collection
in the breeding programme so much the better.
In due course I hope to assemble a comprehensive article on the Namaqua
or Cape Dove based on direct experience and published information, but
more extensive experience with this species is required before this can be
undertaken.
If you are interested in the above and have suitable facilities and are
prepared to make a commitment for 2007, involving one or more pairs,
Alan and I would like to hear from you. Please bear in mind that the Namaqua
or Cape Dove is an inoffensive species that is easily bullied, so suitable
aviary companions for it must be chosen carefully.
Further information is available from Jerry Fisher in Devon (Tel: 01803
528561), Alan Otterenshaw in Nottinghamshire (Tel: 01623 465198) or Paul
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.567326" page_id="56261256"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
Boulden (E-mail:Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk)
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.718454" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261256" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
US BANK ACCOUNT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.955274333333333" page_id="56261256"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
Those who would prefer to make payments in US dollars are reminded
that the society also has a US bank account. Overseas membership for 2007
will remain at US$38 for receiving magazines by regular mail or US$50 for
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.787183666666667">
air mail. Checks and money orders should be made payable to The
Avicultural Society and sent to: The Avicultural Society, c/o Jane Cooper,
12650 Hearst Road, Willits, California 95490-9231, USA.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999328" page_id="56261257"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
186
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9622975" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261257" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
EVENTUALTOTAL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.943079846153846" page_id="56261257"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
An eventual total of 11 Green Aracaris Pterglossus viridis were hatched
this year at The Dallas World Aquarium (website: www.dwazoo.com) all of
which fledged. Two of the clutches were parent-reared, one by a pair the
female of whom had already hatched a clutch earlier this year and who
herself was hatched at the aquarium in 2005. Two of the five female Guianan
Cock-of-the-Rocks Rupicola rupicola (with six males) which Josef
Lindholm works with were nesting (at the time he wrote), though no eggs
had yet been laid. The group of three male and seven female Andean Cock-
of-the-Rocks R. peruviana in the care of his wife, Natalie, also includes two
nest builders. Other cotingas represented in the collection are: Spangled
Cotinga Cotinga cayana, Purple-breasted Cotinga C. cotinga, Bare-necked
Fruitcrow Gymnoderus foetidus and Purple-throated Fruitcrow Querula
purpurata.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.40275575" page_id="56261257"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
* * *
TEN A YEAR
On my most recent visit (October 2006) to The Eden Project
(website:www.edenproject.com) at Bodelva, St Austell, Cornwall, I failed
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.9612796" page_id="56261257"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
to see or hear the white-eyes Zoster ops sp., introduced into the Humid Tropics
Biome to help control insect numbers. On enquiring though, I was assured
they are still there, are Sulawesi White-eyes Z. consobrinorum and about 10
have been bred each year since 2001, thereby maintaining a more or less
stable population.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.514330666666667" page_id="56261257"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
* * *
RARE DOVE BRED FOR THE FIRST TIME
Two White-throated Ground Doves Gallicolumba xanthonura have
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.967251166666667" page_id="56261257"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
been bred at Louisville Zoo in the USA. The first hatched on October 17th
and the second was hatched by the same pair on December 1 st. It is believed
to be the first ever captive breeding of this rare Micronesian ground dove.
Curator of Birds Gary Michael, who developed the environment which
was conducive to the breeeding success in the zoo's Forest Bird Trail Exhibit
in the Islands Pavilion, is thrilled with the success. Breeding the White-
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.785132">
throated Ground Dove was a goal of the Micronesian Avian-Conservation
Program, in which Louisville, Memphis and St Louis Zoos, the US Fish and
Wildlife Service, Micronesia's fish and wildlife officials and the Association
of Zoos and Aquariums (AZA) all cooperate.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700044" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261258" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995799" page_id="56261258"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
187
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990307" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56261258" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
GOOD AND BAD NEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.981481888888889" page_id="56261258"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
Since 2002, Fort Worth Zoo, Texas, has bred 27 Lesser Flamingos
Phoeniconaias minor , from a breeding group consisting of only 18 adults.
Mirrors on the walls create the illusion that the birds are members of a much
larger group. In addition, heat lamps and pools of water create a tropical
atmosphere and timed lighting produces 14-hour days.
Recently The Times (October 21 st) reported than an international rescue
mission, headed by the Wildfowl &amp; Wetlands Trust, has been set up to try to
"save" the Lesser Flamingo in Kenya and Tanzania, where 100,000 birds
have died this year. It has failed to breed there for the past seven years.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.838121" page_id="56261258"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.923148" genericHeader="general terms" page_id="56261258" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
SEEN ON REMOTE LAKE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.980945888888889" page_id="56261258"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
Nine adult and four recently-hatched young Madagascar Pochard Ay thy a
innotata were seen on a remote lake in northern Madagascar by
conservationists from The Peregrine Fund Madagascar Project. Feared to
possibly be extinct, this white-eyed, diving duck, had not been seen since
1991, when a male was captured on Lake Alaotra in central Madagascar and
kept at Antananarivo Zoological and Botanical Garden until its death a year
later.
Cecil Webb visited Lake Alaotra to collect waterfowl in 1929 and 1935
and in 1939 was about to set off again for the lake when over the radio he
heard Neville Chamberlain declare war. On the first occasion he set off for
the lake with Jean Delacour, who was leading an Anglo-Franco-American
ornithology expedition to Madagascar, and with Willoughby Low, who was
official collector for the British Museum. Webb obtained Hottentot Teal
Anas punctata , Meller's Duck A melleri , Red-billed Teal A erythrorhyncha ,
Fulvous Whistling Duck Dendrocygna bicolor , White-faced Whistling Duck
D. viduata, Madagascar Pochard, which he stated was confined to Lake
Alaotra and, White-backed Duck Thalassornis leuconotus which, he wrote,
was the most difficult to get.
In 1935 Webb left Madagascar for England with African Pygmy Geese
Nettapus auritus , Hottetot Teal, Madagascar Pochard, Meller's Duck, Red-
billed Teal, White-backed Duck, "Cuvier's Rail Dryolimnas cuvierf -
presumably the present day White-throated Rail Canirallus cuvieri -
Madagascar Bee-eater Merops superciliosus and other birds. On the way
home the boat stopped at Anjouan, one of the Comoro Islands, where Cecil
Webb took the opportunity to go ashore and, with only an hour to spare,
managed to catch a male Anjouan Sunbird Nectarinia comorensis , the first
of its kind ever to be collected alive.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998726" page_id="56261259"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
188
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.981296" genericHeader="method" page_id="56261259" page_num="188" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
PACIFIC PARROTS APPEAL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993811625" page_id="56261259"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
"The beautiful islands of the Pacific have long captured our imaginations
with visions of palm trees, brilliantly plumaged birds, abrupt mountains
plunging steeply down to white sands and balmy jewel-toned waters. They
are home to spectacular species that exist nowhere else, including one quarter
of the world's globally threatened birds. But beneath the pretty picture a
life and death battle is being waged with a long-standing enemy of island-
nesting birds: the black rat", so reads the opening paragraph of BirdLife
International's 2006 Pacific Parrots Appeal.
It is appealing for help to save several small parrot species such as Kuhfs
or the Rimatara Lorikeet Vini kuhlii , Ultramarine Lorikeet V ultramarina
and Uvea Parakeet Eunymphicus uvaeensis (of which fewer than 750
survive). Such species are confined to only one or a few islands, which
makes them extremely vulnerable to extinction.
Money raised by the appeal will enable the BirdLife International
Partnership to translocate Kuhfs or Rimatara Lorikeets from Rimatara in
French Polynesia to rat-free Atiu, one of the southern Cook Islands. It will
also enable BirdLife International to train staff of local organisations in the
techniques of eradicating rats. It has plans to reintroduce other threatened
species onto suitable islands once the rats have been eradicated. It also
wants to strengthen prevention measures against the invasion of Black Rats
Rattus rattus onto other islands which are the last refuge of endangered
parrots and other species.
Donations in pounds sterling, euros or US dollars (cheques should be
made payable to BirdLife International or in the case of the latter to American
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.61023325" page_id="56261259"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
Friends of BirdLife International, Inc.) can be sent to: 2006 Pacific Parrots
Appeal, BirdLife International, Wei!brook Court, Girton Road, Cambridge
CB3 0NA, UK. Fax:+44 (0)1223 277200.
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.81389" genericHeader="method" page_id="56261259" page_num="188" year="" vol="">
MISSING MAGAZINES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99764925" page_id="56261259"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
It is believed that some copies of the Avicultural Magazine VoL 112, No.3,
may have gone astray in the post. If you did not receive that issue, please
notify the Hon. Secretary/Treasurer, Paul Boulden, whose addresses, both
postal and e-mail, can be found on the inside cover and at the foot of pi 73.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999075" page_id="56261260"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
189
</page>
<table confidence="0.887403424242424" page_id="56261260"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
Contributors to Volume 112 - 2006
Andrews, Bryan
Breeding the Elegant Crested Tinamou Eudromia e. elegans ............... Ill
Breeding tthe White-headed Mousebird Colius leucocephalus ............ 116
Boulden, Paul
The Autumn Social Meeting - 2005 .......................................................... 5
Brickell, Neville
Collated data on the Madagascar Fody Foudia madagascariensis ....... 169
Braslund Jensen, Simon
A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation, Qatar:
working with turacos Musophagidae spp.............................................. 125
Chaney, Andrew
Further success with the Brown Twinspot Clytospiza monte in,
including the first parent reared young .................................................... 2
Cristinacce, Andrew, Ladkoo, Amanda, Kovac, Elise, Jordan, Lara,
Morris, Anne, Williams, Trace, de Ravel Koenig, Frederique,
Tatayah, Vikash and Jones, Carl
The first harid-rearing of Mauritian white-eyes Zosterops spp. ............ 150
Davies, Martin
Breeding the Black-capped Social Weaver Pseudonigrita cabanisi ..... 119
Eitniear, Jack Clinton
Breeding and diet of the Croaking Ground Dove Columbina cruziana .. 75
Francis, John E. R.
Hand-rearing a Spangled Cotinga Cotinga cayana ................................ 19
Gamham, Carl
Breeding the 'Red-billed Buffalo- Weaver Bubaiornis n. intermedins ... 145
Gibson, Derek
Breeding the White-browed Coucal Centropus superciliosus
at Exmoor Wildlife Park......................................................................... 49
Gregson, Jo
On the Edge ............................................................................................ 60
Hewston, Nigel
Breeding the Black-faced Laughingthrash Garrulax affinis .................. 97
</table>
<page confidence="0.997883" page_id="56261261"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
190
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.853261" page_id="56261261"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
Contributors to Volume 112 - 2006 (cont'd)
Hill, Brian A. G.
Memoir, notes and anthology arising from a visit to Brazil... 174
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.395057625" page_id="56261261"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
Jerrard, Jim
Breeding the Sooty-headed Bulbul Pycnonotus aurigaster ... 4
Mangold, Walter
Breeding the Greater Flamingo - the first success in 15 years.71
Owen, Andrew
Breeding the White-bellied Go-away Bird
Corythaixoides leucogaster at Waddesdon Manor..... 62
Peat, Louise
Cotswold Wildlife Park Review of 2005..... 6
Quinque, Henry
Breeding the St Vincent Parrot Amazona guildingii ...24
Restall, Robin
The Chestnut-bellied Seed-Finch Oryzoborus angolensis
in the wild and in aviculture... 10
Reul-Schneider, Martina and Schneider, Holger
Some notes on our experiences of keeping and breeding the
Yeilow-throated Laughingthrush Garrulax galbanus courtoisi ............. 53
Roles, D. Grenville
A flying visit to Costa Rica ...... 84
Sproule, Mark
Notes on the care and breeding of the
Turquoise Tanager Tangara mexicana......... ........ 161
Wilkinson, Roger
Avicultural support for the Echo Parakeet Programme on Mauritius ... 102
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.669317666666667">
Yazzolino, Rick, St Michael, Shawn and Rutkowski, Charlie
Breeding the Green-naped Lorikeet Trichoglossus h. haematodus
in a mixed-species exhibit at Oregon Zoo.... 39
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999193" page_id="56261262"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
191
</page>
<table confidence="0.430158966666667" page_id="56261262"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
Index to Volume 112 - 2006
Amazona guildingii, breeding.................................................................. 24
Book Reviews
International Zoo Yearbook, Volume 40 .......................................... 139
Roberts - Birds of Southern Africa .................................................... 89
The Bedside Book of Birds - An Avian Miscellany........................... 90
The Parrot Companion..................................................................... 182
Turacos - a natural history of the Musophagidae............................. 181
Brazil, memoir, notes and anthology arising from a visit ..................... 174
Bubalornis niger intermedins , breeding ................................................ 145
Buffalo-Weaver, Red-billed, breeding................................................... 145
Bulbul, Sooty-headed, breeding ................................................................ 4
Centropus supereiliosus, probable first UK breeding ............................. 49
Clytospiza monteiri, further success, including parent-reared young ....... 2
Coitus leucocephalus , probable first UK breeding................................ 116
Columbina cruziana, breeding and diet................................................... 75
Corythaixoides leucogaster , probable first UK breeding ........................ 62
Costa Rica, birds seen during a flying visit............................................. 84
Cotinga cayana , successful hand-rearing................................................ 19
Cotinga, Spangled, successful hand-rearing............................................ 19
Cotswold Wildlife Park, Review of 2005 .................................................. 6
Coucal, White-browed, probable first UK breeding................................ 49
Dove, Socorro, captive breeding ............................................................. 60
Eudromia e. slogans, breeding .............................................................. Ill
Flamingo, Greater, breeding, first success in 15 years ............................ 71
Fody, Madagascar, collated data............................................................ 169
Foudia madagascariensis , collated data ............................................... 169
Garrulax affinus , probable first UK breeding ......................................... 97
Garruiax galbanus courtoisi , experiences of keeping and breeding....... 53
Garrulax galbanus courtoisi , in the wild and in captivity ...................... 57
</table>
<reference confidence="0.83685825">
Go-away Bird, White-bellied, probable first UK breeding ..................... 62
Ground Dove, Croaking, breeding and diet............................................. 75
Hombills, in Thailand, report, 2005 ........................................................ 34
Laugh mg thrush, Black-faced, probable first UK breeding ..................... 97
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999395" page_id="56261263"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
192
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.905190333333333" page_id="56261263"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
Index to Volume 112 \0x25A0 2006 (Cont'd)
Laughingthmsh, Yellow-throated, experiences of keeping and
breeding, also in the wild and in captivity......................................... 53, 57
Liocichla, Rugan, discovery of this new species. 123
Liocichla bugunorum, discovery of this new species............................. 123
Lorikeet, Green-naped, breeding in mixed-species exhibit..................... 39
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.677079592592593" page_id="56261263"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
Mousebird, White-headed, probable first UK breeding ........................ 116
Musophaga violacea , developing captive management strategies ........ 125
News &amp; Views ................................................................... 44, 91, 141, 186
Officers and Council Members, as from January 1st 2006 ....................... 1
Oryzoborus angolensis , in the wild and in aviculture ............................. 10
Parakeet, Echo, avicultural support for breeding programme ............... 102
Parrot, St Vincent, breeding..................................................................... 24
Phoenicopterus ruber roseus , breeding, first success in 15 years ........... 71
Psittacula eques , avicultural support for breeding programme............. 102
Pseudonigrita cabanisi , probable first UK breeding .............................119
Pycnonotus aurigaster , breeding ............................................................... 4
Seed-Finch, Chestnut-bellied, in the wild and in aviculture ................... 10
Social Meeting, Autumn 2005 ................................................................... 5
Social Weaver, Black-capped, probable first UK breeding ................... 119
Tanager, Turquoise, care and breeding .................................................. 161
Tangara mexicana , care and breeding ................................................... 161
Tauraco ruspolii , AWWP-funded research in Ethiopia ......................... 125
Tinamou, Elegant Crested, breeding ..................................................... Ill
Trichoglossus h. haematodus , breeding in mixed-species exhibit .......... 39
Turaco, Prince Ruspoli's, AWWP-funded research in Ethiopia ............ 125
Turaco, Violet, developing captive management strategies .................. 125
Twinspot, Brown, further success, including parent-reared young ........... 2
White-eye, Mauritius Grey, first hand-rearing ..................... ..A............. 150
White-eye, Mauritius Olive, first hand-rearing ..................................... 150
Zenaida graysoni , captive breeding ........................................................ 60
Zoster ops borbonica mauritianus , first hand-rearing ............................ 150
Zosterops chloronothos , first hand-rearing............................................ 150
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.620475" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261264" page_num="" year="" vol="">
A VERY ENCOURAGING RESULT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.890774352941176" page_id="56261264"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Gouldian Finch Erythrum gouldiae surveys are conducted annually at
Momington Station in the Kimberley, northern Western Australia (see News
&amp; Views Vol. 112, No. 1, p.48 (2006)) and form a vital part of the monitoring
programme, which includes gauging the effects of changing management
regimes on the flora and fauna. This year's surveys were conducted over a
week around designated waterholes along four watercourses where seed-
eating species using the waterholes during a two-hour period were counted.
All participants observed Gouldians at some stage over the course of the
field work, and some were lucky enough to see over 100 during their surveys.
Although fewer were counted than in 2005, it is thought that they have
again increased on the property. In 2005 there was little water available and
the birds were concentrated around it, making them easier to count, but this
year was wetter and they were widely dispersed. Despite this, only a few
hundred fewer birds were seen. Other species encountered included Peaceful
Doves Geopelia placida , Pectorella Mannikins Heteromunia pectoralis (in
large numbers), Long-tailed Grassfinches Peophila acuticauda and Double-
barred or Bicheno Finches Tceniopygia bichenovii.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.540682" page_id="56261264"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.491812" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56261264" page_num="" year="" vol="">
HABITAT CONSERVATION AND CAPTIVE BREEDING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.957987142857143" page_id="56261264"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The latest Gouldian Finch Ery thrum gouldiae news is reported in
Wingspan Vol. 16, No.4, p.6, December 2006, published quarterly by Birds
Australia. It is followed by news of some of the media coverage there of the
Orange-bellied Parrot/Parakeet Neophema chrysogaster. Earlier in the year,
the Federal Minister for the Environment and Heritage, declined approval
for a wind farm in Victoria, because of how it might affect the Orange-
bellied Parrot/Parakeet, which has a known population of only 150 or so
birds.
Later he announced that the Australian Government would allocate A$3.2
million (approx. #1.2 million or US$2.2 million) to the Orange-bellied Parrot
recovery effort over two years, focusing on habitat conservation and captive
breeding. He also elevated the species' official conservation status to
Critically Endangered. The would-be wind farm developer also offered
A$750,000 (approx. #300,000 or US$570,000) to the recovery effort.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.621261" page_id="56261265"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
3 9088 01283 3570
CONTENTS
1
J
</figure>
<table confidence="0.73702119047619" page_id="56261265"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Breeding the Red-billed Buffalo-Weaver
Bulbalornis niger intermedius
by Carl Garnham. 145
The first hand-rearing of Mauritian white-eyes Zoster ops spp.
by Andrew Cristinacce, Amanda Ladkoo, Elise Kovac,
Lara Jordan, Anne Morris, Trace Williams,
Frederique de Ravel Koenig, Vikash Tatayah and Carl Jones .... 150
Notes on the care and breeding of the Turquoise Tanager
Tangara mexicana
by Mark Sproule. 161
Collated data on the Madagascar Fody
Foudia madagascariensis
by Neville Brickell. 169
Memoir, notes and anthology arising from a visit to Brazil
by Brian A. G. Hill. 174
Book Reviews
Turacos - a natural history of the Musophagidae. 181
The Parrot Companion... 182
News &amp; Views. 186
Contributors to Volume 112 - 2006 . 189
Index to Volume 112 - 2006
</table>
<page confidence="0.958001" page_id="56261265"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
191
</page>
<figure confidence="0.5471655" page_id="56261265"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</figure>
</algorithms>
