<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.858466" page_id="56264563"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 116
No.l
2010
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264564" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.984815548387097" page_id="56264564"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2010 as for 2009: British
Isles #18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please).
The subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the
Society later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of
the AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, ARCADIA, THE MOUNTS, TOTNES, DEVON TQ9 7QJ,
UK.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TNI 3 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail: Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have not
been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of a
particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history. Articles
should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the scientific
names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given. References
cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line drawings,
black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular point in
the article will be used where possible and should be clearly captioned. If
authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when submitting the
article and write their name on the back of each photograph. Tables and
graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be aware of
the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of the page
which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997594" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264564" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982475333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.756491" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264565" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.226443" page_id="56264565"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 116 - No. 1 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2010
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.353921">
The Avicultural Society
</subsectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.992312" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264565" page_num="" year="" vol="">
FOR THE STUDY OF BRITISH AND FOREIGN BIRDS
IN THE WILD AND CAPTIVITY
OFFICERS AND COUNCIL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.560997" page_id="56264565"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
As from March 27th 2010
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.900896125" page_id="56264565"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
President
R. C. J. Sawyer
Vice Presidents
F. Bamicoat (South Africa)
S. Bruslund Jensen (Germany)
M. Curzon MBE (UK)
Dr W. Grummt (Germany)
C. J.S.Marler (UK)
Dr H. Quinque (France)
R. L. Restall (Venezuela)
Dr R. Wilkinson (UK)
Honorary Editor
M. Ellis
Honorary Secretary - Treasurer
P. Boulden
Members of Council
P. Convy
J. A. Ellis
Mrs L. Gardner
R. B. Girling
J. Gregson
N. R. Hewston
G. Masson
S. Pyper
V. P. Sargent
P. G. Schofield
P. Stocks
J. G. Thurlow
B. Tremlett
J. Trollope
Ms R. Wiseman
Chairman C.J.S. Marler
</figure>
<page confidence="0.900358" page_id="56264566"  page_num="2" year="" vol="">
2
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.992132" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264566" page_num="2" year="" vol="">
CHALLENGES AND OPPORTUNITIES FOR
SUSTAINABLE WILDLIFE MANAGEMENT IN
CAMEROON: THE STORY OF PEGGY
AN AFRICAN GREY PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.358837" page_id="56264566"  page_num="2" year="" vol="">
by Ajaga Nji, Simon A. Tamungang, W. L. Asong,
Mbafor Fidelia, Tsafack Antoine and Sabi B. Nji
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.916061" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264566" page_num="2" year="" vol="">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989663709677419" page_id="56264566"  page_num="2" year="" vol="">
Parrots have historically been, and continue to be, the most exploited
wild birds, vast numbers of them being taken from the wild, many of them
destined to become household pets. However, it is frequently daunting to
keep what was once a wild bird, that has been removed from its natural
habitat. We report on our experience of managing a Grey Parrot Psittacus
erithacus, named Peggy, in captivity. The management of Peggy, both before
and following an accident, enabled us to better understand and appreciate
the intricacies involved in the captive management of parrots in Cameroon.
Peggy's accident led to us having to perform experimental emergency surgery
in a attempt to save her life. We have no knowledge of such surgery being
attempted before and it has compelled us to rethink how to manage a similar
case, should it occur, in the future. Current policies and activities on wildlife
management in Cameroon suggest that the country has both the will and the
potential to sustainably conserve and exploit her wildlife endowment amidst
socioeconomic and administrative setbacks. There is increasing interest in
both the public and private sectors in conserving parrot populations and their
habitats. There is an urgent need, however, for more specialist attention
and material investment in wildlife management in Cameroon; and, above
all, there is a need for further research and innovation in the management
and conservation of the Grey Parrot population, in particular, and wildlife
in general.
Introduction
With its varied wildlife habitats and ecosystems, Cameroon has some of
the most spectacular wildlife in Africa. These assets represent the country's
biological diversity and are part of Africa's biological heritage. At the same
time, the country has a fast-growing human population, most of whom are
rural dwellers, often living in poverty admidst increasing environmental
degradation. The majority of the rural population depend on the land
for traditional agriculture, but this is not sustainable given the current
rapid growth rate of the population. The Cameroon Government strives
to sustainably conserve the biodiversisty of the country, but has suffered
</bodyText>
<copyright confidence="0.23099">
NJI ET AL. - AFRICAN GREY PARROT
</copyright>
<page confidence="0.973953" page_id="56264567"  page_num="3" year="" vol="">
3
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999464024390244" page_id="56264567"  page_num="3" year="" vol="">
setbacks emanating mostly from the way her environmental conservation
policies have evolved since the colonial period. However, the government in
collaboration, principally with a number of non-governmental organizations
(NGOs), is making efforts to ensure that its existing policies are more
effective and efficient and guarantee the sustainability of biodiversity
conservation in Cameroon.
Parrots form part of the country's most cherished and exploited biological
diversity, and the increasing demand for parrots is driving a probable
unsustainable harvesting of the wild birds (CITES, 2001). The unsustainable
harvesting of the wild parrots and the failure to manage their exploitation
on a rational basis have led to population depletion in African countries,
as tens of thousands of parrots are captured legally and illegally for local
consumption and for export (Fry et al. 1988; Dandliker, 1992; TRAFFIC
International, 2005).
Yet, here in the Cameroon, the number of parrot species, their population
sizes and their geographical distribution are not well documented. Besides
the direct removal of parrots from the wild, there is persistent deforestation
and fragmentation of the remaining forests for timber, plantations, dams,
road construction, real estate and various urbanisation projects. From
1994-2006, CITES annual export quota for Grey Parrots from Cameroon
was 12,000 birds, though this quota was exceeded in some years when up
to 24,000 Grey Parrots were exported (Dandliker, 1992; Mulliken, 1995;
CITES, 2001). At present, the Cameroon authorities have no population
based data that can be used to decide sustainable harvesting levels for
parrots. The dearth of information and technology make it difficult for the
administration to take sustainable parrot management decisions. Cognizance
of this vacuum contributed to the design of the Cameroon Parrots Project,
PARROTPRO, in 2000.
Its major goals are to enhance parrot resources conservation and related
areas of wildlife conservation, by seeking suitable mechanisms for providing
feedback to local communities on conservation strategies, the exchange of
field experiences and best practise with parrot-friendly people in Cameroon
and beyond. The overall goal of the project is to empower the conservation
of parrot resources by the civil society through rural communities and, for
the alleviation of poverty, while at the same time promoting the sustainable
exploitation of their ecosystems.
One of the gaps that PARROTPRO has begun to fill is in improving
the livelihoods of parrots in captivity in Cameroon. This is carried out
through conservation education forums with individuals who keep parrots
as household pets. We advise them on the best ways to improve the health
and happiness of their parrots, by improved feeding (Tamungang et al. 2002;
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.980931" page_id="56264568"  page_num="4" year="" vol="">
4
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.995289897435898" page_id="56264568"  page_num="4" year="" vol="">
NJI ET AL. - AFRICAN GREY PARROT
Tamungang &amp; Ajayi, 2003), human-parrot interactions, cage construction
and management, and also advise them on dealing with parrot diseases.
Background to study area
The Republic of Cameroon (Republique du Cameroun) is a unitary
republic in West Africa, on the Gulf of Guinea. It covers an area of475,442sq
km (183,569sq miles) and is the world's fifty-third largest country (it is
somewhat larger than California). It is often called "Africa in miniature,"
on account of its geological and cultural diversity. Natural features include
beaches, deserts, mountains, rainforests and savannahs. The highest point
is Mt Cameroon (4,096m, (13,435ft)) and the largest cities are Douala,
Yaounde and Garoua. There are over 200 different ethnic and linguistic
groups. Cameroon is well known for its native styles of music, particularly
makossa and bikutsi, and its successful national football team. English and
French are the official languages.
Cameroon is divided into five major geographical zones, distinguished
by their dominant physical, climatic and vegetative features. The coastal
plain extends 15km-150km (10 miles-90 miles) inland from the Gulf of
Guinea and has an average elevation of 90m (295ft). Exceedingly hot and
humid and with a short dry season, it is densely forested and includes some
of the wettest places on earth. The South Cameroon Plateau rises from the
coastal plain to an average elevation of650m (2,130ft). Equatorial rainforest
dominates this zone and the alternation between wet and dry seasons makes
it less humid than the coast.
An irregular chain of mountains, hills and plateaus, known as the
Cameroon range, extend from Mt Cameroon on the coast almost to Lake
Chad at Cameroon's northern tip. This region has a mild climate, particularly
on the Western High Plateau, although rainfall is high. Its soil is among
the most fertile in Cameroon, especially around volcanic Mt Cameroon.
Vulcanism here has created crater lakes. On August 21 st 1986, one of these,
Lake Nyos, belched out carbon dioxide and killed 1,700-2,000 people.
The southern plateau rises northward to the grassy, rugged Adamawa
Plateau. This stretches from the western mountain area and forms a barrier
between the north and south of the country. Its average elevation is 1,100m
(3,600ft) and the temperature ranges from 22*C-25*C (71.6*F-77*F) with
high rainfall. The northern lowland region extends from the edge of the
Adamawa Plateau to Lake Chad and has an average elevation of300m-350m
(980ft-l, 150ft). Its characteristic vegetation is savannah shrub and grass.
This is an arid region with sparse rainfall and high median temperatures.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.566216">
Materials and methods
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9968855" page_id="56264568"  page_num="4" year="" vol="">
Hundreds of people keep parrots in captivity in Cameroon. The majority
keep them as household pets, but they are also kept for a multitude of other
</bodyText>
<copyright confidence="0.22849">
NJI ET AL. - AFRICAN GREY PARROT
</copyright>
<page confidence="0.952398" page_id="56264569"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
5
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998133609756098" page_id="56264569"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
reasons. Some are kept for use in traditional medicines and a few people
keep them as a ready source of red feathers, which are plucked from the
birds and used in cultural rites. Whatever the objectives of keeping a parrot
at home, generally they are not well cared for, their health care, feeding and
housing being of greatest concern. Many of the problems associated with
the management of captive parrots are related to poor cage construction and
management. In 2006, when we carried out a survey of cages constructed
in Cameroon, we found that the standard of the cages we examined fell far
below our expectations (see photo on following page). There are a number
of reasons why many parrot keepers do not house their parrots in what we
would consider to be good cages. These include not knowing where to obtain
a good cage, because of poverty being unable to afford to buy a good cage,
and ignorance of the required qualities of a good parrot cage. In response to
these problems, two of the authors, Dr Simon A. Tamungang (Ornithologist
and Project Leader of PARROTPRO) and Prof. AjagaNji (Rural Sociologist),
both of the University of Dschang, Cameroon, designed a model parrot
cage. The objective was to construct a suitable cage that is economically
affordable, socially desirable, culturally acceptable, politically expedient and
technically efficient (Nji, 1992). It will not only improve the happiness of
the parrot, but also provide optimum hygienic conditions and promote social
interaction between the parrot and members of the household. As can be
seen in the photographs on p.7, it is of metal construction and when ready
for use is fitted with wooden perches, to simulate those in the parrot's natural
habitat, and add to the parrot's comfort, safety and happiness.
To test the suitability of the cage, a Grey Parrot, aged about two years
old, was bought from a government certified parrot exporter in Yaounde,
Cameroon. We named the bird Peggy. She was placed in the cage, which was
positioned at the entrance to the inner residence of Prof. Nji and his family,
to give her the opportunity to interact with family members and visitors. It
enabled her to become people-friendly, socialize easily and learn from regular
interaction with the residents of the house. The family also has two German
shepherd, guard dogs, about which there will be more later.
A fast learner
Within a few days of Peggy's arrival, we realised that she was an
intelligent and fast learner. She began by imitating sounds such as the car
alarm going off and the barking of the dogs. After a few months, she had
begun to call the names of members of the family, beginning with that of
Ngum, four-and-half years of age, the youngest daughter, who had been
given the parrot as a birthday present. Within a year, Peggy had learnt the
names of virtually every member of the household. In a voice identical
to that of a human, she could call: Ngum, Sabi, Agwe, Mundih, Junior
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.992103" page_id="56264570"  page_num="6" year="" vol="">
6
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9907175" page_id="56264570"  page_num="6" year="" vol="">
NJI ET AL. - AFRICAN GREY PARROT
and Mummy. We suspect that she never called Daddy, because the name
was scarcely ever used in the household and, therefore, she rarely got the
opportunity to learn it. To enable her to learn a sound, such as a name, she
had to hear it regularly.
This was the smallest cage we found during our survey in
2006. The bird had no space to play and could not turn
around freely.
An example of the type of crate that is used to transport parrots in
Cameroon. The food is usually thrown on the floor, as a result of which it
quickly becomes soiled by the birds' faeces.
A good time keeper
Mundih is the family member whose room was closest to Peggy's cage
and she passed Peggy each time she entered or left her room. Mundih is
</bodyText>
<copyright confidence="0.232896">
NJI ET AL. - AFRICAN GREY PARROT
</copyright>
<page confidence="0.994419" page_id="56264571"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
7
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999126333333333" page_id="56264571"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
an early riser, who usually gets out of bed at 5.30am, to begin her daily
activities, or by 6.00am if she is a little late. As she went past Peggy's cage,
she would say, "Good morning Peggy." Thus, Peggy's day would begin at
5.15am-5.30am, with the chorus of bird calls and other sounds that herald
the arrival of dawn. At about 5.30am Peggy would begin to call Mundih
and, if by 5.45 am, Peggy had not seen Mundih, she would begin to call her
loudly but very fondly. At 5.30am her calls of "Mundih, Mundih, Mundih,"
would be sharp and quick, but by 5.45am-6.00am her calls tended to be
gentle, romantic and elastic. She would call: "Mund-i-h-oooooh, M-u-n-d-
i-h-ooooh, M-u-n-d-bh-ooooh." With this wake-up call, other members of
the household would know it was, or would soon be, 6.00am.
The parrot cage constructed in 2007 in which Peggy was housed. For easier
cleaning and transportation, it can be dismantled into five main parts.
The second person for whom Peggy acted as a faithful timekeeper was
Ngum. The family run a nursery and primary school within the housing
complex, where the youngest members of the household, Ngum and Ajaga
Nji Jr, attend the nursery school, which opens its doors to pupils at 7.15am.
They are expected to assemble by 7.30am for morning devotion and a hygiene
check. Therefore, both Ngum and Ajaga Nji Jr, passed by Peggy at about
7.30am on their way to class each day of the school week.
At exactly 7.30am, Peggy would begin to call Ngum, using short, loud
calls, in the same way that she called Mundih. She would call her at least
three times every few minutes for five to six minutes. Then, if Ngum did
not show up within that time, Peggy would send out a kind of SOS call,
</bodyText>
<bodyText confidence="0.993602047619048" page_id="56264572"  page_num="8" year="" vol="">
NJI ET AL. - AFRICAN GREY PARROT
that was both loud and elastic. Instead of just calling "Ngum," she would
call, "N-g-u-u-m, N-g-u-u-m" three or four times or until Ngum appeared
and said, "Yes, Peggy," to which she would respond by saying, "Hello," as
she greeted Ngum.
Throughout the day, Peggy would call out to other members of the
family until they had all answered her. She was very healthy, active and
friendly. With her beak she would reach out to the two German shepherd
dogs, Gendarme and Police, and they would kiss her with their tongues. The
dogs and Peggy were good chums and regularly had fun together. Therefore,
we were quite unprepared for what happened next.
The accident
Accidents never announce the time they will happen, just as burglars
do not announce their coming. At 3.30am on Saturday, January 24th 2009,
Prof. Nji was awakened by a loud sound, as if someone was opening the gate
leading into the porch where Peggy's cage was located. About 10 minutes
later, he was startled to hear her cry of distress. He jumped out of bed, ran
downstairs and opened the door, to find that the gate to the porch was indeed
open, and was shocked to discover that Peggy was bleeding profusely from
a gaping wound in her neck. She was wailing, as in fright and confusion,
she jumped from one perch to another, as blood continued to drip from the
wound. The dogs had retreated into their kennels and wrapped themselves
up, seemingly in regret, apologetic and engulfed by fear, as if they might
have known the terrible injury they had inflicted on Peggy. There had been
a power failure that night, so there was no electricity and Prof. Nji had to
use a kerosene lamp in order to determine the full extent of Peggy's injury.
A closer examination revealed a deep wound and serious damage to the
thyroid cartilage. Peggy was still trying to breathe but not in the normal
manner, as the opening of the air passage was visible externally and could
be seen opening and closing, as she tried to breathe in and out.
Prof. Nji went to the home of co-author Simon Tamungang to inform
him of the accident and they immediately returned together to examine
Peggy and determine the best course of action. Even though Dschang is a
university town and a divisional headquarters, however, no information was
available as to where in the community a veterinarian could be contacted.
There used to be two vets at the university's Department of Animal Science,
but neither were in town that week. Three veterinary books were consulted
(those by Forse, 1999; Davis, Karstad &amp; Trainer, 1981; Hoff &amp; Davis, 1982),
but not even the first of these, Where there is no Vet , proved of any help.
Consequently, we used household hydrogen peroxide to clean the wound
and attempted, to the best of our ability, to administer first aid to Peggy.
She was struggling to drink, but because her oesophagus had been severed,
</bodyText>
<copyright confidence="0.230802">
NJI ET AL. - AFRICAN GREY PARROT
</copyright>
<page confidence="0.980247" page_id="56264573"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
9
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9946115" page_id="56264573"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
Peggy's horrific injury.
was unable to do so.
Prof. Nji phoned a vet in Bamenda (120km (approx. 68 miles) away),
but after he had described the extent of the injury, the vet concluded that if
the oesophagus had indeed been severed, there was no medical treatment
available that could save the bird.
Peggy was very thirsty and hungry, but all efforts by her to drink from her
bowl, were futile. We tried to feed her and give her water using an infusion
kit. This was obtained from a clinic and carefully washed and sterilized.
The bottle was then filled with water and placed on the cage above her head,
in the hope that the dripping water would entice her to open her mouth and
let the water trickle down into it. Even this though did not work.
In his efforts to save Peggy's life, Prof. Nji attempted to contact the
town's renowned surgeon, an experienced physician of the Royal College
of Surgeons in London, with nearly 30 years of dedicated service to human
health in Dschang. However, he was out of town attending the funeral of
a colleague and friend.
The veterinary nurse
The following day, Sunday, January 25th 2009, little Ngum went to
Peggy's cage to play with her in her usual way, but when she saw what
had happened to her special friend and birthday gift, she burst into tears.
Shortly before this, Simon Tamungang had called to say that he had found
a veterinary nurse, who would be available at 1.00pm, following the church
service. Furthermore, the surgeon was back in town. He was called and
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997476" page_id="56264574"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
10
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.972936709677419" page_id="56264574"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
NJI ET AL. - AFRICAN GREY PARROT
urged to undertake experimental surgery on Peggy, but was reluctant on the
grounds that the anatomy of parrots and other lower animals was outside
his realm of expertise.
After receiving assurances, he was persuaded to undertake surgery on
Peggy and, at 2.00pm, a team of four, Simon Tamungang, Prof. Nji, the
veterinary nurse and the surgeon, met to examine her and attempt to come
up with a life saving strategy. By then the sun was blazing down and Peggy
had not had any food or water for the past 35 hours. Preliminary discussions
centred on the bird's anatomy, what would be required for the surgery and
the possible outcome, the consensus being that there was perhaps a 50%
chance of success.
The preparation
It was, as far as we were aware, going to be the first surgical operation ever
to be performed on such an animal in Cameroon. Therefore, it was difficult
to know exactly what to do and where to obtain the appropriate surgical
materials and equipment. On the list were: lidocaine (lignocaine), hydrogen
peroxide, cotton wool and gauze, surgical gloves, suture needles, catgut
thread, silk sutures, scissors, forceps, syringes and needles, scalpel blades,
antibiotics (oxytetracycline 5%), anti-inflammatory drugs, a pre-sterilized
surgery pack containing drapes, syringes, needles, swabs, a pair of scissors,
a kidney dish, gauze, iodine, catgut suture thread (absorbable), sterile silk
thread (non-absorbable), stress vitamins, sterilised dressings, etc.
It was three hours later before we were ready to begin surgery. This was
because of a number of difficulties:
1. Some of the items were not available in the local pharmacies and
those that were available were expensive. Insulin syringes (preferred
because of the small size of the needle) were, for example, on sale in
the pharmacies at 300 francs CFA (approx. US$0.65) each. However,
we succeeded in buying them from a street vendor for 100 francs CFA
(approx. US$0.25) each.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.7850442" page_id="56264574"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
2. It took 15 minutes longer than we hoped to clean the wound and
administer the local anaesthetic.
3. Because it was a Sunday there was a lack of emergency services and
we had to improvise at times in order to proceed with the surgery.
4. The veterinary nurses (the first nurse was joined by a second nurse)
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.9835235" page_id="56264574"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
had not done this kind of work before. Surgery on animals had only
been taught on a fairly superficial level at their schools. Therefore, even
more responsibility fell on the surgeon, who demonstrated his dexterity
handling the needles and tiny sutures.
</bodyText>
<copyright confidence="0.233311">
NJI ET AL. - AFRICAN GREY PARROT
</copyright>
<page confidence="0.998851" page_id="56264575"  page_num="11" year="" vol="">
11
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.931015175" page_id="56264575"  page_num="11" year="" vol="">
The operation
The surgery was performed in a specially prepared operating theatre in a
renown human clinic, under the professional guidance of the surgeon.
One of the veterinary nurses cleaned the wound with hydrogen peroxide,
then a local anaesthetic, 0.1ml of lidocaine (lignocaine), was administered
to the tissue of the neck and oesophagus, using a disposable insulin syringe.
The second veterinary nurse and Peggy's attendant held her beak and claws,
under the supervision of Simon Tamungang, while the surgeon proceeded
to suture back together the torn anterior and posterior sections of the
oesophagus, the damaged thyroid glands and neck muscles, etc. That having
been completed, the skin was sutured back together, making sure that the
tom parts of the lower mandible were held in the correct position, on either
side of the jaw. Two stitches were inserted on the right side and another on
the left side. During the suturing, Peggy was turned from side to side to rest.
Approximately 0.1ml of dexaphenylamine, an anti-inflammatory dmg, was
injected into the right sternal muscle. It was administered following surgery
and was expected to remain effective for three days. In addition, 0.1ml of
stress vitamins were injected into the left sternal muscle and they too were
expected to remain effective for three days. Finally, a tincture of iodine
was applied to the wound. Peggy remained calm but active throughout the
operation which took one-and-a-half hours.
Postoperative therapy
As Peggy had not had any food or water for 48 hours prior to the surgery,
the team felt that she should be given some glucose to boost her energy and
help keep her afloat. However, a vein could not be found through which
the glucose solution could be injected, therefore, we administered the anti-
inflammatory dmg and an anti-stress solution. The wound was cleaned with
Povidone iodine. The operation appeared to have been successful and the
prognosis looked good and we were hopeful she would recover. At 7.00pm
(19.00hrs) she was taken home.
Outcome
On arrival home, Peggy was placed in her cage and we watched for 15
minutes, in the hope that a miracle would occur. Unfortunately, however,
20 minutes later, Peggy shivered, as if trying to fly, and at 7.35pm (19.35hrs)
dropped dead. The surgical team greeted the sad news with a mixture of
regret, that after all that she had been through, she had died, but with the
satisfaction that each of them had done the best they could to save her life.
Peggy had 10 long red tail feathers and three new ones coming through,
together with 22 shorter red tail-coverts, which we have preserved to honour
her memory.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99521" page_id="56264576"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
12
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.503124" page_id="56264576"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
NJI ET AL. - AFRICAN GREY PARROT
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.833874">
Results and discussion
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.938425826086956" page_id="56264576"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
Our experience, described above, reveals:
1. The saliency of multidisciplinary teams in wildlife research in
order to achieve a better understanding, explanation and prediction of
wildlife behaviour and handling in post-captivity. This is evidenced by
the combination of ideas and skills that culminated in the surgery on
Peggy.
2. The need for curriculum development in wildlife management and
appropriate training for veterinarians. Just as engineers and technologists
in Africa need appropriate training to keep pace with rapid social change
and the technological revolution, the training of veterinarians needs
sharpening, both in quality and relevance (Nji, 1979; 1985a). Research,
particularly in the livestock sector, has for a long time been identified
as one of the weak links in agricultural development in Africa (Nji,
1993).
3. The emerging fulfilment of the dream to save parrots in Cameroon
(Tamungang, 1996). Parrot cage design, construction and placement
are paramount in ensuring the health and safety of a parrot in the home
environment. A good cage for a Grey Parrot is expensive, but it is worth
it, to ensure that the bird remains healthy, happy and secure. Acquiring a
parrot before looking around for a cage can often result in the untimely
death of the bird, due to poor housing, handling and feeding conditions.
In Cameroon cheap cages are often made with wood, which the Grey
Parrot has a natural tendency to chew holes in and escape.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.9250341" page_id="56264576"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
4. The urgent need to integrate social science into all research pro-
grammes in order to capture the dialectic between man and the
environment (Nji, 1991). The composition of Peggy's surgical team
reveals the saliency of this assertion.
5. A scarcity of animal clinics, drugs and other appropriate resources
and established policies.
6. Problems of availability and affordability of both wildlife and livestock
equipment.
7. A dearth of knowledge and information on the management of the
Grey Parrot and some other bird species and, of their interaction with
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.976435714285714" page_id="56264576"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
other animals, such as dogs. Knowledge of the latter would possibly
have led us to take greater precautions, which could have prevented the
accident which led to Peggy's untimely death.
Prior to the accident, Peggy had been a healthy and smart pet and member
of the household, who had learnt fast, socialized early and integrated herself
rapidly into the home environment. The accident that led to her death,
occurred in the middle of the night and, therefore, exactly what happened
</bodyText>
<copyright confidence="0.2334">
NJI ET AL. - AFRICAN GREY PARROT
</copyright>
<page confidence="0.999463" page_id="56264577"  page_num="13" year="" vol="">
13
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9991349" page_id="56264577"  page_num="13" year="" vol="">
can only be a matter of conjecture. We believe that Police, being a huge
and tall dog, might have manipulated the gate until it finally came open. He
was then free to approach Peggy's cage and put his paw in to touch/caress
her as usual, but she pulled away from his long claws and this resulted in
the accident. Several times during the day the dogs had been seen playing
with Peggy, so it was not the first time that they had been in close contact
with each other. We believe that if the dogs had been out to harm Peggy,
they would have tried to have done so well before this. Once the door of
Peggy's cage was accidentally left open, when the dogs were loose, and
nothing untoward happened.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.494044">
Conclusions and recommendations
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.920287588235294" page_id="56264577"  page_num="13" year="" vol="">
This case has added to our knowledge of the Grey Parrot and particularly
our knowledge of its captive management and, especially, its interaction
with domestic animals such as dogs. Looking back, we realise that we
may have made some mistakes in the management of Peggy and in the way
the operation was handled. This has led us to come up with the following
recommendations:
1. The design of the present parrot cage is in our experience satisfactory,
except that the mesh should be smaller to prevent an animal such as a
dog being able to reach in through it. However, the larger mesh does
enable the keeper to have easy and frequent tactile interaction with the
bird, which we consider to be an important factor. A Grey Parrot living
alone in a cage may suffer from loneliness and boredom and, if prevented
from interacting with humans and other animals, may resort to feather
plucking. Therefore, if a smaller mesh is used to prevent animals such
as dogs and cats from being able to reach the bird, another means of
playing/interacting with the bird must be found, perhaps by letting it out
of the cage each day for controlled play/interaction with its keeper.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.8088605" page_id="56264577"  page_num="13" year="" vol="">
2. When guard dogs, cats or wild animals are kept in a household, a parrot
(or any other pet bird) should be confined within a safe, well protected
area.
3. Parrot owners should be encouraged and assisted to acquire sufficient
skills to enable them to give basic first aid treatment to their bird.
4. Not enough is known about administering anaesthetics to birds and
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.889462428571428" page_id="56264577"  page_num="13" year="" vol="">
other small animals. We believe it is high time that bird protection
organisations and researchers recognised the need for factsheets and
'tool kits' for those keeping such birds as the Grey Parrot.
5. We believe that the decision to administer a local anaesthetic and
proceed with the surgery, despite the fact that Peggy had not had any food
or water for 48 hours, was the best option available to us at the time. We
debated at length whether or not surgery should proceed without the use
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999568" page_id="56264578"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
14
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.848717875" page_id="56264578"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
NJI ET AL. - AFRICAN GREY PARROT
of a local anaesthetic, but the team was of the unanimous opinion that
to proceed without the use of anaesthetic would have been tantamount
to cruelty.
6. We used hydrogen peroxide, in preference to alcohol, as we considered
the latter too powerful an antiseptic with which to clean Peggy's wound.
It is possible that in the process of cleaning the wound, some of the
liquid went into her stomach and accelerated her demise. We considered
having an autopsy, but were dissuaded by the cost, particularly in view
of the likely outcome. In retrospect, we believe, it might have been a
mistake to have proceeded with the local anaesthetic, when Peggy had
not had any food or water for 48 hours. Equally, we believe, that Peggy
may already have been exhausted and suffering from hunger and/or
dehydration, leading up to the operation, during which she suffered
further stress. She had to be restrained and her beak and legs held by
surgical-gloved hands, whereas appropriate instruments of restraint,
had they been available, would have been helpful. Inhalation of air and
atmospheric microbes through the open oesophagus may have caused
secondary infections and hastened her death. Above all though, the main
cause of Peggy's death was likely to have been as a result of the stress
and loss of blood immediately following the accident.
7. Our views and concerns highlight the need for further research and
innovation in the conservation and captive management of the African
Grey Parrot.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.687767" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56264578" page_num="14" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.7054185" page_id="56264578"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
PARROTPRO is grateful to Loro Parque Fundacion, Spain and the
British Ecological Society for financial support. It is also indebted to
the management of the Fiangep Clinic, Dschang for the use of its clinic,
equipment and materials.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.887876" genericHeader="references" page_id="56264578" page_num="14" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.884646857142857">
Davis, J. W., Karstad, L. H. and Trainer, D. O. 1981. Infectious Diseases of Wild mammals.
The Iowa State University Press, Ames, Iowa.
CITES 2001. HISTORY OF SPECIES REVIEWED UNDER RESOLUTION CONF. 8.9
(Rev.). AC 17 Inf.3-Pl, July, 2001.
Dandliker, G. 1992. The Grey Parrot in Ghana: A population survey, a contribution to the
biology ofthe species, a study of its commercial exploitation and management recommendations.
A report on CITES Project S-30, p.132. CITES Secretariat, Lausanne, Switzerland.
Forse, B. 1999. Where there is no Vet. Macmillan Press, Ltd., London.
Fry, C. H., Keith, S. and Urban, K. E. 1988. The Birds of Africa Vol.3, Academic Press,
London.
Hoff, G. L. and Davis, J. W. 1982. Non-infectious Diseases of Wildlife. The Iowa State
University Press, Ames, Iowa.
Mulliken, T. A. 1995. Trade review: South Africa s Trade in African Grey Parrots. A Traffic
East/Southem Africa Report:l-30.
</reference>
<copyright confidence="0.22979">
NJI ET AL. - AFRICAN GREY PARROT
</copyright>
<page confidence="0.978817" page_id="56264579"  page_num="15" year="" vol="">
15
</page>
<reference confidence="0.921744485714286">
Nji, A. 1993. Constraints to Livestock Development in the North-West Province of Cameroon
(West Africa). Pp.75-99. In Livestock Development in Developing Countries: Development
Issues and Research Needs. Deutsche Stiftung fur International Entwicklung (DSE), Feldafing,
Germany.
Nji, A. 1992. The dialectic between appropriate technology, public policy and rural
development. Discovery and Innovation 4,1:33-45.
Nji, A. 1991. Bringing Man Back In(to) Agronomic and Animal Science Research. Tropicultura
9,2:49-50.
Nji, A. 1985a. Appropriate Technology: A case for its evolution, adoption and diffusion in
developing counties. Annals of the University Centre ofDschang l,l,:73-83.
Nji, A. 1985b. The Education and training of African Engineers and Scientists for development.
Journal of the Royal Swaziland Society of Science and Technology 7,1:27-36.
Nji, A. 1979. The need for appropriate education &amp; training in Africa. Approtech 2,3:10-14.
Tamungang, S. A. 1996. The Vanishing Grey Parrots of Cameroon: Conservation Prospects.
Malimbus 18:70-71.
Tamungang, S. A. and Ajayi, S. S. 2003. Diversity of food of the Grey Parrot in Korup National
Park, Cameroon. Bulletin of the African Bird Club 10,1:33-36.
Tamungang, S. A., Ayodele, I. A. and Tan, P. V. 2002. Nutrient Concentration Levels of
some Diets of the Grey Parrot in the Korup Rainforest, Cameroon. Proceedings of Cameroon
Bioscience Association. Ngaoundere, Sept. 2-4, 2000. Vol.3,4:15-2.1.
TRAFFIC International. 2005. Results of the 13th CITES meeting. TRAFFIC Bulletin
20,2:51-54.
Prof. Ajaga Nji, Department of Rural Sociology and Agric Extention,
Faculty of Agronomy and Agricultural Sciences, PO Box 138, Dschang,
Cameroon. E-mail: ajaga_nji@yahoo.com
Dr Simon A. Tamungang, Department of Animal Biology, Faculty of
Science, University of Dschang, PO Box 146, Dschang, Cameroon. E-mail:
atamungang@yahoo. com
W. L. Asong, Surgeon, Fiangep Clinic, PO Box 206, Dschang,
Cameroon.
Mbafor Fidelia &amp; Tsafack Antoine, Divisional Office of Livestock,
Department of Disease Control and Hygiene, PO Box 55, Dschang,
Cameroon.
Sabi B. Nji, Ngumys Fantastic International School, PO Box 138,
Dschang, Cameroon.
</reference>
<bodyText confidence="0.949682333333333" page_id="56264579"  page_num="15" year="" vol="">
The authors are keen to get as much feedback as possible on all aspects
arising from the above article and, in particular, those leading up to the
accident and their subsequent efforts to save Peggy s life. They welcome
comments and criticism of their theories, methodology and the views they
have expressed. I would suggest that these are sent to Dr Simon Tamungang
at the University of Dschang. E-mail: atamungang@yahoo.com
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99704" page_id="56264580"  page_num="16" year="" vol="">
16
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.98997" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264580" page_num="16" year="" vol="">
THE SPIRIT OF JEAN DELACOUR LIVES ON
AT PARC DE CLERES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997770513513514" page_id="56264580"  page_num="16" year="" vol="">
by Pierre de Chabannes
One whose main interests are neither zoology or birds, could hardly
imagine what lies hidden behind the walls of the Parc de Geres. At first
glance it does not look as so it is home to one of the finest collections of
pheasants and waterfowl in the world. When I first visited it in 2006, it fitted
my idea of a typical French country estate, with a chateau, a manor house
and landscaped gardens, which could have belonged to an aristocratic family.
After walking only a short distance in the grounds of the Parc de Geres,
however, one finally realises that it is much more than merely somewhere
to take a casual "Sunday afternoon walk."
The village of Geres is in the hilly part of northern Normandy, in north-
west France. It is a drive of 40 minutes from the city of Rouen, which is
famous for its cathedral and boat festival, called L \Armada de Rouen, which
takes place there each year. For those who prefer travelling by rail, there are
regular trains from Paris, with a change at Rouen main station.
The Chateau de Geres was acquired by the late Jean Delacour in 1919
in order to house his bird collection. He had aviaries built in the gardens,
some of which remain in use today, to display the numerous pheasants he
collected during his many field trips to south-east Asia. He also collected
many other tropical birds, including hombills, fruit doves and other Asian
softbills, as well as an impressive number of waterfowl, that he kept and
bred at Geres.
Parc de Geres was badly bombed during the Second World War and the
collection was lost. Delacour, who had left France in 1940 to pursue his
ornithological work in the USA, where he acted as a Technical Adviser at
Bronx Zoo and worked as a Research Associate at the American Museum
of Natural History, before later becoming Director of History, Science and
Art at Los Angeles County Museum, opened the park to the public in 1947
and gifted it to the Paris-based French Museum of Natural History, in the
hope of accelerating its rehabilitation following the war. Although Delacour
continued to reside in the USA, he returned to Geres each summer until
his death in 1985.
Until 2008, the museum owned and administered the park, but it was
clear that it did not have the funding and time to renovate the old aviaries
and build new exhibits in order to attract more visitors. In early 2009, it was
decided that the park should come under the administration of the Regional
Council of H aute-Nor man die- so that the long-awaited development of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.614104" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264581" page_num="17" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - PARC DE CLERES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.956352" page_id="56264581"  page_num="17" year="" vol="">
17
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.93970144" page_id="56264581"  page_num="17" year="" vol="">
Pierre de Chabannes
Chateau de Cleres for many years the home of Jean Delacour, President of the
Avicultural Society 1972-1985.
park could finally begin. It has made a start by building new aviaries to
house owls, Madagascar birds and egrets; and to house lemurs. In addition,
a number of other projects are being studied with a view to the park playing
a major role in international wildlife conservation.
The Parc de Cleres currently occupies an area of 70 hectares (approx.
170 acres), 13 hectares (approx. 30 acres) of which are open to the public.
My favourite time of the year to visit Cleres is in the spring, around about
April-May, in order to see most of the ducks in breeding plumage and to try
to catch glimpses of the nuptial displays of the pheasants.
The aviaries
Arriving early in the morning, I chose to first have a look at the aviaries.
On my way to them, I passed a breeding pair of White-cheeked Gibbons
Nomascus leucogenys. The first of these gibbons to be kept in captivity in
Europe were brought from what was then Indochina in the mid-1920s by Jean
Delacour. Above their enclosure is a small row of aviaries housing Peach-
fronted (Golden-crowned) Conures Aratinga aurea and White Cockatoos
Cacatua alba. A short walk through a lovely garden, leads to the oldest
exhibits in the park, which house the first of the pheasants, some waterfowl
and other tropical birds. The particular way in which these aviaries are
landscaped help give the park its charming atmosphere of being part of an
"ancient French chateau," although it must be said that the aviaries do not
always meet the occupants' requirements.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997677" page_id="56264582"  page_num="18" year="" vol="">
18
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.814802" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264582" page_num="18" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - PARC DE CLERES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.982311268292683" page_id="56264582"  page_num="18" year="" vol="">
Among the birds housed in these aviaries are a group of Pied Avocets
Recurvirostra avosetta , a pair of the now rarely exhibited Mikado Pheasants
Syrmaticus mikado , some Wonga Pigeons Leucosarcia melanoleuca , a pair
of Fischer's Turacos Tauraco fischeri , a breeding group of Stone Curlews
Burhinus o. oedicnemus, some Ringed Teal Callonetta leucophrys, a few
Northern Lapwings Vanellus vanellus , a Blacksmith Plover V armatus, a
pair of the Endangered Edwards's Pheasant Lophura edwardsi and the very
rare Greater Brazilian Duck Amazonetta brasiliensis ipercutiri.
From there I usually go to the smaller aviaries, located on the left-hand
side of the complex, in which are kept medium-sized species of parrot,
such as Derbyan Parakeets Psittacula derbyana , Green-cheeked Amazons
Amazona viridigenalis. Grey Parrots Psittacus erithacus and Eclectus
Eclectus roratus. Also housed in these aviaries are Red-billed Pigeons
Patagioenas f flavirostris, a species not kept anywhere else in Europe,
a male Ceylon Junglefowl Gallus lafayetii and one of the last San Bias
Jays Cyanocorax sanblasianus kept in a European park. The path ends by
an aviary built in 2008 to house a small group of Great Grey Owls Strix
nebulosa lapponica.
On the other side of the aviary is a grassy enclosure which was created
in 2009 to display a young pair of Red-crowned Cranes Grus japonensis.
This Endangered species is now much more common in European zoos than
it is in Asia, but it is still hardly ever bred. Let us hope that this pair which
only recently arrived at Cleres produce many offspring for the European
Endangered Species Programme (EEP).
Another new exhibit is a walk-through aviary. It is nicely landscaped
and houses a breeding group of the Critically Endangered Northern Bald
Ibis Geronticus eremita , along with Little Egrets Egretta garzetta and
Black-crowned Night Herons Nycticorax nycticorax. Then there is a large
Madagascar exhibit which was completed in 2008. It houses Alaotran
Bamboo Lemurs Hapalemur alaotrensis , the first lemurs to be kept in the park
for many years. They have already bred, having first done so in late 2008
and then again in 2009. They live along with the Endangered Madagascar
Teal A. bernieri and Meller's Duck A. melleri, that were first kept there in
the 1930s. It is odd that apart from Paris Zoo (Parc Zoologique de Paris,
Vincennes), which has closed for extensive renovation, very few French
collections have Madagascar exhibits, showing lemurs and birds, etc.
On the other side of the narrow path is a row of medium to large aviaries
used exclusively for keeping and breeding Galliformes. These aviaries have
recently been landscaped and now have more plant cover and more perches
available, which has led to improved breeding results, especially for rarer
species such as the Crestless Fireback L. e . erythropthalma, which is not
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.636755" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264583" page_num="19" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - PARC DE CLERES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999027" page_id="56264583"  page_num="19" year="" vol="">
19
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.982665804878049" page_id="56264583"  page_num="19" year="" vol="">
shown anywhere else in France. There are also Great Curassows Crax r.
rubra , a pair of recently arrived Ocellated Turkeys Meleagris ocellata, a
pair of Vieillot's Crested Firebacks L. ignita rufa and, most importantly,
two pairs of the rarely seen Salvadori's Pheasant L. i. inornata from
Sumatra. The park is famous worldwide for its breeding successes with
both Edwards's Pheasant, which is the subject of a European Endangered
Species Programme (EEP), and the Vietnamese Pheasant L. hatinhensis, as
well as with Salvadori's Pheasant which, for a long time, has not been seen
in captivity anywhere else in Europe. Alain Hennache, Curator of Birds at
Cleres, Studbook Keeper for Edwards's Pheasant and (with Dang Gia Tung,
Curator of Birds at Hanoi Zoological Gardens) joint Studbook Keeper for the
Vietnamese Pheasant, is among pheasant experts investigating whether or not
the Vietnamese Pheasant is a valid species. He has observed how Edwards's
Pheasants hatched at Cleres regularly go on to grow white tail feathers (a
characteristic of the Vietnamese Pheasant) despite the fact that their parents
are pure-bred Edwards's Pheasants. The investigation is continuing and could
lead to a change in the taxonomic status of the Vietnamese Pheasant.
By following the main path, one arrives at the upper section of the
pheasant breeding area. On the left is a huge block divided into approximately
a dozen aviaries, each quite small, dark, and not very well landscaped. This
very old exhibit will soon be demolished and new, bigger, more suitable
aviaries built in their place. The present aviaries house more rarities such as
(Berlioz's) Silver Pheasant L. nycthemera berliozi (a subspecies described by
Delacour &amp; Jabouille 1928), which breeds very successfully at Cleres and
a large number of which are kept there, along with three other subspecies,
namely L. n. lewisi (also described by Delacour &amp; Jabouille 1928), L. n.
engelbachi and L. n. beaulieui (both described by Delacour 1948). Also
housed in these aviaries are a pair of Himalayan Monals Lophophorus
impejanus , some more Edwards's Pheasants, a pair of the now rarely kept
Elliot's Pheasant S. ellioti , a pair of (Honshu) Green Pheasants Phasianus
versicolor robustipes , a male Palawan Peacock-Pheasant Polyplectron
emphanum , a Lady Amherst's Pheasant Chrysolophus amherstiae , a pair
of Temminck's Tragopans Tragopan temmincki and a pair of Blue Eared
Pheasants Crossoptilon auritum - a quite common species in the past but
now getting rare in aviculture, especially in France. There is a flock of
Red-billed Pigeons, a Barred Cuckoo-Dove Macropygia u. unchall , a group
of Laughing Kookaburras Dacelo novaeguineae and a pair of Red-billed
Blue Magpies Urocissa erythrorhyncha occipitalis , as well as a female
Hume's Pheasant S. h. humiae , which following the death of the last male
in 2008, is now the last specimen of this species in a public collection in
France. Finally, there is a pair of Imperial Pheasants L. imperials, a bird
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.781489" page_id="56264584"  page_num="20" year="" vol="">
20
</page>
<table confidence="0.5579286" page_id="56264584"  page_num="20" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - PARC DE CLERES
Pierre de Chabannes
Female Salvadori's Pheasant.
Pierre de Chabannes
Crested Duck Anas ( Lophonetta ) specularioides alticola.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.636893" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264585" page_num="21" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - PARC DE CLERES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996977" page_id="56264585"  page_num="21" year="" vol="">
21
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.980900619047619" page_id="56264585"  page_num="21" year="" vol="">
Blyth's Tragopan.
discovered by Delacour in Vietnam in 1923 (and described by Delacour &amp;
Jabouille 1924). The original two birds were brought to Cleres, where they
bred for the first time in 1925 and it was from this pair that the European
and American populations were descended. Modem research, however,
suggests that the Imperial Pheasant is in fact a naturally occurring Silver
x Edwards's Pheasant hybrid. Captive-bred Silver x Edwards's Pheasant
hybrids match perfectly the few known Imperial Pheasants. The latter are
almost impossible to find in captivity nowadays and the birds at Cleres are
probably the only known captive pair in Europe and, possibly, anywhere
else in the world, at this moment.
A grassy enclosure behind the above facility, houses a pair of Emus
Dromaius novaehollandiae and Cereopsis Geese Cereopsis novaehollandiae.
The final group of public aviaries are a lot larger and much better landscaped.
The largest house waterfowl, such as Hooded Merganser Lophodytes
cucullatus. Greater Brazilian Duck and the rarely exhibited Blue-winged
Teal Anas discors, which are considered too delicate to be kept free on the
large lake. On the other side there are a pair of White Eared Pheasants C.
crossoptilon drouinyi (the only subspecies kept in European collections),
a pair of Satyr Tragopans T. satyr a, a pair of Temminck's Tragopans and a
single male Cabot's Tragopan T. caboti (a species being bred off-display at
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997264" page_id="56264586"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
22
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.855341" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264586" page_num="22" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - PARC DE CLERES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9209165" page_id="56264586"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
the park), as well as the rare Puff-backed Bulbul Pycnonotus eutilotus , a small
group of Brush Bronzewings Phaps elegans, some Crested Quail-Doves
Geotrygon versicolor and a few Crested Pigeons Ocyphaps lophotes.
Most of the pheasant collection is not on view to the public. I was
though once fortunate enough to visit the off-display area and recall seeing
a pair of Cheer Pheasants Catreus wallichi, a male Ruffed Grouse Bonasa
umbellus, which displayed in front of me for several minutes, some Grey
Peacock-Pheasants P. b. bicalcaratum , a Croaking Ground Dove Columbina
cruziana and the only known captive Blyth's Tragopan T. blythii in France
- the bird in question being an old male.
The chateau used to house a delightful collection of tropical birds,
including hombills (the Great Buceros bicornis being the highlight), toucans
and a few hummingbirds, but this is no longer open to the public.
Free roaming
One may think, as I did during my first visit, that most of the more
interesting birds are to be seen in the aviaries, but after discovering the
beautiful gardens and the area around the lake, I quickly changed my
opinion.
There is a really beautiful area with several paths leading up into a wooded
area towards the back of the park, where there are Bennett's Wallabies
Macropus rufogriscus , a herd of Blackbuck Antilopa cervicapra , some
Chinese Water Deer Hydropotes i. inermis and lots of Blue Peafowl Pavo
cristatus , including some white ones, roaming free.
There are two different areas with ducks and other waterfowl, etc. The
first is an enclosed grassy field with a stream and a small off-display area
into which the birds can retreat and get away from the visitors. Usually, the
first birds which come into view are the Demoiselle Cranes Anthropoides
virgo , European White Storks Ciconia ciconia , a pair of Southern Screamers
Chauna torquata and a breeding group of Sacred Ibis Threskiornis
aethiopicus. Then, looking more closely and waiting patiently, one is
likely to see Chiloe Wigeon A. sibilatrix , Lesser Canada Geese Branta
canadensis minima , now frequently treated as a subspecies of the Cackling
Goose B. hutchinsii minima , Red-breasted Geese B. ruficollis , a large flock
of Magpie Geese Anseranas semipalmata , White-faced Whistling Ducks
Dendrocygna viduata , Black-bellied Whistling Ducks D. autumnalis and a
single specimen of the West Indian Whistling Duck D. arborea - a species
almost never seen in French zoological collections. There are also Emperor
Geese Anser canagicus, a pair of Ross's Geese A. rossii , a single, now rarely
seen, Ashy-headed Goose Chloephaga poliocephala , the Vulnerable Lesser
White-fronted Goose A. erythropus, a pair of Maned Geese Chenonetta
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.636792" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264587" page_num="23" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - PARC DE CLERES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998886" page_id="56264587"  page_num="23" year="" vol="">
23
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.993532487804878" page_id="56264587"  page_num="23" year="" vol="">
jubata and a pair of the rarely exhibited Blue-winged Goose Cyanochen
cyanopterus. Four, nearby, small grassy enclosures, each close to the water,
house several species of duck, including a group of Spot-billed Ducks A.
p. poecilorhyncha , a breeding group of Falcated Ducks A. falcata , some
Ruddy Ducks Oxyura jamaicensis , the Critically Endangered Laysan Teal
A. laysansensis and a small group of Buffleheads Bucephala albeola , as well
as Trumpeter Swans Cygnus buccinator.
The lake and surrounding area are home to an extravaganza of waterbirds,
which are joined sometimes by a few Blackbuck and peafowl, that are fed
close by at the end of the day. For visitors, the most eye-catching of the
waterbirds are, of course, the flamingos. The flock is composed mostly of
hybrids, a mix of Chilean Phoenicopterus chilensis , Caribbean P. ruber and
Greater Flamingos P. roseus. They are free to roam, but usually remain out in
the middle of the lake and come to the water's edge only at feeding time.
The large, friendly flock of Hawaiian Geese B. sandvicensis that breed
each year, mingle with the visitors, begging them for food and sometimes,
as happened to me, pecking at their clothing and shoes. The large flock of
Bar-headed Geese A. indicus usually spend most of the day in the tall grass
in a nearby field and are best seen in the early morning and towards the end
of the day. The pair of Greater Magellanic Geese C. picta leucoptera is
easy to spot and there is a small group of Greater White-fronted Geese A.
albifrons flavirostris and some Snow Geese A. c. caerulescens. Some of the
less shy ducks, such as the Chestnut Teal A. castanea , a species not often
encountered in French zoological collections, can often be found resting
close to the main path.
Most of the ducks stay close to the water and usually spend the day resting
on the muddy bank, separated from the visitors by a low fence. There are
Black Swans C. atratus , a group of Fulvous Whistling Ducks D. bicolor ,
Barnacle Geese B. leucopsis , Ruddy Shelducks Tadorna ferruginea , a pair
of Australian Shelducks T. tadornoides and a single male paired with a
female South African Shelduck T. cana, as well as a large group of Common
Shelducks T. tadorna and a lone female Radjah Shelduck T. r. radjah.
There are many Wood Ducks or Carolinas Aix sponsa and Mandarins A.
galericulata , Eurasian Wigeon A. penelope , Gadwall A. strepera , a small
group of Baikal Teal A. formosa , some Common or Eurasian Teal A. c.
crecca , a large group of Speckled (Chilean) Teal A. f flavirostris , Cape
Teal A. capensis, a pair of Yellow-billed Ducks A. undulata and some more
Spot-billed Ducks. The single, rare specimen of the Pacific Black Duck A.
superciliosapelewensis, is a bird I had never seen before. Other waterfowl
living on and around the lake, include Northern Pintails A. acuta , a large
group of White-cheeked Pintails A. bahamensis rubrirostris , Silver Teal
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998146" page_id="56264588"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
24
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.836424" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264588" page_num="24" year="" vol="">
DE CHABANNES - PARC DE CLERES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991677458333333" page_id="56264588"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
A. versicolor and the closely related Puna Teal A. puna , Cinnamon Teal A.
cyanoptera , a species rarely seen in French zoological collections, three
pairs of Philippine Ducks A. luzonica , a female Red Shoveler A platalea,
a breeding group of European Shove lets A. clypeata, a male Hottentot
Teal A, hottentota, some Marbled Teal Marmaronetta augutirostris, a large
group of Red-crested Pochard Netta rufina, Rosybill /V peposaca, Common
Pochard N. farina , Tufted Ducks Ay thy a fuligula , Lesser Scaup A affinis and
the two subspecies of the rare Crested Duck, namely Anas (. Lophonetta ) s.
specularoides and A. (L.) s. alticola.
A pair of Buff-cheeked Gibbons N. gabriellae live in the trees on an island
in the lake and plans have been made to introduce a group of Ring-tailed
Lemurs Lemur katta. Living in three grassy enclosures by the water are
Reeves's Muntjac Muntiacus r reevesi, Black Crowned Cranes Balearica
p. pavonina and a further pair of White Eared Pheasants.
I was struck by the amazing diversity of the Anatidae collection and
was especially pleased to see the Crested Ducks, which are so rarely seen in
French zoological collections. I was also impressed by the way in which so
many of the species are identified right down to the correct subspecies.
There have been difficulties in the past, but good progress is now being
made at the Parc de Cleres, and the spirit of Jean Delacour continues to
live on. Situated in the Normandy countryside, it provides a good insight
into the history of captive bird keeping and breeding and an enjoyable day-
out away from the noise and hustle and bustle that are all too often part of
modem day life.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.86951" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56264588" page_num="24" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9518332" page_id="56264588"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
I would like to thank Dr Alain Hennache and all the keepers who
welcomed me to the park and answered all my questions. Their valuable
help was very much appreciated and the writing of this account of my visit
would have not been possible without their assistance. I would also like to
thank Josef Lindholm, Senior Aviculturist at Dallas World Aquarium, whose
insights, guidance and kind words helped and encouraged me to write about
my visit the Parc de Cleres, as well as to other collections around the world,
which will be the subjects of articles in future issues of the magazine.
Pierre de Chabannes lives at Le Chesnay in France. E-mail:
pedroyayadrums@yahoo . com
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9145575" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264589" page_num="25" year="" vol="">
WELTVOGELPARK WALSRODE -
THE BEGINNING OF A NEW ERA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.984892" page_id="56264589"  page_num="25" year="" vol="">
25
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.932605384615385" page_id="56264589"  page_num="25" year="" vol="">
by Simon Bruslund Jensen
The takeover of Vogelpark Walsrode by the Belgian company Floralux
and its owners Kris Carrein and Geert Vermeersch in April 2009, heralded
the beginning of a bright new era here at the park. It has been renamed
Weltvogelpark, which in German means world bird park and is in many ways
self-explanatory. "The park is not changing direction, so much as getting
back on the right course," said General Director Geer Scheres.
Weltvogelpark Walsrode
Compared to the chicks of other storks, those of the African Open-billed Stork are
especially active and have very characteristic loud quacking calls.
A specialised zoological institution with an outstanding collection of
birds, Weltvogelpark Walsrode plans to set new standards for bird parks.
Our first breeding season under new ownership went very well and there
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.992913" page_id="56264590"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
26
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.815787" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264590" page_num="26" year="" vol="">
JENSEN - WELTVOGELPARK WALSRODE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990997780487805" page_id="56264590"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
were a number of highlights.
The two most southerly species of pelican are the Australian species
Pelecanus conspicillatus and the Peruvian Pelican P. thaga. They are
genetically programmed to breed during the southern summer, so, in Europe
breed in the winter months. Our birds are housed during the winter in heated
greenhouses with a large pool. During the 2008/2009 breeding season we
succeeded in rearing four Australian Pelicans and nine Peruvian Pelicans,
which was a good result that strengthens both breeding groups for the future.
At the time of writing (March 2010), the 2009/2010 breeding season is still in
progress. The freshly-laid eggs are carefully removed by keepers Matthias-
Melte Muller and Thomas Eichler, who are also responsible for keeping
records of which birds are paired together and which pairs have produced
the eggs. Leaving the eggs with the parents would be too hazardous in our
very lively small colony. One Australian Pelican chick has been hatched so
far this year in our hand-rearing station.
Our Madagascar Pond Herons Ardeola idae reared their own young in
2009 in our communal aviary for Madagascan mangrove birds. Due to their
secretive behaviour one of the nests was not detected until the chicks were
almost ready to fledge. The Madagascar Pond Heron is currently maintained
in captivity only at Weltvogelpark Walsrode, therefore, the five young raised
in 2009 will play an important role in enabling us to maintain a viable
population of this endangered species. In the same aviary the equally rare
Blue-eyed Sacred Ibis Threskiornis bernieri succeeded in rearing a single
youngster. African Open-billed Storks Anastomus lamelligerus also occur
in the depleted mangrove forests of western Madagascar. Although the
three species nest alongside each other in the wild, in our aviary the Open-
billed Storks are by far the most dominant species and disturb the ibises
and herons, not least because they steal nest material from one another and
from the other species.
Because Open-billed Storks feed almost exclusively on large freshwater
snails that are difficult to obtain here in northern Germany, the parents
rarely succeed in rearing their own young. Fortunately, we have managed
to perfect the hand-rearing of them using commercially available digestive
enzymes such as Creon and best quality day-old rats. In 2009, 14 young
were successfully reared in our hand-rearing station, an improvement on our
previous record from 2005, when seven chicks were reared.
With the rarely kept Southern Bald Ibis Geronticus calvus and the rarely
kept Madagascar Crested Ibis Lobhotibis cristata , most of the eggs are
removed for artificial incubation and the chicks are hand-reared. This is a
safety precaution until the populations reach sufficient levels to guarantee
their viability. By hand-rearing the chicks, we were able to raise eight
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.51839" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264591" page_num="27" year="" vol="">
JENSEN - WELTVOGELPARK WALSRODE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997004" page_id="56264591"  page_num="27" year="" vol="">
27
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998417097560976" page_id="56264591"  page_num="27" year="" vol="">
Southern Bald Ibis in 2009 and 10 Madagascar Crested Ibis.
As in previous years, we did very well with our couas (non-parasitic
members of the cuckoo family from Madagascar). We have been especially
successful with the Crested Coua Coua cristata. Almost 80 chicks have been
hatched since 2000. Only hand-rearing was successful in 2009. We lost a
few juveniles being reared by their parents, probably due to poor weather.
The breeding cycle of the Crested Coua is amongst the fastest of any species
of bird. The chicks, up to two in number, hatch after an incubation period
of 13 days and remain in the nest for only 11 days before they fledge.
It proved to be quite a productive breeding season for our Greater
Roadrunners Geococcyx californianus, which successfully reared nine
young. There are a number of Greater Roadrunners in European zoos, but
despite this the population seems to be in trouble. In the past few years
Weltvogelpark Walsrode has been the only institution producing successful
breeding results. Unfortunately, almost the entire population seems to be
closely related to each other and inbreeding may, in the future, be difficult
to avoid.
In 2009, we succeeded in rearing Spectacled Owls Pulsatrixperspicillata
for the first time at Walsrode. Two of these remarkable coloured owls were
reared in our hand-rearing station.
Just three months after they had been introduced to each other, our newly-
formed pair of Red-and-yellow Barbets Trachyphonus e. erythrocephalus
surprised us by producing two chicks. Both turned out to be males
(identifiable by their black throat patch), that were left with their parents and
assisted with the rearing of a female chick from the subsequent clutch. The
pair nested in a burrow in an artificial sandstone wall, intended for bee-eaters.
There is an inspection door in the rear section, but following the first few
inspections, the pair decided to move the clutch closer to the burrow entrance,
where it was not possible to see what was happening. The preferred rearing
foods were mealworms and hill mynah pellets that had been soaked.
Late in 2008, we received a group of five Sudan Golden Sparrows Passer
luteus , that began nest building in early spring 2009. Due to a skirmish
within the group at the time that the young of the first pair were ready to
fledge, the chicks of the second pair were ejected from their nest, the day
after hatching. The four minuscule chicks were taken to our hand-rearing
station and were reared with surprising ease by our experienced team of
keepers. The two pairs went on to rear a further 10 young during 2009,
without any more disputes. At about six months of age, the young Sudan
Golden Sparrows moulted into adult plumage. Interestingly, two of the
young that were hand-reared began nest building and went on to lay eggs,
but nothing came of them.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.986406" page_id="56264592"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
28
</page>
<table confidence="0.794280333333333" page_id="56264592"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
JENSEN - WELTVOGELPARK WALSRODE
Weltvogelpark Walsrode
Young Greater Roadrunners are initially similar to young couas, however, their
husbandry requirements are considerably less demanding.
Ingo Klinger
One of two Sudan Golden Sparrow chicks is offered a mealworm.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.517914" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264593" page_num="29" year="" vol="">
JENSEN - WELTVOGELPARK WALSRODE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994222" page_id="56264593"  page_num="29" year="" vol="">
29
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.371715">
Weltvogelpark Walsrode
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998332105263158" page_id="56264593"  page_num="29" year="" vol="">
Four day old Montezuma Oropendola. The pale coloured bill markings probably
help the female locate the chick's open gape in the darkness of the hanging nest,
which may be up to 1m (3ft 3in) deep. The clutch consists of a single egg and the
chick is reared by the female alone.
Our small group of Montezuma Oropendolas Psarocolius montezuma
is the only such group in Europe (another group is maintained at the Bronx
Zoo in New York). For this reason the breeding of this species is particularly
important to us. Our birds are kept in our large free-flight aviary, together
with species such as Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber and Roseate Spoonbills
Platalea ajaja. They build their impressive hanging nests, made of fresh
grass, at the very top of the aviary. The parents having previously been
unsuccessful in rearing their young, we decided to try to hand-rear them.
The first challenge was to retrieve the eggs, which was not an easy task and
required a member of staff with a head for heights. Eventually, we managed
to secure two eggs and hatch them successfully but, unfortunately, lost one
of the chicks, but to our great joy, the other chick was reared successfully.
For the very latest up-to-date information about what is happening at
Weltvogelpark Walsrode you can visit our website:www.weltvogelpark.de
The above report is based on Simon s Weltvogelpark Walsrode March
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.628976" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56264593" page_num="29" year="" vol="">
2010 Newsletter.
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.991227" page_id="56264594"  page_num="30" year="" vol="">
30
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.937371" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264594" page_num="30" year="" vol="">
HAND-REARING A WHITE-CROWNED ROBIN-CHAT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.942222529411765" page_id="56264594"  page_num="30" year="" vol="">
Cossypha albicapilla AT EXMOOR ZOO
by Derek Gibson
Exmoor Zoo has for several years exhibited the White-crowned Robin-
Chat Cossypha albicapilla , but until recently had not succeeded in breeding
this charming species. Eggs had been laid on more than one occasion, but
had always proved to be clear.
Nest and egg.
Our present pair consists of a male hatched at Jersey Zoo on July 26th
2004 and a female hatched on June 21 st 2002 at London Zoo. The pair share
a heavily planted aviary with three other species: Red-billed Quelea Quelea
quelea , Crowned Plover Vanellus coronatus and Crested Pigeon Ocyphaps
lophotes. In 2008, the female robin-chat constructed a nest made of coconut
fibres and dried bamboo leaves in a hanging basket some 2m-3m (6ft 6in-9ft
9in) above the ground. A chick hatched, but when it was estimated to have
been about two days old, it was found dead on the aviary floor.
The birds were provided with a foraging tray that was filled with moss
and Beech leaves Fagus sylvatica , to which was added the robin-chats' daily
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.871865" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264595" page_num="31" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-CROWNED ROBIN-CHAT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999717" page_id="56264595"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
31
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.975182473684211" page_id="56264595"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
Hand-rearing record of chick hatched on June 16th 2008 at Exmoor Zoo.
Date 16.06.08 Weight 4g
12.30 (12.30pm) Removed from incubator and placed in a brooder set at a temperature
of 35*C (95*F); offered a drop of water. 16.30 (4.30pm) Fed % pinkie mouse stomach
soaked in water. 19.30 (7.30pm) Fed !4 pinkie mouse stomach soaked in a solution of
probiotics and water. 20.30 (8.30pm) Fed Vs pinkie mouse stomach soaked in a solution of
probiotics and water; faeces noted. 23.30 (11,30pm) Fed % pinkie mouse stomach soaked
in a solution of probiotics and water; faeces noted.
Date 17.06.08 Weight 4g
06.00 (6.00am) Fed !4 pinkie mouse stomach soaked in a solution of probiotics and
water; faeces noted. 08.00 (8.00am) Fed !4 pinkie mouse stomach soaked in a solution of
probiotics and water; faeces noted. 09.30 (9.30am) Begging for food; fed !4 pinkie mouse
stomach soaked in a solution of probiotics and water. 10.30 (10.30am) Fed % pinkie mouse
stomach soaked in a solution of probiotics and water. 12.30 (12.30pm) Fed !4 pinkie mouse
stomach soaked in a solution of probiotics and water; fed !4 pinkie mouse stomach soaked
in a solution of probiotics and water; faeces noted. 14.30 (2.30pm) Fed !4 pinkie mouse
stomach soaked in a solution of probiotics and water. 16.30 (4.30pm) Fed % pinkie mouse
stomach soaked in a solution of probiotics and water. 18.10 (6.10pm) Fed !4 pinkie mouse
stomach soaked in a solution of probiotics and water; faeces noted.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.9493615" page_id="56264595"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
Date 18.06.08
Food cut into quarters and papaya added to the diet.
Weight 6g
Date 19.06.08
Eyes beginning to slit.
Weight 7g
Date 20.06.08
Eyes continuing to slit; beginning to call.
Weight lOg
Date 21.06.08
Weight 13g
Beginning to become vocal; pins beginning to appear on wings; moved to larger box. j
Date 22.06.08
Weight 18g
Date 23.06.08
Eyes three-quarters open; making no noise.
Weight 22g
Date 24.06.08
Orange feathers beginning to appear on the breast and in the tail.
Weight 27g
Date 25.06.08
Weight 3Ig
Date 26.06.08
Food cut into halves.
Weight 35g
Date 28.06.08
Weight 38g
Date 29.06.08
Three-quarters feathered; calls when hungry.
Weight 42g
Date 30.06.08
Weight 44g
Date 01.07.08
Weight 44g
Date 02.07.08
Picking up food; fruits and soaked Zoo Diet A.
Weight 42g
Date 03.07.08
Placed in flight cage.
Weight 40g
</table>
<page confidence="0.997005" page_id="56264596"  page_num="32" year="" vol="">
32
</page>
<table confidence="0.532742" page_id="56264596"  page_num="32" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-CROWNED ROBIN-CHAT
Derek Gibson
Aged approximately five weeks.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.871903" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264597" page_num="33" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-CROWNED ROBIN-CHAT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999149" page_id="56264597"  page_num="33" year="" vol="">
33
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997820807692308" page_id="56264597"  page_num="33" year="" vol="">
Fig. h Growth rate of hand-reared White-crowned Robin-Chat chick.
ration of mealworms, waxmoth larvae and black crickets, the idea being
to keep the birds busy while they were rearing their young and, thereby,
hopefully, stop them from throwing their chicks out of the nest. This was not
to be, however, because once again the pair nested and incubated successfully,
but again proceeded to throw the chicks out of the nest.
As the breeding season was rapidly drawing to a close and we desperately
wanted the robin-chats' efforts to be successful, the decision was taken to
artificially incubate the next clutch of eggs. This we duly did. The eggs
measured 25.71mm x 17.77mm and were brown in colour with darker
brown blotches. They were placed in an incubator with the temperature set
at 37.5*C (99.5*F) with relative humidity of 55%. Both eggs were candled
after one week and only one egg proved to be fertile. The incubation period
lasted 15 days.
Upon hatching the tiny chick was placed in a small pot lined with
kitchen paper and plenty of twigs were added to enable the chick to get a
good purchase and help prevent problems with splayed legs. It was moved
to a brooder with the temperature set at 35*C (95*F) and the humidity kept
initially at 80%. This was then gradually reduced, along with the temperature,
over the course of the rearing period.
The chick initially weighed 4g. It was brown/pink in coloration, with
a sparse covering of dark yellow wispy down. It was offered food roughly
every two hours, from 6.00am-10.00pm (2Q.00hrs), for the first nine days.
This varied somewhat, depending on how hungry the chick actually was.
For the first 36 hours the chick was fed small quantities of pinkie mice that
had been soaked in a solution of probiotics and water. Papaya was added
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998198" page_id="56264598"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
34
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.980636" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264598" page_num="34" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-CROWNED ROBIN-CHAT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989766333333333" page_id="56264598"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
to the diet on day two.
The young robin-chat went from strength to strength and was soon at
the weaning stage. All went very smoothly and the young robin-chat was
soon able to be moved into one of our off-display aviaries, with a two year
old Snowy-crowned Robin-Chat C. niveicapilla for company. The young
White-crowned Robin-Chat had begun to sing and was presumed to be a
male. However, as both birds of the adult pair sing, a blood sample was
taken and DNA sexing confirmed that, as we suspected, it was a male. It
later went to make-up a new unrelated pair at Paignton Zoo.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.7105615">
Derek Gibson is Head Keeper at Exmoor Zoo, South Stow ford, Bratton
Fleming, Nr Barnstaple, North Devon, UK. Website:www.exmoorzoo.co.uk/
E-mail:exmoorzoo@btconnect. com &amp; derek. r.gibson@btinternet. com
Louise Peat has set up an Avian Rearing Resources Website - www.
</footnote>
<table confidence="0.664424642857143" page_id="56264598"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
avianrearingresource.co.uk - which aims to compile current hand-rearing
protocols for all species of birds.
*
* *
WEEKEND AWAY
The society is planning a trip to the Netherlands (Holland) over the
weekend of October lst-October 4th to visit Burgers' Zoo, Rotterdam Zoo
and Vogelpark Avifauna. Further details are available from: Howard Travel,
12/13 Church Walk, Trowbridge, Wiltshire BA14 8DX. Tel:01225 777227
E-mail :karli@howardtravel.com
*
* *
ADDITIONAL VISIT
Avicultural Society Council Member Graham Thurlow has arranged a
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.8844195" page_id="56264598"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
visit to see Richard Green's bird collection near Doncaster in Yorkshire. The
visit will take place on Sunday, September 5th and the number of visitors
will be strictly limited. Later the same week, on Saturday, September 11th,
there will be the previously announced visit to see the bird collection at
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.968828333333333">
Leeds Castle, Maidstone, Kent. Further details are available from Stewart
Pyper, 21 Primrose Hill, Nunney, Frome, Somerset BA11 4NP. Tel:01373
836293 (after 6.00pm).
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.626899" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264599" page_num="35" year="" vol="">
MORATON - YELLOW-SHOULDERED AMAZON
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.988748" page_id="56264599"  page_num="35" year="" vol="">
35
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.994839" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264599" page_num="35" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE YELLOW-SHOULDERED AMAZON
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.983611894736842" page_id="56264599"  page_num="35" year="" vol="">
Amazona barbadensis
by Derian A. Silva Moraton
In recent years, pet parrots have been the subject of much discussion.
I have heard it said that they are kept merely for the entertainment of their
owners; that they provide no value to the continuation of their species; that
they become so imprinted that they can never be used for breeding; and
even that the keeping of parrots as pets should be banned. I could write
an entire article on all of the claims I have heard. In fact, pet parrots help
foster an interest in nature, the sciences and conservation; and they can be
as cherished as any family member and grieved over when they die. They
can also be a source of revenue for people living in poor, remote areas. I
have several friends who keep just a single pet parrot, who have travelled to
remote areas to see parrots in the wild, thus fuelling ecotourism and in turn
conservation where it really counts - in the country or countries in which
the birds occur.
Pet parrots, with some exceptions, can often be used for captive breeding.
My experience breeding the Yellow-shouldered Amazon, beginning with a
pair of former pet birds, is a good example of this.
The Yellow-shouldered Amazon has a disjunct distribution across
northern Venezuela, being found in Falcon, Sucre and Anzoatigui, as well
as on the islands of Bonaire, Margarita and Blanquilla. It inhabits dry scrub.
Its numbers fluctuate a great deal, diminishing in very inhospitable years
(during severe droughts) and flourishing during wet years (when there is
good rainfall). There is also pressure on it as the result of birds being taken
for the local pet trade. Throughout its range this species is regarded as a
good talker and birds are consequently traded (albeit illegally) as pets. Most
of the original birds that reached the USA and Europe (mainly through the
Canary Islands) were brought back as pets.
As an aviary bird, the Yellow-shouldered Amazon was ignored until the
late 1970s and early 1980s, when Ramon Noegel began acquiring single pet
birds for breeding. He succeeded in gathering together a small group and, in
1982, bred the species for the first time in captivity. For this achievement he
received a first breeding award from the American Federation of Aviculture
(AFA). (A little later the same year Rosemary Low bred this species for the
first time in the UK.) Since then the Yellow-shouldered Amazon has been
bred with greater frequency. Indeed, in 2009 in South Florida no fewer
than 63 were produced by a handful of breeders; more were produced by
aviculturists in other parts of the USA.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996061" page_id="56264600"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
36
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.895672" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264600" page_num="36" year="" vol="">
MORATON - YELLOW-SHOULDERED AMAZON
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997112390243902" page_id="56264600"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
In 1984, I acquired my first Yellow-shouldered Amazons. The two
had been pet birds. The male, named Herbie, was quite a character, who
was always chattering, dancing and on the move. He was typical of many
representatives of his kind - garrulous and hyperactive. The female, Lolita,
was the opposite - a morose, barely active and quiet bird. They represented
the two personality types that occur. My experience (which many others
share) is that the calmer males are the ones that are most likely to be good
breeders. The hyperactive birds become so aggressive sometimes that the
females eschew them, preventing successful mating.
My two birds, though of contrasting personalities, got along very well.
Within months of being placed together the female nested. Only two eggs
hatched and both chicks were reared. The male was believed to have been
about 23 years old at the time of breeding. The female was acquired as a
nestling by its owner in Caracas and subsequently immigrated with her to
the USA. The male I acquired on loan and the female was purchased when
her owner could not return with it to Venezuela, where she was retiring. One
of the youngsters went to the owner of the breeding male, as part of the loan
agreement. He was given the name Herbie Jr or simply called Junior.
In late January 20091 received a call from the daughter of Junior's owner.
As her elderly mother was going into a nursing home and was not allowed
to keep her bird, she wondered if I would be willing to adopt it. 1 readily
agreed and Junior duly arrived. In many respects he brought back memories
of his father. He spends all day chattering and on the move. However, in
contrast to his father he is never aggressive. His father was a demon when
breeding and more than once bit me as I was changing the food bowls.
Junior passed through quarantine and was kept in the house, but clearly
enjoyed being outdoors and spent the summer in a wire gazebo. As he
preferred to be outdoors, I introduced him into a cage housing several
other Yellow-shouldered Amazons. Within two weeks he had paired with
a young female not quite two years of age. She was not unlike his mother
- morose and very calm, though for short periods twice a day, she becomes
excited and calls. The two birds lived amicably with the others, though they
perched separately from them. As there was no outward sign of fighting, I
did not separate them.
In April, when I was on my way to Europe on business, the pair began
to fight with the other birds. As a temporary measure, my wife placed them
in a cage just 3ft long x 2ft wide x 3ft high (approx. 0.9m long x 0.6m wide
x 0.9m high). It contained a horizontal box 1ft 2in long x lOin wide x lOin
high (35.5cm long x 25.5cm wide x 25.5cm high). The cage was intended
to house the pair only until I returned and could build them a flight.
My wife reported that the pair found the cage very much to its liking.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.625079" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264601" page_num="37" year="" vol="">
MORATON - YELLOW-SHOULDERED AMAZON
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998176" page_id="56264601"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
37
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.981648073170732" page_id="56264601"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
Junior was active and talkative and could chat away to the macaws and
cockatoos on either side. I was away longer than I expected and it was
almost three weeks before I could begin to build the pair a flight. By then,
to my surprise, the female had a swollen vent and, two days short of her
second birthday, laid her first egg. She went on to lay a clutch of four eggs,
all of which, not unexpectedly, proved to be infertile.
I, therefore, took the opportunity to transfer the pair to the new
accommodation I had built. This though was clearly not to their liking. Both
sat on the floor and barely ate anything. The male barely moved or talked.
After three days, I returned them to the cage and they called excitedly and
behaved as if they had been given a new lease on life. Both immediately
began eating and bathed in the water bowl. The following day the female
was back inside the box. Within three weeks she had laid a second clutch of
eggs. Because the birds had been together only a short time and the female
was so young, I did not expect the eggs to be fertile. To my surprise, I was
proved wrong.
The five eggs were fertile. One of them (probably the first) was cracked
accidentally and the second egg failed to develop beyond the second week.
The other three hatched successfully. The pair's behaviour was exemplary.
The male fed the female for the first week and she in turn fed the young.
After the first week, the female would leave the nest and the male would
then enter the nest and feed the young. When they were three weeks old,
they were removed and hand-reared. All three were weaned successfully
and proved to be two females and a male.
They were placed with other Yellow-shouldered Amazons and, in the
future, will be used for breeding. When the large number of young bred
in 2009 mature, they will boost the potential breeding population of this
species. I can clearly see this attractively coloured parrot becoming very
well established in captivity.
Parrot behaviour is clearly inherited. Junior's father would chew his tail
and flight feathers when the female was incubating the eggs; he clearly missed
her and out of boredom damaged his feathers. They grew back again after
the young were removed. Junior did the same. When the female no longer
had a reason to return to the nest (because the young had been removed),
Junior called and became excited - he finally had his playmate back. The
two birds were clearly very fond of each other.
My experience demonstrates that former pet birds can and will breed.
The natural instinct to reproduce is ingrained in the genes and given the
opportunity and suitable conditions, many former pet parrots will breed
successfully.
Derian A. Silva Moraton lives at North Miami Beach, Florida, USA.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998448" page_id="56264602"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
38
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.981595" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264602" page_num="38" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE TAIWAN YUHINA Yuhina brunneiceps
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.975310947368421" page_id="56264602"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
by Gary Bralsford
Back in 1986,1 purchased a pair of Taiwan (Formosan) Yuhinas Yuhina
brunneiceps from a dealer in Derbyshire, here in the UK. He used to have
some very nice small softbills, such as Daurian Redstarts Phoenicurus
auroreus, Blue-and-white Flycatchers Cyanoptila cyanomelana and
yuhinas.
There was a large bank of cages, one of which contained the pair of
yuhinas that were feeding one another. These proved to be a really steady
pair of Taiwan Yuhinas, a species endemic to the island of Taiwan, where
this most attractively marked yuhina inhabits montane forests.
There were not many Taiwan Yuhinas around at the time. Dave Campbell
had imported a few, but there had been no large consignments. The first
UK breeding of this species had been achieved by Bob Beeson in 1984
(his account of the breeding was published the following year in Cage &amp;
Aviary Birds).
I placed my yuhinas on their own in a 10ft x 4ft x 6ft high (approx. 3m
x 1.2m x 1.8m high) aviary, with a 5ft x 4ft (approx. 1.5m x 1.2m) shelter
inside my shed. I placed half-open-fronted nest boxes and wicker nest-pans
inside the shelter and in the outside flight. To provide privacy, all of the
nest sites were screened with conifer cuttings. As the floor of the flight was
paved with 3ft x 2ft (approx. 90cm x 60cm) paving slabs, I placed tubs of
plants around the outside of the aviary. I used Russian Vines Polygunum
baldschuanicum, honeysuckle Lonicera sp. and dwarf conifers. The vines
and honeysuckle were secured to bamboo canes and to the dividing wire of
the flight with wool.
One day I noticed the larger of the two yuhinas trying to tease out fibres
from the wool tying the climbers to the wire and later watched it carrying
these fibres to some conifer cuttings I had tied to the aviary wire. After
watching this behaviour for about an hour, I could not resist taking a look.
I pulled back the conifer cuttings and saw that they had begun to weave a
nest platform that they had attached to the conifer stems in the wire. I left
them alone for a couple of days and when I looked the second time, the
nest was beginning to take shape, with coconut fibre being used and animal
hair being used for the lining. However, I was concerned that the nest was
top-heavy and looked as so it was about to collapse under its own weight. I
quickly cut a piece of chicken wire, which I shaped into a cup. I then wired
this to the frame of the flight beneath the nest to support it.
I just hoped that the pair would return to the nest and that I had not
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.501831" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264603" page_num="39" year="" vol="">
BRALSFORD - TAIWAN YUHINA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998471" page_id="56264603"  page_num="39" year="" vol="">
39
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999800918918919" page_id="56264603"  page_num="39" year="" vol="">
disturbed it too much. I sat back and watched and was greatly relieved to
see the pair return to the nest and continue lining it. About five days after
the pair finished building the nest, the first egg was laid. It was white with
faint rust-red markings on the large end. A total of three eggs were laid
which were incubated by the female. During the incubation period, I found
it hard to resist taking a look every three days or so though, of course, this
Is not recommended, as it can lead to the eggs and young being deserted.
Nowadays, I do not interfere when my birds are breeding, but back in those
days I was less aware of the consequences.
Fortunately, the pair was extremely tolerant and after 14 days all three
eggs hatched within 24 hours. At the time I was off work following an
accident and this meant I had plenty of time to go off and look for livefood.
I found a meadow of wild grasses and flowers and, using a fine net, succeeded
in catching a wide variety of insects, such as moths, beetles and spiders,
which I tipped into large ice cream tubs. I supplemented this wild livefood
with mini mealworms, small brown crickets and waxmoth larvae. With this
plentiful supply of livefood, the three chicks grew rapidly. Soon the small
nest was overflowing with the three almost fully-grown young yuhinas.
Then, on the fourteenth day, disaster struck, for I found one of them dead
beneath the nest. It was fully feathered and I can only presume that it had
fallen out of the nest. The remaining two young fledged at 16 days old and
were independent at 30 days.
The pair went on to raise a further three young that year, giving me a
total of five for the season. I believe these were only the second and third
confirmed breedings of this species in the UK.
In 1986, there was a wealth of birds to chose from and, foolishly, I traded
in all seven yuhinas for other softbills. It is something I now very much
regret. With the ban on the import of birds into the EU (European Union),
there is little chance of this species or other yuhinas becoming available
again. The only yuhina being kept in the UK now seems to be the White-
collared species Y diademata. According to the latest FBF Register of Birds
Bred in the UK under Controlled Conditions for the Years 2005-2008 , 13
White-collared Yuhinas were bred in 2005, but only one in 2007 and none
in 2008. The last recorded breeding of the Whiskered Yuhina Y. flavicollis
in the UK was in 2001.
Gary would like to hear from anyone who has knowledge or experience
of keeping the Taiwan Yuhina,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.975672" page_id="56264604"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
40
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.86902" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264604" page_num="40" year="" vol="">
THE MOUSEBIRDS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.983525789473684" page_id="56264604"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
by Jo Gregson
There are six species of mousebirds, all of which are found in Africa.
The name is apt for these long-tailed birds, some with mainly brownish
plumage and others with mainly greyish plumage, do indeed resemble mice,
as they scurry about in trees and scrubby bushes. Captive mousebirds are
most often kept in large tropical houses in which they tend to be seen at a
distance or are often overlooked. Unless seen at close proximity they can
appear rather drab and uninteresting. At close range, however, the plumage
of the most commonly kept species, the Speckled Mousebird Colius striatus,
is seen to be delicately marked with many shades of brown, and the Blue-
naped Urocolius macroura and the Red-faced Mousebird U. indicus show
flashes of bright colouring.
It is certainly worth spending time taking a closer look at these attractive
and extremely engaging birds. They are very sociable and live in family
groups, that huddle together when roosting and spend a lot of time preening
each other. In fact, mousebirds preen their group mates more than do any
other group of birds. Mousebirds differ from other birds in a number of
ways. The four toes on each foot can, for example, all be used in the forward
position and this enables mousebirds to hang from branches, often in small
tightly formed groups, thereby saving body heat and protecting each other
during rainstorms. Mousebirds have no down feathers and would soon be
soaked to the skin and become chilled if they were to roost alone. Their
wings are short and rounded, enabling them to fly quickly in short bursts.
Long flights are avoided, with mousebirds instead preferring to scramble
amongst the branches in search of food. Whereas most birds, when drinking,
need to raise their head in order to let the water trickle down their throat,
pigeons (and a few other birds) are able to suck up the water without raising
their head, and mousebirds drink in a similar manner. They often hang
from a branch overhanging water and drink in this way, thereby keeping
safe from predators.
Two to three eggs are laid and both the male and female take turns to
incubate them. They changeover frequently, with one bird sitting for only
an hour or so at a time, before the other takes its place. The eggs hatch after
12 days and the young are fed by both parents, as well as by other members
of the group. It is not unusual to find several members of the group roosting
together on the nest, sitting on the eggs or brooding the chicks. By the time
they are 10 days old, the young are able to climb out of the nest and move
about on the branches. At this stage, however, they remain vulnerable and,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.877336" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264605" page_num="41" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - MOUSEBIRDS
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.662835">
Paignton Zoo
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9958976" page_id="56264605"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
Speckled Mousebird. Clements (2007) listed 17 subspecies.
The eye colour is variable.
if they fall to the ground, are unable to get back up onto the branches.
When hand-rearing is necessary, at Paignton Zoo we have found that
a parrot-rearing diet fed to the chicks through a syringe works very well.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998143" page_id="56264606"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
42
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.972638" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264606" page_num="42" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - MOUSEBIRDS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.992795166666667" page_id="56264606"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
As soon as the chicks are big enough, they are encouraged to hang from a
perch, both to strengthen their legs and feet and to ensure that their moist
droppings fall clear and do not foul their plumage. Young mousebirds soon
learn to pick up chopped, soft fruit, out of a hanging dish.
Hand-reared mousebirds become very tame and crave attention, and are
often quite at home clinging to the keeper's shirt as the keeper attends to
other duties. As endearing as this may seem, a few plops of digested fruit
down the front of your shirt, will soon make you think again. Mousebirds
need to eat often and, being fruit-eaters, digest their food very quickly in a
matter six to 20 minutes. New birds are readily accepted into a group and
will push their way into the middle of the cluster to get warm or to shelter
from the rain.
Mousebirds can be pests in fruit-growing areas, consuming fruit, blossom,
buds and even soft leaves (as well as large numbers of insects). If large
groups are kept in tropical houses, they can do considerable damage to the
plant life. Even so they are worthwhile and lively additions to any tropical
house.
Jo, who was recently elected an Avicultural Society Council Member,
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.56827875" page_id="56264606"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
is Curator of Birds at Paignton Zoo Environmental Park, Totnes Road,
Paignton, Devon TQ4 7EU, UK. E-mail:jo.gregson@paigntonzoo.org.uk
* *
*
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.720181" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264606" page_num="42" year="" vol="">
FIELD STUDIES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8965766" page_id="56264606"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
The Field Studies Council (FSC) is an environmental education charity
with a network of centres located in many of the most spectacular parts of
the UK. It has a wide range of natural history courses, which range from
identifying birds by sight and sound to discovering wild flowers. Courses
vary in length from a weekend to a week and are available at a choice of
different levels. The course fee includes full board accommodation, transport
during the course and the expert guidance of its tutors. To view the list of
courses available you can go to: http://www.field-studies-council.org/2010/
index.aspx or alternatively you can view its ebrochure at: http://view.
digipage.net/?id=natural%20history%20courses%202010&amp;page= 18
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.784323" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264607" page_num="43" year="" vol="">
A NOTE ON THE COURTSHIP BEHAVIOUR OF THE
COLLARED GROSBEAK Mycerobas affinis
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999712" page_id="56264607"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9766139" page_id="56264607"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
by Simon Matthews
During December 2009, here at Waddesdon Manor, a pair of our Collared
Grosbeaks which had been first introduced earlier that year and was housed
in one of our off-show aviaries, was shut inside the shelter due to the cold
weather and in order to treat the pair for suspected aspergillosis. Whilst
the pair was shut inside the shelter, very few interactions between the two
birds were observed. At the end of the treatment for suspected aspergillosis,
on a day when the temperature had risen just above freezing, the pair was
allowed access to the outside flight. I was fortunate to be the keeper to
release the pair back out into the flight and, after letting the pair out, spent
a few minutes cleaning the adjacent flights. The pair was very vocal, with
both birds doing a lot of calling and flying back and forth, up and down the
flight. At that point, I began to watch the pair more closely in case there
was any aggression. The female was chasing the male and calling both
whilst in flight and whilst perched; the male called only when perched and
just before taking off The female then began to carry a piece of vegetation
(nesting material!). The male then remained on the perch at the opposite
end of the aviary from where I was observing them and the female joined
him and both birds stopped calling. The female lowered and flattened her
body in the customary position ready for copulation and was gently twitching
her wings. The behaviour of the male, who was perched a few inches
(centimetres) away from the female, was less normal. He lowered his head,
so that his back was horizontal and moved his wings fluidly from there, so
that his wing tips pointed vertically towards the sky. He held this posture
for three to five seconds (not enough time to get a camera unfortunately)
before he mounted the female and attempted copulation, which appeared
to be unsuccessful.
If anyone has observed similar behaviour by this or related species, I
would be interested to hear from them.
E-mail: simon. Matthews@nationaltrust. org. uk
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998028" page_id="56264608"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
44
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.991947" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264608" page_num="44" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEW
WHILE FLOCKS LAST
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999122290322581" page_id="56264608"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
Books on our native British birds have been rolling off the presses at an
amazing pace in recent years, keeping abreast with the growing number of
birdwatchers. When I saw While Flocks Last I hesitated. Should I buy it I
wondered, or was it just another book that would have little to distinguish
it from several other similar books. I did buy it, and from the first page I
realised that not only is Charlie Elder, the author, a very accomplished writer
but he has a great sense of humour and an imagination that makes one keep
turning the pages.
He also hit on a unique idea. An armchair birdwatcher by inclination, he
decided to go in search of all of Britain's threatened bird species and relate
the adventures he had along the way. A journalist by profession, he decided
to somehow fit this venture in between his regular working schedule. As
he lives on Dartmoor in south-west England, and many of the species he
wanted to see live way up in the north, it involved spending a lot of time
alone driving up and back down motorways, much to the despair of his long-
suffering family, who thought he was experiencing a mid-life crisis!
In 2009 the BoCC list - Birds of Conservation Concern - was revised and
a further four species were added to the list. This meant he had to search for
40 rare and elusive birds. I defy anyone to read his account and not laugh
out loud. His self-deprecating style and his wonderful descriptions make
this book hugely enjoyable. Just let me quote what he wrote about his first
sighting of a Hen Harrier, in its stronghold, on the Isle of Man:
"Looking west I noticed that where the weak rays of the pale sun passed
through cold air above the distant moors, a tiny dot had appeared. It grew like
a swirl of dark gasses and spread until it took the form of a living organism.
Wings appeared and with them the power to fly free, and tearing itself from
the bonds of light, ripping its feathers into ragged fingers in the process, it
emerged into the world of living creatures. Behold! A hen harrier, heading
straight towards me!"
This book will make many people stop and think about our native birds,
threatened by human activities - the birds most had no idea were threatened.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.6417678">
Did Charlie Elder see them all? To find out for yourself you will have read
the book.
While Flocks Last (ISBN 978059 3061046) is published by Bantam
Press. Price #14.99 hardback.
Rosemary Low
</reference>
<page confidence="0.997327" page_id="56264609"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
45
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9782005" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264609" page_num="45" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
FOUR SO FAR
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9712055" page_id="56264609"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
Four Andean Cock-of-the-Rock chicks Rupicola peruvianus have been
hatched so far this year at Dallas World Aquarium in Texas. It brings the
total hatched there since 2007 to 23, of which 16 are still living. Again, both
females which have laid each year have produced chicks.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.797331" page_id="56264609"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8817" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264609" page_num="45" year="" vol="">
EUROPE'S LAST JABIRU
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993924666666667" page_id="56264609"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
Chris Brack has drawn my attention to the fact that the last Jabiru Jabiru
mycteria in captivity in Europe has died at the bird park at Timmendorfer
Strand on the Baltic coast of Germany. The bird, a female named Jabi, died
in November 2008. She is said to have lived there for 26 years having, Chris
believes, come originally from Vogelpark Walsrode. This Central and South
American stork can, he says, still be seen at San Diego Wild Animal Park,
which has one, and at Dallas Zoo, which has two unsexed birds, as well
as at Sao Paulo Zoo in Brazil, where there is a female, and at Cali Zoo in
Colombia, which has a pair.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.612774" page_id="56264609"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.945539947368421" page_id="56264609"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
A CASE OF MISTAKEN IDENTITY
Towards the end of my precis-cum-review of the latest FBF Breeding
Register (Vol.115, No.4, pp.198-199 (2009)), I expressed surprise at the
breeding of seven "Scarlet Tanagers Piranga olivacecT here in the UK in
2008 and said I would like to know more about the breeding. Nigel Hewston
has confirmed that, as I suspected, the birds were not Piranga olivacea but
Ramphocelus bresilius , the Brazilian Tanager, a species that used to be well-
known in UK aviculture and was, invariably (and perhaps understandably),
known here as the Scarlet Tanager ( Piranga olivacea being more-or-less
unknown in UK aviculture). Nigel said, that the tanagers in question were
bred by Terry Sayers, whose report and photos of his birds, appeared in
Foreign Birds Summer 2009 issue, in which the mistake appeared originally.
Reuben Girling has confirmed to Nigel that the record refers to the same
birds. Six of these tanagers were bred at Wuppertal Zoo in Germany in
2008. The English summary in the 2008 Annual Report listed them as
"Silver-beaked Tanagers," but the splendid colour photo on p.13 is of the
Brazilian Tanager, which does indeed have a silvery-white base to the lower
mandible, not unlike that of the darker coloured Silver-beaked (or Maroon)
Tanager R. carbo.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99663" page_id="56264610"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
46
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.970772" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264610" page_num="46" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
THE SECRET OF THE WHISTLE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996849235294118" page_id="56264610"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
When describing the management of the Crested Pigeon Ocyphaps
lophotes at Exmoor Zoo in the previous issue of the magazine (Vol. 115,
No.4, pp. 185-191 (2009)), Derek Gibson listed four alternative names for
this familiar Australian pigeon, one of which is Whistle-winged Pigeon. This
is because, as it takes to the air, its rapid wing-beats produce a distinctive
whistling sound, which is made by air passing over a modified primary
feather in each wing. A report in Bird Keeping in Australia Vol. 53, No.4,
April 2010, p.65, reveals that in an experiment using a model of an Accipiter
hawk and then in another in which they did not use a model of a hawk, Robert
Magrath and Mae Hingee of the Australian National University in Canberra,
discovered that the Crested Pigeon produces two different whistling sounds.
One acts as an alarm and causes the birds to take to the sky in panic and the
other fails to produce any response at all. To the human ear, the two whistles
may sound identical, but acoustic analysis revealed that the two sounds are
quite complex and distinctive. The whistling sound that acts as an alarm and
causes flocks to flee in panic is louder and has a more rapid tempo, and the
birds can obviously instantly pick out the difference between the two.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.77559" page_id="56264610"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.786903" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264610" page_num="46" year="" vol="">
SUCCESS WITH SOFTBILLS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.964042909090909" page_id="56264610"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
When the North American population of the Red-faced Liocichla
Liocichla phoenicea dropped recently to just 11 birds, North Carolina
Zoo stepped in and acquired nine of them and is making a concerted
effort to breed this species. So far, three pairs have hatched a total of four
chicks. Last year the zoo also bred two Golden-headed Manakins Pipra
erythrocephala. It is only the second known successful captive breeding of
this species in North America. It also succeeded in fledging a Golden White-
eye Cleptornis marchei. It is believed to be the first ever captive breeding
of this species. Other species of softbill bred in 2009, included Turquoise
Tanager Tangara mexicana , Pekin Robin Leiothrix lutea and Homed Lark
Eremophila alpestris.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.536562" page_id="56264610"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.843269" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264610" page_num="46" year="" vol="">
NEW TO AVICULTURE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995595" page_id="56264610"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
In a 1925 issue of the magazine (p. 191), in what was I suppose the
equivalent of the present day News &amp; Views section, the writer noted that
Dr Emilius Hopkinson had just arrived in England from the Gambia with
several interesting birds, amongst which were two beautiful Chestnut-bellied
Starlings Lamprotornis pulcher , an African Golden Oriole Oriolus auratus
and a Blue-bellied Roller Coracias cyanogaster. All three of these were
believed to be new to aviculture.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.699838" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264611" page_num="47" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.993718" page_id="56264611"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
47
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.897742" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264611" page_num="47" year="" vol="">
INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM ON GALLIFORMES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.803129384615385" page_id="56264611"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
The World Pheasant Association (WPA), King Mongkut's University
of Technology, Thomburi (KMUTT) and the IUCN-SSC/WPA Galliformes
Specialist Group, have jointly organised the Fifth International Symposium
on Galliformes, which will take place from November 7th-November 14th
2010 at Chiang Mai, Thailand. The subject of the symposium will be
the conservation and sustainable management of all species of pheasant,
partridge, quail, francolin and guineafowl, with special emphasis on Asia,
threatened species and their habitats. In addition, there will be a number
of pre and post-symposium tours and workshops. Further information
is available on the WPA website:www.pheasant.org.uk and from Barbara
Ingman, Administrator, World Pheasant Association, Newcastle University
Biology Field Station, Close House Estate, Heddon on the Wall, Newcastle
upon Tyne NE15 OHT.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.580714" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264611" page_num="47" year="" vol="">
AN UNFORESEEN CONSEQUENCE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.941993173913043" page_id="56264611"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
A report in Cyanopsitta No.94, pp.25-26, December 2009, on the trade
in African Grey Parrots Psittacus erithacus, particularly in Cameroon, but
also in other African countries, notes that the EU (European Union) ban on
the import of wild-caught birds (which became permanent on July 1 st 2007),
along with a clampdown since 2007 by CITES (Convention on International
Trade in Endangered Species), had a dramatic and perhaps unforeseen affect
on the trade in Grey Parrots in Cameroon, which according to official figures
exported 367,166 Grey Parrots between 1981- 2005. The most horrifying
aspect is that, deprived of their main European market, some trappers have
turned to killing the parrots and selling their body parts for use in traditional
African rites. An accompanying photo shows a pile of perhaps 200-300 or
more Grey Parrot heads and another shows their red tail packed in plastic
bags. These are said to fetch prices comparable to those paid for the live
birds.
Other traders are selling their birds locally or smuggling them into
neighbouring countries, where they are said to fetch better prices than in
Cameroon. Many Grey Parrots are exported to South Africa, from where
a high proportion are later re-exported. Some traders have, apparently,
found ways to export their birds to Middle Eastern and Asian countries. In
2007-2008 substantial numbers of Grey Parrots were imported into Lebanon,
Bahrain, Pakistan and Singapore. Birds also came into Europe by way of
Serbia, which is not directly affected by the EU ban.
In PsittaScene Vol.22, No.l, p.2, February 2010, reference is made to
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997564" page_id="56264612"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
48
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.925582" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264612" page_num="48" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9923005" page_id="56264612"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
"another massive confiscation" of 1,000 Grey Parrots, the largest single
seizure ever recorded in Cameroon. They joined, it is said, several hundred
others that were confiscated a few months earlier. The World Parrot Trust
(WPT) has dispatched emergency funds to assist with their care.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.70394" page_id="56264612"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.698048" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264612" page_num="48" year="" vol="">
PBFD THREAT TO THE CAPE PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.969562526315789" page_id="56264612"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
Dr Steve Boyes of the Percy Fitzpatrick Institute in South Africa
has, thanks to an individual's generous sponsorship, been awarded #820
(approx. US$1,230) by the African Bird Club Conservation Fund, for
a study of psittacine beak and feather disease (PBFD) in the largest
remaining population of Cape Parrots Poicephalus robustus. With an
estimated population of 1,000-15,000 birds, the Cape Parrot is threatened
by habitat loss, illegal capture for the bird trade and avian diseases. The
primary objective of the study is to capture as many of these parrots as
possible to discover the incidence of PBFD and other diseases, check their
body condition and take blood samples for DNA-archiving, to be used in
the forensic investigation into illegal trade. He will also conduct feeding
trials, with birds temporarily held in field aviaries, in an attempt to better
understand the Cape Parrot's feeding ecology and preference for cultivated
(introduced) pecan nuts over its traditional indigenous food sources. Steve
Boyes, who previously studied Meyer's or the Brown Parrot P. meyeri in
the Okavango Delta (see News &amp; Views, pp.94-95, Vol.114, No.2 (2008))
and experimented with the use of nest boxes, to determine if they can be
an effective conservation tool, plans to use data from that study to come up
with a nest box suitable for the Cape Parrot.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.754001666666667" page_id="56264612"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
* * *
THE MAGNIFICENT HARPY EAGLE
Miami Metrozoo in Florida last year became only the second zoo in North
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.994652375" page_id="56264612"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
America to breed the magnificent Harpy Eagle Harpia harpyja. The chick's
parents were both hatched at San Diego Zoo. A male Harpy Eagle hatched
in 1991 at Nuremberg Zoo in Germany arrived recently at Weltvogelpark
Walsrode as a potential mate for the park's current female, which originated
from South America and arrived in Berlin as a juvenile in 1972. She laid
her first eggs in 1979. An earlier attempt was made to pair the male with
another female at Walsrode, but proved unsuccessful as did an attempt to
pair him with a female at Tierpark Berlin.
</bodyText>
<bodyText confidence="0.991119388888889" page_id="56264613"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
MRS E. M. (BETTY) ROBERTS
Those who in the 1960s-1980s bought birds from David Roberts Wildlife
Limited, PO Box 1051, Nakuru, Kenya, or have visited Lake Baringo, will
be saddened to learn of the death of Betty Roberts, who ran the business for
many years following the untimely death of her husband David.
When, as a result of a prolonged drought in, I think the late 1950s and/or
the early 1960s, there were not enough tilapia to sustain the fish factory he
had established on the shore of Lake Baringo, David Roberts turned instead to
the rich variety of birds which, because of the drought, were concentrated on
and around the rapidly shrinking lake in even greater numbers than usual.
He became for many zoos, bird gardens and approved private
aviculturists, a primary source of African waterbirds such as egrets, herons,
pelicans, Blacksmith, Spur-winged and Kittlitz's Plovers, Black-winged
Stilts, Avocets, African Jacpanas, Yellow-billed Storks and African Fish
Eagles, as well as birds such as Bristle-crowned and Magpie Starlings,
d'Amaud's and Red-and-yellow Barbets, Spotted Morning Warblers and
Red-billed Oxpeckers; and from Lake Hannington, later renamed Lake
Bogoria, just to the south, Lesser Flamingos.
Following his death at a tragically early age from a "mystery illness,"
leaving her with six young children (five boys and a girl), Betty remained at
Lake Baringo and continued to export birds around the world, right up until
the time that the Kenya Government banned the export of birds. Some of the
birds, such as several different species of sunbirds, including the Golden-
winged, Tacazze and Northern Double-collared, as well as birds such as the
Yellow-billed Barbet, robin-chats, Black-headed Gonoleks, Grey-headed
Negrofinches, Red-headed Bluebills and Oriole Finches, came from Tim
and Jane Bamley on the Cherengani Hills of western Kenya. Most of the
Ross's and White-crested Turacos from Kenya at that time, along with the
Splendid Starling's, had been hand-reared by Jane.
Earlier this year I received a letter from Betty Roberts, dated January
24th, asking if I had heard the sad news that Julia, the youngest daugther
of Jane and the late Tim Bamley, had died the previous evening. Her death
was not totally unexpected, but nonetheless came as a terrible shock. Then,
only a matter of weeks later, in the course of a telephone conversation with
Jane Bamley, I learned that, unbeknown to me, Betty had died "peacefully"
a few weeks earlier.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.479089">
Malcolm Ellis
</subsectionHeader>
<address confidence="0.524067">
3 9088 01509 9294
</address>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.69205" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264614" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
J
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.6340015" page_id="56264614"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Challenges and opportunities for sustainable wildlife management
in Cameroon: the story of Peggy an African Grey Parrot
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.920082142857143" page_id="56264614"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Ajaga Nji, Simon A. Tamungang, W. L. Asong,
Mbafor Fidelia, Tsafack Antoine and Sabi B. Nji.2
The spirit of Jean Delacour lives on at Parc de Cleres
by Pierre de Chabannes.16
Weltvogelpark Walsrode - The beginning of a new era
by Simon Bruslund Jensen.25
Hand-rearing a White-crowned Robin-Chat
Cossypha albicapilla at Exmoor Zoo
by Derek Gibson.30
Breeding the Yellow-shouldered Amazon Amazona barbadensis
by Derian A. Silva Moraton.35
Breeding the Taiwan Yuhina Yuhina brunneiceps
by Gary Bralsford.38
The Mousebirds
</table>
<figure confidence="0.728603375" page_id="56264614"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Jo Gregson...40
A note on the courtship behaviour of the Collared Grosbeak
Mycerobas affinis
by Simon Matthews.43
Book Review
While Flocks Last.44
News &amp; Views.45
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
</figure>
</algorithms>
