<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.763069" page_id="56266133"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 111
No. 2
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266134" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990578714285714" page_id="56266134"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2005 as for 2004: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.618871" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266134" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE..
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970951409090909" page_id="56266134"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, ARCADIA, THE MOUNTS, TOTNES, DEVON TQ9 7QJ, UK.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TNI3 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail: Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998476" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266134" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982477333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7398905" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266135" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<category confidence="0.379329">
VoL 111 - No. 2 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2005
</category>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997535" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266135" page_num="" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE ZANZIBAR RED BISHOP IN A MIXED
COLLECTION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9982719" page_id="56266135"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Alan and Beverley Brock
Five years ago we maintained seven aviaries housing a collection of
softbills and seedeaters. However, due to changes in work patterns and the
difficulty in obtaining suitable help for holiday periods, we decided to reduce
our collection and its maintenance to a more practical level. A block of six
aviaries were converted into one large flight measuring 30ft x 6ft x 8ft high
(approx. 9.1m x 1.8m x 2.4m high) with a shelter attached, heated and lit by
electricity. The flight was planted with a number of hardy shrubs and plants
but the depredations of the seedeaters have caused a great deal of damage to
them.
The reduced collection was intended originally to house seedeaters only.
This resolution held good until the acquisition of a pair of R ed crested
Cardinals Paroaria coronata, which in addition to seed, take fruit, livefood
and Bogena. We then began picking up odds and ends from dealers and as
we were providing the above diet for the cardinals, they were soon joined
by a number of softbills.
Four years ago we also obtained some weaver birds, including two pairs
of Zanzibar Red Bishops Euplectes nigroventris . This fairly localised eastern
African species is very like the closely related and more familiar Northern
E. franciscanus and Southern Red Bishop E. orix. However, it is smaller,
measuring about 4in (10cm) in length and when the male is in breeding
plumage, the red on the head extends fully over the crown and forehead.
The other two are bigger, they measure about d'Cm 5in (11.5cm-12.5cm) in
length and the red on the head of the males does not extend fully over the
crown and forehead, which are black.
Most weaver species conduct their courtship display in a similar fashion,
the male puffing-up his head feathers and flicking his wings, while pursuing
the female or challenging another male. There are many mock fights but no
injuries occur. The call or song consists of a curious metallic-like whirring
sound and a harsh chattering note when threatening another bird.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.989054" page_id="56266136"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
50
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.993232704545454" page_id="56266136"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
BROCK &amp; BROCK - ZANZIBAR RED BISHOP
Although weavers are renowned for their reluctance to breed in captivity,
this reluctance does not extend to constructing nests. After we supplied
them with coconut fibre a host of small, spherical nests, began to appear
attached to branches, trellis and the wire panels of the flight. There are also
two pairs of Napoleon Weavers E. afer and a pair of Red-billed Queleas
Quelea quelea in the aviary and some of these nests were undoubtedly built
by them, but they did not exhibit the fanaticism of the Zanzibar Red Bishops.
At one point they constructed three nests on a 6ft (almost 2m) high trellis,
one about 2ft (60cm) from the ground, one in the centre and the other at the
top. Some were started and then abandoned when still no more than a thin
layer of fibre, while others were abandoned when they were well advanced
and were too dense to see through. The two male birds spent a great deal of
time in aggressive posturing and were constantly squabbling with each other
and with the other weavers. We have kept a number of species of weavers
over the years and have observed a great deal of this posturing but, as stated
previously, never any injuries. They appear to be quarrelsome by nature but
not vicious.
We did not make any detailed observations on the Zanzibar Red Bishops
as we did not expect them to breed. However, on August 14th 2003, a
weaver chick was found drowned in one of the concrete bird baths in the
aviary. It was tiny, no bigger than a 5Op coin (which measures fractionally
over 1 in (28mm) across) but appeared to be fully fledged. We were unaware
as to which of the three species it had belonged, so decided to keep closer
observation on all of them.
One of the male Zanzibar Red Bishops was seen to take up a position
slightly above a strongly built nest that was woven into the mesh of one of
the aviary panels. He assiduously drove away any bird that approached and
the female was seen entering the nest. A discreet examination of the nest
disclosed that it contained a small, pale blue egg. The nest, constructed of
coconut fibre, appeared to have very little lining, other than one or two tiny
feathers. However, two days later the female deserted the nest. The egg
was cold and on closer examination proved to be infertile.
Further observations established that only one pair was nesting. The
male of that pair constantly harried any bird which approached the nest,
which was the same one, attached to the panel at the front of the aviary.
Soon we found ourselves facing a curious dichotomy. The female was very
susceptible to disturbance and even the slightest intrusion near the nest
resulted in the eggs being deserted. So, in the end we gave up close
surveillance and instead observed them through binoculars from the kitchen
window, from where the female could be seen entering and leaving the nest.
Yet the chosen nesting site on the aviary panel was less than 2ft (60cm)
from the garden path. The constant use of the path, by ourselves, two dogs
and a cat and the innumerable Foxes Vulpes vulpes that use the path at night
</bodyText>
<copyright confidence="0.239701">
BROCK &amp; BROCK - ZANZIBAR RED BISHOP
</copyright>
<page confidence="0.997347" page_id="56266137"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
51
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.924449" page_id="56266137"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
did not appear to worry her in the slightest. It seemed to be entry into the
aviary and any approach to the nest that she objected to.
Brief diary of frustrating events during 2004 breeding season.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.981571727272727" page_id="56266137"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
July 3rd
July 4th
July 5th
July 23rd
July 24th
July 25th
August 8th
August 12th
August 21st
August 23 rd
September 2nd
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.985114975609756" page_id="56266137"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
Returned home from holiday. Inspected nest using a torch and dental
mirror and found one chick with its eyes not yet open and one egg.
Chick dead in nest. Both it and the egg were cold. Presumably the
female deserted after the nest was inspected.
Egg missing.
One egg in nest.
Two eggs.
Female sitting.
Female sitting. Inspected nest when she left to feed. Two eggs.
Female no longer sitting. Eggs missing.
Female sitting again so did not disturb or inspect nest.
Female sitting intermittenly.
Female no longer sitting. No eggs.
Giving up close surveillance of the nest meant we were unable to record
when eggs were laid, how many were laid, how long they took to hatch and
other valuable information. All we could do was watch from a distance and
wait for the appearance of a fledgling or fledglings.
During the winter months the aviary is completely covered with fine
green nylon mesh. This is sold by garden centres and is used to provide
windbreaks and is also used by builders to protect new brickwork from
frost. During this period the birds could not be observed from outside the
aviary. We found a dead chick, this time on the ground, in late February.
Presumably the fairly mild winter weather coupled with the slightly higher
temperature in the aviary, occasioned by the nylon mesh, encouraged them
to continue nesting.
Part of the mesh was removed in late March 2005, enabling limited
observations to be kept. On April 13th a small fledgling was spotted perched
on a trellis, shaking its wings and begging for food. It seemed to be in poor
condition. It was observed that it was not being fed, but was in fact being
'buzzed' in a most aggressive fashion by both parent birds. Therefore, it
was decided the catch the fledgling before it came to any harm. It was
accordingly brought indoors, measured and ringed (banded) and placed in a
cage with two young Zebra Finches Taeniopygia guttata castanotis. It was
just over 2V2in (6.5cm) in length and was at that time slightly smaller than
the Zebra Finches.
It was extremely hungry and within ten minutes was eating a softfood
mix based on Bogena. It settled down very quickly and takes spray millet
and budgie mixture (although like most weavers it picks out the millet and
leaves most of the canary seed). Seeding grasses have been offered, but so
far it has shown little interest in these. Mini mealworms have been ignored
to date.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995712" page_id="56266138"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
52
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9633633" page_id="56266138"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
BROCK &amp; BROCK - ZANZIBAR RED BISHOP
The fledgling has grown a further Vrin (13mm). At the time of writing
(early May), it resembles the female and the male in eclipse plumage. It
will be returned to the aviary in the summer, when it is better able to fend
for itself.
Maintenance details are as follows:
The aviary is planted with elder, raspberries and blackberries. Fir
branches attached to the trelliswork provide cover. Nesting materials supplied
to the weavers consists of coconut fibre plus some feathers.
Other inhabitants of the mixed collection:
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.937384071428571" page_id="56266138"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
Three Amethyst Starlings Cinnyricinclus leucogaster
Four Emerald Starlings Lamprotornis iris
Two Red-crested Cardinals Paroaria coronata
Three Pekin Robins/Red-billed Leiothrix Leiothrix lutea
One White-cheeked Starling Sturnus cineraceus
One pair Southern Red Bishops/Orange Weavers Euplectes orix
One pair Red-billed Queleas Quelea quelea
One Black-headed Weaver Ploceus cucullatus
Two pairs Napoleon Weavers Euplectes afer
Eight Zebra Finches Taeniopygia guttata castanotis
One pair Spice Birds Lonchura punctulata
Two pairs Bengalese Finches Lonchura striata dom.
Food provided:
Plain canary seed, millets, spray millet, hemp, sunflower. Chopped apple,
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.98781025" page_id="56266138"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
grapes, tomato, sultanas and raisins, half pears, half oranges (occasionally).
Bogena mixed with grated cheese, egg yolk and suet, plus Stress vitamin
powder. Mealwonns and fruit fly cultures, as well as garden compost for
the small invertebrates contained in it.
The species of weaver take two millets, canary seed, mealwonns, fruit
flies and other insects they are able to catch in the aviary. They also take the
Bogena mix and have been seen pecking in the fruit bowl. We were unable
to ascertain whether they were eating the fruit or taking insects attracted by
it.
It is possible that the aggressiveness shown by the parents towards this
fledgling may also have been a factor in the deaths of the previous chicks.
Therefore, we will be observing them as closely as is practical, while bearing
in mind their extreme reactions to disturbance.
Alan and Beverley Brock live in Surrey, England. According to Dave
Coles 'Breeding Records this species, listed there as the Black-bellied Weaver,
was first bred in the UK by J. Henley in 1982.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.626767" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266139" page_num="53" year="" vol="">
THE BREEDING OF THE PIGEON GUILLEMOT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.309507" page_id="56266139"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
Cepphus columba AT LIVING COASTS
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.990245" page_id="56266139"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
53
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9714013" page_id="56266139"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
by Tony Durkin
This North American cousin of our native Black Guillemot C. grylle,
which it closely resembles, is a small (12in-Min (approx. 30cm-36cm) long)
rather beautiful seabird, that occurs extensively throughout the Bering Sea
and north Pacific Ocean, breeding as far south as California.
Pigeon Guillemot in breeding plumage.
The breeding plumage is predominantly black, with the lesser wing-
coverts, middle wing-coverts and tips of the greater coverts white, forming
a distinctive oval wing patch; however unlike the Black Guillemot the greater
coverts are partially black and this forms a diagnostic black wedge at the
lower edge (see photo above). The bird's mouthparts, legs and feet are
bright vermillion. In non-breeding plumage the Pigeon Guillemot has a
white head with dark flecking, the back is mottled and the underparts are
white. The juvenile resembles the non-breeding adult, but is more brownish.
Pigeon Guillemots nest colonially in rock cavities, rabbit burrows and
just occasionally on bridges and piers. They are mature at three to four
years of age, at which time a clutch of one to three eggs is laid, that is
incubated for an average of 28-32 days. The semi-precocial chicks, which
initially are covered in black down, are fledged at 35 days. Both parents
share the incubation of the eggs and rearing of the chicks.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996328" page_id="56266140"  page_num="54" year="" vol="">
54
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.911868" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266140" page_num="54" year="" vol="">
DURKIN - PIGEON GUILLEMOT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.91332568" page_id="56266140"  page_num="54" year="" vol="">
In 2003, at Paignton Zoo's Living Coasts at Torquay, Devon, a group of
13 Pigeon Guillemots, five Tufted Puffins Fratercula cirrhata and six Red-
legged Kittiwakes Rissa brevirostris , were introduced into the newly
constructed auk enclosure. This has a tall cliff rising above a seawater pool
4m deep x 3m wide x 20m long (approx. 13ft deep x 9ft 9in wide x 65ft
long). A wave machine and dump bucket (1 tonne (1 cubic metre) of water
Pigeon Guillemot in non-breeding plumage.
every two to three hours) are added features. The seawater first passes
through a filter which removes large particles, while leaving plankton, eggs
and tiny fry to pass through and develop in the pool and provide dietary
supplements and behavioural enrichment. The aviary is approximately 10m
wide x 25m long x 6m high (32ft wide x 82ft long x 20ft high). Each of the
20 nesting holes cut into the rockwork connects to a 40cm (1ft 3 3 Ain) length
of 14cm (5V2in) diameter plastic piping attached to a box 35cm x 35cm x
35cm (lft PAin x lft PAin x lft PAin). Constructed of marine plywood
and filled to a depth of 8cm (almost 3 ! Ain) with aquatic gravel, each box has
a small inspection hatch. The guillemots' diet consists of chopped sprats,
herrings, white bait and sand eels (when in season). Fish sprinkled with
vitamins are thrown to the birds during the first feed of the day. Some fish
are dropped into the water to provide 'hunting' enrichment.
In early 2004 several pairs were seen displaying. Copulation was
observed to take place on land two days before the first egg was laid on June
19th. Further observations were undertaken to ensure that the egg was being
incubated and, on July 17th, a small chick was seen peeping from the front
entrance. Fish was then placed at the mouth of the pipe to assist the parents,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.750119" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266141" page_num="55" year="" vol="">
DURKIN - PIGEON GUILLEMOT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994706" page_id="56266141"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
55
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.980159272727273" page_id="56266141"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
all of which was taken and by day 23, adults were seen carrying whole
sprats into the burrow. On August 6th the chick was receiving fish at the
entrance. On August 17th, the young bird which then weighed 438g
(compared to the adults which weighed about 480g), was ringed with a split
band and a coloured band. At 35 days the chick fledged and was watched
Pigeon Guillemot swimming.
diving and swimming with both parents calling loudly. It was first observed
feeding two days later.
The Pigeon Guillemot is seldom bred in captivity, indeed few specimens
are held in European collections, and this is almost certainly the first breeding
in the UK.
Bibliography
Gaston, A. J.and Jones, I. L. 1997. The Auks. Bird Families of the World. Oxford University
Press, Oxford, UK.
As described above, the Pigeon Guillemot Cepphus columba, has been
bred at Living Coasts. This is almost certainly the first breeding of this
species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who knows of a previous breeding
is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
In the Avicultural Magazine Vol.110, No. 1, pp. 36-37 (2004), Paul Boulden
described this new exhibit on the quayside overlooking Torbay, on the south
coast of England, and there was a photo of the enormous aviary of a striking,
modern design.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99221" page_id="56266142"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
56
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9863715" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266142" page_num="56" year="" vol="">
PRELIMINARY FINDINGS ON REPRODUCTION OF
CAPTIVE MARABOU STORKS Leptoptilos crumeniferus
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.654569" page_id="56266142"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
by C. W. Kuhar, L. M. Hernandez and K. Amos-Mongiello
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.933507" genericHeader="introduction" page_id="56266142" page_num="56" year="" vol="">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991771085714286" page_id="56266142"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
Despite being one of the most commonly held species of stork in zoos,
the Marabou Stork Leptoptilos crumeniferus is only rarely bred in captivity.
After several years during which there was little reproductive behaviour
and no successful hatchings, husbandry changes at Disney's Animal
Kingdom, Florida, USA, corresponded with the successful hatching of five
chicks between 2001-2002. Examination of daily reports revealed that
reproduction followed the addition of a large pool and the increase in flock
size to 10 birds. While reproductive success remained low overall, the
husbandry data suggest that parent-reared chicks grew more rapidly and
achieved higher adult weights than hand-reared chicks. Although the specific
causative factor associated with the production of chicks cannot be
detennined, these findings along with results from other institutions, suggest
that increasing flock size and providing an enhanced nesting environment,
may result in increased reproductive success.
Introduction
The Marabou Stork is one of the most commonly held storks in zoos
worldwide (Terkel, 1994). According to the 2002 studbook (Hejna, 2002),
the North American population consisted of 116 birds (57.55.4) in 41
institutions. Despite it occurring in large flocks in the wild, only 20% of
institutions house it in groups of three or more. Thus, the captive population
is spread across a large number of zoos in relatively small social groupings.
In addition to which the reproductive success of these birds in captivity is
quite low (Coulter et al. 1989). The first captive hatching of a Marabou
Stork in North America occurred at Busch Gardens in 1978. Since then,
only eight other North American institutions have successfully bred Marabou
Stork, resulting in 44 hatchings in 25 years (Hejna, 2002).
Despite relatively few successes breeding Marabou Storks, little research
has been undertaken to address the causes of reproductive failure. Although
a single study reported on successful reproduction in a zoo environment
(Terkel, 1994), most of the articles that shape the Marabou Stork Husbandry
Guidelines (van Benthem, 2002), come from field studies. Here we report
on changes made to the exhibit structure and flock dynamics that may have
contributed to breeding success in a Marabou Stork group. We document
events leading to successful reproduction of Marabou Stork in an effort to
enhance breeding of this commonly held species. In addition, information
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.437221" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266143" page_num="57" year="" vol="">
KUHAR ET AL - REPRODUCTION IN MARABOU STORK
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997032" page_id="56266143"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
57
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.993559" page_id="56266143"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
on chick development is provided to supplement existing infonnation on
the growth of hand-reared chicks.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.935739">
Methods
Subjects and background
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9900998" page_id="56266143"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
In 1998, eight (4.4) Marabou Storks were housed in the Savanna Overlook
Habitat (hereafter referred to simply as the Overlook) of Disney's Animal
Kingdom. In 1999, the birds began displaying courtship behaviours,
including stick carrying/passing, incubating rocks or lemons, showing
breeding colour, nest building and, mixed sex, as well as same sex, pairings.
During this time abandoned or destroyed eggs were found lying on the
ground, but eggs were never found in nests and no eggs survived. Although
pre-reproductive behaviour was noted, e.g. stick carrying and passing, it
was erratic and asynchronous as only a single bird, or pair of birds, exhibited
breeding behaviour at any time. The pre-reproductive behaviour was
unproductive as no successful hatchings occurred.
The exhibit
The Overlook habitat is a naturalistic exhibit, approximately 1.2 hectares
(3 acres) in size with chainlink fencing that separates it from other exhibit
areas. The middle of the Overlook is open with tall grasses. Dense brush
and trees line the sides, allowing the birds to hide or seek shade. Designed
originally as part of a larger savanna exhibit, the Overlook was partitioned
off to allow for better management of the Marabou flock, as well as other
animals on the savanna. It has therefore undergone several changes in order
to meet the husbandry needs of the birds in this habitat.
Exhibit changes
The separation of the Overlook from the main savanna resulted in a lack
of sufficient roosting opportunities and water sources for the birds, both of
which are recommended for maintaining Marabous in captivity (van
Benthem, 2002). Therefore, several platforms and deadfall were placed in
the exhibit to provide sturdy perching, roosting and nesting areas. In addition,
new sources of water were required to replace the pools and ponds that had
been available on the savanna. Four 15 gallon (approx. 56 litre) rubber tubs
were placed in the Overlook to provide water access, but these required
daily changing and it was thought that they did not provide sufficient water
to induce breeding behaviours.
Research from the field on Marabous has shown that they are found
mainly in open country in the vicinity of large lakes and rivers and that they
utilize wetlands during nesting periods and for feeding (Kahl, 1966).
Therefore, a 1m x 1.5m (approx. 3ft x 5ft) prefabricated plastic pond was
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995899" page_id="56266144"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
58
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.65051" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266144" page_num="58" year="" vol="">
KUHAR ET AL - REPRODUCTION IN MARABOU STORKS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9799075625" page_id="56266144"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
installed in November 2000 to determine if and how the storks would utilize
this larger, permanent water source. Rocks and deadfall were placed around
the pond after it was installed and anecdotal evidence suggested that the
storks immediately increased their use of the area. However, it appeared
that a few aggressive birds dominated the pool. Therefore, a larger, permanent
pool was planned to provide access for all group members.
Construction of the larger pool and filtration system began in August
2001 and the pool was completed three months later. The pool measures
7m x 10m (approx. 22ft x 32ft) with a gradual increase in depth to lm
(approx. 3ft 3in). Large pieces of deadfall were added around one edge of
the pool to provide additional nesting opportunities near the water. The
new pool is large enough to allow all birds simultaneous access. This has
prevented the elevated levels of territorial aggression seen around the
previous pool and provided appropriate nesting areas for all birds (see Table 1).
Table 1. Changes to the Overlook habitat and to the Marabou Stork group
structure that may have impacted on breeding success.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.972011956521739" page_id="56266144"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
Date
Event
November 20th 1998
4.4 moved to the Overlook.
February 28th 1999
Four nest platforms installed.
November 25th 2000
Temporary pond added.
January 1st 2001
1.0 moved to off-exhibit area for management purposes.
January 9th 2001
2.0 moved to off-exhibit area for management purposes.
January 17th 2001
1.0 reintroduced to flock.
August 17th 2001
Work begun on permanent pool.
September 24th 2001
1.0 reintroduced to flock.
November 24th 2001
Permanent pool completed.
March 24th 2002
0.1 moved to off-exhibit area for management purposes.
July 6th 2002
</figure>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.702676">
3.1 introduced into flock.
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9698187" page_id="56266144"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
Group structure changes
In addition to physical changes to the habitat, social manipulation of the
group occurred. Eight birds (4.4) were moved to the Overlook in November
1998. For management purposes, two males were removed from the flock
in January 2001 and housed in an off-exhibit area, leaving four females and
two males on the Overlook. Later, one of these males was exchanged with
a female from the Overlook, leaving three males and three females on the
Overlook and a male-female pair in off exhibit housing. In July 2002, two
juvenile males and the male-female pair from the off exhibit housing were
introduced into the group on the Overlook. This increased the flock size to
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.796949" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56266144" page_num="58" year="" vol="">
10 birds (6.4).
</sectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.437159" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266145" page_num="59" year="" vol="">
KUHAR ET AL - REPRODUCTION IN MARABOU STORKS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996464" page_id="56266145"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
59
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.992744291666666" page_id="56266145"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
Data collection and analysis
Information on habitat and group composition alterations was obtained
from the Daily Report System (DRS) at Disney's Animal Kingdom. Data
on specific reproductive events (e.g. egg laying, egg hatching, egg missing)
including pairings, defined as two birds which commonly moved together,
breeding behaviour and colour as recorded in keeper reports and egg lay
and hatch dates, were collected from a combination of DRS records and a
keeper logbook. Data on breeding colour were summarized by noting the
proportion of birds in the flock that were seen to have entered breeding
colour during each month. This notation did not indicate whether or not the
bird remained in breeding colour throughout the month, only that the bird
had entered breeding colour some time during that month.
Marabou Stork chicks.
As no weights had been recorded for captive bom parent-reared Marabou
chicks, four parent-reared chicks were weighed regularly prior to fledging.
Each chick was removed from the nest, placed in a bowl and weighed. The
bowl and chick were weighed on an Ohaus ES100L bench scale (Florham
Park, NJ). After being weighed the chicks were immediately returned to
their respective nests. Chicks were weighed daily for the first week and
once or twice per week after that, until capture became difficult, usually at
about 120-130 days of age. A single hand-reared chick was included in the
dataset to provide a contrast to parent-reared chicks. This chick was removed
from the incubator and weighed in a bowl as above. This chick was weighed
daily until it was three months of age, after which it was weighed weekly.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.904965">
Results
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9995574" page_id="56266145"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
The proportion of birds in breeding colour was plotted by month and
significant management events were overlaid to show the temporal
relationship between these events and an increase in breeding colour
synchrony (Fig. 1). These data show a slight peak in the proportion of birds
in breeding colour after the completion of the second, larger pool. All birds
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.990441" page_id="56266146"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
60
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.649886" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266146" page_num="60" year="" vol="">
KUHAR ET AL - REPRODUCTION IN MARABOU STORKS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997113230769231" page_id="56266146"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
were in breeding colour and eggs were found in nests for the first time
immediately following the introduction of the new birds.
Information on egg laying patterns is summarized in Table 2. It shows
that each nest usually contained three eggs (mean = 3.14; n = 7 nests) each
laid approximately three days apart. Only 25% of the eggs that were allowed
to remain on the nests hatched, with several going missing or being broken
during incubation. The mean incubation period was 33 days (range 32-35
days). Fig. 2 reveals an exponential increase in chick weights between one
and five weeks, with weights levelling off at 5 kg - 6 kg (approx. 11 lbs--
13lbs) after two months. These data also indicate that the hand-reared chick
weighed less than all parent-reared chicks at all measurement points after
one week, suggesting that parent-reared Marabou chicks grow faster and
reach a greater adult weight than hand-reared chicks.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.773385">
Table 2. Eggs laid during study period, presumed sire and dam, date each
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.980040987261146" page_id="56266146"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
egg was laid, date each egg hatched, plus any comments.
Nest
Egg
Sire
Dam
Laid
Hatched
Comments
l
1
L
BA
31/8/02
DNH
l
2
L
BA
3/9/02
5/10/02
l
3
L
BA
6/9/02
8/10/02
Pulled/DNS
2
4
NN
G
28/9/02
DNH
Missing
2
5
NN
G
1/10/02
2/11/02
2
6
NN
G
4/10/02
DNH
Missing
3
7
K
W
10/10/02
14/11/02
3
8
K
W
13/10/02
15/11/02
DNS
3
9
K
w
15/10/02
17/11/02
DNS
4
10
L
BA
24/6/03
DNH
Pulled/DNS
4
11
L
BA
27/6/03
DNH
4
12
L
BA
29/6/03
DNH
Pulled/DNS
4
13
L
BA
2/7/03
DNH
Pulled/DNS
5
14
NN
G
28/7/03
DNH
Missing
5
15
NN
G
31/7/03
DNH
5
16
NN
G
3/8/03
DNH
Broken
6
17
L
BA
29/8/03
DNH
6
18
L
BA
1/9/03
4/10/03
6
19
L
BA
4/9/03
DNH
7
20
NN
G
18/9/03
DNH
Missing
7
21
NN
G
20/9/03
DNH
7
22
NN
G
24/9/03
DNH
DNH = Egg did not hatch.
Broken = Egg broken during incubation period.
Missing = Egg went missing during incubation period.
Pulled = Egg removed to hand-rear chick.
DNS = Chick hatched but did not survive at least one week.
The mean incubation time for eggs that hatched was 32.9 days.
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.436186" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266147" page_num="61" year="" vol="">
KUHAR ET AL - REPRODUCTION IN MARABOU STORKS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997061" page_id="56266147"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
61
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.8912054">
Fig. 1. Proportion of birds in breeding colour by month and main
management changes. The changes relating to the pool involve the second,
larger pool.
Fig. 2. Growth curves for four parent-reared and one hand-reared chicks.
Days after hatching
</figureCaption>
<page confidence="0.994691" page_id="56266148"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
62
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.3665585" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266148" page_num="62" year="" vol="">
KUHAR ET AL - REPRODUCTION IN MARABOU STORKS
Discussion
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999150170731708" page_id="56266148"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
Terkel (1994) suggested several reasons for enhanced reproduction in a
captive group of Marabou Storks, these include access to nesting materials
and the introduction of new animals into the group. From the information
presented here, it is not clear which of these factors may have most influenced
increased breeding behaviour, but changes in both social structure and
environmental conditions resulted in numerous eggs and five successful
hatchings. While an increase in breeding behaviour followed completion of
the pool, breeding colour became synchronous for the first time immediately
after the introduction of the new birds and continued for several months.
The colours during this time were noted as being much brighter than before.
Previously, all birds had not shown breeding colour simultaneously.
The number of eggs laid and the success of those eggs increased
dramatically following completion of the pool and the introduction of new
birds. Prior to exhibit and group changes, no more than one egg in a nest
had ever been reported and eggs were often laid on the ground and time was
spent incubating rocks and lemons, a phenomenon also reported by Terkel
(1994). Following the manipulations, all pairs that produced eggs laid a
single egg in the nest every third day until there were three eggs in the nest,
a common Marabou pattern (Kahl, 1966; Terkel, 1994). These eggs were
guarded continuously by at least one but usually both members of the pair,
resulting in four parent-reared chicks. However, it should be noted that
overall hatching success remained relatively low.
Juvenile mortality of Marabous is high in the wild (Pomeroy, 1977) and
in captivity (Terkel, 1994; van Bentham, 2002) owing largely to interspecies
aggression. Parents in this study successfully hatched only 25% of the eggs.
Another 20% were destroyed or went missing, and one chick was removed
from the nest and hand-reared due to competition between pairs at the nest.
Our data suggest that Marabou chicks reach their adult weight of 5kg
(approx. 1 libs) at approximately 60 days. Parent-reared chicks may grow
faster and achieve a higher adult weight than do hand-reared chicks.
While the increase in flock size and improvement in nesting conditions
seem to have increased the breeding behaviours and subsequently the
reproductive success of the flock, we cannot determine the single factor
most responsible for this change. Pool construction corresponded with an
increase in reproductive activity in October 2001, but eggs were not reported
until April 2002. No birds were reported in breeding colour during May or
June 2002, but following the introduction of the new birds in June 2002, all
birds were reported in breeding colour for the next six months or so, a
phenomenon never before recorded in the flock. However, we cannot state
with certainty that the introduction of the new birds caused this. The birds
in the flock were fairly young and we cannot discount the possibly that
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.437201" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266149" page_num="63" year="" vol="">
KUHAR ET AL - REPRODUCTION IN MARABOU STORKS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998838" page_id="56266149"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
63
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.990962909090909" page_id="56266149"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
several reached reproductive maturity in late summer 2002. This may have
stimulated more breeding colour and more reproductive behaviour, resulting
in successful reproduction. In addition, we cannot separate the effects of
stimulation from the new birds and improvement of the habitat with the
construction of the pool and the provision of larger amounts of deadfall for
nesting. It may have been the combined effects of these factors that produced
successful reproduction in these birds. However, given the results of Terkel
(1994) and these findings, we recommend larger flock sizes and more
appropriate housing conditions, that include a large area of water and plentiful
nesting materials, to improve the reproductive success of the Marabou Stork
in captivity.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.848338" genericHeader="references" page_id="56266149" page_num="63" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.960414333333333" page_id="56266149"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
Coulter, M.C., Balzano, S., Johnson, R.D., King, C.E., Shannon, P.W. 1989. Conservation
and captive management of storks. Savannah River Ecology Laboratory, Aitken, SC, USA.
Hejna, R., 2002. AZA North American Regional Studbook for Marabou Stork (Leptoptilos
crumeniferus). Disney's Animal Kingdom, Lake Buena Vista, FL, USA.
Kahl, M.P., 1966. A contribution to the ecology and reproductive biology of the Marabou
Stork ( Leptoptilos crumenferus ) in East Africa. Journal of Zoology 148:289-311.
Pomeroy, D.E., 1977. Marabou Stork, Leptoptilos crumeniferus , breeding colonies in Uganda.
Journal of the East African Natural History Society and National Museum 31:1-11.
Terkel, A., 1994. Breeding the Marabou Stork ( Leptoptilos crumeniferus) at the Zoological
Center Tel Aviv and Noorder Zoo, Emmen. International Zoo Yearbook 33:55-62.
van Benthem, J., 2002. Marabou Stork Husbandry Guidelines. EAZA Ciconiiformes/
Phoenicopteriformes TAG, Rotterdam, The Netherlands.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.872873" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56266149" page_num="63" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.889574333333333" page_id="56266149"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
We thank Robert Hejna for her assistance with historical records and
population numbers for Marabou Storks in North America. We also thank
Walter Dupree for his support and assistance with the manuscript.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.9728884">
Christopher W. Kuhar, PhD, Research Fellow, Disney's Animal Kingdom,
PO. Box 10000, Lake Buena Vista, Florida 32830-1000, USA. Tel:(+1) 407
938 3205/Fax:(+1) 407 9381982/E-mail: Chris.x.Kuhar-ND@Disney.com
L. M. Hernandez and K. Amos-Mongiello, Disney s Animal Kingdom, Lake
Buena Vista, Florida, USA.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.997674" page_id="56266150"  page_num="64" year="" vol="">
64
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993162" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266150" page_num="64" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE SOOTY GRASSQUIT Tiaris fuliginosa,
WITH SOME OBSERVATIONS ON COMPARATIVE
BEHAVIOUR
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986530405405405" page_id="56266150"  page_num="64" year="" vol="">
by Robin Restall
Tiaris grassquits are small, tanager-finches that occur in Central and
South America and throughout the islands of the Caribbean. They vary in
size from that of a typical estrildid waxbill to that of a modem domesticated
Zebra Finch Tceniopygia guttata castanotis. The most brightly coloured
and best known in aviculture is the Cuban Grassquit T. canora , which can
probably be regarded as semi-domesticated and which has a tenuous hold in
aviaries from Canada to Australia. Less well-known in captivity and slightly
less well-coloured is the Yellow-faced Grassquit T. olivacea from Central
America and the Caribbean. Both these species are to be found in avicultural
handbooks. Then comes the comparatively poorly-coloured Black-faced
Grassquit T. bicolor , from the Caribbean and northern South America, which
I have written about several times.
The remaining two grassquits are the Dull-coloured T. obscura and the
Sooty Grassquit T. fuliginosa. Both are circum-Amazonia in distribution.
The Dull-coloured Grassquit is aptly named and to the best of my knowledge
has never been represented in aviculture. The adult male Sooty Grassquit is
almost entirely black and the female is dull olive-green. Its inclusion by
Armani in his guide to seedeaters for aviculturists (1985) implies that it has
previously occurred in aviculture, but I know of no published account. Here
in northern Venezuela we have the latter three species. I have been fortunate
in being able to acquire a few specimens of two subspecies of the Sooty
Grassquit. I have acquired them for scientific study and the purpose of this
paper is to describe my experiences so far, in attempting to breed the coastal
subspecies, T. fuliginosa fumosa (see photo p.66).
In October 2003, towards the end of the rainy season, I was brought a
trio of dark, olive-green grassquits. These birds were distinguished by having
a bicoloured bill, the upper mandible being dark fuscous and the lower
mandible being lighter, horn-coloured (see lower photo p66.). The man
who brought them, a competent ornithologist and Head of the Veterinary
Faculty at the local university was, because of their bicoloured bill, certain
they were Dull-coloured Grassquits. This was subsequently confirmed by
the Director of the Phelps Ornithological Collection. I accepted the
bicoloured bill diagnosis, but remained concerned by the fact that the birds
were a richer somewhat lustrous olive-green than I knew the Dull-coloured
Grassquit to be; they were also a little larger. I placed the three in a Terenzani
breeding cage and over the following months systemically offered them a
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.70098" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266151" page_num="65" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SOOTY GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99816" page_id="56266151"  page_num="65" year="" vol="">
65
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999159785714286" page_id="56266151"  page_num="65" year="" vol="">
variety of foods. By March 2004, it was obvious that two of the birds were
moulting into a rich, sooty black on the face and breast and their bills were
darkening and losing their bicoloration, which was fading. They were
undoubtably two males and a female Sooty Grassquit.
The first breeding attempt
I removed one male and placed him in another cage on his own, leaving
the original cage containing just one bird of each sex. I hung a canary
plastic nest-box (see photos pp. 67 &amp; 68) on the outside of the cage, over
the open door and placed a small handful of soft straws, grasses and coconut
fibre twisted around inside it. Using soft grass stems, Haris grassquits
make a large rounded ball of a nest, and it seemed logical they would accept
what I had provided for them. On May 6th, I noticed that every time I
placed additional coconut fibre in the cage, it was being taken to the nest the
moment I left the laboratory. I contrived to watch from a concealed position.
Both birds were collecting the new lot of fibre, quite excitedly, and would
jump into the nest with the fibre, sit and turn, adjust and wriggle a little and
then pop out to get more. In this way, they completely filled the nest-box
and I had to trim or tuck in stray strands in order to be able to remove the
nest-box and examine the contents. Otherwise it would have become
entangled with the cage front and prevented nest inspection. This I did
routinely every morning.
During the nest building process, the male would frequently flicker his
wings in a begging-like movement and sing vigorously at the female, showing
his reddish-pink gape as he did so. She gave a low-intensity solicitation,
but the male did not respond. On May 8th I noted that the courtship display
appeared to be a modified version of the fluttering, parachute display of the
Black-faced and Yellow-faced Grassquits, as the bird never left the perch.
This might have been due to the limitations imposed by the size of the cage
of course, but it seems to be constant. I have now seen it many times. He
follows her and turns to face her as she flies past. All the while his bill is
wide open, showing the reddish-pink gape, and he utters his short song,
u trzzizizizt ",very like that of the male Black-faced Grassquit.
The first egg appeared early on the morning of May 9th. It was whitish-
grey, evenly speckled with maroons, greys and other subtle, cryptic tones.
The second egg was laid the following morning, after which the female
began brooding. On the morning of May 11th a third egg had been laid.
From my observation point, I saw the female leave the nest, presumably to
eat and drink. The male displayed furiously at her, he fanned his tail very
wide, his wings extremely wide, and his gape was wide open. I could not
hear, but the open gape suggested he had uttered a burst of song. The female
returned to the nest very quickly. This sequence occurred again a couple of
hours later and I suspect happened every time she left the nest. The male
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.980384" page_id="56266152"  page_num="66" year="" vol="">
66
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.883666" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266152" page_num="66" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SOOTY GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.903352333333333" page_id="56266152"  page_num="66" year="" vol="">
was then quite defensive of the nest. Any bird that entered the laboratory
from the aviary, and which then perched on the nest, the bath, or the wire of
the cage was flown at fiercely, causing it to retreat at once.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.48996" page_id="56266152"  page_num="66" year="" vol="">
Adult male Sooty Grassquit.
Lorenzo Calcano
Juvenile Sooty Grassquit.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.666551" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266153" page_num="67" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SOOTY GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.937617" page_id="56266153"  page_num="67" year="" vol="">
67
</page>
<table confidence="0.542943" page_id="56266153"  page_num="67" year="" vol="">
Clutch of Sooty Grassquit eggs.
Sooty Grassquit nestling 26 hours after hatching.
</table>
<page confidence="0.998146" page_id="56266154"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
68
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.91215" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266154" page_num="68" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SOOTY GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999339055555555" page_id="56266154"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
They seemed to follow the typical Neotropical finch breeding pattern,
that is, laying a clutch of three eggs but starting to brood following the
laying of the second egg. Thus the third chick is a day younger, behind the
other two and will be first to die in the event of a food shortage.
Cage in which Sooty Grassquits bred.
During the feeding trials earlier, all three birds had taken only dry seed
and ignored all greenfood, softfood and mealworms. At that stage I tried
them with defrosted petits pois (small fresh green peas) and they took them
eagerly. I returned on May 19th, after an absence of a few days, to discover
that the birds had continued to add to the nest every scrap of straw and
coconut fibre they could find in the cage. During this nest-building surge
they had also rearranged the material within the nest and in doing so had
buried the eggs. I uncovered the eggs, tidied the nest and removed loose
nesting material from the cage. Although the female spent a lot of time in
the nest, I reluctantly came to the conclusion that she was no longer brooding
the eggs. By May 22nd one had been broken and the nest had obviously
been deserted. The remaining two eggs - the first of this species to be
collected - are now in the Phelps Collection.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700801" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266155" page_num="69" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SOOTY GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997704" page_id="56266155"  page_num="69" year="" vol="">
69
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998017904761905" page_id="56266155"  page_num="69" year="" vol="">
The second attempt
On May 23rd I removed a substantial amount of material from the nest,
leaving a 'starter lining', and placed fresh material in the cage. By the
morning of May 25th, the nest had been re-lined beautifully and far more
completely than had been the first one, and it contained one egg. It was
almost white, with very faint markings. A second egg appeared on the 27th,
which was very heavily marked with a distinct halo around the larger end. I
do not know if the female began to brood that day, but she was definitely
brooding on the 28th. The inspection on the 29th revealed four eggs. On
subsequent days I repeatedly found one egg in a vertical position and by
June 5th, this egg was firmly buried beneath the other three, which lay neatly
together (see photo p. 67). June 8th was the 11th day and there was still no
sign of the eggs hatching. Meanwhile, the male was finding nesting material
and taking it to the nest while the female continued to brood. He was using
the seeding heads of grasses I supplied daily to all the finches. He continued
to sing vehemently, albeit briefly, whenever the female left the nest.
On June 10th I looked into the nest and saw just two eggs. I immediately
thought that she had decided they were clear and had started to throw them
out. Therefore, I thought it would be a good time to clean out the cage. As
I started to pull out the far tray, I saw eggshell on the floor, with a chick
struggling to get out of it. Obviously what had happened was that the chick
had been struggling to get out of the shell and the female had removed the
shell from the nest with the chick stuck to it. I wanned the chick by breathing
on it, then put it back in the nest alongside the two eggs. The incubation
period appeared to be 13 or 14 days. This is dramatically longer than that of
Sporophila seedeaters and the Volatinia grassquit, and much more like that
of Palearctic species.
Later that day the nestling, which had obviously been fed and brooded,
was begging strongly. Its gape was bright reddish-orange, paler and more
yellowish at the edges. The same time the following day the nestling appeared
to have doubled in size. The photo on p. 67 shows it 26 hours after it hatched.
By the sixth day it was growing well and seemed typical for a chick of its
age when thinking of a Palearctic finch, but was way behind what a
Sporophila or Volatinia chick would have looked like at that age. On June
18th the nestling was eight days old and still effectively naked, with dark
coloured skin. There was certainly nothing precocious about it. It was fat
and heavy and obviously being fed well. The male was singing and carrying
material to the nest, but not covering the nestling. The previous day I had
given the birds a bundle of Guinea Grass Panicum maximum heads but instead
of being eaten, they were being taken into the nest. The increase in green
and unripe seeds incorporated into the nest can clearly be seen in the photo
on p. 70 taken when the nestling was 14 days old.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.993129" page_id="56266156"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
70
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.905977" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266156" page_num="70" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SOOTY GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998013578947369" page_id="56266156"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
By June 24th there had been quite a transformation in the nestling, the
feathers had emerged from their sheaths and the wings had filled-out (see
photo below). When I removed the nest from the cage in order to photograph
the nestling, it hunkered down in the nest as low as possible, and remained
immobile all the while. The parents showed no sign of distress or anxiety
and the female returned to the nest a few minutes after I left the laboratory.
To date, the birds have totally ignored baby mealworms and the seeding
heads of Guinea Grass - except to use the latter to add to the nest. They take
Sooty Grassquit nestling at 14 days.
a little of my softfood/nutrition granules/rearing food mix and also defrosted
petits pois I give almost every day. It appeared that the chick was being
reared almost totally on dry seeds.
On the morning of the 25th, I found the chick dead. It seemed to have
been in perfect condition. Its lower stomach was bloated, but I think this
was caused by bacterial action following its death. The cloaca was perfectly
clean. Moreover, the crop was full, so it had been fed.
The chick appeared to have become wedged between part of the nest,
the side of the nest-box and the bars of the cage. I concluded that it had
been trying to get out of the nest, to fledge, and became trapped.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700208" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266157" page_num="71" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SOOTY GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994904" page_id="56266157"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
71
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.4657105">
Maria Carmen Rodriguez
Female Black-faced Grassquit feeding nestlings.
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9843279375" page_id="56266157"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
The third attempt
I cleaned up the nest a bit, removing just stray strands etc. It was
noteworthy that there was not a single dried dropping in the nest. An hour
later I could hear the male singing. As I watched through the aviary window,
the female was inside the nest and the male was flying back and forth, up to
the nest and back to the far perch. He was performing a whirring, 'helicopter
flight', slowly, all the while singing fiercely. The female left the nest and
the male sat and watched as she collected a strand of grass and took it to the
nest, whereupon he started singing and performing the display flight again
(see drawing p.72). This display flight is very similar to the display flights
of the Black-faced and Yellow-faced Grassquit.
To my surprise, the very next day, June 26th, there was an egg. This
time I marked the egg with a black dot, so that I would be able to identify it
later. I later watched the male 'helicoptering' up into the nest, a moment
after the female had left it. Ten seconds later he 'helicoptered' out of the
nest. Half a minute after that he 'helicoptered' over to the female and perched
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996466" page_id="56266158"  page_num="72" year="" vol="">
72
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.910309" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266158" page_num="72" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SOOTY GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98986896" page_id="56266158"  page_num="72" year="" vol="">
beside her, whirring his wings. She started to respond and they mated twice.
There was a good, steady and purposeful contact. He again performed a
hovering &apos;helicopter flight' as she left and went to the floor to forage. A
second egg appeared on the 28th and this was subsequently marked with
two black dots. A third egg appeared the next day. The following day an
egg was found broken on the cage floor, and the following day the nest was
empty.
For the next six months the birds showed no interest in the nest, then on
New Year's Day 2005, they began building in earnest. The rainy season
was unusually prolonged, it normally ends in November, but this year
continued through to March, stimulating birds to breed all along the Northern
Cordillera, the coastal mountain range within which lies Caracas. The birds
in the laboratory (which has a partly open roof to let in sunshine and rain)
and the adjoining aviary were no exception and several pairs nested at this
time. Disaster struck during my absence on a short trip, during which the
male grassquit appeared to have attacked the female and inficted a bad,
open wound, on a her back. She died the next day.
Future possibilities
I now (early June 2005) have two fit adult males, each of which is singing
in its cage, and each of which has built a nest. I am unlikely to be able to get
a female or fresh juveniles until October, the month when the trappers are
active and this species might just appear in the local trade. There is a positive
and encouraging note to end this story. I also have a pair of Sooty Grassquits
of another subspecies, T. f zuliae. These birds are browner and duller when
compared to If. fumosa. They were brought to me from Merida, a small
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.70095" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266159" page_num="73" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SOOTY GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998458" page_id="56266159"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
73
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.990807780487805" page_id="56266159"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
city in the Andes, to the south-west. This pair is in the aviary. The male is
very bold and often sings from prominent perches. The female sits about a
lot and does not appear to be nest building. However, a wicker basket in a
Ficus shrub is having coconut fibre placed inside, and it seems as so the
male has chosen it for the nest, and is working at enthusing the female. The
rainy season started a couple of weeks ago, and on past experience I am
expecting the female to come into breeding condition within a couple of
weeks.
Could Bengalese have helped?
For a few years I kept a stud of Bengalese. It was maintained purely as
a strategic reserve in the event of the Haris grassquits failing in a breeding
attempt. However, the Bengalese proved to be inappropriate foster parents
for Neotropical finches and were disposed of.
Haris grassquits build a domed, covered-over nest, very similar to that
of many estrildid finches, particularly Lonchura munias. I had reasoned
that the Bengalese would not only hatch the eggs, but also feed and rear the
chicks. The support for this reasoning was a report from Puerto Rico that
the feral Pin-tailed Whydahs Vidua macroura there had used the Black-
faced Grassquit as a host species. The Common Waxbill Estrilda astrild
which also exists as a feral species on Puerto Rico is a natural host species
for this whydah, so the use of the Black-faced Grassquit would be unusual.
A distinguishing behaviour of estrildid finches and the brood-parasitic
whydahs, is that the nestlings beg with a sideways, twisting motion,
presumably evolved to deal with the cramped space in the enclosed nest. I
had previously exchanged clutches of eggs between a pair of canaries and a
pair of Bengalese to explore the extent to which each might be used for
fostering Neotropical finches. Both clutches were brooded and the eggs
hatched, but both sets of nestlings died on the second day. The canaries
were unable to feed nestlings that turned and twisted their necks as they
begged and similarly, the Bengalese had been confused by nestlings that
stretched straight up when begging in the nest. It followed that if the report
from Puerto Rico was true, then the implication was that Haris grassquit
nestlings also begged with a sideways twisting motion. To test the Puerto
Rico story, I took a clutch of Black-faced Grassquit eggs and placed them in
the Bengalese nest. They hatched, but the nestlings died on the second day,
just as the canaries had. I subsequently placed some small nestlings in a
nest of Bengalese, but they were left to die after several failed attempts to
feed them by the confused Bengalese.
I alerted some bird photographer friends on Puerto Rico and eventually
received an entire series of photographs of Black-faced Grassquits breeding
in a garden site. The grassquit nestlings begged by reaching almost straight
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997958" page_id="56266160"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
74
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.912747" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266160" page_num="74" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - SOOTY GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998655" page_id="56266160"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
up, leaning just slightly, as they pointed at the entrance to the nest. The
adult grassquit feeding them did not enter the nest, as would an estrildid
adult, but perched at the entrance and fed the nestlings there (see photo
p.71). It is interesting to note that this entrance-perching by the visiting
adults, wears to opening into a larger hole than it was when the nest is first
built and eggs are being brooded. With hindsight, this was evident with the
nest of my Sooty Grassquits.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.892875" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56266160" page_num="74" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970397" page_id="56266160"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
Thanks particularly to Lorenzo Calcano for use of the photograph of the
juvenile Sooty Grassquit and to Maria Carmen Rodriguez for the photograph
of the female Black-faced Grassquit at the nest.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.868841" genericHeader="references" page_id="56266160" page_num="74" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.972231" page_id="56266160"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
Armani, G.C. 1985. Guide despassereaux granivores. Emberizines. Boubee, Paris.
Restall, R.L. 1976. The Black-faced Grassquit, Tiaris bicolor. AviculturalMagazine 82,3:151-
159.
Restall, R.L. 2003. Breeding the Black-faced Grassquit Tiaris bicolor omissa, with some
notes on behaviour. Avicultural Magazine 109,4:174-179.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.926828333333333" page_id="56266160"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
Robin Restall, Research Associate , Phelps Ornithological Collection,
Caracas, Venezuela. E-mail:Restall@cantv.net
* * M"
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.944599" genericHeader="references" page_id="56266160" page_num="74" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.96326825" page_id="56266160"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
The society has a large stock of back Issues mostly from 1935 onwards
but there are also some earlier issues still available. They are priced #3.00
each (including p&amp;p). Please check availability before placing an order.
Overseas members may be able to pay by credit card through a Paypal
invoice, but this service is not available in all countries. All enquiries should
be addressed to: R Boulden, Hon. Secretary/Treasurer, Avicultural Society,
Arcadia, The Mounts, East Allington, Totnes, Devon TQ9 7JQ, UK or
E-mail: admin@avisoc.co.uk
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994635" page_id="56266161"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
75
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.957924" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266161" page_num="75" year="" vol="">
NOTES ON THE GREAT SPARROW Passer montitensis
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.828798375" page_id="56266161"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
by Neville Brickell
Introduction
The Great Sparrow tends to be treated now as a separate distinct species
endemic to south-west Africa (see Sinclair &amp; Ryan, 2003). They describe
the 'Rufous Sparrows', i.e. the Great Sparrow, Kenya Rufous Sparrow P
rufocinctus , Shelley's Rufous Sparrow P. shelleyi, Kordofan Rufous Sparrow
P. cordofanicus and Socotra Sparrow P insularis, as a complex of closely
related sparrows with largely non-overlapping ranges. Clement et ah (1993)
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.89545">
Neville Brickell
Male Great Sparrow
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.974703333333333" page_id="56266161"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
treated rufocinctus , shelleyi , cordofanicus and insularis as racial variations
(subspecies) of P montitensis , which they called the Rufous Sparrow, though
acknowledging that it is known as the Great Sparrow in South Africa.
None of the above have ever been popular aviary subjects and colleagues
have kept the Great Sparrow solely in the hope of acquiring additional
information about its breeding biology, which to date has still to be fully
recorded.
Description
Length about 15cm (6in). The male's forehead, crown and hind neck/
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.988095" page_id="56266162"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
76
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.85939" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266162" page_num="76" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - GREAT SPARROW
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.95076844" page_id="56266162"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
upper mantle are grey. The chin, throat and lores are black, the sides of the
face, breast and belly are white, shading to pale grey in places (see photo).
The back is chestnut, streaked with black and the rump is also chestnut,
readily distinguishing the Great Sparrow from the slightly smaller House
Sparrow P. domesticus, which has a grey rump. The median coverts are
broadly tipped with white and fonn a short, white wing-bar; most of the
other wing feathers (and tail feathers) are dark brown to black, edged with
chestnut or buff. The bill is black in the breeding season, brown or brownish-
horn at other times. The legs and feet are brown or reddish brown. The
female is similar, though notably paler. The juvenile is similar to the adult
female, with young males showing an ill-defined blackish bib.
Voice
Decribed by Maclean (1993) as having harsh twittering "chreep cheep"
and "chirititif ' call notes and a song almost indistinguishable from that of
the House Sparrow. Described by Sinclair &amp; Ryan (2003) as "cheereep,
cheereeu", similar to that of the House Sparrow.
Behaviour
Solitary or in pairs, though small groups may congregate to drink at
waterholes. Not as sociable as other members of the family.
Distribution
Southern Angola, particularly the south-west, much of Namibia and
Botswana, south-west Zimbabwe and parts of northern South Africa.
Habitat
Semi-arid acacia woodland. Not usually associated with human
habitations.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.413122">
Status
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.784712" page_id="56266162"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
Varies from locally common to an uncommon or rare resident or nomad.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.612459">
Feeding
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997835666666667" page_id="56266162"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
Its feeding habits have not been studied in detail and remain poorly
known. It has been seen consuming the seeds of indigenous grasses, weeds,
shrubs and trees. It also visits the Lucky Bean Tree Erythrina lysistemon
for the nectar found in its 6cm (272in) long bright scarlet flowers. This tree
grows with pleasing effect along the streets of a number of South African
towns. It also consumes grain in fanning regions and there is a record of it
taking mealie pap (porridge) at a feeding table. In captivity it has been
observed taking both mound and alate (flying) tennites and mealwonns.
Birds held in the aviary of the ARU (Avicultural Research Unit) consumed
dried seeds of living grasses namely Guinea Grass Panicum maximum , Blue-
seed Grass Tricholaena monachne and Bur-bristle Grass Setaria verticillata,
purposely grown for Kurrichane Buttonquail Turnix sylvaticus.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.583169" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266163" page_num="77" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - GREAT SPARROW
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.993799" page_id="56266163"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
77
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.97285248" page_id="56266163"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
Breeding
It lays mainly in September-Novcrnber in the east of its range and in
January March in Namibia. It usually nests in a lone-standing and densely
branched thorny tree, particularly favouring a Scented Thom Acacia nilotica
or Umbrella Thom A, tortilis, in which it builds about 2m-5m (approx. 6ft
6in 16ft 6in) above the ground in the uppermost branches (Tarboton, 2001).
There is a record of a nest which measured 24cm high x 37cm long x 30cm
wide (approx. 9 l hm high x 147:in long x 12in wide). The blades and stems
of various grasses are used to make the nest, which is then lined with finer
grasses and feathers. The leaves of an Asparagus sp , locally known as
Katdoring, may also be used. The spout-like side entrance can measure
i 5cm 20cm (approx.6in-8in) in length and 6cm (approx. 2 1 Ain) in diameter.
Nests may or may not have a Nock's nest'. A clutch usually consists of four
or five eggs but can consist of as few as two and sometimes as many as six
have been recorded. They are white, spotted and blotched with slate grey
and lavender. The incubation and nestling periods in the wild remain
unrecorded. An incubation period of 15 days and a nestling period of 21
days have been recorded in captivity. The nest was constmcted on a cross
beam which secured the roof of the sleeping quarters to the aviary. It was
made of Guinea Grass and had inner walls of dried Chickweed Stellaria
media and Common Blackjack Bidenspilosa and was lined with feathers of
15 different species, mostly doves, quail and weavers, also living in the
aviary. Both sexes incubated the eggs, but with the female doing more of
the incubation and also playing the greater role in feeding the young.
The Great Sparrow is monogamous. Its nest may be parasitized by the
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.739828">
Diederik Cuckoo Chrysococcyx caprius.
Housing
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994332333333333" page_id="56266163"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
Prior to breeding, birds were transferred from the aviary of the ARU to
the aviary of the Indigenous Bird Breeder's Research Group, whose aviary
measures about one-third of the size of a standard tennis court.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.957655" genericHeader="references" page_id="56266163" page_num="77" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.9971163">
Brickell, C. (Ed.-in-Chief). 1996. A-Z Encyclopedia of Garden Plants. Dorling Kindersley,
London.
Clement, R, Harris, A. and Davis, J. 1993. Finches and Sparrows. A &amp; C Black, London.
Maclean, G. L. 1993. Roberts' Birds of Southern Africa. John Voelcker Bird Book Fund, Cape
Town.
Sinclair, I. and Ryan, R 2003. Birds of Africa south of the Sahara. Struik Publishers, Cape
Town.
Tarboton, W. 2001. A guide to the Nests &amp; Eggs of Southern African Birds. Struik Publishers
(Pty) Ltd., Cape Town.
Neville Brickell lives in Durban, KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.996705" page_id="56266164"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
78
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.767636" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266164" page_num="78" year="" vol="">
SOME PERSONAL OBSERVATIONS ON BIRD BOOKS
by Derek Goodwin
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998557631578947" page_id="56266164"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
When I was nine or 10 I was given three bird books for my birthday.
One I cannot recall at all. The second was remarkable for its rather poor
colour plates, though not so poor, I now realise, as were my efforts to paint
birds, which took up much of my spare time from when I was four years old
until I was 14. The third book was Frank Finn's Talks About Birds , which
enthralled me with its wealth of information about everyday birds. Still, at
the age of 85,1 enjoy re-reading it and, like its author, appreciate the interest
and beauty of common birds as much as that of rarities.
Often books, articles and letters written prior to about 1970 and especially
prior to about 1940, are I feel more interesting to read, though not usually so
well illustrated as many of the books published in recent decades which
often put emphasis on identification and on political correctness both in an
ornithological and in a more general sense.
Most, if not all books and other publications are apt to contain a few
errors and my own are no exception. For example in my first book (Goodwin,
1961) I instanced the normal coloured Budgerigar Melopsittacus undulatus
as a species which was well camouflaged when in trees in leaf, or on grassy
ground. When in 1965, I saw wild Budgerigars in Australia, I found that
they, and other predominately bright green parrots, were very conspicuous
against the duller green foliage of most Australian trees in the dry interior,
and especially so when they fed on bare, often reddish, soil between scattered
dry clumps of Spinifex grass and other ground herbage.
More reprehensible is when writers deliberately make statements which
they know to be false in order to deceive. As, for example when bygone
writers claimed to have seen tree-nesting ducks carry their young down
from the nest hole or Passenger Pigeons Ectopistes migratorius display in
the same manner as Rock Columba livia or domestic pigeons or when modem
"experts" claim that, unlike the introduced Mink Mustela lutreola , the Otter
Lutra lutra is friendly towards aquatic birds, when in fact Otters habitually
kill them. Or that, unlike the "cruel" and "wicked" Magpie Pica pica , the
Sparrowhawk Accipiter nisus has "developed" a bill to enable it to kill its
prey instantly. In fact, like other species of the genus Accipiter , the
Sparrowhawk holds its head and bill well up and away from the stmggling
prey which it then proceeds to stab repeatedly with its talons with a quick
trampling-like action in which the feet appear to shift positions, in turn.
This may result in a quick death even for largish birds but often does not.
In any case, as soon as the prey can no longer struggle violently, the
Sparrowhawk begins to pluck and eat it, often while it is still alive. Especially
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.864559" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266165" page_num="79" year="" vol="">
GOODWIN - BIRD BOOKS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99723" page_id="56266165"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
79
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998499928571429" page_id="56266165"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
if the prey is a full-size Wood Pigeon Columba palumbus , which she cannot
carry to a spot where she is screened from above or behind, but yet can
make a quick get-away, she is in danger of being killed herself if Goshawks
A. gentilis are in the area and if, as where I live now they mercifully are not,
of being robbed of her prey. In any area to which the public have access, so
have their dogs and it will not usually be many minutes before one of these
most numerous of all large predators has robbed the hawk of her prey.
Where neither dogs or Goshawks are present (as in my garden and many
others), Foxes Vulpes vulpes , cats, other birds of prey and even crows may
deprive the Sparrowhawk of her prey. Only a few months ago, a hen
Sparrowhawk flew low across my garden, flipped over the fence into my
neighbour's garden and caught a feral pigeon which she dragged towards
the shelter of some shrubs only to be robbed by a cat which had been lurking
there. However before the cat had got far with her booty a Fox came running
up, took the still flapping pigeon from the cat and ran off with it.
Of course neither of the above strictures apply to books which were
written long before the facts became widely known in ornithological circles.
Glaring as some of the errors in the works, or translations of them, may
seem to us, the writings of Aristotle, Pliny, Chaucer, Shakespeare and
Goldsmith are well worth reading and show that much of our apparent
discoveries from about 1880 onwards have been in the nature of "re-inventing
the wheel" if with a few modem improvements and clarifications. I have,
incidentally had to rely on Frank Finn and Stresemann for my knowledge of
what Aristotle and Pliny wrote. Although in some cases it is unwise to rely
on second-hand accounts of what someone has written (of which more anon),
I do not think this is ever the case with Frank Finn's or Prof. Erwin
Stresemann's publications.
I was, incidentally, amused on re-reading Frank Finn's Bird Behaviour
to see that he was well aware of my discovery (as I thought) that pigeons
must get some stomatic pleasure or otherwise from their food and are not
able to detect this by scent or taste when it is held in the bill. At least not
when dealing with such foods as grain, peanuts, bread etc. They can detect
water contaminated by oil and Fox urine.
There is one thing I can, from experience warn everyone against. That
is assuming that all statements emanating from standard works and from
eminent and high-ranking people are bound to be correct. This is far from
the case.
Writers of books on birds often have to rely in part on statements of
others and often are unable to check on the origins where the books they
need to consult are not easily available. Also human beings, like our relative
the Chimpanzee Pan troglodytes and the Wolf Canis lupus which some
animal behaviourists think, wrongly in my opinion, is more affectionate
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.991657" page_id="56266166"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
80
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.965679" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266166" page_num="80" year="" vol="">
GOODWIN - BIRD BOOKS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99905388372093" page_id="56266166"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
and morally superior to doves and has passed this moral superiority to its
domestic derivative the dog, instinctively tend to follow, appease, emulate
and fawn upon the dominant individuals in their own social group, pack or
nation and thus much error is perpetuated.
Look how long after it had been disproved by competent aviculturists
and field observers (Meade-Waldo, 1897 &amp; 1906; St Quentin, 1905) it was
stated that sandgrouse did not bring water to their young in their plumage
but gave them food and water from the crop like pigeons. Even in spite of
contrary statements (Maclean, 1967 &amp; pers. com.; del Hoyo et al. 1997) one
sees the statement that pigeons are the only birds that can suck up water
without raising the head at each mouthful, and/or that pigeons always take
only one such drink at each visit to water, neither of which statement is
correct, as I pointed out in some detail (Goodwin, 1965).
Audubon's accounts of his adventures and misadventures are well worth
reading but like many observers since he, to put the kindest interpretation
on it, sometimes failed to differentiate between what he had observed and
what he thought ought to happen. While his very un-lifelike paintings of
birds are still valued more highly than very much more lifelike and therefore,
in my opinion much more beautiful, depictions of birds created before and
since, from the wall pictures of some ancient Egyptian tombs that I have
seen, to the superb and beautiful work of such modem bird artists as the late
Dietrich Bomhalm, Hilary Bum, Trevor Corbett, John Cox, Robert Gillmor,
Lars Jonsson and several others.
Writers are quite often misquoted. For most readers and many writers it
may be impossible for them to look up the original writer's work and find
out if he or she really wrote what they are claimed to have done. In one
volume I read, to my surprise, that I had recorded for the Red Avadavat
Amandava amandava some behaviour (citing my 1960 article on this species
and the Goldbreast A. subflava in our magazine) which I could not recall
having ever seen from this species, let alone had published, though I did
remember I had seen it in one or more of the three species of cordon-bleus
Uraeginthus spp. that I had kept. However, on checking my article I found
I had not said what was claimed, though I certainly had, as I knew, recorded
it of cordon-bleus. Evidentally, the writer who had cited me had also read
one or more of my publications on cordon-bleus and muddled them with
what I had written about Avadavats.
Similarly, several writers have stated that in Burma (Myanmar), the Jay
Garrulus glandarius nests in colonies, like the Rook Corvus frugilegus.
When I looked up the original source of this statement (Harington, 1911;
Wickham, 1929) I found no such claim had been made, only that on one
occasion seven nests (condition not stated) were found fairly closely together
and it was stressed that this was exceptional.
It is still stated in standard works that the Woodcock Scolopax rusticola
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.977191" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266167" page_num="81" year="" vol="">
GOODWIN - BIRD BOOKS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998912619047619" page_id="56266167"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
carries its young between its legs. For example, Campbell &amp; Lack (1985)
stated that, "The European Woodcock has been recorded on several occasions
carrying the young between its legs, against the belly". Though I suspect
some doubts about this ornithological dogma prompted the statement by
Hay man, Marchant and Prater (1986) in their excellent monograph
Shorebirds that the "Female apparently can carry chicks in flight."
It has not, I gather, been apparent to people who have studied Woodcock
in recent times (1950 onwards) and although in earlier periods some very
eminent people claimed they had seen the Woodcock carry its young in its
bill. Perhaps inspired by Lord William Percy (1951) who in his book Three
Studies in Bird Character had not only seen but photographed a Water Rail
Rallus aquaticus doing this.
In its distraction display, the Woodcock caring for young, flies slowly in
a peculiar upright posture, suggestive of that of a hovering Pied Kingfisher
Ceryle rudis with the tail brought forward between its legs. When I first
saw this my first thought was an astonished "It is true after all!" Fortunately
the bird flew towards me and then swerved away when within a few feet
(approx, lm) of me and Eric Knowles who was with me. By searching
where the parents had first appeared, we soon found what was probably the
sole survivor of her brood, a fully feathered (but presumably not yet able to
fly) young Woodcock, which had crouched motionless on a carpet of wet
green moss, where its plumage, evolved to make it almost invisible on a
typical 'dead leaves and debris' woodland floor, made it glaringly obvious.
We were careful not to pick it up, as this with young waders, as with young
gamebirds, gulls and plovers, usually results in cries of terror which elicit
close approach and furious outcry by the parents and frantic running away
to a distance by the chick when released again, all of which considerably
endangers it.
My guess is that within a few more generations, the chick carrying of
the Woodcock will be acknowledged as having been based on at best a
genuine and understandable error but at worst on lying, or sycophancy.
Well I must bring this article to an end. The reference list is mostly of
books I have read and often re-read with pleasure and benefit. I would
especially recommend most of Frank Finn's and many of W.H. Hudson's
books, two bird-addicts who have, in my opinion, often been too lightly
dismissed and/or been too harshly criticised and often by people whose
knowledge of birds was often no greater and in some aspects of bird
behaviours probably less than that of those they criticised. W.H. Hudson
(1927) was the first (so far as I know) prior to myself, to record that the
spring gatherings of the Jay, often, perhaps always, start with a single Jay
giving the "kraah"call.
Of particular interest to members of our society is our late and very
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995856" page_id="56266168"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
82
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.962895" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266168" page_num="82" year="" vol="">
GOODWIN - BIRD BOOKS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997169285714286" page_id="56266168"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
much missed member Jean Delacour&apos;s autobiographical book The Living
Air. His opening statement in the prologue (p.ll), that one is either bom a
naturalist or one never becomes one is usually, if not always, tme. How I
wish my pessimism was as cheerful and indulgent as his (p. 13) and I certainly
share his fears for the future of both people and birds (pp. 172 &amp; 173). Though
I am not convinced one ought to refrain from criticism and advice unless
asked for, as my readers will know.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.935364" genericHeader="references" page_id="56266168" page_num="82" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.538079807692308" page_id="56266168"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
Aristotle: in Finn, F., Bird Behaviours, pp.222-224, and Stresemann, E. 1975. Ornithology
from Aristotle to the Present, pp.3-7,8,11-17,22.
Campbell, B, and Lack, E. 1958. A Dictionary of Birds. T&amp;AD Poyser Ltd., Culton,
Staffordshire, England.
Chaucer, G. The Canterbury Tales.
Delacour, J. 1966. The Living Air: Memoirs of an Ornithologist. Country Life Ltd., Tower
House, Southampton Street, London.
del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A., Sargatal, J. 1977. Handbook of the Birds of the World. Vol.4. Lynx
Edicions, Barcelona, Spain.
Linn, F. (no publication date, probably before 1907). Bird Behaviour. Hutchinson and Co.,
Paternoster Row, London.
Linn, F. (no publication date). Talks About Birds. Adam and Charles Black, Soho Square,
London.
Linn, F. 1907. Ornithological and other Oddities. John Lane, The Bodley Head, London.
Goodwin, D. 1961. Bird Behaviour. "Instructions to Young Ornithologists" series. Museum
Press, Old Brompton Road, London.
Goodwin, D. 1965. Remarks on Drinking Methods of some Birds. Avicultural Magazine 71,3:76-
80.
Harington, H.H. 1911. Some Maymo Birds. Journ. Bombay Nat. Hist. Soc. 20:1003-1004.
Hayman, R, Marchant, J. and Prater, P. 1986. Shorebirds. Croom Helm Ltd., London and
Sydney.
Hudson, W.H. 1927 (but first published 1909). Birds and Man. New Readers Library,
Duckworth, 3 Henrietta Street, London.
Hudson, W. H. 1951 (but first published 1910). Far Away and Long Ago. J.M. Dent and Sons
Ltd., Aldine House, Bedford Street, London.
Hudson, W. H. 1936 (but first published 1909). Afoot in England. J.M. Dent and Sons Ltd.,
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.952149857142857">
Aldine House, Bedford Street, London.
Maclean, D. I. 1967. Die Systematische Stellung der Flughiihner (Pteroclididae). J. Orn.
108:203-217, and pers. comm.
Meade-Waldo. 1886. Sandgrouse breeding in captivity. Zoologist 1886:298-299.
Meade-Waldo. 1897. Sandgrouse. Avicultural Magazine 3:177-180.
Meade-Waldo. 1906. Sandgrouse. Avicultural Magazine (New Series) 4:219-222.
Meade-Waldo. 1929. Observations on the sandgrouse. Bull. Brit. Orn. Club 42:69-70.
Percy, Lord William. 1951. Three Studies in Bird Character. Country Life, 2-10 Tavistock
Street, London.
Smythies, B. E. 1953. The Birds of Burma. Oliver and Boyd, London.
St. Quentin, W. H. 1905. The Breeding of Pterocles exustus Avicultural Magazine (New Series)
3:64-66.
Wickham, P. F. 1929. Notes on the birds of the Upper Burma Hills. Journ. Bombay Nat. Hist.
Soc. 33:804.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998692" page_id="56266169"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
83
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.985606333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266169" page_num="83" year="" vol="">
STRESS MANAGEMENT - AN IMPORTANT FACTOR IN
THE EFFECTIVE BREEDING OF THE
CHEER PHEASANT Catreus wallichii
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.960998787878788" page_id="56266169"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
by Dr Lalit Mohan and Sat Pal Dhiman
Summary
The Cheer Pheasant is endemic to the Western Himalayan region, where
it has a restricted range. In India it is one of the most threatened species of
galliformes. It could become extinct if adequate measures to protect it are
taken as early as possible. The Indian state of Himachal Pradesh has viable
populations of Cheer Pheasants and has a great responsibility in ensuring
the long term survival of this species and it is imperative that immediate
conservation initiatives are taken. This study was conducted with captive
populations of Cheer Pheasants at four pheasantries in Himachal Pradesh.
The stress factor with specific regard to breeding, i.e. egg laying, hatching
and survival of chicks was studied and analysed. There was no breeding at
all where stress was very high. With stress reduced there was some breeding.
The breeding results were high at Blossom Pheasantry, Chail, where measures
were adopted to deal with stress. The various measures adopted to reduce
stress are described in this paper. This study will we hope prove an immense
help in future conservation breeding programmes for the Cheer Pheasant in
Himachal Pradesh and strengthen the ex-situ conservation efforts.
Introduction
The scientific name of the Cheer Pheasant derives from Catreus (Greek)
= a peacock-like bird; and wallichii , after Dr N. Wallich, Botanist and
Superindendent of the East India Company's garden at Calcutta. The IUCN
has declared the Cheer Pheasant Vulnerable (i.e. facing a high risk of
extinction in the wild in the medium-term future) and it is high time earnest
efforts were made for the conservation of this species.
Distribution
The Cheer Pheasant is restricted to northern Pakistan, northern India,
where it is confined to the states of Jammu &amp; Kashmir, Himachal Pradesh
and Uttarachal, and west-central Nepal.
Population status
Given its patchy distribution and specialised habitat requirements, it is
thought that the number of Cheer Pheasants could be fewer than 10,000
individuals (McGowan &amp; Garson, 1995) and the total could conceivably be
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.989429" page_id="56266170"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
84
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.482751" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266170" page_num="84" year="" vol="">
MOHAN &amp; DHIMAN - CHEER PHEASANT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.988924414634146" page_id="56266170"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
far lower. Gaston &amp; Singh (1980) suspected there might be fewer than
5,000 birds in the wild.
In Himachal Pradesh the Cheer Pheasant is found at Killlu, Chamba,
Solan and the Shimla Hills at 1,200m - 3,000m (approx. 3,900ft - 9,800ft).
The population was estimated to be about 1,000 pairs (Report of Himachal
Wild Life Project 1981). At present in the above area the Cheer Pheasant is
found at Chail, Majathal, Nargu, Kais, Kanawar, Tirthan, the Great
Himalayan National Park, Kullu, Bandli, Tundah, Kalatop, Rupi Bhaba,
Shimla catchment and Daranghati sanctuaries. The Blossom and Kharium
areas of Chail Wildlife Sanctuary are the world's most important refuges for
this species (Gaston &amp; Singh, 1980; Garson, 1983, 1987). The wild
population, which in 1979 was about 60 pairs (Gaston &amp; Singh, 1980), was
reported to have declined to 32 pairs at the time of the 1983 survey in Chail
Wildlife Sanctuary (Garson, 1983). In 1983, Majathal Wildlife Sanctuary
was reported to have had the highest population density of Cheer Pheasants
at 24 pairs per sq km (approx. 0.386sq mile) (Garson, 1983). Chail Wildlife
Sanctuary had a density of six pairs per sq km (approx. 0.386sq mile) (Gaston
&amp; Singh, 1980; Gaston et al. 1981). Cheer Pheasant call count surveys in
April and May 1997, revealed there were 17 calling positions per sq km
(approx. 0.386sq mile) in Majathal Wildlife Sanctuary and five calling
positions per sq km (approx. 0.386sq mile) in Chail Wildlife Sanctuary (Kalsi,
1998). Over the passage of time populations of Cheer Pheasants have
declined as reported and also as experienced by the authors in the field. The
latest survey of the present population and distributional trends in the state
is yet to be conducted.
Threats
During the field survey conducted by the authors, it was observed that
the following threats have played a major part in the decline of this species:
Habitat loss: Grass cutting and cattle grazing as per recorded rights are a
frequent cause of disturbance and are responsible for habitat loss. The
clearing of scrub and woody vegetation by local people has also caused
shrinkage of the habitat.
Fires: Fires are a serious threat. Typical habitat with grasses and highly
inflammable pine needles is prone to fires which normally occur during
April, May and June, destroying nesting birds and eggs and leaving no cover
for remaining birds. Controlled burning would be preferable, as it would
benefit the habitat and reduce the chances of fire during the breeding season.
Hunting: The birds are hunted and sometimes trapped on account of the
attractive flavour of their meat. However, at present, incidences of hunting
are negligible. Eggs are taken sometimes by local people.
Heavy predation pressure: Because of its ground-dwelling habits the
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.305383" page_id="56266171"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
MOHAN &amp; DHIMAN - CHEER PHEASANT
</equation>
<page confidence="0.785874" page_id="56266171"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
85
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.96437" page_id="56266171"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
Cheer Pheasant suffers heavy predation. Potential predators include the
Yellow-throated Marten Martes flavigula, Leopard Cat Felis bengalensis,
Leopard Panther a pardus, jackal, civet and Himalayan Griffon Vulture Gyps
himalayensis. Snakes and rats are known to eat the eggs and chicks.
Climatic changes: The early monsoon rains cause mortality among newly-
hatched chicks and the humid conditions aid the spread of diseases.
Scarcity of food and shelter: The Cheer Pheasant prefers grassy slopes.
The removal of grass by local people renders the ground open, leaving no
shelter for the pheasants and a scarcity of food.
The aforementioned factors contribute to stress and put the wild
population in danger.
The captive population
The captive population is located at three places in Himachal Pradesh,
namely Blossom and Khariun at Chail, the Himalayan Nature Park, Kufri
and Shimla Bird Park at Chaura Maidan, Shimla. The breeding behaviour
of this species was studied at these sites and the results were not encouraging,
in part due we feel to insufficient efforts having been made in the past.
Various factors are important if breeding is to be successful, one of these
being stress management. The authors considered it appropriate to study
the breeding behaviour of the Cheer Pheasant under stress as well as under
more natural conditions in order to better understand its impact on the
breeding of this species in captivity.
Factors causing stress in captivity are human interference, noise, the
threat posed to captive birds by predators such as those mentioned earlier,
interference by other species sharing their enclosures and sometimes even
interference by individuals of the same species cannot be ruled out. Other
factors can include an unsuitable/unnatural environment, with a lack of hiding
places, a lack of nest sites and nest material and the lack of a sufficiently
balanced, nutritious diet.
Objectives
As the Cheer Pheasant population is declining fast in its natural habitat
and the captive breeding of this species and others such as the Western
Tragopan Tragopan melanocephalus and Himalayan Monal Lophophorus
impejanus is proving difficult in Himachal Pradesh, it was decided to study
the effect of stress on the breeding behaviour of the Cheer Pheasant in
captivity. Stress management will be one of the major factors which will be
taken into account when fonnulating a conservation breeding project for
pheasants.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.971907" page_id="56266172"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
86
</page>
<equation confidence="0.341249" page_id="56266172"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
MOHAN &amp; DHIMAN - CHEER PHEASANT
Methodology
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.996278714285714" page_id="56266172"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
As stated earlier, the study was carried out at the pheasantries at Shimla
Bird Park, the Himalayan Nature Park, Kufri, and Blossom Pheasantry at
Chail. The Cheer Pheasants in the Himalayan Nature Park are kept in two
pheasantries. In one the birds are on public display whereas visitors are not
allowed at the other pheasantry. Breeding behaviour was observed and the
stress factor studied. In addition, the breeding records for previous years
were collected and analysed.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.956096">
Results
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.962524935483871" page_id="56266172"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
The data collected detailing the patterns of egg laying, hatching and
survival of chicks at the above pheasantries is tabulated in the tables
p. 87.
Observations
Shimla Bird Park is located in the heart of the town of Shimla. It is one
of the tourist attractions, with the basic objective of displaying birds to
visitors. A total of 32 birds including Cheer Pheasants, Himalayan Monals,
Kalij Pheasants Lophura leucomelanos hamiltoni , Red Junglefowl Gallus
gallus , parrots and ducks, are housed in an enclosure approximately 35m
long x 20m wide x 6m high (about 115ft long x 65ft wide x 20ft high). It is
a walk-in enclosure/aviary into which visitors are allowed to go. On average
the park has about 50 visitors a day, but this number almost doubles during
March-June, which is the breeding season for the Cheer Pheasant. Because
of the close proximity of visitors the birds come under considerable stress,
which increases during the breeding season. As a result the Cheer Pheasants
have failed to breed successfully. Eggs were laid but were infertile.
The Cheer Pheasants are, as previously stated, kept in two places in the
Himalayan Nature Park. In one enclosure the pheasants are on display to
visitors who view them from outside the enclosure. There are other
enclosures behind this in which the pheasants are not on display. On average
about 300 visitors visit the park daily, but there is a threefold increase during
March-June, the breeding season. The results were analysed and throw
light on their breeding behaviour under stress. Table 2 shows that the
pheasants on display to visitors never bred, whereas Table 3 shows that
those not on view to the public bred a number of times. This indicates that
Cheer Pheasants under stress due to disturbance by visitors do not breed
whereas those subjected to considerably less disturbance breed successfully.
The breeding behaviour and effect with regards to stress and other factors
were studied in detail in Cheer Pheasants kept at Blossom Pheasantry and
the work done by the authors was published in the World Pheasant
Association, International Newsletter (Jan. 2004, p. 11) and was also
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.985078619469027" page_id="56266173"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
MOHAN &amp; DHIMAN - CHEER PHEASANT
87
Tables 1-4. Data from the four study establishments with Cheer Pheasants.
Opening No. of
No. of
No. of
Year
stock
eggs
chicks
chicks
Transfers
Deaths Total
MF
laid
hatched
survived
MF
Data from Shimla Bird Park
2001-02
1
1
-
-
-
-
-
1
1
2002-03
1
1
5
-
-
_
_
1
1
2003-04
1
1
6
-
_
-
-
1
1
2004-05
1
1
5
-
-
-
-
1
1
Data from Himalayan Nature Park, Kufri - Display Pheasantry
1994-95
1
1
6
-
-
-
-
1
1
1995-96
1
1
5
-
-
-
M-l
0
1
1996-97
0
1
-
-
_
-
-
0
1
1997-98
0
1
-
-
-
-
_
0
1
1998-99
0
1
-
-
-
-
-
0
1
99-2000
0
1
-
-
-
F-l
-
-
.
2000-01
-
-
-
-
T
-
_
-
-
2001-02
-
-
-
.
-
M+2, F+2
-
2
2
2002-03
2
2
-
-
&apos;
-
-
2
2
2003-04
2
2
_
_
-
M+2, F+2
-
4
4
2004-05
4
4
-
-
F+L
-
4
5
Data from Himalayan Nature Park, Kufri - Non-Display Pheasantry
99-2000
-
-
-
-
-
M+l, F+l
-
1
1
2000-01
1
1
7
6
4
-
_
3
3
2001=02
3
3
5
3
2
M-3, F-3
-
1
1
2002-03
1
1
8
6
4
-
-
3
3
2003-04
3
3
5
3
1
M-2, F-2
-
1
2
2004-05
1
2
6
4
2
F-l
-
2
2
Data from Blossom Pheasantry - Chail Wildlife Sanctuary
1994-95
1
2
7
5
4
_
1
6
1995-96
1
6
-
-
-
-
-
1
6
1996-97
1
6
6
4
1
-
F-4
2
2
1997-98
2
2
6
-
4
-
-
2
2
1998-99
2
2
8
5
1
M-2, F-l
F-l
0
1
99-2000
0
1
-
-
-
_
-
0
1
2000-01
0
1
-
-
-
M+5, F+l
-
5
2
2001-02
5
2
9
7
4
-
-
7
4
2002-03
7
4
16
10
5
-
F-l
9
6
2003-04
9
6
44
11
5
M-2, F-l
F-3
7
7
2004-05
7
7
40
32
12
-
F-2
1410
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.462758" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266174" page_num="88" year="" vol="">
MOHAN &amp; DHIMAN - CHEER PHEASANT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.901111483870968" page_id="56266174"  page_num="88" year="" vol="">
reproduced recently by the Pheasant Specialist Group UK in the magazine
Tragopan. Though the Blossom Pheasantry was established during 1987,
no significant breeding results were obtained prior to 2002-2003. To achieve
successful results effective measures with respect to all factors including
stress were taken into consideration. The following measures were taken to
control stress and achieve successful breeding:
i) The pairing of male and female was done before the start of the breeding
season, and only one pair was kept in each of the six enclosures.
ii) The behaviour of each pair was studied for one month and if necessary
birds were shifted in order that they were more comfortable and
compatible pairs were established.
iii) Other species of birds were shifted from each enclosure, leaving just
a pair of pheasants.
iv) The pheasantry was closed to visitors from breeding until the chicks
were one month old.
v) All holes used by predators such as snakes, rats and martens were
plugged.
vi) To help ward off predators the enclosures were also covered with an
extra layer of chicken wire.
vii) Grasses/bushes were grown in each enclosure to provide shelter and
hiding places for the birds.
viii) Nicely woven bamboo sticks with grasses were provided to create a
nesting environment in each enclosure.
ix) Interference by keepers was minimized during the breeding season.
x) Gunny bags (coarsely-woven jute sacks) were used to provide sight
barriers between adjacent enclosures, to prevent males seeing each other,
which would have caused disturbances and resulted in the males fighting.
xi) To supplement their diet the birds were provided with trays containing
wheat and barley grass. Also, the soil in the enclosures was replaced
periodically with fresh soil containing roots, tubers, grubs and insects
etc.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.762586">
Discussion
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9755265" page_id="56266174"  page_num="88" year="" vol="">
From the study carried out and the results obtained it is clear that at
Blossom Pheasantry, Chail, when care was taken to reduce stress, the Cheer
Pheasants bred successfully. Prior to 2002-2003, when stress was not
controlled, the results were unsatisfactory at this pheasantry. The pheasants
also bred in the Himalayan Nature Park, Kufri, in the enclosure to which
visitors were not allowed access, but because no other efforts had been made
to control stress, the breeding results were less successful than those achieved
at Blossom Pheasantry, Chail. The Cheer Pheasants kept in Shimla Bird
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.382749" page_id="56266175"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
MOHAN &amp; DHIMAN - CHEER PHEASANT
</equation>
<page confidence="0.993546" page_id="56266175"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
89
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.980334696969697" page_id="56266175"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
Park and those on display in the Himalayan Nature Park, Kufri, were under
a high degree of stress, so never bred in captivity. It is worthwhile perhaps
to mention that the domesticated birds, such as the ducks, kept in Shimla
Bird Park, did not appear to suffer from stress and bred successfully under
the same conditions which the pheasants failed to breed. It shows that non-
domesticated birds need a stress-free and more natural environment and
that birds such as the Cheer Pheasant should be subjected to the minimum
of interference during the breeding season. It is also notable that no successful
breeding took place in the case of the Himalayan Monals kept at Shimla
Bird Park and the Himalayan Nature Park, Kufri. However, the breeding
results were satisfactory in the case of the Red Junglefowl kept in these two
pheasantries. This clearly shows that pheasants such as the Cheer and
Himalayan Monal, which are naturally shy and retiring species, need stress-
free and more natural environments than Red Junglefowl and domesticated
ducks etc.
Conclusion
From the study we have concluded that for the successful breeding of
pheasants such as the Cheer, enclosures need to provide an environment
that is as stress-free and natural as possible. This is clearly indicated by the
successful breeding at Blossom Pheasantry, where a number of measures
have been taken to provide an environment as stress-free and as natural as
possible.
In the case of the Cheer Pheasants, those at Shimla Bird Park, Shimla,
and those at the Himalayan Nature Park (Display Pheasantry), Kufri, which
were under stress, failed to breed successfully. At the Himalayan Nature
Park (Non-Display Pheasantry), Kufri, where stress was not so high, there
was a degree of success, while at Blossom Pheasantry, where a number of
measures have been taken to provide a stress-free environment, there have
been a number of successful hatchings, especially from 2002-2003 onwards.
On the basis of this study carried out at four sites, it has been concluded
that when formulating conservation breeding projects, especially for the
Cheer Pheasant, high priority must be given to controlling stress in order to
produce successful results.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.947712" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266175" page_num="89" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.87478" page_id="56266175"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
For their continuous support of wildlife conservation, the authors wish
to thank Sh. Ashok Thakur, Principal Secretary Forests Himachal Pradesh,
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.9641924">
Sh. R. A. Singh, Principal Chief Conservator of Forests Himachal Pradesh,
Sh. A. K. Gulati, Additional Principal Chief Conservator of Forests-cum-
Chief Wild Life Warden Himachal Pradesh. For their valuable advice and
support during the studies, thanks are also due to Sh. R. S. Chauhan,
Divisional Forest Officer, Wild Life Division, Shimla and Sh. Satish Gupta,
</reference>
<page confidence="0.978806" page_id="56266176"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
90
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.435655" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266176" page_num="90" year="" vol="">
MOHAN &amp; DHIMAN - CHEER PHEASANT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.91078775" page_id="56266176"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
Divisional Forest Officer, O/o Conservator of Forests Wild Life South,
Shimla. The authors also wish to thank their families for their contribution
in encouraging them to carry out the above studies in the cause of wildlife
conservation.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.25954">
Bibiliography
</subsectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.916477857142857">
Garson, P. J. 1983. The Cheer Pheasant Catreus wallichii in Himachal Pradesh: an update.
Journal World Pheasant Association 8:29-39.
Gaston, A.J., Garson, P. J. and Hunter, Jr., M. L. 1981a. Present distribution and status of
pheasants in Himachal Pradesh, Western Himalaya. WPA Journal VEI0-30.
Gaston, A.J., Hunter, M. L. and Garson, P. J. 1981b. The Wildlife of Himachal Pradesh,
Western Himalaya: Report of the Himachal Wildlife Project. Technical Notes No.82, University
of Maine, Orona,USA.
Gaston, A. J.. and Singh, J. 1980. The status of Cheer Pheasants Catreus wallichii in the Chail
Wildlife Sanctuary, Himachal Pradesh. Journal World Pheasant Association 5:68-73.
Lelliot,A. D. 1987. Survey of Cheer Pheasants near Dhorpatan, West Nepal, 1981. Pheasants
in Asia 1982. Rekha Printers, New Delhi/World Pheasant Association.
Kalsi, R. S. 2000. Density Index and Habitat Association of the Cheer Pheasant Catreus
wallachii. Final Report submitted to the Oriental Bird Club UK and the World Pheasant
Association, South Asia Regional Office.
</reference>
<figureCaption confidence="0.4314936">
Kaul, R. and Jitender, S. J. 2001. Pheasant Survey in Chamba, Himachal Pradesh. Mor, 4
(Bef.):2-3.
Mohan, L. and Dhiman, S. P. 2004. Successful parent rearing of Cheer Pheasants Catreus
wallichii at Blossom Pheasantry, Chail in Himachal Pradesh, India. The International Newsletter
of the World Pheasant Association 72:11.
</figureCaption>
<table confidence="0.961966666666667" page_id="56266176"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
Dr Lalit Mohan, Conservator of Forests, Wildlife (South), Mist Chamber,
Khalini, Shimla - 171002, Himachal Pradesh, India. E-mail: cfwls@
yahoo.com
Sat Pal Dhiman, Range Forest Officer, Wildlife Range, Chail, Disst.-
Solan-173217, Himachal Pradesh, India. E-mail:satpaldhiman@yahoo.com
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.577217" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56266176" page_num="90" year="" vol="">
NEW BIRDS OF PREY WORKING GROUP
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.964118857142857" page_id="56266176"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
In South Africa the Endangered Wildlife Trust (website: www.ewt.org.za)
has combined its Vulture Study and Raptor Conservation Groups to form
the Birds of Prey Working Group. However, Vulture News will continue
under the editorship of Dr Mark Anderson and a concerted effort is to be
made to upgrade the raptor group's biannual journal, Gabar , to the same
standard as Vulture News. Talon Talk and Gyps Snips , the groups' newsletters,
have been replaced by a single electronic newsletter called The Eagle s Eye.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996144" page_id="56266177"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
91
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.982637" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266177" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
CUCKOO-SHRIKES TO THRUSHES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.810449" page_id="56266177"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
Handbook of the Birds of the World Vol. 10, which will include wrens,
thrushes, chats, robins, bulbuls, mockingbirds, dippers, waxwings, leafbirds
and accentors, is due to be published shortly. The price will be #120. Lynx
is offering the set of the first 10 volumes for #980 and has introduced a
variety of monthly instalment plans for purchasing past and future volumes.
For further details contact: Lynx, Montseny 8, E-08193 Bellaterra
(Barcelona), Spain. Tel:+34 93 594 77 10/Fax:+34 93 592 09 69/ E-
mai 1: lynx@hb w. com/Website: www. hb w. com
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.49846" page_id="56266177"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.959489" genericHeader="general terms" page_id="56266177" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
RECORD YEAR FOR LORO PARQUE FUNDAgiON
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996335846153846" page_id="56266177"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
A record 1,458 young birds were bred at Loro Parque in 2004, a 6%
increase on the previous year. The undoubted highlight was the breeding of
two Spix's Macaws Cyanopsitta spixii , both females. Another important
event was the breeding of two Palm Cockatoos Probosciger aterrimus , after
a break of 10 years. The Scaly-naped Amazons Amazona mercenaria, which
bred for the first time in 2001, raised three chicks after a two year break.
The pair of Great Green Macaws Ara ambigua, consisting of a male more
than 30 years old and a considerably younger female (see News &amp; Views
Vol. 110, No.4, p. 186 (2004)), eventually had four young, two were reared
by the pair and another two were reared by another pair of macaws.
Bred for the first time at Loro Parque were: White-eyed Conure Aratinga
leucophthalma, Brotogeris versicolurus versicolurus and B. v. chiriri , Hawk-
headed Parrot Deroptyus accipitrinus fuscifrons , Collared Lory Phigys
solitarius and Edward's Lorikeet Trichoglossus haematodus deplanchii. The
Tanimbar Islands subspecies of Eclectus Parrot Eclectus roratus riedeli also
bred for the first time. The eggs were placed with an experienced pair of the
subspecies E. r. polychlorus, which hatched two chicks in mid-December.
Other parrots bred in 2004 included five Red-tailed Amazons A.
brasiliensis, three Marajo Yellow-headed Amazons A. ochrocephala
xantholaema , eight Red-browed Amazons A. rhodocorytha, six Gang Gang
Cockatoos Callocephalon fimbriatum and an Orange-breasted Fig Parrot
Cycolopsitta gulielm itertii .
On view to the public for the first time at Loro Parque are pairs of Blue-
eared Lory Eos semilarvata and Collared Lory, which have been transferred
from the Loro Parque Fundacion breeding station, where both species have
bred successfully during the past two years.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995051" page_id="56266178"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
92
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.980861" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266178" page_num="92" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
LATEST COUNT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9289408" page_id="56266178"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
The latest count of the Cape Parrot Poicephalus robustus, South Africa's
only endemic parrot species, suggested there are just over 1,000 or so of
these birds left in the wild. Most of them live in the forests of the Eastern
Cape, but there are thought to be about 250 in KwaZulu-Natal, mainly in
the Creighton area. Prof. Colleen Downs of the University of KwaZulu-
Natal, Pietermaritzburg said the most recent count, in May, produced similar
results to those of the past eight years. She pointed out that merely counting
the parrots is pointless unless the information is used to devise strategies for
their conservation. If you would like further information or wish to help e-
mail: manager@birdlife.org.za
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.69792" page_id="56266178"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.559141" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266178" page_num="92" year="" vol="">
ENDANGERED HORNBILL BRED FOR FIRST TIME
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9535423125" page_id="56266178"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
The Critically Endangered Visayan Wrinkled Hombill Aceros waldeni
has bred for the first time ever in captivity, in aviaries on the West Visaya
State University College of Agriculture and Forestry Campus on Panay, one
of the Visaya Islands of the Philippines. With financial support from the
Loro Parque Fundaqion in partnership with Chester Zoo, Vogelpark Walsrode
and the Zoological Society for the Conservation of Species and Populations
the aviaries, for breeding threatened endemic parrots and hombills, were
constructed in 2002.
Programme Manager Prof. Lucia Lastimosa told the Loro Parque
Fundaqion that two pairs had produced young that had fledged and another
female had sealed herself into a nest cavity. Twelve or more Tarictic Hombills
Penelopides panini were expected to fledge in July. Having first laid a
clutch of three infertile eggs, a female Blue-crowned Racquet-tailed Parrot
Prioniturus discurus had hatched a second clutch of five eggs and was rearing
the chicks. The male of the pair had died and the female had accepted an
older male as her new mate. He was guarding the nest and feeding her.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.498229" page_id="56266178"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
* * *
IN SEARCH OF FOOD
By capturing Knobbed Hombills Rhyticeros cassidix in nets set high in
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.888796" page_id="56266178"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
the rainforest canopy on the Indonesian island of Sulawesi and fitting the
birds with radio transmitters, Margaret F. Kinnaird and her husband Tim
O'Brien have found that the hombills may fly up to 20 miles (approx. 32km)
in search of food, even locating wild fruiting trees, such as fig trees, alongside
roads and in agricultural plots. The Knobbed Hombill is one of two species
that occur on Sulawesi, the other being the Sulawesi Hombill or Sulawesi
Dwarf Hombill Penelopides exarhatus.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700135" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266179" page_num="93" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.989381" page_id="56266179"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
93
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996726" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266179" page_num="93" year="" vol="">
SPREO'S COMPLEX LIFESTYLE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.883428705882353" page_id="56266179"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
Dustin R. Ruben stein, a PhD candidate in the Department of
Neurobiology and Behavior at Cornell University, has been studying the
Superb Starling or Superb Spreo Spreo superbus in East Africa and
discovered that it has one of the most complex family lives of any bird.
Writing in Birdscope Spring 2005, Vol. 19, No.2, published by Cornell Lab
of Ornithology, he described how this starling lives in large social groups of
as many as 30 or more birds, often consisting of extended families of parents,
step-parents, siblings, aunts, uncles, nieces and nephews. Within these
groups, usually only two to four pairs breed. Usually they build their nests
in thorny acacia trees and when the young hatch, other non-breeding members
of the group, both males and females, may help them raise their young.
Although most of these helpers assist their own parents, they often also help
at a number of other nests simultaneously. Even other breeding birds may
help at nests that are not their own. To help understand how and why this
complex lifestyle evolved, he is using DN A - based techniques in the Lab's
Evolutionary Biology Program to unravel the precise family relationships
within these large social groups.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.258101" page_id="56266179"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.458241" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266179" page_num="93" year="" vol="">
SEEN AGAIN AFTER ALMOST TEN YEARS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.929153083333333" page_id="56266179"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
The Cozumel Thrasher Toxostoma guttatum exists nowhere else but on
the island of Cozumel off Mexico's Yucatan Peninsula. Although there was
once an estimated population of some 10,000 birds, it had become extremely
rare by the late 1980s. In the early 1970s, after a film company had finished
filming on the island, it released some boa constrictors and these may have
contributed to the thrasher's decline. Then in 1988 Hurricane Gilbert swept
across the island and a few years later, in 1995, the island was hit by Hurricane
Roxanne. The Cozumel Thrasher had not been seen since 1996 and was
thought by many to be extinct. Then last year, a team of biologists sponsored
by the American Bird Conservancy and Conservation International, working
in conjunction with Villanova University and the Mexican counterpart of
the Island Endemic Institute, saw a single individual.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.388389" page_id="56266179"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.874554" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266179" page_num="93" year="" vol="">
PUBLISHED IN USA
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.54325025">
Birds of Western Africa by Nik Borrow and Ron Demey, reviewed in the
previous issue (. Avicuitural Magazine Vol.Ill, No.l, pp.44-45 (2005)), is
published in the USA by Princeton University Press (website:
www.birds.princeton.edu). Price US$40.00
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998266" page_id="56266180"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
94
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.981726" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266180" page_num="94" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
UNDER SEVERE THREAT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.973678217391304" page_id="56266180"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
BirdLife International is appealing for donations to help protect one of
the world's forgotten forest regions and its remarkable but threatened birds
and other wildlife.
The Tumbesian region stretches from western Ecuador south into the
coastal lowlands and foothills of north-western Pern. Bordered by the Pacific
Ocean, the Andes, humid Choco and coastal desert, it is home to dry forests
of a kind found nowhere else and has 84 endemic bird species and eight
endemic mammal species. Protecting it is considered one of the world's
highest conservation priorities.
Unless action is taken soon, birds such as the White-winged Guan
Penelope albipennis (see News &amp; Views Vol. 109, No.4, pp. 184-186 (2003))
and the Marvellous Spatuletail Loddigesia mirablis (a species of
hummingbird) will be lost forever.
Working through the Bosques Sin Fronteras ("forests without frontiers")
programme, BirdLife International is working with local communities in
three of the most important endemic bird areas. The project includes
environmental education (both within schools and the wider community)
and is helping local people improve their livelihoods through management
of natural resources, development of ecotourism and improved agriculture.
It will be a model conservation programme, which can be used elsewhere to
benefit other parts of Latin America.
If you would like to help in the efforts to protect the Tumbesian region,
cheques should be made payable to BirdLife International and sent to:
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.919263666666667" page_id="56266180"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
Tumbesian Appeal, BirdLife International, Wellbrook Court, Girton Road,
Cambridge CBS ONA, UK. Website:www.birdlife.org
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.552395" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266180" page_num="94" year="" vol="">
RARE SUMATRAN PHEASANT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9104866" page_id="56266180"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
According to Pheasants, Partridges &amp; Grouse by Steve Madge and Phil
McGowan (Helm, 2002), Salvadori's Pheasant Lophura inornata was only
rediscovered after nearly 70 years in 1986. However, while researching the
life and career of W. J. C. (Wilfred) Frost for biographical notes about him
which I hope to publish in the magazine, I discovered that he had brought
some of these rare Sumatran pheasants to London in June 1939. Writing
from the USA in 1943, Jean Delacour mentioned that Frost had brought him
"a cock and three hens". They must have been lost in 1940 when Cleres
came under heavy bombing, which is presumably why their importation
passed almost unnoticed.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.695322" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266181" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.972358" page_id="56266181"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
95
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.994734" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56266181" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
PROTECTING THE PICATHARTES AND THEIR HABITAT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.984421153846154" page_id="56266181"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
A joint conservation project between the RSPB (Royal Society of the
Protection of Birds), the Conservation Society of Sierra Leone and the Sierra
Leone Government, to conserve the Gola Forest, received a boost in June
when President Alhaji Ahmad Tejan Kabbah launched the project and gave
it his seal of approval.
The 75,000 hectare (185,000 acre) West African forest has several nesting
colonies of White-necked Picathartes Picathartes gymnocephalus. It is also
home to the rare White-breasted Guineafowl Agelastes meleagrides , which
according to Steve Madge and Phil McGowan in Pheasants, Partridges &amp;
Grouse (Christopher Helm, 2002), was in the late 1980s found in three areas
of the Gola Forest, where there was an estimated 5,700-8,700 birds.
For further information about the amazing birds and other creatures living
in the Gola Forest, and the RSPB's efforts to conserve them, you can visit:
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.351638333333333" page_id="56266181"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
www.rspb.org.uk/intemational/conservation/sierraleone
Copyright Christopher Brack
Grey-necked Picathartes.
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.980460333333333" page_id="56266181"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
Earlier in the year, the environmental charity Earthwatch appealed for
volunteers to continue research in the Cameroons, West Africa, in an effort
to save the threatened Grey-necked Picathartes P. oreas. The aim is to
recommend appropriate measures for the protection of this species and its
habitat. International volunteers are essential to the project. The local
community welcome them and a tmsting relationship has been established
with a common goal. Volunteers are not required to have prior experience,
just enthusiasm. Further information can be found on the Earthwatch
website: w w w. e arth watch. org
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994542" page_id="56266182"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
96
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.963002" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266182" page_num="96" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
ARE YOU FAMILIAR WITH THE GUIRA CUCKOO?
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.988364193548388" page_id="56266182"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
Robin Restall is in the final stages of preparing a guide to the birds of
northern South America, with almost 6,000 individual birds illustrated in
colour. As many plumages as he has been able to find are shown, including
females, juveniles, subspecies, morphs and even in some cases, worn
alongside fresh plumages, plus dramatic in-moult birds. Just about every
vagrant is also included. Among these is the Guira Cuckoo Guira guira,
that apparently does not normally occur north of the Amazon, but for which
there is a single record of an emaciated bird in fine plumage, that was
collected on the island of Curasao, off the coast of Venezuela, in 1954.
Robin wonders whether the bird was a genuine vagrant or an escaped
cage bird and would like to know the views of members who have experience
of this species. He promises to acknowledge all responses and will publish
whatever relevant information emerges. His e-mail address is:
restall@cantv.net
Based on my experience of looking after two of these birds, which lived
in the Bird House at London Zoo, lam convinced that the flight of the Guira
Cuckoo is far too weak for it to have flown that far. I think it was almost
certainly an escaped cage bird.
In his London Zoo Notes, Avicultural Magazine Vol.60, No.4, pp.144-
145, July-August 1954, J. J. Yealland wrote of Gerald Durrell and his wife
having returned from Argentina and Paraguay with a collection of birds
which included the two Guira Cuckoos (above), along with some other birds
that they had obtained at Rio de Janeiro on the way home. The Guira
Cuckoos were ridiculously tame and were extremely comical characters,
that could not land on a branch or anything else without toppling
forward and almost falling off. Gerald Durrell wrote very amusingly
about them, and there were several drawings of them, in his book about the
journey. It would be interesting to re-read it to find out if there was any
mention of them having lost any Guira Cuckoos as they sailed northwards.
I think that at least one of the zoo birds lived until the early 1960s, after
which this species seemed to disappear from aviculture. Then, a year or two
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.907227166666667">
ago, advertisements offering Guira Cuckoos for sale started to appear in
Cage &amp; Aviary Birds published here in the UK, and last year I saw two in
Raymond Sawyer s aviaries. In the past few years, this species has bred
successfully at Burgers 'Zoo in the Netherlands and at the World of Birds in
South Africa (see Avicultural Magazine, News &amp; Views, Vol.110, No. 2, p. 93
&amp; Vol.110, No. 4, p.182 (2004)) and possibly in other collections. - Ed.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998168" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266183" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ROSEMARY RETURNS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.908353142857143" page_id="56266183"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Rosemary Low has returned to the Canary Islands, to take up a position
with the Loro Parque Funda^ion (LPF), which will include editing its
magazine Cyanopsitta. She will be working alongside Prof. David Waugh,
Director of the LPF, and Matthias Reinschmidt, Curator of the bird collection.
Her latest book Amazon Parrots: Aviculture, Trade and Conservation ,
will be reviewed in the next issue of the Avicultural Magazine , which will
also include Rosemary's account of a birdwatching trip she made to
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.80755337037037" page_id="56266183"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Peninsular Malaysia.
DNA Bird Sexing from blood sample (1 drop) GBP 6,99
DNA Bird Sexing feather sample (34 feathers) GBP 8,99
DNA Bird Sexing O Feather Disease GBP 16,-
DNA Bird Sexing O Polyoma Virus GBP 16,-
DNA Bird Sexing O Aspergillus GBP 16,-
DNA Bird Sexing O Pacheco's Disease GBP 16,
DNA Bird Sexing O Feather Disease
O Polyoma Virus or Pacheco's Disease GBP 23,
DNA Bird Sexing O Feather Disease
O Polyoma Virus or Pacheco's Disease
O Chlamydia psittaci GBP 33,- _
DNA-Tests: Mycoplasma, Avian Influenza Virus,
Newcastle Disease, Herpes Virus, Candida, and m ore.
Please send your probes to the following addresses:
In Europe and rest of the world:
Genekam ^1/
Biotechnology AG # j
DammstraBe 31-33, D-47119 Duisburg, Germany
Fon +49 [2033 5 5 5 8 58-31 Fax +49 [203] 35 82 99
Email: query@genekam.de  |Internet: www.genekam.de
In USA: Genekam Biotech Inc. USA
\0x25BA Combi Offer O (Two tests)
\0x25BA Combi Offer 0 (Three tests)
\0x25BA Combi Offer 0 (Four tests)
More tests available.
GENEKAM BIOTECHNOLOGY  |TWO STEPS AHEAD
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.77468" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266184" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.939571272727273" page_id="56266184"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
3 9088 01173 7129
Breeding the Zanzibar Red Bishop in a mixed collection
by Alan and Beverley Brock.49
The breeding of the Pigeon Guillemot Cepphus columba
at Living Coasts
by Tony Durkin.53
Preliminary findings on reproduction of captive Marabou Storks
Leptoptilos crumeniferus
by C. W. Kuhar, L. M. Hernandez and K. Amos-Mongiello.56
Breeding the Sooty Grassquit Tiaris fuliginosa , with some
observations on comparative behaviour
by Robin Restall..64
Notes on the Great Sparrow Passer montitensis
by Neville Brickell.75
Some personal observations on bird books
by Derek Goodwin.78
Stress management - an important factor in the effective breeding
of the Cheer Pheasant Catreus wallichii
by Dr Lalit Mohan and Sat Pal Dhiman...83
News &amp; Views.91
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</table>
</algorithms>
