<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.6238384" page_id="56260765"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
&amp; AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 109
No. 4
2003
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260766" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990574571428571" page_id="56260766"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2003 as for 2002: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.619209" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260766" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE..
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.969533" page_id="56260766"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, ARCADIA, THE MOUNTS, TOTNES, DEVON TQ9 7QJ, UK.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TN13 1LG,UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail: Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998476" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260766" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982477333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.70371" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260767" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.363665" page_id="56260767"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 109 - No. 4 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2003
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.668697" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260767" page_num="" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE GREY TREEPIE Dendrocitta formosae
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.816799" page_id="56260767"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Neil Owen
Description
Also known as the Himalayan Treepie, this species is, including its long
tail, approx. 40cm (about 15 3 Ain) in length. Much of the plumage is various
shades of grey to slightly brownish grey, lighter on the crown and underparts
Andrew Owen
Adult female.
and very dark, almost black on the face and neck (see photo above). The
mantle is brown and the wings are shiny black with a clear white patch at
the base of the primaries. The rump is white and the tail is black with some
grey in the central feathers. The under tail-coverts are chestnut. The bill is
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999433" page_id="56260768"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
146
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.877155" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260768" page_num="146" year="" vol="">
OWEN - GREY TREEPIE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.974674641025641" page_id="56260768"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
black and as I have found to my cost can deliver quite a powerful bite.
Seven subspecies are recognised (Madge and Bum, 1999), with western ones
having a grey or greyish-white rump and eastern subspecies having a very
white rump; there are also differences in size and the length and coloration
of the tail.
Distribution
The Grey Treepie occurs throughout a large part of the Himalayan
foothills, from extreme north-eastern Pakistan, across much of northern India
(with an isolated population in eastern India), eastwards to China, with
isolated populations on Omei Shan (south Sichuan), Hainan and Taiwan. It
is thought to be fairly common over most of its range,except for the Hainan
subspecies D.f. insulae , which may be endangered by forest destruction
(Madge and Bum, 1999). I believe my birds belong to one of the Chinese
subspecies.
Voice
The most frequent call is a short, loud metallic clucking sound which is
usually delivered by two birds together and is almost always accompanied
by the birds flicking their tails right up vertically. The only other sound I
have heard is the harsh scolding cackle when anyone approached their nest
or young.
Accommodation
The birds are housed in a large aviary measuring approximately 6m x
2.5m x 2m high (20ft x 8ft x 6ft 6in high). It has a wooden shelter at one
end into which they can be confined during severe weather. It has a low
wattage light bulb and can if necessary be heated. The flight is planted with
a couple of small conifers, a flowering redcurrant bush and a large clump of
bamboo. There is also a passion flower which has taken over much of one
end and part of the roof. Wooden panels are attached to one side of the
flight to give the occupants additional protection from the elements and part
of the roof is covered with clear corrugated Perspex (Plexiglas) for a similar
reason. The floor has a covering of leaf litter and there is a shallow pool for
bathing, but the birds rarely come to the ground.
Diet
The birds receive a basic diet of a coarse grade insectile mixture to which
I add various chopped fruits, a little lean minced (ground) beef, mashed
hard-boiled egg and mynah pellets. A few mealworms or crickets were
given most days and occasionally a chopped piece of day-old chick. Often
there was a lot of food left the following day and I was quite surprised how
good the birds looked, when they seemed to eat hardly anything.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.612605" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260769" page_num="147" year="" vol="">
OWEN - GREY TREEPIE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997048" page_id="56260769"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
147
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.978249682926829" page_id="56260769"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
Behaviour
Compared to other corvids I have kept I found the treepies extremely
shy and often I had to wait very patiently near the aviary for a long time in
order to observe anything, in fact the only time I could get really close was
when they were nesting, when they would come right up to me making an
alarm call similar to the call of the European Magpie Pica pica .
Breeding
In late August 2001 while visiting a friend's aviaries I saw a pair of Grey
Treepies and as jays and magpies are among my favourites I decided to buy
the pair. I was told that the pair had nested but the chicks had either died or
disappeared at an early age. The aviary housed several other large birds
including laughingthrushes Garrulax spp., and it was not possible to establish
the exact reason why the chicks died or disappeared.
On returning home the pair was released into the aviary described earlier
and soon disappeared as far away from me as possible. After moulting in
October the pair spent an uneventful winter mostly outside, although the
pair was confined to the shelter on a couple of stormy nights when I thought
the whole aviary might be blown away.
In mid-March I put up in the flight various nest baskets and boxes and
as most treepies build their own nests, I made sure there were plenty of
sticks, coconut fibre and leaves. I also placed a bunch of thin twigs in the
fork of the conifer where the birds often sat. In mid-April I noticed that this
pile of sticks seemed to have been formed into more of a solid platform. I
did wonder whether it was my imagination, but the next morning one of the
treepies flew off the platform as I approached and on April 21 st I was thrilled
to see a light blue egg with dark speckles precariously balanced in the nest.
The birds were still very flighty when I was near and any courtship must
have been earned out in private.
The egg could clearly be seen from outside the aviary, as the nest was
little more than an unlined platform with a very shallow depression in the
centre. Only about 13cm (Sin) in diameter, the nest seemed small compared
to the size of the birds and reminded me of the kind of feeble nest usually
made by pigeons and doves. The next day there were two eggs and as the
weather was getting warmer I was quite hopeful that things would go well.
The birds began eating a lot more food than usual. Towards the end of
April the weather turned much colder and windier but the birds continued to
sit tight, not even leaving the nest when I went into the aviary to change the
food pots. On May 5th the adults were off the nest and I could see that there
were then four eggs.
I began offering a wider variety of livefood, including small waxworms,
crickets and small pinky mice. The first chick hatched on May 9th. At
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998879" page_id="56260770"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
148
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.874593" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260770" page_num="148" year="" vol="">
OWEN - GREY TREEPIE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999407434782609" page_id="56260770"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
which point I provided a few spiders, waxworms and white mealworms
lightly dusted with a 'stress' vitamin and mineral supplement. A second
chick hatched the next day and by April 11 th I was very pleased to see four
tiny black chicks bobbing up and down in the nest.
The adults were eating everything I offered them and things were going
very smoothly. Disaster struck on May 18th when I found a chick dead and
half-eaten in the shelter. Knowing of the pair's dodgy history regarding
disappearing chicks, I decided to take the remaining three young indoors
and attempt to hand-rear them. At first all three took a few waxworms and
bits of pinky mice but as the evening wore on they refused to open their
beaks. As they were continuing to refuse food at 6.00am the next day I
reluctantly had no choice but to put them back out with their parents.
Amazingly both parents immediately began taking food to them and the
female brooded them the rest of the day.
They were feeding them mainly waxworms and small mice and the chicks
were growing rapidly. By May 21st all three had their eyes open but two
days later my hopes were dashed again when another headless chick was
found. The other two were feathering up nicely, and the parents were very
protective of them if I went too close, when they would quiver their wings
as they chattered at me. Chopped-up pieces of mouse and more fruit were
now being eagerly taken.
On May 26th both chicks were standing up on the edge of the nest and
the next day were perched nearby on a branch. They were well cared for by
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.613233" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260771" page_num="149" year="" vol="">
OWEN - GREY TREEPIE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999337" page_id="56260771"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
149
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997051615384615" page_id="56260771"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
the parents and grew rapidly over the next few weeks. On July 6th they
were seen feeding themselves and as they could by then hardly be
distinguished from the adults I decided to remove them. As I was charging
around the aviary trying to catch them in a net I only just noticed that the
nest contained another two eggs.
The young were removed from the aviary and the adults again produced
a clutch of four eggs. The second clutch mirrored the first in that all four
eggs hatched and one of the chicks was killed at a week old. This time
though three chicks were reared and left the nest on August 7th. I was very
upset therefore when one of these was found dead without a mark on it a
week later. The remaining two reached independence soon afterwards, so I
really could not complain as four young were reared in my first season
keeping this species.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.803429" genericHeader="references" page_id="56260771" page_num="149" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.966798625" page_id="56260771"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
Madge, S. and Burn, H. 1999. Crows and Jays. A Guide to the Crows, Jays and Magpies of
the World (paperback edition). Christopher Helm/A C Black, London.
As described above, the Grey Treepie Dendrocitta formosae, has been
bred by Neil Owen. This is probably the first successful breeding of this
species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who knows of a previous breeding
is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
Neil Owen, who lives in Carmarthenshire, Wales, was recently awarded
the society's medal for the first breeding of the Yellow-breasted Magpie Cissa
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.556647">
hypoleuca in Great Britain or Ireland. He was also first to breed the
Chestnut-tailed Minla Minla strigula.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.994082" page_id="56260772"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
150
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.981071" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260772" page_num="150" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE CHESTNUT-BACKED THRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.960198641025641" page_id="56260772"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
Zoothera dohertyi
by Gary Bralsford
Having for nearly 20 years or so kept all kinds of birds from Bengalese
Lonchura striata dom. to kingfishers, and having tried the show circuit and
found it very much for people with plenty of spare cash, early in 2003 I
decided to sell all my birds that I considered I was keeping just for the show
bench, and settle down to keeping a certain group of birds.
I started looking for foreign birds from Asia, so that they would breed in
spring and summer here in England, which would also mean that they would
moult in August-October. In the weekly journal Cage &amp; Aviary Birds I
found various adverts for Asian birds and as a result of one of these, I travelled
to the premises of a well-known dealer in Preston. Having decided to buy
pairs of Shamas Copsychus malabaricus and Magpie Robins C. saularis I
then looked up at the top cages which were only just visible, where in a big
treble-breeder were some thrushes which were absolutely stunning. These
were the Chestnut-backed Thrushes Zoothera dohertyi which are the subject
of this breeding account. I asked the dealer how much they were but he said
they were not for sale. I asked him to keep me in mind if they came up for
sale in the future and returned home with my new Shamas and Magpie
Robins, still yearning after the thrushes. So keen on them was I that I decided
to phone the dealer and try to persuade him to change his mind, which I
succeeded in doing by promising him any youngsters I might breed (though
I thought my chances of breeding them were only slim).
When I returned to purchase these beautiful thrushes, I asked the dealer
if he thought they were a true pair? He said he was convinced that the two
were a pair. Both had yellow split rings, the male had the ring on the right
leg and the female had the ring on the left leg,he said. He added that the
bird with the ring on its right leg had been singing for a couple of weeks -
this was early in February.
On arriving home I placed the two birds in a flight in my birdroom. The
flight is 8ft long x 4ft wide x 6ft high (approx. 2.4m long x 1.2m wide x 1.8m
high), as are all the flights in my birdroom. The birdroom is equipped with
daylight lighting tubes, tubular heaters and has ionisers. I decided to try to
breed all my softbills indoors in the birdroom so that I am able to control the
lighting and heating all year round. The Chestnut-backed Thrushes were in
one flight on their own and the Magpie Robins were in the next flight. I also
have outside flights but thought that the Chestnut-backed Thrushes being
tropical ground thrushes would do better indoors than, for example, the Black-
breasted or Grey-backed Thrush Turdus dissimilis. At the beginning of March
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.580853" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260773" page_num="151" year="" vol="">
BRALSFORD - CHESTNUT-BACKED THRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998526" page_id="56260773"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
151
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998045809523809" page_id="56260773"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
I put up a Sin x Sin (12.7cm x 12.7cm) nesting platform, consisting of a
bracket-type ledge with holes drilled into the overhang at the front, into
which I put conifer cuttings to provide cover. In various parts of the flight I
also put up salad racks with coconut fibre, dried grasses, dog combings and
other animal hair. Nothing happened for a few weeks, during which the
male was hiding on the platform well away from the female. In late April I
decided to put up a large open-fronted nest-box. I then saw a lot more
activity, with the birds becoming more vocal and one starting to feed the
other. To my surprise, the so-called male, the bird with the ring on its right
leg, was the one being fed by the other bird. The bird doing the feeding
must therefore, I decided, be the male. This bird had a lovely, but not very
loud song, and sang from its chest. The female sang loudly, and like a
thrush does, sang with its beak and tongue going 'ten to the dozen.' I decided
to provide some leaves, mud and fresh grass cuttings. By then it was the
beginning of May and according to my book on thrushes, they should start
breeding from early May. The female was being fed by the male with
waxworms on a regular basis and I put in the flight a large tub of compost
buried in which were mealworms.
By May 17th the female had started building a nest in the half-open-
fronted nest-box. She used just coconut fibre and finished off with leaves.
No mud was used in the construction of the nest, which was completed by
May 23rd. The female started to sit on May 24th and sat for five days or so
before leaving the nest. When I checked there were no eggs in the nest.
Apparently thrushes warm and shape the nest for a few days before egg
laying. May 27th the female was sitting tightly and the male was feeding
her on the nest. Before entering the box with food, the male made low
piping calls to her. When the female came off the nest I noticed she was
swollen around the vent, so I was sure she had started laying. She laid three
eggs and sat for 14 days. According to my records, two chicks hatched after
15 days and the other egg was clear. I provided the parents with waxworms,
earthworms and crickets, and also buffalo worms. All other foods were
ignored, apart from the softfood mix which had dried insects in it.
When they were five days old both chicks were thrown out of the nest.
The chicks appeared well fed and I could not understand why they had been,
ejected. The male continued going to the empty nest with beakfuls of worms.
I rang a friend who breeds thrushes and he suggested that the problem could
have been caused by e. coli. Anyway, two weeks later the female was sitting
again. When she came off the nest I checked it and another three eggs were
present. These hatched after 15 days. The first seven days I fed just
earthworms and waxworms then introduced crickets later. I am sure that
the amount of waxworms was the key and played a big part in this success.
About 2,000 waxworms were taken and about 2kg (41bs 6ozs) of earthworms.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997994" page_id="56260774"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
152
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.361750666666667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260774" page_num="152" year="" vol="">
BRALSFORD - CHESTNUT-BACKED THRUSH
Gary Bralsford
Adult Chestnut-backed Thrush.
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993281416666666" page_id="56260774"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
After 14 days in the nest the two chicks emerged and were smaller, duller
versions of the parents. I continued with the livefood for another 14 days
and when the young were 28 days old I put rings on them and placed them
in a 7ft (approx. 2.1m) breeder to moult out. The parents went back to nest
twice more. With the third brood the chicks were again thrown out of the
nest at five days old, while with the fourth nest one egg was clear and the
chick that hatched survived until it was six days old.
Then in late September the pair went to nest again. There were again
three eggs from which two chicks hatched. I again supplied just earthworms
and waxworms. At the time of writing (October 2003) two chicks have
again fledged and are 22 days old. So, to date four chicks have been reared
and I am going to stop the parents nesting again until next year (2004).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.581063" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260775" page_num="153" year="" vol="">
BRALSFORD - CHESTNUT-BACKED THRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.9996" page_id="56260775"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
153
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.992542827586207" page_id="56260775"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
When I contacted Dave Coles, he told me that it is the first recorded captive
breeding of this species. The Chestnut-backed Thrush is a lovely bird. It
has the crown to the nape and mantle black; the wings are also black, with
white wing bars. The face is black and white, the chin is black and there is
black spotting on the breast. The rump is chestnut. The young have similar
markings, but these are duller and they are more browner on the breast instead
of white. Having bred four young, I am now on the look-out for fresh blood
to pair back to my youngsters. My adult pair was part of a shipment of birds
from Timor, Flores and neighbouring islands.
Breeding thrushes is very challenging and is very rewarding if you have
luck on your side. Breeding my birds in inside flights has definitely worked
for me. The heating and lighting can be controlled, except when the hot sun
overheats the birdroom, when I can fit a wire-mesh door and put in fans. I
know that a lot of continental European breeders use the indoor breeding
method with more success than many UK breeders.
This year I have also bred six White-eared Bulbuls Pycnonotus leucotis,
seven Chinese Greenfinches Carduelis sinica and 10 Red-crested Cardinals
Paroaria coronata, as well as having near misses with my Japanese Robins
Erithacus akahige, Shamas, Yellow-throated Buntings Emberiza elegans,
Red-headed Tits Aegithalos concinnus and Chinese Zosterops Zosterops
palpebrosa. So I will continue with this method in 2004. All my breedings
have been witnessed by members of the Foreign Bird League.
As described above, the Chestnut-backed Thrush Zoothera dohertyi,has
been bred by Gary Bralsford. This is thought to be the first successful
breeding of this species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who knows of
a previous breeding is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
Gary Bralsford is a new member of the society who lives in Yorkshire.
He has also submitted accounts of breeding the White-eared Bulbul
Pycnonotos leucotis and Red-crested Cardinal Paroaria coronata.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999704" page_id="56260776"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
154
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.894433" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260776" page_num="154" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE BEARDED BARBET Lybius dubius AT
DISNEY'S ANIMAL KINGDOM
by Susan Congdon
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994316794117647" page_id="56260776"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
At the heart of the Pan gam Forest Exploration Trail at Disney's Animal
Kingdom (DAK), Florida, is an aviary housing African birds. Amongst
these is a striking species of barbet, the Bearded Barbet Lybius dubius. The
following is an account of DAK's parent-rearing and hand-rearing successes
with this species.
Natural history
Barbets are part of the diverse Order Piciformes, which also includes
toucans, honey guides and woodpeckers. Barbets are found in the Neotropics
and African and Asian tropics. Mostly fruit-eaters, they will supplement
their diet with insects when chicks are present. Most excavate nesting cavities
in dead trees, and these cavities may also be used for roosting.
Barbets have long been popular avicultural subjects, and a member of
the barbet family is sure to fit the theme of most exhibits. With its spectacular
coloration and incredibly active personality, the Bearded Barbet is an
especially fascinating species to display in an aviary. Coloured red, yellow
and black, this West African species uses its sharp, serrated-edged beak for
eating fruits growing on fruiting trees.
Very little is known about the breeding habits of the Bearded Barbet.
Except for allopreening and tail flicking, no descriptions of courtship
behaviour or nesting in the wild could be found. The Bearded Barbet has
been reported to lay a clutch of two white eggs (Short and Home, 2001), but
our pair fledged three chicks in 2002. Also, there was speculation that the
Bearded Barbet might be among species in which helpers (offspring from
earlier nests) assist their parents raise subsequent broods. This was confirmed
when the 2001 chick was observed entering the nest the following year and
feeding the 2002 chicks once they had fledged.
Enclosure and diet
The walk-through African aviary is approximately 50m long x 20m wide
x 14m high (approx. 162ft long x 62ft wide x 45ft high). It is divided into
two distinct sections. The first of these is densely planted with various
tropical African trees, shrubs and other plants. The trees are tall and
effectively help to disguise the view of the wire mesh at the top of the aviary.
The second section contains a pond that is fed by a two-story waterfall. The
first waterfall pool is approximately 9.1mx6.1mxl .5m deep (30ft x 20ft x
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.947822">
5ft deep). The second is a large pond that is approximately 15.2m x 6 dm
</footnote>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.835574" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260777" page_num="155" year="" vol="">
CONGDON- BEARDED BARBET
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999283" page_id="56260777"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
155
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.988494073170732" page_id="56260777"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
(50ft x 20ft). The guest (visitor) walkway forms a bridge over the pond and
visually divides it into two, though waterfowl can swim beneath it. There
are no trees directly over the pond to allow more light to reach this area.
The back of the aviary is formed by a gunnite wall that is approximately
3.7m tall x 2.1m wide (12ft tall x 7ft wide). The height and design of the
aviary has created three distinct zones: the forest floor, sub-canopy and
canopy.
The Bearded Barbets currently share the exhibit with approximately 120
other individuals of 32 species. These include Amethyst or Violet-backed
Starlings Cinnyricinclus leucogaster, Superb Starlings Lamprotornis
(formerly Spreo ) superbus , Golden-breasted Starlings L. or Cosmopsarus
regius , Wattled Starlings Creatophora cinerea, Hammerkops Scopus
umbretta. White-headed Buffalo Weavers Dinemellia dinemelli and Magpie
Shrikes Urolestes melanoleucus. There are ten feeding stations throughout
the aviary that are utilized by the Bearded Barbets, five on the upper level
and five on the lower level. There are mixed species bowls comprised of
chopped mixed fruit, soaked Mazuri(R) parrot breeder and small bird breeder
pellets, greens, carrots, seeds and Bevo(R)(a commercial insectivore diet).
One of these mixed species bowls also contains Toronto(R) carnivore diet.
The Bearded Barbets also favour the chunks of fresh fruit that are spiked on
branches to provide enrichment. Food bowls are also placed daily in several
built-in trap cages to acclimate the birds to going in and out of these. They
are used when there is the need capture birds and are also used to introduce
new birds into the aviary.
There are many nest-boxes positioned throughout the aviary. There are
also several sections of dead palm tree that have been placed at different
elevations. In addition, the aviary contains numerous large pieces of deadfall
that are suitable for species that bore their own nest cavities.
Breeding
Disney's Animal Kingdom introduced two pairs of Bearded Barbets into
the African aviary in May 1998. By July, all four birds were observed
removing shavings from the same nest-box. They went on to do this with
several different boxes and palm logs but no eggs were laid. In late 1998,
one of the females died and in early 1999 a male disappeared and was not
seen again. No aggression had been observed within the group.
In early 1999 the remaining pair had excavated a cavity in a palm log
and were displacing other species from the area. The pairs' courtship
behaviour often consisted of the male feeding the female, tail flicking by
both sexes, and a raspy bark-like vocalization by the male. During the 1999
breeding season the pair laid four clutches of eggs over a five-month period.
Each time eggs were laid, they disappeared from the nest. One disappeared
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999605" page_id="56260778"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
156
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.932147" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260778" page_num="156" year="" vol="">
CONGDON- BEARDED BARBET
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987724037037037" page_id="56260778"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
just five days from hatching. A video camera was set up and showed the
female carrying an egg out of the nest; she was carrying it in her beak.
Unfortunately the male was found dead in October, but luckily the two eggs
that were in the nest (see photo below) were removed and the chicks were
successfully hand-reared. A detailed account of the hand-rearing is given
later in this paper.
Greg Bockheim
Two eggs in palm log.
In February 2000 a new male was acquired to pair with the female and
was introduced to her in May. By June the two were observed tail flicking
and spending time near the same palm log. By September 2000 a piece of
rotten deadfall that extended over a pond was being excavated. In May
2001 we believed that the birds were incubating, but the log was too deep
and narrow to be able to see inside. On May 12th the adults were observed
participating in an insect feeding. The presence of a chick was confirmed
on June 21st and by July 1st the chick was beginning to put its head out of
the nest. The chick fledged on July 13th. Using Zoogen(R) sexing it was later
determined to be a female.
In September of that year the pair as well as the juvenile female were
observed drilling into palm logs, nest-box fronts, deadfall, and even the
wooden cupola of a building. Early March 2002, the three were often
observed entering the nest cavity that was used in 2001. At the beginning of
April, there was one bird in the nest cavity most of the time. This was often
the female chick from the 2001 clutch. On April 20th the adults were
observed carrying insects to the nest. By April 30th, they were taking mostly
fruit to the nest. Because the cavity was 52cm (1ft 8 V 2 in) long and the
opening was only 5.4cm (fractionally over 2in) in diameter, it was impossible
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.835581" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260779" page_num="157" year="" vol="">
CONGDON- BEARDED BARBET
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999163" page_id="56260779"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
157
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9913871" page_id="56260779"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
to see all the way down into it. On May 14th a chick was seen sticking its
beak out of the nest cavity, and by May 19th it had fledged.
Until then it was believed that as in 2001 we had just one chick. However,
on May 20th a second chick was identified. During this time the adults had
frequently been observed entering a palm log in another part of the aviary.
On May 22nd a third chick was located in this palm log. It was slightly
smaller and was believed to be the youngest. It was thought to have fledged
from the same nest as the other two and had taken cover in the palm log. We
hypothesize that the presence of the 2001 chick assisting with the rearing,
increased the pair's ability to raise all three chicks. She was observed
numerous times entering the nest and also feeding the chicks once they had
fledged.
By June the adults were again drilling into various areas of the aviary.
In March 2003, the pair was on several occasions observed feeding each
other and tail flicking. Two of the 2002 chicks were females and one was a
male. The group of six was kept in the aviary to see if they would act as
helpers this year. No aggression towards the offspring by the adults was
seen, unlike at St Louis Zoo, where aggression towards a male offspring by
the adults was reported (pers. comm.). On April 16th of this year (2003) our
male offspring was found dead, but the cause of death could not be determined
due to decomposition. The pair and its three female offspring remain in the
aviary and move about as a group.
Hand-rearing
June 24th 1999, two eggs were removed from the African aviary and
placed in a Grumbach incubator in DAK's nursery. Following a 20 day
incubation period both eggs hatched without any problems. The chicks
were housed in a bowl lined with paper towels and placed in an AICU (Avian
Intensive Care Unit) to simulate the nest environment. Using forceps they
were fed pieces of soaked Mazuri(R) parrot breeder, chopped pinkies and
chopped fruit. All the pieces of food were soaked and dipped in Pedialyte(R).
We began with 50% pinkies, 25% pellets and 25% fruit, and modified these
percentages as the chicks grew. Further details are provided in the
accompanying table (p. 160).
Chick development
Both chicks developed at a consistent rate. Strong gape responses and
vocalizations were present from day one. Feeding was made difficult by
the chicks' rapid head movements and eagerness to eat. Feather tracts on
the wings and the pin feathers of the tail were already emerging on day one.
Yellow pin feathers on the chest were emerging by day 14. The eye-slits
were formed by day 10 and both eyes were open by day 15. The areas of
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994009" page_id="56260780"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
158
</page>
<figure confidence="0.7176606" page_id="56260780"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
CONGDON- BEARDED BARBET
Greg Bockheim
Heel pad of six-day old chick.
Greg Bockheim
Chick aged 10 days old eating a piece of newborn mouse.
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.830933" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260781" page_num="159" year="" vol="">
CONGDON- BEARDED BARBET
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.988001" page_id="56260781"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
159
</page>
<figure confidence="0.979332333333333" page_id="56260781"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
Greg Bockheim
Chick showing signs of dehydration.
Bearded barbet chick weights
Chick 1
*- Chick 2
Age in days
</figure>
<tableCaption confidence="0.998252">
Table 1. Care and development of hand-reared chicks days 1-42.
</tableCaption>
<page confidence="0.990862" page_id="56260782"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
160
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.595112" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260782" page_num="160" year="" vol="">
CONGDON- BEARDED BARBET
Development ]
</sectionHeader>
<listItem confidence="0.381521333333333" page_id="56260782"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
1 Feather tracts on wings, pin feathers of tail !i
Feather tracts on legs and head
Faeces encapsulated in faecal sac
] Pin feathers emerging on back and tail ]
Back, primaries and tail pin feathers emerging
 |Bill tip turning yellow, eyelids formed \
Yellow cast to eyelids and tail
! Yellow pin feathers on chest, feather tracts on body jj
i Both eyes open i
</listItem>
<figure confidence="0.80852323255814" page_id="56260782"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
Tail pin feathers unfurling f
Chick out of nest within AICU
1 Beginning to self-feed |
j Beginning to fly jj
Completely self-feeding
Brooder
u
m A
&amp; #
]Q m
ON w
U
a? ^
"*&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
ON w
6 s
o
* ^
U
o
as
S?o U
* fo
ON C
U
0
r &amp;apos;V
&lt;N r )
r
fe 00
o ri
# C,
G
o
ON
00
&lt;N
o
00
o
o
as
00
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.903910615384615" page_id="56260782"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
(N
Ph
o
T sf
OO
77*F (25*C)
U
o
CN
Ph
o
O
r-
</equation>
<table confidence="0.922866529411765" page_id="56260782"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
 |Feedings j
9 times a day,
every 2 hours 15 mins
8 times a day,
every 2 hours 20 mins
7 times a day,
every 2 hours 30 mins
6 times a day,
every 3 hours
5 times a day,
every 3 hours 30 mins
4 times a day,
Every 3 hours 45 mins
3 times a day,
every 4 hours
Diet
50% finely chopped pinkies, 25%
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.953010133333333" page_id="56260782"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
soaked Mazuri parrot breeder pellets,
25% diced grape, papaya, banana
same as above but size of pieces
increased
same as above
same as above
same as above
same as above
same as above but size of pinkies
decreased
40% pinkies, 35% soaked Mazuri
breeder pellets, 25% chopped fruit
30% pinkies, 35% pellets,
30% fruit (with the addition of apple)
same as above
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.946790529411765" page_id="56260782"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
1 tea S
-
m
VO
OC
ON
o
&lt;N
m
NO
OO
20
28
o
33
\C
37
</figure>
<page confidence="0.9694" page_id="56260782"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
42
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.835604" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260783" page_num="161" year="" vol="">
CONGDON- BEARDED BARBET
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998611" page_id="56260783"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
161
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.947344090909091" page_id="56260783"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
thick, rough skin below the tarsometatarsal joints were becoming less
prominent by day 18. These heel pads (see photo p. 158) are an adaptation
possessed by the chicks of many species that are hatched in unlined nest
cavities. On day 28 the chicks were found perched on the edge of the bowl
and were found out of the nest cup completely by day 30. The chicks also
began eating on their own around day 30 and were completely self-feeding
by day 37. Deep guttural vocalizations, similar to those of the adults, were
heard by day 31. The chicks began to fly on day 36. On day 38 they were
moved from the AICU to a large standing cage.
Greg Bockheim
Newly fledged young barbet.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.7014">
Medical
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985251454545455" page_id="56260783"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
Around day 11 both chicks appeared dehydrated. Their skin was flaky
and sloughing off and also around that time the cloacal area was very dirty
with dried faeces and had to be cleaned at each feed. We began giving them
0.5cc of fluids orally for a few days until the hydration problem was resolved.
Around day 27 we began to see undigested food,mostly newborn mice, in
their faeces. Prokura(R) was prescribed by the veterinarians and was added to
the food to aid digestion. Around that time we observed that the chicks had
a strong preference towards fruit and pellets. By day 35 they were all but
refusing the parts of newborn mice and eating only pellets and fruit.
Even though the chicks were housed on what we considered an
appropriate substrate, on several occasions we noted that they had splayed
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998723" page_id="56260784"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
162
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.932956" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260784" page_num="162" year="" vol="">
CONGDON- BEARDED BARBET
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.863881333333333" page_id="56260784"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
legs. However, their legs and stance developed normally without any
intervention. This was also noted by Parr (1996) when raising Flame-fronted
Barbets Megalaima armillaris.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.884315" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56260784" page_num="162" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.879028" page_id="56260784"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
This paper would not have been possible without the detailed daily
observations of the aviary staff. Special thanks to former DAK aviary keeper
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.944367428571429" page_id="56260784"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
Greg Bockheim, current Director,Potowatomi Zoo, Indiana, for the photos.
Commercially manufactured foods
Bevo Insectivore Diet: Manufactured in Belgium, distributed by All Bird Supply. Tel:(305)
597-0640; Birds to Grow. Tel: (209) 869-5900.
Mazuri parrot breeder 56A9 and Mazuri small bird breeder: Purina Mills Speciality Group,
PO. Box 66812, St Louis, MO 63166-6812, USA. Tel: (314) 768-4592.
Toronto Carnivore Diet: Toronto, Canada. Tel: (416) 869-5900.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.647729" genericHeader="references" page_id="56260784" page_num="162" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.9956308">
Parr, K. 1996. Breeding the Flame-fronted Barbet. afa Watchbird 23,6:30-35.
Short, L. L. and Home, J. F. M. 2001. Toucans, Barbets and Honeyguides . Oxford University
Press, Inc., New York, USA.
Susan Congdon is an Aviary Keeper at Disney&amp;apos;s Animal Kingdom, PO.
Box 10,000, Lake Buena Vista, Florida 32830-1000, USA.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.992452" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260785" page_num="163" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE BLUE-CROWNED MOTMOT AT
RIYERBANKS ZOO AND BOTANICAL GARDEN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998725" page_id="56260785"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
163
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.965463675675676" page_id="56260785"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
by Elizabeth Prouse
The Blue-crowned Motmot Momotus momota is a beautiful, arboreal
bird that has a rather large, robust body with large areas of bright green and
blue plumage. The descriptive part of the common name comes from the
crown of brilliant blue feathers that adorn its head. However, its most
distinctive feature is the long, racquet-like tail that strikes back and forth
like a pendulum and often pauses at the height of each swing. This peculiar
behaviour serves as a form of communication and is usually accompanied
by a faint "tick-tock" vocalization. Its range covers most of Central and
South America, from humid rainforests to arid, evergreen woodlands. It
also frequents plantations, orchards, and even coastal beaches. Fortunately,
most of its native land is protected, and it is not threatened.
The Blue-crowned Motmot is a popular zoological exhibit. Zoos of the
American Zoo and Aquarium Association (AZA) currently maintain a total
population of about 80 of these birds, all of which are managed through an
AZA approved studbook. Based on these data, birds can be selectively
paired through a Population Management Plan to help maintain the genetic
diversity of the population.
Aviary design
The Bird Conservation Center (BCC) at Riverbanks Zoo is home to a
genetically valuable pair of wild-caught Blue-crowned Motmots. Both birds
were acquired from separate sources in 2000 and moved to the BCC in
2001. Neither of these birds had bred in captivity, making any offspring
they produced an important addition to the managed population. The pair is
housed in an indoor aviary that is 15ft long x 3ft wide x 8ft high (approx.
4.5m long x 1m wide x 2.4m high). The aviary is one of 28 enclosures that
comprise the BCC. All have concrete floors and are well lit by several rows
of fluorescent lights. The tubes are the standard white type, rather than the
full-spectrum lighting of the type used for plants and aquaria. However,
clerestory and large windows along the walls allow exposure to natural
sunlight. To optimize breeding, a temperature of 75*F (23.9*C) and up to
80% relative humidity is maintained year-round.
Diet
Our birds are provided with fresh food twice a day. This consists of
chopped fruit covered in Marion Zoological Tropical Bits(TM) pellets, hard-
boiled egg, Hills Science Diet Canine Maintenance(TM) kibble (soaked
overnight) and Nebraska Brand(TM) bird of prey meat. Livefood such as
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999226" page_id="56260786"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
164
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.525017" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260786" page_num="164" year="" vol="">
PROUSE - BLUE-CROWNED MOTMOT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996257857142857" page_id="56260786"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
earthworms, large mealworms and lin (26mm) crickets are also provided.
The crickets and mealworms have for several days before use been fed a
diet of Purina Game Bird Chow(R). This chow is high in calcium and helps
ensure that the livefood achieves a more balanced calcium to phosphorous
ratio (2:1), as well as improving the overall nutritional content. Motmots
do not usually drink from or bathe in standing water. Therefore, they benefit
from a short misting with the water hose every day to help keep them clean
and well hydrated.
Artificial nest tunnels
Even with the favourable artificial climate we have created, it was
doubtful that a pair of wild-caught motmots could be persuaded to breed in
an enclosure of the type described above. In the wild, motmots dig a tunnel
in the forest floor or the embankment of a stream, and this leads to an
underground nesting burrow. The concrete floor of the aviary met none of
the motmots' breeding requirements. Nevertheless, the birds expressed a
desire to nest by excavating soil from the large potted plants that furnished
the aviary.
Eager to accommodate their nesting needs, keepers gathered a few ideas
from other zoos and designed an artificial nest site comprising three tunnels
which terminate at a nest-box. Built entirely within the aviary, the tunnel
system occupies about 15% of the space. The tunnels are made of 5in
(approx. 13cm) diameter corrugated drainage pipes of the kind used for
landscaping. The pipes are attached to a Vdn thick x 4ft high x 3ft wide
(approx. 7mm thick x 1.2m high x lm wide) piece of plywood positioned
vertically and fixed across the aviary. The plywood is covered with mesh
and impregnated with coloured stucco to give the appearance of a mud bank.
Tree roots have been inserted into the fake mud to provide perches and
complete the effect. The drainage pipes extend from the artificial mud bank
to the wooden nest-box which measures 1ft x 1ft x 1ft (approx. 30cm x
30cm x 30cm). The box is fastened to the back of the aviary at a level which
creates only a slight downward slope of less than 1 in (25 mm) per foot (30cm),
from the tunnel entrance to the end of the tunnel. Two of the tunnels, each
3ft (almost lm) in length, merge into one tunnel at a Y-shaped junction,
before connecting to the front side of the box. The third tunnel is 5ft (approx.
1.5m) long and bends at an angle of 90* before connecting to the adjacent
side of the nest-box. Therefore, three tunnels start at the artificial mud bank,
but only two terminate at the nest-box. All three tunnels are supported by a
2in x 4in (approx. 5cm x 10cm) wood frame and secured with cable ties.
The three pipes are suspended at mid-height in the aviary, allowing the
birds to utilise the airspace above them while at the same time
accommodating the daily routine of hosing and disinfecting the concrete
floor beneath them. In fact, the birds are undisturbed by the hosing of the
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.202774" page_id="56260787"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
PROUSE - BLUE-CROWNED MOTMOT
</equation>
<page confidence="0.998888" page_id="56260787"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
165
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997913714285714" page_id="56260787"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
floor during which one of them remains in the tunnel system. When we first
installed the pipes, both birds spent a lot of time perched on them, essentially
hidden from view. To prevent this, the tunnel system is completely enclosed.
All three tunnels were packed with a mixture of 90% damp top soil and
10% sand. This was packed into the tunnels from the front (through the
artificial bank) and tamped in with a blunt stick. The tunnels were not
completely filled, but sufficient quantities of the mixture were used to provide
the semblance of an earthen bank. The nest-box had been partly filled with
soil when we installed the tunnel system. A large potted ficus tree was
placed in front of the artificial mud bank to give the birds a much needed
sense of privacy. Indeed, the tree was so large it almost filled the aviary.
Following the birds' temporary removal for completion of the tunnel
system, the pair was returned to the aviary. On the first evening the pair
began digging in the far left tunnel. Within a week, all three tunnels had
been excavated. The birds travelled in and out, rarely exiting by the same
tunnel by which they had entered. Then, as abruptly as they had started,
they stopped digging. The birds ignored the burrows, seemingly having
become disinterested in nesting.
The pair was observed sitting beside its apparently abandoned nest burrow
for one month before it was noted one day that the female was missing. We
now know that she had disappeared into the nest to begin laying her first
clutch of eggs. It is not uncommon for motmots in the wild to prepare their
burrows in September-October, several months before nesting, which usually
occurs between February-June. This is thought to be because the ground is
so much softer in the wet season than in the dry breeding season.
Incubation and chick rearing
Blue-crowned Motmots usually lay between two and four white, rounded
eggs, but may lay as many as five. Incubation is shared equally by both
sexes. The male was observed to be sitting during the day, while the female
took the evening shift. Consequently, they also ate in shifts. Throughout
the incubation the two birds were rarely seen together. There was always
one in and one out of the tunnel. Then, on the 18th day of incubation, a
significant change was observed in the pair's behaviour. Both parents
disappeared for several minutes at a time, spending most of this time together
inside the nest. It appeared that at least one chick had hatched. The following
day, however, they spent most of their time outside the nest and we began to
question whether any chicks had actually hatched?
We were soon reassured when food consumption increased. The preferred
rearing food was pinky mice, but lin (25mm) crickets, medium-sized
mealworms, and earthworms dusted with calcium carbonate were also
eagerly accepted. As they fed frequently, fresh food was offered every two
hours throughout the day. During the first week, both parents took 10-15
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998911" page_id="56260788"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
166
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.531495" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260788" page_num="166" year="" vol="">
PROUSE - BLUE-CROWNED MOTMOT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997541147058823" page_id="56260788"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
pinky mice daily, beating them on a perch or the concrete floor before
delivering them to the chicks. They began feeding small amounts of fruit
on day 13. Soon thereafter, pinky mice and livefood consumption doubled
and we became unsure of how many mouths were being fed. On day 24,
food consumption dropped significantly as the parents withheld food to
encourage the chicks to fledge.
The first chick fledged at 28 days of age; a second chick followed one
day later. Both were healthy, were brilliantly coloured and could fly
surprisingly well at their first attempts. They had slightly thinner bodies
than their parents and had almost identical plumage to that of their parents,
the only obvious difference being their short, stubby tails.
The two young motmots were extremely timid and easily frightened.
As it is easy for young birds to permanently injure their bills and damage
flight feathers if they collide with the wire mesh or other objects, the keepers
approached the aviary very carefully when cleaning and feeding; and for
the first few days we did not clean the floor.
The chicks weaned quickly. Two weeks after fledging, they were
separated from their parents and assigned separate enclosures that had been
prepared in advance. Each was well planted and provided plenty of hiding
places. The wire mesh was covered with Enkamat(TM) (a plastic erosion control
material used in landscaping) to protect the birds from potential collisions
with the wire mesh. Their plumage remained in excellent condition and
over several weeks their tails grew to the same length as those of the adults.
As their tails brushed against the foliage and perches, a small section of
weak barbs near the tips of their tails broke off, leaving the racquet-shaped
tips for which motmots are so well known.
A second pair of Blue-crowned Motmots has since bred in the natural-
like setting of The Birdhouse at Riverbanks. This pair dug a burrow in the
soil floor of the South American exhibit and followed the same behavioural
patterns as the pair that bred in the BCC. While both breedings are notable,
the breeding in the BCC is more significant in our estimation because the
pair bred successfully in a small, indoor, concrete-floored aviary. In view
of this, it is our opinion that almost any facility has the capability to breed
this species.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.949999" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56260788" page_num="166" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.6132766" page_id="56260788"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
I would like to thank all the members of the Bird Department for their
considerable help in the preparation of this article.
Elizabeth Prouse is a Bird Keeper at Riverbanks Zoo &amp; Botanical Garden,
PO. Box 1060, Columbia, South Carolina 29202-1060, USA. Website:
www.riverbanks .org
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.973245" page_id="56260789"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
167
</page>
<figure confidence="0.8121966" page_id="56260789"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
A HISTORY OF THE GENUS Picathartes IN CAPTIVITY,
1948-2002
by Marvin L. Jones
Copyright Zoological Society of London
Picathartes gymnocephalus at London Zoo in 1957.
</figure>
<page confidence="0.984038" page_id="56260790"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
168
</page>
<figure confidence="0.920137807692308" page_id="56260790"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
JONES - GENUS PICATHARTES
CQ
3 ^
X) #
o
4) OV
Cu oo
to ov
4)
&amp;quot;S On
--I 00
03 oo
a
4 ) 4&amp;gt; O
&amp; &amp; *
ST 3 O
C2 # 5
a *.g
"4H X
O 3 -s
-o 00 &amp; 1
o # ^
4&amp;gt; Cfl
p O 33
t-c t&amp;apos;-&amp;apos; 3
0^3
c ft.
i?*
&amp;gt;v ^ J
c
4&amp;gt; S Si
fc! .2 ^
3 *2 -D
O P 3
P_ &lt; &lt;*&amp;gt;
N 4) 4)
2 "S 5
3
OD --;
3 VO
&amp;apos;$ 2
.S 2
^ op
3 #
u g
x d o-
4-h 3
o .g
g o 33
&amp;apos;O (D 0)
'S 3 &amp;apos;&amp;quot;3
CO
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.953267428571429" page_id="56260790"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
c3 O
* J 2 Q
&lt;u S o
x
o o
PQ 2
&lt;2 o
o o
d N
_ *-i
O cd
O cd
N S
&amp; 3
4&amp;gt; cd
* #
C * -
&lt; *n
.. o
3f Q
vo 2
ON O
--I o
Vi N
3
3 2
P d
o
o
N
p
&lt;3
#
o
o
N
&amp; 1
4)
#
O
c
N
g co
# 4
o
to *
&lt;u N
o ^
Vh
</equation>
<page confidence="0.59383" page_id="56260790"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
3
</page>
<figure confidence="0.6006775" page_id="56260790"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
2
3
</figure>
<page confidence="0.745018" page_id="56260790"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
3
</page>
<equation confidence="0.984079235294118" page_id="56260790"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
PQ Q
c -- 1
O
o g
P o
M ,V-l
o d.
rJ x
O o)
O # O 4&amp;gt; O
o ^
r- VO
# (N
&lt;Z3 33
&lt;10
x&amp;gt; o'
# o'
</equation>
<page confidence="0.749272" page_id="56260790"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
3
</page>
<figure confidence="0.992835291666667" page_id="56260790"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
&lt;
C/3
&lt;D
&lt;
*--\0x25A0
&lt;
t/3
#
#
^t-
O
Ov
VO
Ov
cn
3l&amp;quot; g
&amp;apos;d -
&amp;quot;d -
VO
C/D
r-
4)
VO -g
VO
VO
OV
&lt;D
ov
3
OV 33
Ov
Ov
&amp;gt;
O
3
Kj
.s
' 5-(
o
4)
fli
o
^2
3 |
3
cd
3
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;
</figure>
<page confidence="0.914305" page_id="56260790"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
33
</page>
<equation confidence="0.954993857142857" page_id="56260790"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
O
X
S * O
2 33 o
P 3 --
3
4&amp;gt; ,3
&amp; a
% 1
f #
. r~-
4) vo
OV
o ,
, # o
dd 4&amp;gt; _
&amp;quot;o ^ U
n ^ 3
! 8
_ VO
o 2
</equation>
<page confidence="0.837739" page_id="56260790"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
33
</page>
<figure confidence="0.859270416666667" page_id="56260790"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
* .2
go 33
" O
X --&lt;
# o'
oo
s I -i
&amp;gt;S11
00 o 3
# Z #
S 2 S
S " **
</figure>
<page confidence="0.492038" page_id="56260790"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
3
</page>
<equation confidence="0.836014489795918" page_id="56260790"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
\0x25A0g &amp;quot;S
X &amp;apos;o
l-S S
2 S &amp;gt;
33 #&lt; 2 !
2 # 2
d 8 f
O 1/3
# 8
e ,
t c
sr cs
O
o
N 4)
Id u
4) &amp;gt;
&amp;gt; p
u
PQ
5 0 3
^ &amp;gt;
g o
^ #
3 4)
&amp;gt;, # ^
1 5*
PQ
33
2 O PQ
X X
\0x25A0B ^ ^
PQ 4) M
e ^ .#
g O C
*d ^ PQ
c ^ #
&amp;gt; -g o
# " S
O 3 &amp;gt;
# -o o
N N
g S
i 2
sg
&amp;!
oo Z
poo
o' o o'
</equation>
<figure confidence="0.987083020547945" page_id="56260790"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
o N
CO
# &lt;
o
oC
_. m
^3 Ov
O
o
o
O
O
o
O
N
C/3
4)
N
o
N
o
N
O
N
o
N
p
a
M
C
OO
P
,3
T3
P
a
P
a
M
P
a
a
-x
s
cd
PQ
3
P
PQ
3
3
&amp;apos;-H
PQ
3
3
PQ
3
3
\X
3
cd
lx
3
X
3
3
*--
PQ
CN
3
VO
vO
Ov
oo
3j-
no
3
vO
VO
Ov
4)
33
3
#
3
4)
vO
Ov
Ov
VO
Ov
S-i
Q
VO
Ov
o
3
C/5
o
O-i
W)
41
Q
&amp;gt;
o
3
3
C
#
U
PQ
3d
2
4)
OO
33
4)
o
O
#
o
3
&lt;
OV
3
O
o
no
3
o
cd
3J-
d
OO
/VI
CO 3
&amp;apos;S 2 33 |
_ to 33 ^
P
1/3
1 1
33 M
O
o &amp;quot;1 Q S
Hf P d
* &amp;gt; ^ 4)
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.42721" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260791" page_num="169" year="" vol="">
JONES - GENUS PICATHARTES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.939379" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
169
</page>
<figure confidence="0.953282275862069" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
_Q
4)
S &amp;
o
o
N
2
13
2
o
2 ts
m 8
in c /3
vo -
OS 4&lt;S
^ .S
2 pq
o rt
G
G
&amp;gt;
^ s
2 g
(c) ^
'-H 42
2 #
A* S 3
pq
o
</figure>
<page confidence="0.993965" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.302788" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56260791" page_num="169" year="" vol="">
Q
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99632" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<table confidence="0.273519" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
In 8
* 3
</table>
<page confidence="0.980025" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<equation confidence="0.746522444444445" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
is
o
o
I s
T3 Os
O ^
d S
CO
O
C
2 VO
G t&amp;quot;-
.5 os
CO
r~ o
On 1 ?
\0x25A0M ts
43 v--&lt; ~h
Oh 2 ^
G S ^
G (c) 43
bfi
O (c)
N N
&lt;z&amp;gt; "
43 ^
13 13
</equation>
<page confidence="0.30847" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
60
</page>
<figure confidence="0.872259068965517" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
g 5
&lt; &lt;
O O
2 2
r- jo
VD F&amp;quot;
On Ov
pv 43
43 "
oo Q
^ o
6 ^ ^
b 0
o
CO
43 ^
tc \0x25A0&amp;gt;
O G
&amp;, -G
2 &amp;apos;o
Oh 5
g 5
"2 oo
. Os
2 ^
2
O O
O O
N N
8 g&amp;gt;
N *S
* G co
G --H fr!
2 &amp;
# S
43 .P
Z PQ
42 O
^ d
VO ^
SO #
Os Os
#&amp;gt;0 &amp;gt;s
3 2
&lt; s
O co
(N Cl
-a t3
-1 Q
o o
o 2
f *
1 N
2 #
00 o
2 oo
Os os
C/3 2
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.955024868421052" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
VO ^
(N VO
T3 G
43 G
^ 2
p o
--i d
o --
^ Qh
*S3 #
43 43
E- S
1 1
3 g
G #
^ o
- o
2 bO
H--( _
5 I
"S V3
Oh ^
N .ti
Z -a
42 #
&amp;quot;O o
G -C
S &lt;"
43 Oh
2 N
# Z
w
G
o &amp;apos;O
8 9
N |
44 40
Oh 2?
</equation>
<page confidence="0.763955" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<equation confidence="0.821106064516129" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
g
C/3
a
Oh
S #
&amp;gt;&amp;gt; 43
T3 ^
2 oo
*1 00
* d
# S
*!&amp;
2 Z,
40 43
Gh 40
# H
43 +J
2 8
G &amp;
# o
o 43
Oh -
&lt; i
vo 53
rH C/3
G
#
G
O
o &amp;gt;.
Q *g
</equation>
<page confidence="0.954507" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<figure confidence="0.993198588235294" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
PQ
if
Q o
N
c3
||
G g
&lt; 2
in (c)
2 2
1 8
G N
8 g
2 o
^ pq
43 O
g w N
cl!
3 *-H 44
# CO a
G G 2
G 43 pQ
# ^ VO
^O &amp;gt; ^
20 *
IJI
"n ^ m
S 3
m ^
Oh
&lt;
o o
o o
N N
</figure>
<page confidence="0.721417" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<figure confidence="0.99083505882353" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
PQ
s M . s
43 43
PQ pQ
OS
M 21
G ^
# |
G ^
43 CO
TO
H 3 3
g 43 43
g 3 3
^ d
CO ^ hH
dip
d ^ d
N
o &lt;*&amp;gt;
- Q o S
VH ^ N
^ "g ^
C .5 G
43 E C
5S PQ 43
bfi a
&lt; e
c 52
^ I
I p
os
2 a
* c-
</figure>
<page confidence="0.804529" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<figure confidence="0.920791" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
G
o
</figure>
<page confidence="0.802395" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<figure confidence="0.99341225" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
H-l
G
C 43
43 3S
hH ^ hH
O O
O O
N N
</figure>
<page confidence="0.942991" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.358128" genericHeader="introduction" page_id="56260791" page_num="169" year="" vol="">
C/3 M
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.943548" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<figure confidence="0.989207315789474" page_id="56260791"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
in (c) ^
vo 2 VD
os J as
tH ^ tH
bf) G bo
&lt;3
OO c
hh o
PQ &lt;
&amp;gt;
o
- 3 3
# 2 2
P &amp;apos;S -3
-GOO
^ d o
0.0.1 reed ? Berlin Zoo IZN census 1966: Antwerp Zoo 0.0.2; Berlin Zoo 0.0.2;
0.0.1 died 7 Sep 1965 Berlin Zoo Brookfield Zoo 0.0.2; Frankfurt Zoo 1.1.3; Los Angeles Zoo 0.0.2;
Memphis Zoo 0.0.4; St Louis Zoo 0.0.2;
</figure>
<page confidence="0.826459" page_id="56260792"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
170
</page>
<figure confidence="0.947861192893401" page_id="56260792"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
JONES - GENUS PICATHARTES
G
0 )
a
u O
Oh t _ h &amp;apos;
o
o
N
o
too
D
5
G
G
00
NO
NO
ON
I 8
\0x25A0G X)
3 C
03 .^h
n &amp;gt;
O G
1 o
ON &lt;D
r- rG
ON &lt;+H
^ o
* 8
o
o
N
o
toO
CD
-O QQ
o
o
N
o
too
&lt;D
o
o
N
C/5
_CD
&amp; OO
o o
o o
N N
cZ5 c/5
CD JD
O 3
bo too
C G
&lt; &lt;
C/5 C/5
o o
J J
OO 00
NO NO
ON ON
ce
CD
\0x25A08 8
d N
.5 t;
m 3
" 52
C G
CD CO
*a
&lt;N
(c)
d
o
o
N
&amp;
CD
#
CD
&lt;D
M
G
G
3
C/5
JD
G
G
CD
CD
M
&amp;gt;
o
&amp;gt;
o
CD
(D
O
a
o
d
CDN
&amp;gt;
O
ON
3
&lt;D
Q
in
PQ
u
G
a
S
s
ON
Q
o
c
'C
PQ
G
Z
Z
On
Q
o
Z
TO
a
G
o
in
G
G
C/5
a
&lt;N
c
CD
&lt;m
1--1
&lt;N
1--1
cn
no&amp;quot;
&amp;apos;CD
1
in
&lt;
TO
C/5
CD
&lt;3
nO
o
d
G
G
TO
in
&lt;D
#
to
c
ON
C/5
C/I
G
NO
On
&amp;gt;
PQ
G
G
G
M
G
G
TO
CD
2
a
o
cm
O
M
O
#
o
h 0
TO
OD
3
#
o
G
d
TO
OD
3
#
o
G
d
TO
CD
CD
M
&amp;gt;
a
o
TO
0 &amp;gt;
3
X 3
CD
3
T 3
CD
CD
Gh
&lt;
C/5
TO
_(D
3
_o
o
d
TO
a
3
#
o
c
mC
TO
a
3
#
o
c
M
CZ!
G
c/5
G
OD
(c)
G
TO
CD
(c)
C
G
(c)
G
G
cN
3 ,
(N
(D
p
.a
p
c
G
p
G
G
CD
[v ,
x&amp;gt;
#
G
u
G
C/5
d
TO
cd
o
to
o
d
o
#
o
o
p
d
o
*
d
p
o
TO
O
o
TO
o
o
TO
CD
W
o
-1
- G 1
i I 5
&lt;D 2
% 5 &lt;2
*- G U
NO 3 tO
NO c g
On O O
i--i -G CD
. .*j o
k # m
&lt; s -1
&lt;B 'S S
G CN O
G Q O
o o Z
G C
p  |&lt;D
G ^
CD TO
3 3
G O
O o
PQ
C/5
O 3
c PQ
fc S
o
to 3
CD G
CD TO
a i
3 &amp;
o o
d Z
o o
O o
N N
*S .a
&lt;D CD
PQ pg
NO
NO
On
tO TO
O CD
P P
(c) O
o o
o o
o o
N N
-e t;
3 a
1 =
G c3
^ i--H
PQ PQ
NO &lt;N
NO P-
On On
!-i m
Oh CD
c o
Z O
*
o ^
o oo
N
PQ
P x5
3. P
d d
# o
0.2.0 reed 8 Dec 1966 Philadelphia Zoo Brookfield Zoo 1.1.0; Frankfurt Zoo 0.0.7 (cb 0.0.1); Los Angeles Zoo 0.0.3;
wb, from van den Brink (see note p. 168) Memphis Zoo 0.0.3; Monrovia Zoo 6.10.0; Philadephia Zoo 0.0.2;
0.1.0 missing 10 Dec 1970 Philadelphia Zoo St Louis Zoo 0.0.2; Busch Gardens, Tampa 0.0.1; Wassenaar Zoo 1.1.0
0.1.0 died 19 Feb 1977 Philadelphia Zoo
laid eggs 1974/1975 1.1.1 reed 1967 Amsterdam Zoo
</figure>
<address confidence="0.241887">
JONES - GENUS P1CATHARTES
</address>
<page confidence="0.790356" page_id="56260793"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
171
</page>
<figure confidence="0.96500650802139" page_id="56260793"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
o
(c)
Cd
a,
#
O
-- v &amp;quot;
i|
s N
CO
09 ^
0) O
&lt;5 &lt;2
OX) *
c o
=# o
N
&amp;gt;v OO
S ov
(c)
d
o
o
2 N
f 1
4&amp;gt; S3
2 ^
PU
O -r;
2 &lt;3
N PQ
.2 oo
-H VO
&lt;3 ov
cq t*
(c) &amp;apos;O
o &lt;u
2 (c)
d d
o d
oo oo
VO vo
Ov 7 On
-- 1 O --&amp;apos;
too 00
3 &amp;apos;I 3
&lt; &amp;&lt;
oo " on
1 co 1
&amp;N
(c) ^
&lt;L) ^
3 3 .2
33 U 13
~ Q -
2 8 2
O c" o
&amp;.=
&lt;D
#
&lt;
2 &lt;sf
2 Q
-- d
N N
# 2
#3 o
b i
# 2
&lt; "
as d
vo o
2 d
w o
P o
c N
8 g
2 o
N
d
vo
r-H 03
8 I
N 2
.2 .
*&amp;gt; 2
2 g
S 1
So
(c) 33
Q g
O P
O PQ
O . _
N o
2 d
CO
d
o
o
o
o N
d 2 ^
8 55 *
\0x25A02 *3
2 (c) o
&amp; O 34
O 03
O CLh
N -
CQ
2 2 w
OX G, &lt;u
&lt;=? l! o
o 2 ^
N P ^
o o
o o
N N
&lt;D 0)
CQ CQ
ov
vo
Ov
(c) (c)
O 4)
CD 33
o o
d o
O
vO
Ov
G
&lt;D
00
bo
o
CQ
(c) - (c)
O # (D
o O 33
in H (c)
(c) 33 (c)
ex # (c)
3
&lt;D
Q
1 8
d n
*a #
o -a
03
U o 2
^ 2 P
d d d
d ^ d
&lt;o oo
tX) vo
bo tx)
c c
&lt;D JS
bQ c/3
C .cd
.# &lt;
r-
vo
5
o
o
VD
Ov
&lt;u
OJ
&lt;2 #
OV
P
Ov
l-H
C/3
C3 ^
m
v" 1
-Q
dJ
S3
03
Gh
</figure>
<page confidence="0.91319" page_id="56260793"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<figure confidence="0.999258588888889" page_id="56260793"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
C/2
&lt;D
Ph
VO
GX
c
# S
cn
m
PQ
o z
S3
c
S3 C
4)
&lt;u
34 O
PJ
PS
C 'P
P '35
C
cd
S3
cd
4) O
CJ Oh
T3
&amp;gt;
-d
&amp;quot;O
&amp;gt;
# 2
o
#
2
o
#
N N
#
-H
r- o-
Ov Ov
(c)
&lt;D
Jj ^
d d
^ d
(c) (c)
o (U
4) (c)
o (c)
d o
o ^
o oo
N vo
x ^
PQ
Oh -X
&lt; .#
rxi PQ
Ill
R # #
2 2 S
30 rv ^
P u g
&lt; O0 g
^ m ox
OX 1--I
p - p p p
O g 4) 0) 4)
# p (c) (c) (c)
VO d -7 'd
o d p o o
d ^ d d d
o
o
N CN
X Jr
S3 0\
O ^
m S
\0x25A0d o
2 ea
T3 ^3
CO to
S S
O 4)
O O
d d
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.4755694">
wb, Sierra Leone, from van den Brink, Busum 1.0.0 loan 27 Jan 1976 Brookfield Zoo
0.0.1 died 11 Nov 1973 Wassenaar Zoo 1.0.0 died 11 Apr 1976 Brookfield Zoo
1.0.0 died 11 Jun 1979 Philadelphia Zoo
IZY census 1968: Amsterdam Zoo 1.1.1; Antwerp Zoo 0.0.2; Berlin Zoo 0.0.1;
Bronx Zoo 0.0.6; Brookfield Zoo 0.0.2; Frankfurt Zoo 0.0.4 (cb 0.0.1); Koln 0.0.1 reed ? Baltimore Zoo
</reference>
<page confidence="0.99545" page_id="56260794"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
172
</page>
<equation confidence="0.923775675675676" page_id="56260794"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
JONES - GENUS PICATHARTES
o
o
N
o o
o *#
&lt;3 2
G g
Q #
LTi o
tp OO
On on
(c) (c)
o o
(c) -S
. 2 a 2
T3 &lt;U
o c
(c)
^ o
o
_ r-
&lt;n (c)
2P o ^
P no a)
&lt; 2 an
00 d ^
o&lt;
on
o r-
CQ on
I "
O 03
Oh
j |
c/3 (c)
&lt;D _
</equation>
<figure confidence="0.952107466666667" page_id="56260794"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
d o
# d
(c) ^ (c)
.O g .&lt;u
(c) m (c)
d S &lt;=*
O ^ -1
2 O
2 (c)
o
0#j S
8 %
# S
b d
&amp;gt;
</figure>
<page confidence="0.8175" page_id="56260794"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
03
33
</page>
<equation confidence="0.754485738461538" page_id="56260794"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
O
(c) (c)
O
&lt;D
&lt;D c/j
s (c)
(c) b *.
d Oh d
o
O o
N 2
# d
2 -o
# 3
(c) *o
Cu
cq d
., o
d S
(c) N
8 &lt;1
N 3
&amp; 3
 |&amp;
G P
&lt; P
* ~ O
d o
-H o
d N
o 2
O o
N cp
# o
o3 O
"0 S-H
b CQ
&lt;L&amp;gt; W
I ^
J p
&lt; O
_; o
r-- O
os N
^ x
oo G
G O
oo ^H
G CQ
&lt;L&amp;gt; ^
O Qh
" S
3 -h:
00 (c)
p- (R)
o d
(c) #
8 2
N #
# &lt;D
5 s
Hr o&amp;apos;
o d
o ^
_ 3
</equation>
<figure confidence="0.968270628571429" page_id="56260794"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
O Oh
-3 |
.2 d
2 "T
Oh C
1 -i
Cy ^5
a *
eu x:
. ^ o
d g
(c) CQ
o
_ (N
8 P
N o
co O
CD O
2 N
G* *
&lt; S
C/3
J &lt;
Oh
E
#
G
&lt;u
(c)
S-i
G
o
pq
G
2
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.735055266666667" page_id="56260794"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
oi 2
O a)
o d
G t i-|
o &amp;quot;2
bb #
\0x25A0I I
*8 J
2 -
i&amp;gt; O
si
Z rb
On
NO
ON
G O
-- q
(c) N
8 O
s S
CD O
&lt;D (c)
-O ^
o pq
-G
o 2
(c) 8
&lt;D CD
# 2
# #
+3 X5
2 .2
CQ T3
O O
o o
N N
&lt;u c
o 2
.8 ^
1 2
CQ o
., o
d o
S"5
o 2
N ^
&amp; S
% ^
g d
&lt; P
.. o
p o
o o
N
o 2
O 0&amp;gt;
N d
- ^
I 8
T3 ^
</equation>
<figure confidence="0.995378573333334" page_id="56260794"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
s-h ng
3 2
g vo
J ^
o g
On N
' -l X
c" G
D O
C/3 S-h
G CQ
c .
PQ
o d
N o
y S
oi -i
&lt;L) C1|
g&amp;gt; I
3 a
. ^ (D
-O
o os
d O
m C
\0x25A0s &lt;
o P
o
o
N
&amp;
&lt;u
#
o
o
N
&amp;
&lt;D
#
&lt; &lt;
0^0
g 2 o
2 2 o
^ G ,--1
c
o
o
N
&amp;
0)
t&amp;quot;&amp;quot;
On oo
^ C
&amp; d
2 &lt;D
ON ^
2
3 &amp;quot;5b d
&lt;u g &lt;u 2r a)
d S d ^ d
O 2 O O
* H-H * C3
* T3 P TJ *
O O o O
-t3
C/3 &lt;Z3
C
1 I
o 2
&lt;U G
Oh 2
c" ^
a c
d o
\0x25A0o G
C
03 T3
- 03
&lt; m
cn 2
. D #
g (u g
8 d *
&amp; C o
# -^ c
o ^ -
*r -o
PQ #
2
#
G
C o
&lt;D O
2 N
8 .2
&lt;U G
d 2
&lt;/s "
#
G
G
&lt;u
&lt;
&amp;gt;
G
p
o
&lt;u
rG
_o
2
c
G
t/3
&lt;D
Q
CS
G
bo
c
#
c
o
l&amp;gt;
&amp;gt;n
G
c
p
o
ON
ON
&lt;u ^
&amp;o (A
W o3
o
on a b
NO X!
On O ^3
2 .8 o
H-H O (U
S3 &lt;D M
y d 2
d 2 &lt;d
G O
o o
o o
N N
S 2
-G T3
O O
</figure>
<figure confidence="0.89703109375" page_id="56260795"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
JONES - GENUS PICATHARTES
*g T3
3 &lt;3
1 6
&lt; &lt;
ON ^ ON
7 (N "
^ ^
^ &amp;apos; O
^ d ~
a,
co
T3 ~
2 d
o N "0
t3 ^ .2
n S "0
&amp;apos;l ^ ^
o 4 &amp;gt; o
d Q d
ON 2J
c (c)
3 &lt;N
d U0
Cl
co
*8 X
ft SS
-c s
(N 3
v- 3
O &lt;D
d Q
4)
13
&amp;quot;O
S #
3 "
bO Hi
Cl
03 "
N
Oh X
N H
# -a
# .1
On G
^ &lt;
11
cn .2
3
g
&lt;u
5 o
.1 .S
\0x25A0i \0x25A0S
$ I
CL Cl
N N
# &amp;apos;Z
^ #
o
ON ON
&amp;quot;0 T3
T3 -
Q g cu cu
2 p &amp;quot;3 d
CN d, '&amp;quot;t &amp;apos;C
dioo
d ^ d d
bfl
3
&lt;
in
(N
t&amp;gt;0 --
Is
d&amp;quot;
OX)
Si
-H (S|
d &lt;N
Cl
CO
T3 ---
2 d
Q N T3
3 ^ .2
fi u T3
^ -X ,
* 3
O &lt;u O
o&amp;apos; Q o
W) 4 )
.2 &amp;quot;g
S I
\0x25A0is bX)
c* (R)
c/3
_ o
r-. x
on pq
OX) S
3 g
&lt; C
o &lt;
(N
3
C
o
*8 2
4 ) c
-o -O
odd
Eod
&lt;u X
11
|5
4)
3 -C
Tt H
03 X)
g #
&amp;gt; o
\0x25A0c c
*S 2
.2 w
d c
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.910391186046511" page_id="56260795"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
O 4)
o -o
N S
O JG
1 $
&lt; 1
S *
(TM) a
t--i G
r- 3
- O
X) r
4)
o
o
o
o
o
o
o
o
o
o
N
N
N
N
N
.o
o
_o
o
_o
c
c
*c
&amp;apos;a
'S
o
o
o
o
o
</equation>
<figure confidence="0.981044560000001" page_id="56260795"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
G
e
G
G
c
&lt;
&lt;
&lt;
&lt;
&lt;
G
c
c
C
G
3
3
3
3
3
00
00
00
00
OO
o
l&amp;gt;
r-~
r-
o
On
ON
On
ON
On
1
T-- 1
l--l
1-H
_Q
Hi
H
4)
42
4)
4)
4&amp;gt;
Ph
PI
Pi
Pi
Pi
CO
3T
d&amp;quot;
&amp;gt;n
OO
4)
tj
(c)
d d
# -
c
o ^
2 o
x -d
I Q
T3
-a
o
d
&amp;apos;--i O O o O
ON
On
OX)
3
&lt;
00
&lt;N
|i
 |Q
^ Q
$ $
Ci Ph
N N
z z
oo o
r- oo
ON ON
c
3 3
^ X
CO CN
o o
(c) W
N G
.2 S
C c"
i ?
3 2 ;
" r-
OO On
ON
o
s o
3 ,_H
4)
00
3
g
O
fi t) " tl c
3 4) C 0) 3
O 1C 4) x O
3h T3 "a T3 3 h
O O &amp;gt;. O O
3 3 d3 * '
\0x25A0 \0x25A0 o * *
0 0 3 0 0
3 O
4) *-
&amp;gt; o
4) a)
# a
^32
^ 4) &lt;tb
00 1 &amp;apos;fl
OO co 3
ON 3 7j
-o X
H H
S i o
5 3 O
3 g N
G3 ,4) O
3 S
3 oo
g C^-
*-* c .2
g u Q
00 x&amp;gt;
d! oo ax
o c OO
.3 ON
-d &amp;gt; d
4) 3 _
Ilf
2 ~
ra Lb
oo Z oo
</figure>
<page confidence="0.608077" page_id="56260795"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
173
</page>
<table confidence="0.459134333333333" page_id="56260795"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
0.0.1 hatched 26 Mar 1971 Amsterdam Zoo TO BE CONCLUDED IN THE NEXT ISSUE
Dekker/ZT 13, pp.120-121
0.0.1 died 4 Apr 1971 Amsterdam Zoo
</table>
<page confidence="0.999568" page_id="56260796"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
174
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.98681" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260796" page_num="174" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE BLACK-FACED GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.59335" page_id="56260796"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
Tiaris bicolor omissa ,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.916503" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56260796" page_num="174" year="" vol="">
WITH SOME NOTES ON BEHAVIOUR
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987109216216216" page_id="56260796"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
by Robin Restall
The genus Tiaris consists of five species of small tanager-finches known
as grassquits. They range from northern South America up through Central
America and across the Caribbean islands. The Cuban Finch T. canora
from Cuba is the only one that is well-known. The Black-faced Grassquit T.
bicolor has reached vagrant status in Florida and the Yellow-faced Grassquit
T. olivacea (which in the early birdkeeping books used to be called the Olive
Finch) has attempted to breed just north of the Mexican border in Texas.
These three are well-known in their native habitats, being so accepting of
humans that in some areas they will enter open kitchen doors to look for
crumbs on the floors. Despite this they are all poorly known in aviculture;
the possible exception being the Cuban Finch. There are such conflicting
reports in the literature about this bird's behaviour that one may be forgiven
if it seems there are different species involved and it warrants an empirical
study.
The Cuban Finch is well established and effectively domesticated in
Australia and Europe. It also occurs in aviculture in the USA, but appears
to be dependent on imported birds for survival there. As well as occurring
naturally on Cuba, it is a well established feral species on New Providence
in the Bahamas. The Yellow-faced Grassquit, a mainly Central American
species that also occurs on a few Caribbean islands, appears to be a bird of
the past as far as aviculture is concerned, with the few references being half
a century or more ago (e.g. Boosey, 1959; Goodwin, 1959). The Black-
faced Grassquit from northern Colombia and Venezuela and ranging right
through the West Indies - being absent only from the island of Cuba - is also
known in aviculture (Goodwin loc. sit.; Restall, 1976, 1984, 1987) but that
too seems to be a bird of the past. The other two species, the Sooty Grassquit
T.fuliginosa and the Dull-coloured Grassquit T. obscura are mystery birds,
even to ornithologists. Both are associated with bamboo and probably, like
the Magpie Mannikin Lonchurafringilloides in Africa (Restall, 1996), have
bursts of highly productive breeding when bamboo is in seed. I have both
species of grassquit in the laboratory at the time of writing (November 2003),
and hope eventually to be able to prepare some notes on their behaviour.
I came to know the Black-faced Grassquit when I first lived in Venezuela
in the early 1970s. It was a very common garden bird then, and I grasped
the opportunity to conduct a one-year survey of it in my garden, trapping
and banding (ringing) as many individuals as I could, and subsequently
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.629987" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260797" page_num="175" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - BLACK-FACED GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999087" page_id="56260797"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
175
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.987712205128205" page_id="56260797"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
observed their behaviour. Little did I know that 10 years later I would be
living in London again when I would keep the birds and be able to study
their behaviour in an aviary (Restall, 1984). The male of the pair I kept in
London attempted to breed, but whilst he obligingly built the basis of a nest
for the female, I can see now that both the site and the aviary were too
exposed for her liking, and she failed to finish the nest. In 1995 I retired,
and moved from Hong Kong to settle in Venezuela. Here I am now working
on a series of ornithological projects, most involving Neotropical seedeaters
and one project in particular is a comparative study of the northern South
American grassquits. It is thanks to this that I have finally bred the Black-
faced Grassquit.
Black-faced Grassquit
It is a small, fairly rounded and sturdy looking little finch, not well
illustrated in the field guides as the illustrations are based on museum
specimens and the olive-green of the upper plumage fades over the years in
museum cabinets. This incidentally is true also of the other two northern
South American grassquits, the Dull-coloured and Sooty, both of which are
a rich olive-green above, very similar to that of the Black-faced. Perfect
photographs of the Bahama race of the Black-faced Grassquit T. b. bicolor
can be seen in the excellent photographic guide by Beadle and Rising (2002)
and also in Birding (Restall and White, 2003). This northern subspecies is
not as olive-green above and the adult male has less black than the mainland
bird, T. b. omissa , of Venezuela.
In Venezuela, the Black-faced Grassquit is a bird of the northern lowlands,
up to 950m (approx 3,000ft) in the Caracas Valley, but generally lower.
Away from habitation, it usually occurs in xerophytic country, dry open
scrubland with trees and thorns and cactus. Yet it is commonest in the rough,
grassy areas in and around Caracas, gardens, overgrown plots, parks and
golf courses. It is perhaps the commonest species at garden bird feeders.
It may be encountered at all levels, from tree-tops, where it can be seen
nipping off buds and flowers which it eats avidly; the odd little nodules on
Cecropia trees are a particular favourite. It will take almost any kind of
food at bird feeders, but noticeably prefers seed. I can leave my feeder
unattended for weeks, as I do in the rainy season, but as soon as I pour some
seed into it, I can be sure the grassquits will be there within an hour or two,
and then almost continually until the food is all gone.
A male will chase another male away from the table, but usually females
and juveniles - both of which lack any black on the face and are .a little
duller, less greenish, and more drab - are tolerated.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999201" page_id="56260798"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
176
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.657854" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260798" page_num="176" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - BLACK-LACED GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.974588261904762" page_id="56260798"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
Breeding
Like so many Neotropical finches, it breeds in the rainy season. Courtship
begins in earnest and territories are defended once the rain comes with any
frequency. Nest building begins a few weeks after the rains are well
established and the grasses that produce masses of soft, green, protein-rich
seeds are everywhere. The courtship display of the Black-faced Grassquit
appears to be similar to that of the other grassquits. The male faces the
female, droops his wings a little and with his bill open wide he lets out an
explosive "tzit-tzweeee"\ This may be accompanied by a short display flight
and, if the male is perched higher than the female, possibly lm (approx.
3ft) away, he will 'parachute' towards her with his wings quivering, and
uttering a short series of the song.
In the case of the three northern South American species, the gape of the
male is pink, becoming brighter, reddish, when he is in breeding condition.
This may be quite noticeable by a pink flange at the sides of the gape. The
male has a black bill and the plumage of the face and breast is black, so the
red-pink shows up particularly well. I do not know if the Cuban and Yellow-
faced Grassquits have pink gapes (can anyone help me with this, please?)
but I suspect not, and in their cases the contrasting colour combination of
pink and black is replaced by contrasting yellow and black facial patterns.
The male Black-faced Grassquit selects a nest site and builds a basic
shallow saucer that leaves the whole thing looking like a gardener's basket.
If the female accepts the site, she will assist in completing the nest, probably
finishing the interior by herself. The nest is usually placed in a shrub or
among the spiny leaves of a Yucca (a favourite garden plant here in Caracas),
lm (approx. 3ft) or so above the ground, and invariably within reach. I use
the word "placed" deliberately, for the nest can be picked up and removed
whole and complete, without damaging it. The close proximity of humans
seems to be irrelevant. It occurred to me that this may even be an adaptation
for protection, for where there are humans there are fewer natural predators
- which are many, including the Great Kiskadee Pitangus sulphuratus and
many other birds, lizards, large ants, snakes, monkeys, and so on, all of
which are far more likely to steal the contents of a nest than the average
human.
There is an interesting nest phenomena that I have observed several times
with this species. I have found nests that were virtually overrun with small
ants, yet the nestlings were apparently untouched and were being fed quite
normally by their parents. My hypothesis is that the ants were collecting
and taking back to their nests the droppings of the nestlings and using the
material for the fertilization of a fungus the ants cultivate as food for their
queens and babies.
The nest of the Black-faced Grassquit is built of grasses and straws, is
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.629975" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260799" page_num="177" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - BLACK-FACED GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998881" page_id="56260799"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
177
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999318975609756" page_id="56260799"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
completely domed and has the entrance at the front, that is to say, looking
forward out of the shrub or Yucca. Two to five eggs are laid, though in my
experience two or three is the usual number. They are white with brownish
speckles and blotches. When begging to be fed, the nestlings stretch up and
out towards the entrance. They do not twist their necks like estrildid finch
nestlings. When researching whether the Pin-tailed Whydah Vidua macroura
has adapted to brood&amp;apos; parasitize the Black-faced Grassquit on Puerto Rico
(on which the former is well established and the latter is common) I took a
clutch of three eggs and on another occasion a pair of newly-hatched nestlings
from Black-faced Grassquit nests and placed them with Bengalese. In both
cases the young grassquits died within a day or two as the Bengalese were
flummoxed by their begging behaviour and ceased to feed them. I believe
that a neck-twisting nestling whydah would be ignored among a brood of
normal straight-stretching grassquits.
Neotropical finches are adapted to producing small clutches the young
from which fledge very quickly as a strategy against heavy nest predation.
The eggs are incubated from the laying of the second egg and hatch in 12
days. The young fledge between nine and 12 days later. Undoubtably the
earlier fledging is caused by nest disturbance. The birds will go to nest
again almost immediately if the first brood is lost. If the brood is successful,
I believe they will go to nest a second time a little later, possibly after the
mid-rains lull.
In an aviary
Goodwin (1959) kept Cuban, Yellow-faced and Black-faced Grassquits
in a large planted aviary at Cornell University. He remarked on how the
Black-faced, but not the others, spent a lot of time clinging to the aviary
wire. He concluded this was not an attempt to escape, as the birds dived
into cover when a human entered the aviary and would run on the ground
into cover. In contrast, the Cuban species flew about the upper part of the
aviary, while the Yellow-faced hid in the bushes. I have noticed my birds
spending a lot of time at the wire, and the wild birds in the garden spend a
lot of time on the wire. The birds outside are definitely trying to get in, and
I suspect the birds inside are looking for a way round the wire, not so much
to escape, but simply because these birds are continually moving, exploring
and travelling around their teritories. If the birds in the aviary are given a
choice - such as when I have them loose in the birdroom, and the outside
door is left open so that they can fly away, they will spend much more time
inside than out, and having left, will return at regular intervals during the
day. Birds of the year and unpaired birds are continually moving and travel
over much wider areas than the resident pairs. Once banded (ringed) in the
garden it can be months before I trap such birds again, whereas local residents
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998789" page_id="56260800"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
178
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.901627" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260800" page_num="178" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - BLACK-FACED GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999194047619048" page_id="56260800"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
will usually enter the trap several times a day, sometimes within five minutes
of being released. I have over the last few years caught many specimens,
banded them and after taking measurements and notes, released them.
Occasionally I will retain a bird, or a pair of birds, for one particular reason
or another.
In cages and aviaries they are quite harmless with other birds, I have
never seen any bickering or any sign of any kind of aggression to another
species. They are also very easy to feed and and maintain in good condition.
Many years ago I discovered that they did very well on two pots of seed,
one containing a standard canary mixture and the other mixed millets (brown
Panicum and Japanese millets are favoured, and these mix nicely with regular
white millet). These two seed mixtures are provided in hoppers in my aviary,
and feed all the birds. The grassquits will take a little lettuce and a few
mealworms. All the other birds will take a little soft mix and are keen to
very keen on defrosted peas, but the grassquits have never been seen to take
either.
In the aviary they may be seen searching diligently through the tree and
other plants, presumably looking for insects. I have observed this behaviour
with all the seedeaters. The first attempt at breeding was in a wicker basket
of the kind commonly used for estrildid finches, that was fixed to the side of
a hanging plant basket and almost obscured by overhanging leaves. Two
eggs were laid, and subsequently deserted. This might have been due to my
inspection of all the nests I could find. Neotropical finches seem to be
particularly sensitive in this respect. The following season I made no
inspections. Several times the female was seen entering a half-open box
under the eaves of the house (The aviary is built against the side of the
house, up to the roof, and my studio on the first floor looks directly into it).
I did not know if the grassquits were breeding or not. At the end of the
season I had a major clean up in the aviary, during which I removed all the
bamboos in their pots (the plants have to be rotated regularly - they are
always badly damaged as the birds eat all the tender shoots) and several
potted trees. I caught up more Black-faced Grassquits than I remembered
releasing into the aviary, and thought it rather odd and wondered if perhaps
there had been more unplanned entries into the aviary than I realised! It was
not until after I had released them that it occurred to me that the original pair
must have produced two or three young.
At the start of 2003, the aviary planting was totally rejuvenated, with
fresh clumps of Cyperus alternifolius and water hyacinth in the fish pond,
fresh pots of bamboo, plus a great Ficus benjaminus about 5m (approx.
17ft) tall, that reached the roof of the aviary and bent over. A female Black-
faced Grassquit from the previous year was released into the aviary, together
with a freshly-caught very well coloured male from the garden. The aviary
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.629973" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260801" page_num="179" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - BLACK-FACED GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999187" page_id="56260801"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
179
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99861876" page_id="56260801"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
included a small collection of Sporophila seedeaters, a pair of Blue-black
Grassquits Volatinia jacarina a Blue Grosbeak Passerina caerulea and a
pair of Pileated Finches Coryphospingus pileatus.
Two months after the rain started I saw the first fledgling grassquit in
the aviary. It was slightly smaller than the adults, like the female in colouring,
and with a very short tail. I saw both parents feeding it. It sat in a clump of
Papyrus Cyperus alternifolius , overhanging the pond. It occasionally moved
to another perch, but never strayed from the Papyrus. Two nights later we
had one of the most awful rainfalls imaginable, it resulted in several dozen
houses sliding down hillsides in poor parts of the edge of the city where
buildings are pretty shoddily - and illegally built. The morning after the
rain I found the fledgling floating in the pond. A couple of days later I was
amazed to see an identical bird in the bamboo, although it might have been
slightly larger. I also saw a fledgling Blue-black Grassquit being fed by its
mother. Subsequently we had more of these appalling rain storms but only
one more loss, this time the adult male Blue-black Grassquit, which was
found dead on the ground.
The first time the Black-faced Grassquit was bred in captivity appears to
have been in England in 1910 (Hopkinson, 1938) and the second time at
Cornell in the USA (Goodwin, 1959). My own record is far from
distinguished and owes little if anything to my ability as an aviculturist.
Next year I am hoping to breed the Sooty and Dull-coloured Grassquits in
the aviary, as well as repeat my success with the Black-faced species. I will
also see whether the Black-faced Grassquit will go to nest in a breeding
cage.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.864783" genericHeader="references" page_id="56260801" page_num="179" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.512366764705882">
Beadle, D. and Rising, J. 2002. Sparrows of the United States and Canada -The Photographic
Guide. Academic Press, London.
Boosey, E. J. 1956. Foreign Bird Keeping. Iliffe, London.
Goodwin, R. 1959. Breeding the Black-faced Grassquit, Tiaris bicolor, in captivity and some
notes on the comparative behaviour of the genus. Avicultural Magazine 65,4-5:131-134.
Hopkinson, E. 1938. Breeding records, summary. Avicultural Magazine Fifth Series Vol. Ill,
8:114-129.
Restall, R. L. 1976. The Black-faced Grassquit Tiaris bicolor. Avicultural Magazine 82,3:151-159.
Restall, R. L. 1984. More Finches and other Seed-eating Birds (Part 1). Avicultural Magazine
90,3:145-173.
Restall, R. L. 1987. Neo-Tropical Finches. Avicultural Magazine 94,4:207-222.
Restall, R. L. 1996. Magpie Mannikin, Lonchura fringilloides , species account, in Munias
and Mannikins (pp.74-77). Pica Press, Sussex.
Restall, R. and White, A. 2003. Advances in Identification - Grassquits in the United States.
Birding 35,4:356-366. American Birding Association, Colorado Springs, USA.
Robin Restall is a Research Associate, Phelps Ornithological Collection,
Caracas, Venezuela. E-mail:restall@cantv.net
</reference>
<page confidence="0.995365" page_id="56260802"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
180
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9911475" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260802" page_num="180" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
CAIQUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995713368421053" page_id="56260802"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
Caiques , the latest book by Rosemary Low is one that has been needed
for a very long time. I have often been asked if I could recommend a book
on these South American parrots, and until now the answer has had to be no.
Caiques have become very popular both as pets and as breeding stock, and
such a book has been long overdue. Those interested in these birds should
read from cover to cover all 86 pages and digest what she has written. I
would even suggest that those who breed and hand-rear these parrots as
pets, purchase copies and hand one to each buyer of their youngsters, so this
way they will know that the pet bird they have sold is able to get the best
start in life. This is done on a regular basis by dog breeders and I see no
reason why parrot breeders cannot do the same.
With 10 chapters that cover among other things Care and Housing, Diet
and Nutrition, Caiques as Pets, Breeding, Hand Rearing, Health Care, as
well as a chapter of Your Questions Answered, it is a book full of information.
It has 27 colour plates, these include photos of all subspecies and chicks at
various stages.
A thing that Rosemary mentions, that always springs to mind about
caiques, is the noise factor. I well remember in the late 1960s seeing some
Pallid Caiques in the late Ken Lawrence's collection. I was asked if I would
like to buy them and after some thought left it, but about two weeks later
phoned Ken and asked if he still had them? I was told that his neighbour
(who lived quite a distance away) had complained about the noise they were
making, so he had sent them to Mr Bertagnolio's collection in Rome.
In the chapter on care and housing, Rosemary gives good advice regarding
cage perches (recommending natural wooden ones), wood for chewing and
things with which to occupy their minds. Cage sizes and types of cages are
discussed and aviaries also come within this chapter, with topics discussed
including size, position, seclusion, floor coverings, etc.
The various types of food, fresh and frozen vegetables, cooked rearing
foods, and even livefood, are covered under diet and nutrition.
There are details on breeding caiques in cages as well as in aviaries, the
best size of nest-box and the recommended use of off-cuts of wood fixed
inside for the female to chew on rather than destroying the box.
Measurements and weights of eggs are given, as well as incubation times,
what to be aware of when eggs are about to hatch, and weights of chicks at
certain ages.
Hand-rearing is fully covered and even those who do not believe in it
will find things of interest such as possible ways of saving a chick by hand-
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909723" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260803" page_num="181" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998515" page_id="56260803"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
181
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999383818181818" page_id="56260803"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
rearing it for a few days until it is strong enough to be returned to the nest.
In the Wild, covers the areas that the various caiques come from, with a
descriptive text about each one, plus foods that they are known to eat in the
wild. The final chapter covers questions that are asked about these birds
and the answers.
All in all, this is a well produced book and anyone thinking of obtaining
a caique, but who is perhaps not too sure, will find that it explains all that
they are likely to need to know.
Caiques (ISBN 80-7322-042- 3) is available from the author Rosemary
Low, PO. Box 100, Mansfield, Notts. NG20 9MZ, UK. Price #13.95 post
paid. It is also available from leading avicultural booksellers.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.552179" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260803" page_num="181" year="" vol="">
Cliff Wright
IN HEALTH AND DISEASE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999715692307692" page_id="56260803"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
The stated objectives of Captive Birds in Health and Disease: a practical
guide for those who keep gamebirds/raptors, parrots, waterfowl and other
species are to give a broad outline of avian diseases and to explain how to
promote the health of captive birds by the employment of good husbandry
techniques. The book is aimed principally at aviculturists, both professional
and enthusiastic amateurs, as well as veterinary surgeons developing an
interest in avian medicine.
The main author, John Cooper, is a highly qualified exotic animals
veterinary surgeon who has worked both within institutions and extensively
in the field where part of his workload has involved training local
veterinarians, students and field workers. His wife, Margaret, is a qualified
lawyer with many years experience of national and international animal and
conservation law.
The first section of this book consists of six chapters containing general
information as well as discussion on the biology of birds, health versus disease
(an overview of the factors affecting these two states), maintenance of health
\0x25A0 the importance of management (including aspects of accommodation,
nutrition, daily care, record keeping, health checks, control and prevention
of diseases, and a discussion of stress and stressors), recognising the signs
of health and disease, types of disease, and investigation and diagnosis of
disease (with an emphasis on the partnership between birdkeeper and
veterinarian).
The second part of the book is more specific with chapters on diseases
affecting the skin and plumage, diseases of the digestive tract, respiratory
diseases, diseases of the liver and other internal organs, diseases affecting
fertility, hatchability and the survival of young, the use of medicines and
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998648" page_id="56260804"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
182
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.971785" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260804" page_num="182" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994008023809524" page_id="56260804"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
disinfectants, and accidents, emergencies and supportive care.
The chapter entitled A Veterinary Vade Mecum is aimed at giving concise
information on general avian veterinary principles, medicines, surgery, pain
relief, euthanasia and work with wild birds for vets just embarking on avian
work. This would also prove useful to the aviculturist working with
veterinary guidance. The chapter on legislation should be read by all people
working with birds as the laws governing the keeping, breeding, handling
and trading of birds become ever more complex and ever more stringently
policed. "Ignorance is no defence in the eyes of the law".
Finally there are nine appendices. These include useful addresses and
sources of information; examples for daily record sheets, live and dead bird
submission forms, laboratory sample and egg submission forms; health
hazards from birds (important information for health and safety precautions
in professional and public collections), equipment for the birdkeeper and
avian veterinarian, and a glossary of scientific names. References and further
reading together with the index complete the book.
There is much information in this book that will be useful for reference,
and more that will prove informative and educational especially for the
professional or keen amateur aviculturist. Chapter 13 on emergency
procedures, for instance, contains valuable detail on this subject as well as
highlighting important nursing principles. Some of the tabulated data, for
example on medicines, will be consulted regularly. I would have liked to
see more on the anatomy and physiology of birds, as many birdkeepers
have only limited knowledge of these subjects. Many of the plates serve as
general rather than as specific illustrations and I feel that they often fall
between two stools - either oversimplifying or being too technical (for
example a photomicrograph of a tick which I felt would be better illustrated
by a macrophotograph of it in situ). However, I feel the line drawings are
more helpful and relevant.
I believe the authors have achieved their aims for this book and I see its
importance, not as a clinical textbook but rather as an introduction and general
approach to the principles of maintaining a high health status within a
collection. As such, it would be of real benefit to aviculturists and keepers
who will be able to improve their knowledge of the recognition and treatment
of bird diseases as well as how to help avoid them. Captive Birds in Health
and Disease will also prove a useful induction to avian medicine for
veterinary surgeons with a fledgling interest in this field as well as being a
most suitable reference book for veterinary nurses and other bird carers.
Captive Birds in Health and Disease: a practical guide for those who
keep gamebirds, raptors, parrots, waterfowl and other species (ISBN 0-
88839-538=8) by John E. Cooper, with a chapter on the law by Margaret E.
Cooper, and illustrations by P. Athene Smith, 132 pages, 17 tables, 49 line
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909688" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260805" page_num="183" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999109" page_id="56260805"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
183
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.552915125" page_id="56260805"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
drawings, 22 black and white plates and 32 colour plates, is published in the
UK by the World Pheasant Association, 7-9 Shaftesbury Street,
Fordingbridge, Hampshire, SP6 1JF. E-mail: admin@pheasant.org.uk Price
#29.50. In North America and elsewhere in the world it is published by
Hancock House Publishers, 1431 Harrison Avenue, Blaine, WA 98230-5005.
Website: www.hancockhouse.com/E-mail: sales@hancockhouse.com Price
$34.95 in USA.
J.C.Waine, B.Vet.Med., M.R.C.Y.S.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.283477" page_id="56260805"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.320168" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260805" page_num="183" year="" vol="">
SOCIAL MEETINGS 2004
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.937562714285714" page_id="56260805"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
Saturday April 17th the society will visit Busbridge Lakes, Godaiming,
Surrey, to see Mrs Fleur Douetil&amp;apos;s collection of waterfowl, pheasants and
other birds.
The President&amp;apos;s Garden Party will this year be held on Saturday July
10th.
Details of the third meeting of the year are still to be finalised. Booking
forms for the above meetings will be sent Out at appropriate times.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.633246" page_id="56260805"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.969606" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260805" page_num="183" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9702945" page_id="56260805"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
A large stock is available including some early issues. Further details
are available from: The Membership Secretary, Stewart Pyper, 21 Primrose
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.5039015">
Hill, Nunney, Frome, Somerset BA11 4NP, UK. Tel:01373 836293 or
E-mail: Paul @ pboulden .fsnet .co .uk
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999541" page_id="56260806"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
184
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.982414" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260806" page_num="184" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
NEWS FROM WACO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996265625" page_id="56260806"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
In their Christmas card, Josef Lindholm and Natalie Mashbum-Lindholm
mentioned that at Cameron Park Zoo (website: www.waco-texas.com),
White-headed Buffalo Weavers Dinemellia dinemelli, Inca Terns Larosterna
inca, Salvin's Pigeons Columba oenops and Black-necked Stilts Himantopus
mexicanus have been added to the collection. Also, after five years of living
with turacos and hornbills, the zoo's lone Laughing Dove Streptopelia
senegalensis has finally been paired. Surprisingly, only five other zoological
collections in the USA exhibit this species.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.848736" page_id="56260806"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.93058" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260806" page_num="184" year="" vol="">
RECENTLY DISCOVERED SEEDEATER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997821" page_id="56260806"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
Carrizal Island in the River Caroni, Venezuela, on which a seedeating
finch new to science was discovered recently, was within a few weeks of
the discovery razed and later inundated to make way for a major hydroelectric
project.
In the dense virtually impenetrable spiny bamboo on the island, a
scientific survey team had collected two males and a female. This new
species has been named the Carrizal Blue Seedeater Amaurospiza
carrizalensis . Avicultural Society member Robin Restall, one of the team
that described it, examined the stomach contents of one of the males, and
found it contained some unidentifiable vegetable matter and the remains of
some insects. The latter were almost certainly weevils. Whether these
weevils are specific to this species of bamboo is among the mysteries
surrounding this new species which, to date, has been found nowhere else.
It is hoped an expedition can be sent to the area around the new dam to
look for unexplored spiny bamboo forests in the hope of finding more of
these seedeaters. Robin plans to be part of such an expedition and hopes to
bring back live birds to Caracas for the kind of study of their behaviour that
would be virtually impossible in the wild.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.62576" page_id="56260806"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.96081" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260806" page_num="184" year="" vol="">
WHITE-WINGED GUAN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9919538" page_id="56260806"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
The White-winged Guan Penelope albipennis is a Peruvian species that
inhabits the dry forests of the north-western coast. For a great many years
thought to be extinct, it was rediscovered in 1977, with an estimated
population of probably fewer than 300 birds. One of its rediscoverers,
Gustavo del Solar, founded a centre to study and breed this species with a
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.698674" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260807" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99576" page_id="56260807"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
185
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.204107">
Copyright Chris Brack
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993735869565217" page_id="56260807"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
White-winged Guan at Cracid Breeding Centre, Zutendaal, Belgium.
primary objective being to reintroduce captive bred birds back into the wild.
The Reintroduction Pilot Project was implemented in 2000, when the
first 16 birds were selected for reintroduction. They were first moved to a
large semi-natural enclosure that had been constructed in part of their natural
habitat and remained there for six to 12 months before being released. During
that period a trained hawk was used to condition them to raptors, and they
were ringed. In addition, 10 were fitted with radio transmitters to monitor
their movements in the wild.
The release site was in the Chaparri Private Conservation Area, which
includes part of the guan's former range, from which it was extirpated by
hunting. Following the release of the birds at least three pairs formed and
all three attempted to breed in the next breeding season (January-April 2002).
Artificial nests were provided, but only one was used, the other two pairs
constructed their own nests. Two nests were predated at the egg stage, but
another nest in a tree 5m (approx. 16ft) above the ground and well covered
by vines, was successful. Only one of the two eggs was fertile and hatched
early in April, and the chick was successfully reared by its parents. It remained
with them for about 11 months, after which it left them and met up with and
joined a small group of reintroduced birds that later moved to a neighbouring
ravine.
In 1997, two pairs arrived at Crax Stichtung in Belgium. Six chicks
have been hatched there, one of which died. Over a seven-year period Crax
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999316" page_id="56260808"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
186
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.90674" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260808" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9571445" page_id="56260808"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
Stichtung has, through Gustavo del Solar, sponsored work on the above
project to the tune of US$350,000 (approx. #200,000).
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.641038" page_id="56260808"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.868821" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260808" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
PARROT JUNGLE MOVES TO NEW HOME
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991972666666667" page_id="56260808"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
Neville Brickell has sent a cutting from a travel page of a South African
newspaper. The cutting is of a report about Parrot Jungle, Miami, Florida,
having moved to a US$47 million (approx. #28 million) new home on Watson
Island, off the McArthur Causeway that connects downtown Miami and
Miami Beach's upmarket South Beach, in Biscayne Bay.
The new Parrot Jungle (website:www.parrotjungle.com) now features
over 1,000 tropical birds of a wider variety of species than before. While
the new Parrot Bowl, a covered ampitheatre in which free-flying bird shows
are staged, can seat 1,200 visitors. Flamingo Lake, that was filmed for the
opening credits of the TV series Miami Vice, has been recreated on the island,
as have many other popular features of the old Parrot Jungle. "We have
created our own jungle on a barren island." said Bert Levine.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.6289875" page_id="56260808"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
* * *
SIX HORNBILLS FLEDGED
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.970385222222222" page_id="56260808"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
In the Avicultural Magazine Vol.109, No.2, p.69 (2003), Roger Wilkinson
described the fledging of a Great Hornbill Buceros bicornis in June 2002 at
Chester Zoo. May 22nd 2003, two young fledged at Wilhelma Zoo, Stuttgart,
Germany. At Central Florida Zoological Park, Lake Monroe, Florida, USA,
two Wreathed Hombills Aceros undulatus were fledged in June. One was
raised by its parents and the other, the smaller of the two nestlings, was
hand-reared and was later reintroduced to its recently fledged sibling and
parents, which immediately began feeding it. The park's pair of Silvery-
cheeked Hornbills Bycanistes brevis also fledged two young.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.527433" page_id="56260808"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.966504" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260808" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
BLUE-THROATED MACAW RECOVERY PLAN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998319" page_id="56260808"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
With an estimated maximum population of 120 individuals, and possibly
as few as 50 Blue-throated Macaws Ara glaucogularis, divided into several
sub-populations, remaining in the wild in the Beni Department of northern
Bolivia, Loro Parque Fundacion and the Bolivian NGO Armoma have
produced a recovery plan to be presented to the Bolivian Government. Its
aim is to provide a comprehensive and integrated framework to guide future
efforts to save this species.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998721" page_id="56260809"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
187
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.813148" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260809" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
DR C.J.O. HARRISON
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996398933333333" page_id="56260809"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
Our late member and former Assistant Editor (1968-1973) Dr Colin
Harrison grew up in a London suburb where as a boy he won a scholarship
to a local grammar school. Later he worked as a librarian, a schoolteacher
and in a laboratory before he joined the staff of the Sub-department of
Ornithology at the British Museum, where he became a professional (and
very knowledgeable) ornithologist and obtained his doctorate for studies on
the colour patterns of bird plumages.
Much of the above I have 'cribbed' from the dust jacket of what I believe
was the last book he wrote, The History of the Birds of Britain (Collins,
1988). This I reckon to be one of the most interesting, informative and
well-written bird books that I have read and one which I frequently 'dip
into' for pleasure as well as information. It is beautifully illustrated with
colour plates by the late David Reid-Henry.
I first met Colin sometime (I think two or three years) before he became
a colleague of mine at the museum. I forget exactly when and where we
met, but then or shortly afterwards he was keeping firefinches in cages in
his bedroom and wrote an interesting article about their courtship display
which was duly and deservedly published in the Avicultural Magazine.
At that period we met and talked and argued about bird behaviour to, I
think and hope, our mutual pleasure and enlightenment. I recall that on one
occasion we found to our surprise a Green Woodpeckers' nest hole with
young, only about 3ft (approx. 1m) above the ground in a rotten stump and
on another occasion, quite late in October, were equally surprised to see a
Hobby perched in a conifer.
Colin found, like me, that working in the Bird Room gave him many
advantages over his previous jobs although, unlike me, he later felt that had
he worked in the private sector his financial rewards would have been greater.
Long time readers of the Avicultural Magazine will be in no doubt of
Colin's concern with and contributions to aviculture. As well as his
involvement with The Avicultural Society he was Life President of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.641181" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56260809" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
ASPEB A (Association for the Study and Propagation of European Birds in
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991085777777778" page_id="56260809"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
Aviaries). Colin had very many articles published in omithogical journals.
He also belonged at various times to several organisations concerned with
ornithology, conservation and allied subjects and also an organisation within
the museum, whose name I have forgotten but which seemed, at least to me,
to be a sort of scientific workers' trade union.
I think it was probably Colin's many activities, not least the time he
spent writing and reading, that was the reason, so far as I know although he
kept and studied at different times, three species of firefinches, a Violet-
eared Waxbill, Bearded Tits, Wonga Pigeons, Emerald-spotted Doves,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998812" page_id="56260810"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
188
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.954085" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260810" page_num="188" year="" vol="">
OBITUARY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.983626181818182" page_id="56260810"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
Spotted Doves, and a pair of Trumpeter Finches, which he got as far as the
hen laying a clutch of eggs in a cage in his room at the museum (after we
had all moved to Tring in 1971), none of the birds in his care ever bred
successfully.
His devotion to aviculture and his 'political' abilities were exemplified
in Australia. The museum, in the late 1960s and 1970, undertook a series of
expeditions to Australia, in order to procure an adequate collection of skins
and skeletal material and spirit specimens of Australian birds, all with
complete data. This object was, I think, largely achieved, though of course
not without sundry difficulties, setbacks, and a lot of work by all concerned.
The hardest, most responsible, most stressful job on such expeditions is
that of the leader. Luckily for me, and I think also for the museum, I was not
one of those chosen to lead one of the expeditions. But Colin was. Other
leaders had, (as I should have been in their position) content to bring back
dead specimens, the notes they had made on behaviour, ecology and
distribution of various species, themselves, their colleagues and their
equipment. Colin went further. He had heard that the German ornithologist
Dr Klaus Immelmann, who had been (and was for long after until his sadly
early death) studying Zebra Finches, had been unable to obtain living wild
Zebra Finches.
In his book about his year in Australia studying wild Zebra Finches and
other birds, Im Unbekannten Australien (In unknown Australia) (Verlag
Gottfried Helene, 1960), Dr Immelmann paid fulsome tribute to the help he
had received from all the official and non-official Australians he had met.
Colin, however, discovered that this help had not extended to allowing him
to take some wild Zebra Finches home with him.
Colin thought that his powers of persuasion might prove more effective.
They did. Colin returned with a number of live wild Zebra Finches and
with a number of live Maned Ducks which I believe had been requested by
some prestigious organisation but I am unsure which, though I think Colin
told me at the time.
Dr Immelmann was, I gather, delighted to get the Zebra Finches and in
return sent Colin some Bearded Tits.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.329177">
Derek Goodwin
</subsectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998674" page_id="56260811"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
189
</page>
<table confidence="0.785380321428571" page_id="56260811"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
Contributors to Volume 109 - 2003
Bailey, Tom and Hallager, Sara
Management of bustards in captivity 1
Bralsford, Gary
Breeding the Chestnut-backed Thrush Zoothera dohertyi 150
Congdon,Susan
Breeding the Bearded Barbet Lybius dubius
at Disney's Animal Kingdom 154
Cox, Alison S.
Breeding the White-bellied Bustard Eupodotis senegalensis
at Jacksonville Zoological Garden 107
Ellis, Malcolm
The Purple-throated Fruitcrow Querula purpurata 78
Goodwin, Derek
The Avicultural Magazine and me: a symbiosis 103
Obituary: Dr C.J.0. Harrison 187
Gregson,Jo
Breeding the Wrinkled Hombill Aceros corrugatus
at Paignton Zoo and Environmental Park 80
Hardy, Angela
Breeding and hand-rearing the Blue-winged Leafbird
Chloropsis cochinchinensis at Riverbanks Zoo and Botanical Garden 14
Hewston, Nigel
The President's Garden Party 40
Jones, Marvin L.
A history of the genus Picathartes in captivity, 1948-2002 125,167
Lepperhoff, Lars
The Festive Amazon Amazona f. festiva in the wild and in captivity 29
</table>
<page confidence="0.985616" page_id="56260812"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
190
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.82567975" page_id="56260812"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
Contributors to Volume 109 -- 2003 (cont'd)
Oehler, David A.
Nest activity in Rhinoceros Hombills Buceros rhinoceros
in relation to artificial rainfall patterns 53
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.88117864" page_id="56260812"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
Owen, Andrew
The capture of eight Montserrat Orioles and their subsequent
establishment and breeding at Jersey Zoo 116
Owen, Neil
Breeding the Chestnut-tailed Minla Minla strigula 12
Breeding the Grey Treepie Dendrocitta formosae 145
Peat, Louise
Cotswold Wildlife Park Review of 2002 38
Wonga success 9
Prouse, Elizabeth
Breeding the Blue-crowned Motmot at Riverbanks Zoo 163
Racheli, Luigi
A brief note on the feeding behaviour of two Agapornis species 41
Restall, Robin
The Tri-coloured Munia Lonchura malacca in Venezuela 49
Breeding the Black-faced Grassquit Haris bicolor omissa 174
Schofield, Philip
Notes on a visit to Pakistan 98
The society's visit to Blackbrook Zoological Park 133
Schutz, Paul
Breeding the Hoopoe Upupa epops at Disney's Animal Kingdom 22
Sweeney, Roger C.
The hand-rearing of a St Vincent Parrot Amazona guildingii 62
Wilkinson, Roger
Chester Zoo Bird Review 2002
</figure>
<page confidence="0.886137" page_id="56260812"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
69
</page>
<page confidence="0.999171" page_id="56260813"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
191
</page>
<table confidence="0.821936875" page_id="56260813"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
Index to Volume 109 - 2003
Acems corrugatus , breeding at Paignton Zoo Environmental Park 80
Agapornis , a brief note on the feeding behaviour of two species 41
Amazona festiva festiva, in the wild and in captivity 29
Arnazona guildingii , the hand-rearing of 62
Amazon, Festive, in the wild and in captivity 29
Barbel: ; Bearded, breeding and hand-rearing of at DAK 154
Book Reviews
A Photographic Guide to the Birds of India 137
A Photographic Guide to the Birds of Indonesia 137
A Photographic Guide to the Birds of Southeast Asia 137
Birds of Venezuela 82
Caiques 172
Captive Birds in Health and Disease 173
Greenfoods and Seeds 139
Hummingbirds of Colombia 84
Loros de Colombia 83
Swan Keeper 's Handbook 138
Buceros rhinoceros, possible key to successful nesting 53
Bustards, management in captivity 1
Bustard, White-bellied, breeding at Jacksonville Zoological Garden 107
CD Review
Bird Song of The Gambia &amp; Senegal 140
Chloropsis cochinchinensis , breeding and hand-rearing 14
</table>
<reference confidence="0.906485666666667">
Dendrocitta formosae, breeding . 145
Eupodotis senegalensis, breeding at Jacksonville Zoological Garden 107
Fruitcrow, Purple-throated, in the wild and in captivity 78
Grassquit, Black-faced, breeding, behaviour 174
Hoopoe, breeding at Disney's Animal Kingdom 22
Hombill, Rhinoceros, possible key to successful nesting 53
Hombills, in Thailand 57
Hombill, Wrinkled, breeding at Paignton Zoo Environmental Park 80
Icterus oberi , capture, establishment and breeding at Jersey Zoo 116
</reference>
<page confidence="0.99947" page_id="56260814"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
192
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.8896623" page_id="56260814"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
Index to Volume 109 - 2003 (cont'd)
Leafbird, Blue-winged, breeding and hand-rearing at Riverbanks Zoo 14
Leucosarcia melanoleuca, breeding success with 9
Lonchura malacca, in Venezuela 49
Lybius dubius, breeding and hand-rearing of at DAK 154
Magazine, The Avicultural, and me: a symbiosis 130
Minla, Chestnut-tailed, breeding 12
Minla strigula, breeding 12
Motmot, Blue-crowned, breeding at Riverbanks Zoo 163
Motmotus momota, breeding at Riverbanks Zoo 163
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.777302923076923" page_id="56260814"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
Munia, Tri-coloured, in Venezuela 49
News &amp; Views 42,86,142,184
Obituaries 46,187
Officers and Council (as from August 30th 2003) 97
Oriole, Montserrat, capture, establishment and breeding 116
Pakistan, notes on visit to 98
Parrot (Amazon), St Vincent, the hand-rearing of 62
Picathartes, a history of the genus in captivity, 1948-2002 125,167
Pigeon, Wonga, breeding success 9
President's Garden Party 2002 40
Querula purpurata, in the wild and in captivity 78
Thrush, Chestnut-backed, breeding 150
Tiaris bicolor omissa, breeding, behaviour 174
</table>
<reference confidence="0.9470765">
Treepie, Grey or Himalayan, breeding 145
Upupa epops, breeding at Disney's Animal Kingdom 22
Wildlife Park, Cotswold, review of 2002 38
Zoo, Chester, bird review 2002 69
Zoological Park, Blackbrook, society's visit to 133
Zoothera dohertyi, breeding 150
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.983069" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260815" page_num="" year="" vol="">
KEN DOLTON
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.977263166666667" page_id="56260815"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Just before Christmas we were saddened to learn of the death of Ken
Dolton. Ken joined The Avicultural Society in 1953, he was elected to the
council in 1980 and became a Vice President in 1994. He was awarded the
society's medal for the first breeding in the UK of the Thick-billed Parrot
Rhynchopsitta pachyrhyncha and later for the first breeding of the Yellow-
naped Amazon Amazona ochrocephala auropalliata. For his breeding of
Duivenbode's Lory Chalcopsitta duvenbodei, Ken received a Certificate of
Merit, having just been beaten to the medal by Rosemary Low and Bob
Grantham. Ken's widow, Mona (Mo), wishes to thank all those members of
The Avicultural Society who sent letters and cards, following Ken's passing
on December 13th 2003. An Obituary will be published in the next issue of
the magazine.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.815908" page_id="56260815"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.531231" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260815" page_num="" year="" vol="">
US BANK ACCOUNT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.917374142857143" page_id="56260815"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The society has opened a US bank account for the convenience of North
American members, would-be members and subscribers who wish to make
payments in US dollars. Overseas membership for 2004 will be US$38 for
receiving the magazines by regular mail or US$50 for air mail. Checks and
money orders should be made payable to The Avicultural Society and sent
to: The Avicultural Society, c/o Jane Cooper, 12650 Hearst Road, Willits,
California 95490-9231.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.632161" page_id="56260815"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.725303" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260815" page_num="" year="" vol="">
BLACK-WINGED STARLING IN DANGER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.942531153846154" page_id="56260815"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
In very recent years the Black-winged Starling Sturnus melanopterus
population has been almost decimated in the wild by trapping and it is now
classified as Endangered. Trapping has and probably continues to be mainly
for the local trade on the Indonesian islands Java and Bali, which it is native
to and on which it is considered lucky to keep a white bird. This species
searches for food in open agricultural areas and its numbers may also have
been affected by the excessive use of pesticides.
A captive breeding programme could be important for its survival. Olivier
Amoult, along with a few other interested people, is attempting to discover
if there are any of these handsome starlings being kept in Europe. If you
keep this species and you would like to know of other aviculturists who
keep it, please contact Olivier Amoult, 16 Chemin du Peyronnet, 06500
Menton, France. E-mail: oamoult@monaco377.com
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9877945" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260816" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION LIBRARIES
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.966009076923077" page_id="56260816"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
3 9088 01769 6527
Breeding the Grey Treepie Dendrocitta formosae
by Neil Owen.145
Breeding the Chestnut-backed Thrush
Zoothera dohertyi
by Gary Bralsford.150
Breeding the Bearded Barbet Lybius dubius at Disney's
Animal Kingdom
by Susan Congdon.154
Breeding the Blue-crowned Motmot at Riverbanks Zoo and
Botanical Garden
by Elizabeth Prouse.163
A history of the genus Picathartes in captivity, 1948-2002
by Marvin L. Jones.167
Breeding the Black-faced Grassquit &amp;apos;Haris bicolor omissa, with
some notes on behaviour
by Robin Restall. 174
Book Reviews
Caiques.180
In Health and Disease. 181
News &amp; Views.184
Dr C. J. 0. Harrison.187
Contributors to Volume 109 - 2003 . 189
Index to Volume 109 - 2003 . 191
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</table>
</algorithms>
