<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.49857" page_id="56266185"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Ql
e wAVICULTUR AL
MAGAZINE
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990772" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266186" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991765142857143" page_id="56266186"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in freedom and captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2001 as for 2000: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.548818" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266186" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.844479" page_id="56266186"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Subscription, changes of address, orders for back numbers etc. should be
sent to:
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, P.O. BOX 47, EDENBRIDGE, KENT TN8 7WP, ENGLAND.
Enquiries regarding membership should be sent to:
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.88044725" page_id="56266186"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE MEMBERSHIP SECRETARY, Stewart Pyper, 21, Primrose Hill,
Nunney, Frome, Somerset BA11 4NP.
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.996379833333333" page_id="56266186"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998437" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266186" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.9972025">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.739392" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266187" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<category confidence="0.324965">
Vol 107 - No. 3 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2001
</category>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990657" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266187" page_num="" year="" vol="">
NOTES FROM COBHAM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997397290322581" page_id="56266187"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by R. C. J. Sawyer
In 19971 wrote an article titled Twenty-five years at Cobham (Avicultural
Magazine Vol. 103, No.2, pp.49-66). These notes follow on from there up
until about March 1999. At which time there were no new aviaries to report
on and the plant-life here remained largely unchanged, except that the
vegetation in some aviaries had been severely pruned back to make it easier
to see the birds and to prevent the interiors of some of the aviaries becoming
too jungle-like.
Red-billed Choughs Pyrrhocorax pyrrhocorax were bred during 1998.
I have kept choughs at different times and had acquired this pair some years
earlier. The two had been surgically sexed but after they nested during their
first year here and laid eight eggs all of which were clear, I had them re-
sexed and both proved to be females. Subsequently, one, a 1984-bred female,
was exchanged for a three or four year old male. The new pair was housed
in what I term the secluded aviary, where there is an old potting shed. It is
built of stone and it was inside this shed that the pair nested. I put up a wire-
mesh platform to which some twigs were added and very quickly a nest was
constructed. Four eggs were laid from which two or three young hatched
but only one was raised successfully. The others disappeared, perhaps having
been eaten by their parents. Choughs are very highly strung birds.
Later I obtained three more pairs, which I housed in the garden aviary. I
wondered if they would breed in a group. The choughs are fed mealworms,
insectivorous food and minced (ground) meat. They are of course long-
lived birds which can exceed 20 years of age. Hoopoes Upupa epops, if
they want to, can be very free breeding. It was a good year for them in
1998, with six young being reared, after which the female promptly died.
Speaking with other aviculturists, they too seem to encounter this problem.
You have one or two years perhaps when they successfully rear numerous
young, then one of the pair dies and no further breeding occurs. When the
six young were sexed, most proved to be males. Fortunately, I was able to
swap one with Leeds Castle aviaries in order to introduce new blood and
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999498" page_id="56266188"  page_num="98" year="" vol="">
98
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.885167" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266188" page_num="98" year="" vol="">
SAWYER - NOTES FROM COBHAM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.935664880952381" page_id="56266188"  page_num="98" year="" vol="">
form a new pair which was soon sitting on eggs. Hoopoes are of course
highly insectivorous, almost too much so. I just wish they would take a
wider variety of the foods offered to them. Bartlett's or Mindanao Bleeding
Hearts Gallicolumba criniger were also very prolific in 1998. All three
pairs nested successfully. Remember that this dove lays only one egg per
clutch. It is important that pairs settle down for if they remain flighty
successful reproduction is very difficult.
Red-billed Oxpeckers Buphagus erythrorhynchus were added to the
Cobham collection in 1997. The pair was in a very rough condition on
arrival here. They were housed first in one of the six indoor heated aviaries
and were later released into the large original aviary, and it was only when
the nest-box they were roosting in was taken down that a young oxpecker
was found dead in the bottom. The box was being put inside for the winter
and the oxpeckers were being brought inside because they dislike cold
weather. Prior to the box being taken down I had no idea that they had
nested. A young bird had been found on the aviary floor and I could not
think what it was at the time, but realise now that it was a young oxpecker.
In 1998 I acquired four more Red-billed Oxpeckers which later went to
Birdworld. The original pair nested again in 1998 but were again
unsuccessful. I wonder now if the minced liver was perhaps too bloody for
them.
Green Wood Hoopoes Phoeniculus purpureus successfully raised a single
youngster in 1998. My Wattled Jananas Jacana jacana though were
unsuccessful and the old female has died now. The Superb Starlings
Lamprotornis superbus proved to be very prolific but they were very
aggressive towards my lutino Princess of Wales Parrakeets Polytelis
alexandrae. Red-tailed Laughing Thrushes Garrulax milnei reared a single
youngster and the Island Thrushes Turdus poliocephalus reared two more
young, a male and a female. The Azure-winged Magpies Cyanopica cyana
proved to be two females. I was successful in breeding a single Red-crested
Touraco Tauraco erythrolophus but my Knysna Touracos T. corythaix let
their young die and the Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber lost a chick. The
Roulroul Partridges Rollulus roulroul produced lots of young. They breed
best indoors in heated accommodation but do look lovely in the landscaped
outdoor aviaries. Splendid Sunbirds Nectarinia coccinigastra nested in the
tropical house but I suspect that the youngster may have been taken by the
Spangled Cotinga Cotinga cayana.
Beautiful Ptilinopus pulchellus and Black-naped Fruit Doves P.
melanospila both bred successfully. A pair of Scarlet Tanagers Ramphocelus
bresilius, acquired from a dealer, bred in one of the three aviaries behind the
Koi pond. A single youngster was raised in a small basket. The parents
were provided with livefood and fruit, etc. No problems arose between the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.589534" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266189" page_num="99" year="" vol="">
SAWYER - NOTES FROM COBHAM
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998149" page_id="56266189"  page_num="99" year="" vol="">
99
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.950604125" page_id="56266189"  page_num="99" year="" vol="">
tanagers and the other occupants of the aviary, which were a breeding pair
of Bartlett's or Mindanao Bleeding Hearts and a colony of mutation Gouldian
Finches Erythrura gouldiae. In the next aviary the Black-cheeked
Woodpeckers Melanerpes pucherani raised four more young in 1998.
Members may not believe it but two 1997 birds housed in the large original
aviary were killed by a pair of Stella's Lorikeets Charmosyna papou.
My Eclectus Parrots Eclectus rnratus proved to be very prolific. Some
of the young were parent-reared and some were hand-reared by Sheila Becker.
Philippine Hanging Parrots Loriculus philippensis had a single chick and
the pair of melanistic Stella's Lorikeets successfully raised a single chick in
the lakeside aviary.
Before finishing I must tell you about my waders. Two pairs of Black-
necked Stilts Himantopus mexicanus raised nests of three young each and
my three pairs of Avocets Recurvirostra avocettta had three nests. The adult
breeding pair of Masked Plovers Vanellus miles and a 1997 pair both nested
successfully. So that at that time the collection contained 10 Masked Plovers.
They seem very tough and easy to keep and breed.
NEW HON. SECRETARY/TREASURER
Lee Gardiner, P.O. Box 47, Edenbridge, Kent TN8 7WP , England,
is the new Hon. Secretary/Treasurer of the Avicultural Society. He
takes over from Geofrey Greed, who has retired. Geoffrey has also
retired as Director of Bristol Zoo Gardens, and the society will no
longer be based there. The new Director is Jo Gipps, who was Director
of London Zoo.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.974855" page_id="56266190"  page_num="100" year="" vol="">
100
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.960435" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266190" page_num="100" year="" vol="">
PATHOLOGY AND DISEASES OF TOURACOS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996021157894737" page_id="56266190"  page_num="100" year="" vol="">
by J. Waine
The dictionary defines pathology as 'the branch of veterinary science
examining the essential nature of disease especially on the changes in body
tissues and organs which cause or are caused by disease'. Essentially this
means dealing with dead material - dead bodies, dead tissues, dead organs.
Such material may be presented in the form of samples taken from a live
bird (for example biopsy of tissue, swabs for bacterial or viral culture or
even just smears from a crop to examine under the microscope), or post
mortem examination of a dead bird with samples taken for further tests as
necessary. It could be argued that the examination of dead birds is not a lot
of use to the aviculturist, but these techniques are our most useful aid to
achieving a diagnosis as well as improving our understanding of disease
and allowing us to advise the birdkeeper about the best ways of avoiding or
controlling the spread of disease. My interest in pathology is fuelled by the
fact that our knowledge of avian diseases is pathetically small and that we
have hardly started scratching the surface of this subject. The vast majority
of research has been aimed at the intensive poultry and game bird producing
industries with most of the remaining work being done on parrot and raptor
diseases. Problems associated with softbills have hardly been examined
and even fairly casual observation can add to our limited understanding in
this area.
The touracos are a group of 23 or so species (the exact number depending
on which taxonomic authority you use) in six genera belonging to the family
Musophagidae. Most taxonomists include this family with the cuckoos in
the order Cuculiformes, principally by reason of the similar arrangement of
their toes. Even this, somewhat tenuous link, does not strictly hold true as
the touracos have a medial digit which can be moved sideways. In many
respects, for example their muscles, feather tracts and skull anatomy, the
touracos appear distinct and I believe that they should be in an order of their
own. Another feature unique to this group of birds is the presence of copper
bearing pigments - turacin and turacoverdin - in the feathers. One or both of
these pigments can be found in the feathers of almost all of the species of
touraco.
The touracos constitute a very individual group of birds with special
disease patterns and pathology. As part of my work and interest in these
birds I have on database the details of 80 autopsies that I have carried out on
birds of this family - a figure that begins to have some statistical value. The
results indicate several diseases of importance:
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.927324" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266191" page_num="101" year="" vol="">
WAINE -TOURACOS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999182" page_id="56266191"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
101
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.996048317073171" page_id="56266191"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
Yersiniosis or pseudotuberculosis
On my database 20% of all birds examined had died as a result of
yersiniosis or pseudotuberculosis. It is caused by a bacterium called Yersinia
(or Pasteurella ) pseudotuberculosis. It causes a very rapid and usually fatal
inflammation of the liver (known technically as a peracute hepatitis).
Contamination of food or water by the infected droppings from rodents and
wild birds, as well as possible carriers within a collection, is the principal
cause of its spread. Touracos (together with hornbills, toucans and barbets)
are highly susceptible to this disease, often dying without showing any, or
only few, signs of illness. The post mortem picture is fairly typical with a
grossly swollen liver studded with small, white or off-white spots. Often
the spleen is similarly affected and usually the carcass is in good physical
condition.
Treatment is based primarily on speed of action. If a bird in the collection
appears vaguely off-colour, I advocate immediate use of appropriate
antibiotics rather than waiting to see whether or not there is a genuine
problem. Wait, and the next stage could be a dead bird. The best antibiotic
to use is a matter for discussion with your own veterinary surgeon. I advocate
the use of a drug called Synulox administered by crop tube twice daily for a
minimum of seven days. The distress caused by catching a bird and treating
it 14 times is often cited as a reason for waiting to treat but, in my opinion,
there is a definite risk of fatality if this approach is adopted. This view may
well be controversial, as good medical practice demands a diagnosis before
applying treatment - a philosophy with which I am in complete agreement
most of the time. However, in this case, experience has shown time and
again that speed of treatment is essential.
Prevention of yersiniosis relies on food and water hygiene. Store food
in sealed, rodent-proof containers. Perform regular and frequent rodent
control measures: always assume you have a rodent problem, never believe
you are free of mice. Do not place food and water bowls under netted roofing,
where wild birds can sit and defecate through the netting.
Iron storage disease
This is a metabolic problem wherein iron is stored in the liver and
eventually reaches poisonous levels that cause damage to the liver cells.
This disease has been traditionally associated with Ramphastids but there is
increasing evidence that it also affects touracos and barbets. A veterinary
student at Bristol University has undertaken a scientific study of this disease,
in toucans originally, but later broadened the scope to include touracos.
Affected birds usually suffer acute death showing no clinical signs. At post
mortem the birds are in good physical condition and the liver appears normal.
Diagnosis is based on histopathology of the liver (looking at stained tissue
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999268" page_id="56266192"  page_num="102" year="" vol="">
102
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.98044" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266192" page_num="102" year="" vol="">
WAINE -TOURACOS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998748875" page_id="56266192"  page_num="102" year="" vol="">
samples under the microscope) and on liver iron assays.
There is no specific treatment and the best means of prevention is to
feed susceptible species diets low in iron. Recently I visited The Gambia
and while there had the opportunity to study Buffon's Touracos Tauraco
persa buffoni and Violet Touracos Musophaga violacea. In the wild their
diets consist mainly of greenstuffs (leaves from various unidentified trees),
buds of fig trees and the fig fruits. When we examined the fig fruits, we
found that they often contained many small insects suggesting that the birds
take livefood as a regular part of their diet. I believe that we should be
looking critically at their diet in the wild, in particular at the species of
plants they eat as one or more may have iron-chelating chemicals that reduce
iron levels.
Other areas of research into this disease are suggested by the fact that
birds susceptible to iron storage disease are also susceptible to yersiniosis.
Is there a link? In particular, does damage to the liver cells by excess iron
storage make birds more likely to succumb to yersiniosis infection? Also,
could there be a link in touracos between copper and iron metabolism? This
group of birds is very efficient at extracting and using copper for feather
pigmentation (it has been estimated that 20mg of copper are required for the
plumage and a bird would therefore have to eat about 20kg of fruit to get the
necessary amount). As iron is fairly closely related to copper in the periodic
table of elements, could this mean that iron extraction is similarly efficient?
Indeed, this one disease serves to illustrate how we have many more questions
than answers.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.540371">
Aspergillosis
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999701375" page_id="56266192"  page_num="102" year="" vol="">
Another disease commonly encountered is aspergillosis, a fungal
infection commonly affecting the windpipe (trachea), voice box (syrinx),
lungs and/or air sacs. It is usually a secondary infection, i.e. it occurs after
the bird's immune system has been compromised either by stress, chronic
disease or drugs. The spores of the fungus are found almost everywhere but
extreme contamination will increase the risk of infection. Such contamination
can occur with mouldy food, the use of hay or straw bedding in poorly
ventilated areas or mould accumulating in the aviary itself. Sensible hygiene
precautions will reduce the risk. Also beware of it in carrying boxes: if
these are allowed to get damp and soiled with droppings they can encourage
the growth of mould. You then put a stressed bird into the box and stress it
further by transporting it to strange surroundings. This encourages open
mouth breathing which increases the risk of taking in infection even more.
The symptoms of the disease are very variable and range from an apparent
healthy bird suffering acute respiratory distress and sudden death (caused
by a fungal growth in the syrinx) to a slowly developing disease causing
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.927329" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266193" page_num="103" year="" vol="">
WAINE -TOURACOS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999684" page_id="56266193"  page_num="103" year="" vol="">
103
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.991744625" page_id="56266193"  page_num="103" year="" vol="">
gradual deterioration of body condition with, or without, breathing problems
(caused by air sac infection). Signs at autopsy are quite unmistakable with
fungal growths, sometimes very large, in the windpipe, voice box, lungs or
air sacs.
Other, assorted, diagnoses on my database include: arteriosclerosis a
metabolic disease causing thickening of the walls of the arteries. There is
just one case but worthy of mention because it was so unexpected as touracos'
diets are so low in fats. There are also single cases of a carcinoma and
valvular endocarditis (the latter an infection of the heart valves causing
damage to the valves and leading to congestive cardiac failure). Metabolic
bone disease (a failure of bones to mineralise properly especially during
growth) is recorded commonly in young birds. In such cases the diet should
be examined carefully and either adjusted or supplemented with calcium
and vitamin D. Aggression injuries are a fairly common cause of death in
mixed aviaries although the injuries are often inflicted by the bird's own
mate. Such incidents have been associated with reproductive failure or with
overt sexual behaviour from one of the pair. Damage to part of the gut from
foreign body ingestion is not uncommon. Such foreign material has included
wire from aviary mesh, thorns, twigs and, in one case, a paper clip.
Another example of the unique nature of this group of birds is its peculiar
reaction to isofluorane anaesthesia. Isofluorane is a particularly safe gas
anaesthetic causing little trouble with most birds, but with the touracos, if
they are at all stressed prior to anaesthesia, it poses a significant risk. Such
a risk is especially great for routine procedures such as sexing when birds
may be caught up in batches. I would suggest always catching the birds at
least 90 minutes in advance of anaesthetic and keeping them quiet in a
darkened box for this period.
I would like to conclude by discussing the usefulness of post mortem
examination. Most aviculturists regard a dead bird as a dead loss and either
put it in the waste or have it stuffed. Although I understand how owners feel
on these occasions I would urge you to think again. Examining a bird after
death may answer a number of questions:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.979614666666667" page_id="56266193"  page_num="103" year="" vol="">
1) Why did the bird die?
2) Does this suggest an underlying disease in the collection?
3) Does it indicate an underlying management problem?
4) Is this disease a zoonotic (i.e. can it be spread to people)?
5) Was the disease brought in with introduced stock?
6) What can be done to prevent further problems?
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.894379" page_id="56266193"  page_num="103" year="" vol="">
I think question five needs further comment, as I believe purchaser's
quarantine to be a very important aspect of disease control in a collection.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999703" page_id="56266194"  page_num="104" year="" vol="">
104
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.980403" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266194" page_num="104" year="" vol="">
WAINE -TOURACOS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.960497" page_id="56266194"  page_num="104" year="" vol="">
Irrespective of the previous history of a recent addition to a collection, each
new bird should be kept isolated in quiet surroundings for at least 35 days
after its arrival. This is inconvenient and time consuming but it does allow
the bird a period to settle in and get over any stress it may have been subject
to prior to its arrival and it gives any latent disease being carried by the bird
a chance to show itself and may avoid the transmission of disease to
susceptible birds in the collection.
In addition to these factors, post mortem examination of birds also gives
us veterinary surgeons the chance to learn more about avian disease and
facilitates research into new areas of knowledge.
The cost of an autopsy varies quite considerably and an autopsy can be
performed on two levels:
1) Gross examination only: this does not involve laboratory tests but
can often result in a suggested diagnosis and sometimes provides a complete
answer.
2) Laboratory back-up: performing laboratory tests as well as a gross
examination is more likely to achieve a definitive diagnosis but can become
expensive depending on the number and type of tests involved.
I have been conducting private research into avian pathology and
anatomy, both in wild birds and exotic birds, for over 10 years. Current
research topics include developing a database on touraco disease, anatomical
examination of the skull and providing material for investigations into iron
storage disease in touracos. In the course of this research, I perform gross
examination post mortems free of charge. If anyone is interested in supplying
me with material please contact me at the address below. I must emphasis
that this in no way should be considered a replacement for any service offered
by your own veterinary surgeon and I am interested only in looking at cases
which would not normally be autopsied.
The above is a synopsis of the talk given by the author at the Annual
General Meeting of the International Touraco Society held at the Cotswold
Wildlife Park on April 2nd 2000. It is reproduced here by the kind permission
of the author and Louise Peat, Editor of the International Touraco Society
Newsletter, in which it appeared first.
J. Waines address is:- 97Mount Pleasant, Redditch, Worcs. B974JD,
UK. Tel:01527 550111/E-mail:waine@attglobal.net
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999445" page_id="56266195"  page_num="105" year="" vol="">
105
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.724387" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266195" page_num="105" year="" vol="">
LAST OF THE GREAT COLLECTORS
by Malcolm Ellis
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.967398675675676" page_id="56266195"  page_num="105" year="" vol="">
When Ken Dolton wrote saying that with the death of Jack Barlass who
joined the society in 1934, we had lost the person who had been a member
for the longest time {Avicultural Magazine Vol. 106, No.3, p. 143), it set me
wondering. I could recall having seen that Fred Shaw Mayer had joined the
society in 1922 and was an honorary life member, and thought that sometime
in the past five years or so I had seen an address for him at what looked to be
a retirement home in Queensland, Australia.
Not having seen an obituary, I wrote to Cliff Frith, co-author of Birds of
Paradise (Oxford University Press, 1998), in Queensland, and asked whether
he knew if Fred Shaw Mayer was still alive? It transpired that he had died
and Cliff had been among those who had helped in the preparation of a four-
page obituary by W.S. Peckover and G. G. George, published in Emu (1992),
a photocopy of which he sent me.
Perhaps as a result of upheavals in the Avicultural Society following the
death of Harry Hors well, no obituary or mention of the death of Fred Shaw
Mayer appears to have been published at that time in the magazine. In an
attempt to remedy this omission I have compiled the following notes, relying
heavily on the obituary in Emu , as well as finding other sources of
information.
Fred Shaw Mayer MBE 1899-1989
Frederick William Shaw Mayer MBE died at Nambour, Queensland,
September 1st 1989, 25 days short of his 90th birthday. Born in September
1899 and educated in Sydney, after working as a surveyor and in the building
trade, he turned to collecting museum specimens for Lord Rothschild's Tring
Museum here in England and live birds for London Zoo and the private
collections of Jean Delacour, Alfred Ezra, John Spedan Lewis and Herbert
Whitley - four prominent members of the Avicultural Society.
During the years 1928-1931 he collected extensively in the Moluccas
and western New Guinea (now Irian Jaya), with most of the bird skins going
to Tring Museum. The following year Lord Rothschild sold his collection
of 250,000 skins to Harry Payne Whitney's widow for the American Museum
of Natural History, New York, in memory of her late husband. According to
B. and R. Meams (1998), Rothschild offered his collection to the museum
for US$225,000 (roughly #150,000 at the present exchange rate), but
absolutely refused to part with his cassowaries and other ratites.
He was particularly proud of his collection of cassowaries. As a young
keeper at London Zoo, I can recall an older keeper telling me that Wilfred
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999197" page_id="56266196"  page_num="106" year="" vol="">
106
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.823779" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266196" page_num="106" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - FRED SHAW MAYER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998574523809524" page_id="56266196"  page_num="106" year="" vol="">
Frost had told him how he (Frost) had brought back young cassowaries for
Lord Rothschild, which were kept at the zoo until they matured into perfect
museum specimens!
The Shaw Mayer obituary includes a long list of references from the
literature about New Guinea covering the period 1928-1952, as a record of
the localities in New Guinea where he collected during that period. It was
in 1938 that he sent the British Museum (Natural History) the two central
tail feathers and some other feathers obtained from a missionary, of what
proved to be a hitherto undescribed bird of paradise - Astrapia mayeri -
formerly called Shaw Mayer's Bird of Paradise, but known now as the
Ribbon-tailed. The subspecies of the Dwarf Cassowary Casuarius bennetti
shawmayeri is another bird which helps perpetuate his name.
From Walter Goodfellow's article in the Avicultural Magazine , first
published in 1934 and reproduced in Vol. 104, No. 3, pp. 106-113 (1998),
we know that in 1933 Goodfellow and Shaw Mayer travelled to the New
Hebrides (now called Vanutu), where they collected live Royal Parrot Finches
Erythrura cyaneovirens regia , which they brought to England in April 1934.
In 1953 Fred Shaw Mayer took over the management of Sir Edward
Hallstrom's aviaries at Nondugl in the Wahgi Valley of Papua New Guinea.
These had been established in 1948, the first manager having been Captain
Neptune (Ned) Blood. Shaw Mayer was an expert at hand-rearing young
birds, especially birds of paradise. He had noticed that if their young were
not doing well, female birds of paradise would capture certain species of
spiders to feed to them. He assumed these had a medicinal effect and sought
the same species to feed to birds he was rearing, should they be off-colour.
Apparently he made extensive use of natural foods and included the dried
pupae of tree-nesting ants in the bird of paradise food mixture fed to the
birds each day. A male Paradisaea raggiana salvadorii hand-reared by him
at Nondugl in 1959 and later housed at the Baiyer River Sanctuary, was still
in prime condition 25 years later and there is no knowing how long it would
have lived had it not been killed by a python.
Peter Scott (yet to be knighted) visited Nondugl in December 1956, and
described the visit in his diary, extracts of which were published in Animals
Magazine (1964). He, his wife and a TV cameraman were greeted by Fred
Shaw Mayer, who Scott described as: 'tall, quiet, a scientific collector and
ornithologist, in his late 60s, burned dark by the sun, slow of speech,
courteous of manner'.
The collection consisted of about 200 birds of paradise, some bowerbirds,
parrots, three cassowaries, 20 Salvadori's Ducks Salvadorina waigiuensis
and 12 or more tree kangaroos. The ducks were more striking in appearance
than Scott had expected, with the barring on the back and flanks, less precise
and neat than he had shown it in The Waterfowl of the World (Country Life,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.461264" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266197" page_num="107" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - FRED SHAW MAYER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99962" page_id="56266197"  page_num="107" year="" vol="">
107
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.975861428571429" page_id="56266197"  page_num="107" year="" vol="">
1954-1964). Shaw Mayer thought tadpoles form the basis of their diet in
the wild and fed them these most of the year, except in the wet season when
they are difficult to get, when he augmented their diet with meat and,
sometimes, tripe. They had bred there twice, rearing three and two young
from two clutches of three eggs each.
During the four days that Scott's party spent searching the rivers, they
saw Grey Teal Anas gibberifrons, a male P. r. salvadorii, though not in full
colour, Black-headed Shrikes Lanius schach stressemanni , Black-shouldered
Kites Elanus caeruleus wahgiensis, Mountain Red-headed Honeyeaters
Myzomela adolphinae in bushes beside a path, and 15ft (4.5m) high reeds
full of 'Wahgi Munias' or New Britain Mannikins Lonchura spectabilis
wahgiensis, but failed to see any wild Salvadori's Ducks.
Jean Delacour visited Nondugl in November 1962 and wrote about his
visit in the Avicultural Magazine (1963). He was welcomed by Fred Shaw
Mayer who had, he wrote, laid out the grounds with great skill and taste, to
include large ponds, beautiful trees, shrubs and orchids. Within this setting
were nearly 100 aviaries, most of which were thickly planted, except for a
few housing parrots and birds of paradise particularly destructive to
vegetation, and each had a large shelter at the back.
Housed in them were about 160 birds of paradise of 12 species: Raggiana,
Lesser P. minorfinschi, Blue P. rudolphi , Ribbon-tailed, Princess Stephanie's
A. stephaniae. Brown Sicklebill Epimachus meyeri, Queen Carola's Parotia
Parotia carolae, Loria's Loria loriae, Wattled-billed Loboparadisea sericea.
King Cicinnurus regius. Magnificent Diphyllodes magnificus hunsteini and
King of Saxony Pteridophora alberti. Four species had nested successfully,
the Blue, Lesser, Ribbon-tailed and Princess Stephanie's, the last two having
also produced hybrids. To this list was added P. r. salvadorii. Three plumeless
males and several females were living in a large aviary in which there was a
nest, and although Shaw Mayer doubted non-adult males could breed, when
he and Delacour looked into the nest it contained newly hatched chicks.
Delacour noted that the climate at Nondugl is temperate and at night the
temperature can drop to 40*F (4.4*C), therefore the birds living in these
high valleys must be fairly hardy. It is warm during the day, but there is
little sun and much rain, with the sky often being overcast. He had never
seen anything like the aviaries there and concluded that the way birds of
paradise were kept in Europe and the USA was wrong. Their cages were
too small, they were given too much heat and were overfed. He considered
that all but the smallest species should be kept in large, outdoor aviaries,
well protected from winds and with a large shelter at the back heated to
40*F - 50*F (4.4*C - 10*C) on the coldest days. In the mornings at Nondugl
they were fed a mixture of mashed papaya and banana (10% of the latter),
crushed dog biscuit and fresh ant eggs. This had been eaten by mid-day,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999534" page_id="56266198"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
108
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.831433" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266198" page_num="108" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - FRED SHAW MAYER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998013121212121" page_id="56266198"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
when they were given plain fruit and any available berries. They received
no meat and just six to 10 mealworms a day.
Sir Edward Hallstrom was Chairman of the Taronga Park Trust and often
sent collections, the most prized of which included birds of paradise, to
overseas zoos, often in exchange for stock for Taronga Zoo in Sydney. The
obituary noted that the Victoria Crowned Pigeons Goura victoria there were
survivors of about 50 collected by Shaw Mayer in the Ramu Valley. Similarly,
the White-bibbed Ground Doves Gallicolumba jobiensis were collected by
him from Yule Island or the mainland opposite. We had some at London
Zoo, which we called Jobi Island Ground Doves, and received collections
of birds of paradise in 1957 and 1965.
In 1966 Sir Edward decided to sell his remaining interests at Nondugl
and offered part of his collection of birds of paradise to the government.
The controlling trust employed Shaw Mayer to establish and manage what
became the Baiyer River Sanctuary. However, his health began to fail and
eventually G. G. George took over. About 1969 he moved to Lae and
regularly visited the market to look for young tree kangaroos and cuscuses.
One of the species he obtained there, Matschie's Tree Kangaroo Dendrolagus
matschiei , went on to become established in US zoos. His last expedition
was in early 1970, when he accompanied the American naturalist/
photographer Crawford H. Greenewalt to the Huon Peninsula.
In 1972, Queen Elizabeth II honoured him with the award of the MBE
(Member of the Order of the British Empire) for his work in establishing the
Nondugl and Baiyer River Sanctuaries and breeding birds of paradise.
On his retirement to Nambour, he kept exotic finches and on moving to
a retirement village, the management built him two large aviaries in which
he kept finches and pheasants. He reverted to the name Fred Mayer, having
throughout most of his career been known as Fred Shaw Mayer to avoid
confusion with the German A. B. Meyer, who published material on New
Guinea birds between 1874 and 1895, and the American Ernst Mayr, who
worked in the field in New Guinea at about the same time as Shaw Mayer's
early collecting expeditions there.
He was survived by his sister Miss Janet Mayer.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.985529" genericHeader="references" page_id="56266198" page_num="108" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.992742">
Delacour,J. 1963. Notes on Austral and Southern Pacific Birds. Avicultural Magazine 69,6:231-
234.
Goodfellow, W. 1934 &amp; 1998. The Royal Parrot Finch Erythrura cyaneovirens regia. Avicultural
Magazine (Fourth Series) XII,7: 173-182 &amp; 104,3:106-113.
Meams, B. and R. 1998. The Bird Collectors. Academic Press, San Diego and London.
Peckover, W. S. and George, G. G. 1992. Obituary: 'Masta Pisin' - The Bird Man of New
Guinea Fred Shaw Mayer M. B. E. 1899-1989. Emu 92:250-253.
Scott, P. 1964. Journey to New Guinea: The search for Salvadori's duck - an extract from the
diaries of Peter Scott. Animals 5,4:94-101.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999091" page_id="56266199"  page_num="109" year="" vol="">
109
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.689943" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266199" page_num="109" year="" vol="">
THE OMEI SHAN LIOCICHLA Liocichla omeiensis
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.95027125" page_id="56266199"  page_num="109" year="" vol="">
by Nigel Hewston
Introduction
This paper briefly describes the bird, its habitat, range, status and
husbandry, and summarises research and conservation to date originated
through interest in this species in captivity. This species provides an example
of how the interest of amateurs can lead to significant advances in knowledge,
and how this might be built on to develop more formal and professional
research and conservation programmes using the network of regional zoo
associations.
Description
The Omei Shan, Omei or Mount Omei Liocichla (Omei Shan means Mt
Omei) is a medium-sized (between Leiothrix and Garrulax) babbler
Timaliinae, one of three species in its genus. It is largely olive green above
and grey below with a pale belly, and with areas of bright yellow, orange
and red on wings and tail (see photo p. 113). This species is unusual (but
not unique) among babblers in its obvious sexual dichromatism which is
exhibited in the wing and tail plumage.
The flight feathers are mainly black with yellow leading edges in both
sexes, but the bases are orange, which is brighter and more extensive in
males. There are orange areas at the tips of the secondaries which are also
brighter and larger in males, so that they form a patch on the folded wing,
whereas in females they form a row of spots. The tail feathers are dark
olive, barred black above (more strongly in males) and tipped with yellow,
but males have the central four feathers tipped orange and the next four with
some orange on the yellow tips. The under tail-coverts are black edged with
yellow, but broadly tipped orange in males.
The orange on the wings (and tail in males) is formed by hair-like (i.e.
with no barbules) extensions to the feathers, on the leading edge of wing
feathers and the tip of tail feathers. Males in fresh plumage can be a vivid
red-orange in these areas, but the nature and location of the bright areas in
wings and tail can lead to wear and fading, while the under tail-coverts
retain their colour. This makes this the most reliable feature for sexing
captive birds, though wing plumage might be the most useful field character.
The eye is dark with a small black spot above, the bill and feet are greyish
horn. Juvenile plumage is similar, but duller, with all sexual characters
present on fledging.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995868" page_id="56266200"  page_num="110" year="" vol="">
110
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.5521085" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266200" page_num="110" year="" vol="">
HEWSTON - OMEI SHAN LIOCICHLA
Voice
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9941472" page_id="56266200"  page_num="110" year="" vol="">
Males have a loud, whistling song of six or more notes, falling in pitch
at the end. Males sing for most of the year except when moulting. Females
have a loud one- or two-note whistle usually only heard from unpaired birds
or those separated from their mate. There are quieter calls and a churring
call used in alarm and often before roosting.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.535905">
Range and Status
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994285484848485" page_id="56266200"  page_num="110" year="" vol="">
This species is endemic to China and is known only from a few mountains,
including Omei Shan and Erllang Shan, in central Sichuan (Collar, Crosby
and Stattersfield, 1994). It is found in the undergrowth of primary and
secondary forest between 1,000m and 2,400m (approx. 3,280ft - 5,870ft).
Robson (1989) records it as often seen around scraps and garbage near the
toilets at Wannian Temple at 1,020m (approx. 3,300ft) on Omei Shan.
IUCN lists this species as Vulnerable because of its small, fragmented
range coupled with habitat destruction, trapping and assumed consequent
decline in numbers. C.R. Robson (pers. comm. 1996) considers it likely
that the range is larger than presently known and that the bird's adaptability
to secondary habitats may reduce the threat from habitat loss.
The appearance of this species in trade in recent years is an obvious
cause for concern, though there is no firm evidence at present to suggest
that trapping occurs at a threatening level. Robson has not seen evidence of
trapping on visits to Omei Shan but the source of traded birds is not known
and neither is the bird's status or that of its habitat at sites other than Omei
Shan. The species was placed on CITES Appendix II in 1997.
Avicultural history
A. Broadbent (pers. comm.) first saw this species in the UK in 1980.
From the late 1980s it has appeared regularly in trade, usually in small
numbers (10 birds or fewer per consignment and probably no more than 30
birds in most years, and in some years few or none). These birds have come
into the UK from Belgium or Holland, and birds have presumably been
traded from these to other European countries and perhaps from Europe or
China to other regions. For a few months during 1998 the EC (European
Community) imposed a ban on importation of birds from China because of
avian influenza, though Chinese birds (not necessarily of this species) seem
still to have entered the EC via Indonesia. H. Bishop (pers. comm.) found
only three birds at Belgian dealers on several visits over about six months in
1998. The species' recent CITES listing should lead to the collection of
trade data.
The Omei Shan Liocichla was first bred in the UK by Richard Cockerill
in 1993 (Cockerill, 1993) and subsequently by Andrew Blyth in 1995 and
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.729922" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266201" page_num="111" year="" vol="">
HEWSTON - OMEI SHAN LIOCICHLA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999147" page_id="56266201"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
111
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.922632871794872" page_id="56266201"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
the author in 1996. Breeding has continued in all three collections. No
details are known of captive breeding in other countries. A census of known
keepers conducted in March 1998 recorded 21 males and 20 females in 10
collections, with nine males and two females reared in 1997.
Research
As so little is known about this bird in the wild, observations by
aviculturists have added significantly to knowledge of the species. Andrew
Blyth first noted (pers. comm.) the sexual dichromatism in adults, and I was
able to confirm this in juvenile birds. Breeding behaviour has only been
observed in captivity, and notes on breeding and plumage have been passed
to Craig Robson for a forthcoming book on babblers. A recording of song
has also been passed to Craig for use in the field. Specimens have been
passed to the Natural History Museum, which had no material at all for this
species. There are now skins of adult and juvenile males in the collection as
well as eggs, nestlings and nests.
Conservation
Contact was made with JNCC (Joint Nature Conservation Council (UK
Government conservation advisors)) early in 1997 on behalf of the Zoo
Federation's Passerine TAG with the aim of gaining CITES listing for the
species. These efforts were overtaken by The Netherlands' successful
proposal for CITES II listing. This does not ban trade but should bring it
under licence and lead to the collection of data on trade which may eventually
be useful in assessing whether trade is threatening. Efforts have been made
to encourage captive breeding by making contact with keepers and
prospective keepers through the Zoo Federation, Cage &amp; Aviary Birds and
individual contacts. This has led to a number of birds being sexed and
paired. Captive-bred birds have been moved to zoos in the hope that the
breedings in private collections can be repeated in zoos. This process is at
an early stage but, if successful, the institutional support of zoos should
give the species a more secure captive future in the long term than the efforts
of a few individuals. A British Isles studbook is proposed which, once
established, may be expanded to an EEP studbook covering Europe. It is
hoped that the profile of the species has been raised among those who might
contribute to its future without stimulating further trade in wild-caught birds.
Avicultural management
Housing
The species has bred in aviaries from about lm x 2m (approx. 3ft 3in x
6ft 6in) upwards, and in the company of birds ranging in size from yuhinas
Yuhina spp. and fulvettas Alcippe spp. to turacos Musophagidae and Wonga
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999094" page_id="56266202"  page_num="112" year="" vol="">
112
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.898283" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266202" page_num="112" year="" vol="">
HEWSTON - OMEI SHAN LIOCICHLA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.979344170731707" page_id="56266202"  page_num="112" year="" vol="">
Pigeons Leucosarcia melanoleuca. Pairs are highly territorial towards
conspecifics and should not be housed more than one pair per aviary, but
aggression towards other species is rare. These birds can be egg predators,
certainly of Painted Quail Excalfactoria chinensis and possible of Red-billed
Leiothrix Leiothrix lutea (A. Blyth pers. comm.), but birds in my aviaries
have ignored eggs of turacos and hill partridge Arborophila spp., and other
passerines of a similar size have been able to nest successfully. There have
been instances of aggression by males towards females, but this is rare and
pairs can generally be housed together all year round.
The birds are hardy in the UK and while they may use an enclosed shelter
if available, will winter outdoors successfully if provided with sheltered
roosting sites such as evergreen trees or bushes.
Feeding
These birds thrive on diets normally provided for omnivorous softbills
and will take foods such as universal food, soaked mynah pellets, diced
fruit, soaked sultanas and sweetcom. Livefood such as mealworms is given
daily, but not in quantity except when feeding chicks.
Breeding
The breeding season in the UK is usually from April - July, though birds
may nest as early as February (R. Cockerill pers. comm.) and as late as
September (H. Bishop pers. comm.). The nest is a deep cup built mainly by
the female, though males often display to females while carrying nesting
material and invite females to inspect prospective nest sites. The birds readily
build nests in conifers, evergreen bushes and bamboo, and have accepted
wire or wicker baskets placed in trees or bushes.
Materials used include coconut fibre, grass, bamboo leaves and moss,
the last in small quantities only. Hair seems to be ignored. Nests may be
built almost entirely of coconut fibre in twiggy bushes, but in bamboo dry
grass is usually necessary to anchor the base of the nest before it can be
completed using fibre. Cockerill (1993) and I have both experienced coconut
fibre nests which have been built in conifers and then fallen out complete,
leading to the loss of eggs. Nests in my aviaries have been built at heights
from 0.5m to 1.2m (approx. 1ft 8in - 4ft), but a pair at Chester Zoo built a
nest at about 2.5m (almost 5ft). Successful nests have been built in Lonicera
nitida, Spiraea bumalda, Asparagus, Chamaecyparis lawsoniana and
bamboo (unknown sp.).
Bamboo may be a particularly attractive site, as one pair in an aviary
with a L. nitida bush and bamboo used the bush successfully the first year
while the bamboo was very small, struggled to build in the bamboo the
following year but also nested in the bush and were eventually successful
in both, and the third year ignored the bush completely as the bamboo was
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.729773" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266203" page_num="113" year="" vol="">
HEWSTON - OMEI SHAN LIOCICHLA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999026" page_id="56266203"  page_num="113" year="" vol="">
113
</page>
<author confidence="0.5216">
Roger Wilkinson
</author>
<bodyText confidence="0.9903236" page_id="56266203"  page_num="113" year="" vol="">
Omei Shan Liocichla at Chester Zoo
now large enough to provide good nest sites. They have also transferred
their roosting site from the bush to the bamboo. Nests are not re-used,
though subsequent nests may be built very close to previous sites.
Clutch size is two to four (two clutches of two, nine of three, three of
four eggs) and both sexes incubate for about 14 days. Chicks seem to be fed
entirely on invertebrates at least until fledging at 13-14 days. Waxmoth
Galleria mellonella larvae are a favourite food, and Brown Crickets Acheta
domestica are also accepted, as are mealworms Tenebrio molitor. These are
fed as mini mealworms (15mm-18mm) for up to a week after hatching, then
as regular mealworms (25mm-30mm). In both cases white, soft-skinned
mealworms are selected whenever possible. Livefood is provided at least
four, and if possible six or more times daily once chicks have hatched.
Young have been reared on just waxworms and mini mealworms for the
first few days, followed by regular mealworms only. Wild invertebrates
caught in the aviaries must also contribute to the diet of the chicks. Wild
invertebrates are also collected and released into tanks or buckets in the
aviaries, particularly grasshoppers, mainly Meadow Grasshopper
Chorthippus parallelus , also Common Field Grasshopper C. brunneus.
These are often plentiful when second broods are being reared in July and
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999707" page_id="56266204"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
114
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.914717" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266204" page_num="114" year="" vol="">
HEWSTON - OMEI SHAN LIOCICHLA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.969470857142857" page_id="56266204"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
August, and appear to produce more brightly-coloured fledglings than
commercial livefoods.
Chicks are fed by both parents at the nest and after fledging. One brood
which was observed frequently was fed regularly to 42 days old, and one
bird was fed at 52 days. First-round young have not been observed helping
with incubation or feeding of subsequent broods, in fact they tend to hijack
parents en route to second nests with choice food items, and are often fed in
this situation. Young birds are tolerated by their parents until around the
end of the year, though it is safer to remove them at the latest when the adult
males start to sing again in October-November following the moult.
Mortality
There are few data available. Post mortem findings for the few deaths
investigated indicate trauma, Yersinia (A. Blyth pers. comm.), or are
inconclusive, but mortality in adult birds is generally low.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.726308">
Future Objectives
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999847777777778" page_id="56266204"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
It is hoped to develop a studbook and captive breeding programme,
initially in the British Isles. If successful this could be extended to Europe
and possibly to China or elsewhere as appropriate. There is considerable
potential to develop research on captive birds if the species becomes
established in zoos. Song and ethology would be good subjects for student
projects, and the other liocichlas, the Red-faced L. phoenicia and Steere's
L. steerii, are both breeding in British aviaries at present so comparative
studies might be possible. The appearance of this species in captivity has
provided a window of opportunity which I hope will be exploited.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.803014" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56266204" page_num="114" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9509919" page_id="56266204"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
Cockerill, R. 1993. Breeding Omei Shan Liocichla. Beak and Claw 89:8-10.
Collar, N.J., Crosby, M J. and Stattersfield, A.J. 1994. Birds to Watch 2. BirdLife International,
Cambridge.
Robson, C. 1989. Birdwatching areas: Omei Shan, Sichuan, China. Bull. Oriental Bird Club
9:16-21.
The above paper was published first in Proceedings of the Passerine &amp;
Pigeon Symposium (held 19th-20th May 1998, at Bristol Zoo Gardens) and
is reproduced here by kind permission ofABWAK (Association of British
Wild Animal Keepers). Copies of the Proceedings, price #4 including p &amp;
p, are available from:-Rick Green, ABWAK, 4 Llys Close, Oswestry SY11
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.269963" genericHeader="introduction" page_id="56266204" page_num="114" year="" vol="">
2UZ, UK. E-mailjrkgreen@talk21.com
</sectionHeader>
<figure confidence="0.168244" page_id="56266205"  page_num="115" year="" vol="">
THE MOULTING CYCLE OF THE AFRICAN JA^ANA
Actophilornis africanus IN AVICULTURE
by Greg Bockheim
</figure>
<page confidence="0.999614" page_id="56266205"  page_num="115" year="" vol="">
115
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99745727027027" page_id="56266205"  page_num="115" year="" vol="">
The African Ja#ana inhabits lakes and marshes throughout sub-Saharan
Africa from sea level up to 2,500m (approx. 8,200ft) (del Hoyo, 1998). It is
described as common throughout much of its range, with birds dispersing
widely to take advantage of flooded land and, once this becomes dry again,
moving onto wetter areas. It is one of the few bird species which is
polyandrous, females copulating and laying eggs with several males in a
single season. Under certain conditions in the wild pairs remain monogamous
(as they do in captivity because they are most often housed in pairs).
The coloration of the male and female African Jagana is identical. There
is a great difference in their body sizes though, with the males being nearly
half the weight of the females; proportionally the birds appear the same.
However, upon closer inspection it is clear that the male's feet and toes are
as large as those of the female, even though its body is so much smaller. At
Disney's Animal Kingdom (DAK) adult female weights have fluctuated
from 216g-250g and adult males from 120g-136g. Having large feet but
being of smaller size and weight than the female has for the male ja^ana
pros and cons. The male's large, weight-displacing feet and smaller size
afford him, as well as the chicks in his care, the opportunity to escape from
land-dwelling predators by subsisting on floating vegetation farther from
the shore. The larger size of the female jagana allows her to dominate the
male, it also makes it physiologically possible for her to lay numerous eggs
in numerous clutches for several males. Eggs are laid one per day during
the breeding season and the female may lay clutches for one to 10 males
(Tarboton, 1998).
The African Ja^ana moult is synchronous, meaning the flight and tail
feathers are shed at the same time, rendering the bird incapable of flight. At
first appearance this method of moulting may seem an ineffective strategy
for survival in the wild and, if unknown to the bird's keeper, it can come as
a surprise to discover handfuls of feathers in the bird's exhibit. In its natural
habitat the ja^ana moult may coincide with environmental conditions that
favour its flightless condition, the bird's secretive behaviour also affords it
protection when in close proximity to water and water plants.
Our experience with the j ananas at DAK revealed that when the moulting
process begins the birds initially become secretive. Within a few days
however they overcome this secretiveness, and exhibit what we consider to
be normal behaviour. Two or three days prior to moulting their flight feathers
many of the jaganas become less attentive towards the staff and remain hidden
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999416" page_id="56266206"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
116
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.473211" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266206" page_num="116" year="" vol="">
BOCKHEIM - AFRICAN JA#ANA
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.421273">
Greg Bockheim
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.976298" page_id="56266206"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
After about 18 days
even when live insects are being distributed; and during the 48 hours in
which the feathers are moulted the birds can often be observed hiding
amongst the vegetation in or surrounding the water. Soon after these feathers
are moulted, the birds resume their normal foraging behaviour.
During the moulting cycle, when they are flightless, the African Jaganas
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.405691" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266207" page_num="117" year="" vol="">
BOCKHEIM - AFRICAN JA#ANA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995336" page_id="56266207"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
117
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.911674666666667" page_id="56266207"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
Greg Bockheim
After nearly 20 days the process is almost complete
at DAK can be described as perceiving danger yet often choosing to roost in
'visitor busy' and predator accessible areas. They often spend the night
standing on the ground on the visitor (or guest) bridge, making it relatively
easy for DAK staff to capture them and physically examine them and record
their weights. One would expect a bird that has temporarily lost its main
mode of making a speedy retreat to be more secretive and seek refuge in
one of the many other areas of water, away from danger.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.62468">
Moulting
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999473166666667" page_id="56266207"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
Body contour feathers are replaced throughout the year in a manner
similar to that of most other birds - at a rate in which no obvious or
recognisable physical affect is demonstrated by the birds. By the time the
jaganas have moulted and regrown their flight and tail feathers their overall
appearance is that of robust and sleek birds.
The jaganas at DAK are quite uniform in the rate and order in which
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99913" page_id="56266208"  page_num="118" year="" vol="">
118
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.780083" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266208" page_num="118" year="" vol="">
BOCKHEIM - AFRICAN JA#ANA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997949390243902" page_id="56266208"  page_num="118" year="" vol="">
they moult their primary, secondary and tail feathers. The most conspicuous
moulting of these feathers occurs over the course of 72 hours, and with
some birds, less than 48 hours. One of the earliest signs of the onset of the
moult is the slightly dishevelled and fluffed appearance of the secondary
flight feathers and body contour feathers. In these instances the secondaries
have been observed hanging vertically to the ground while the primaries are
still held intact. Within the next 24 hours the secondaries fall out in clusters
followed within hours by the primaries. Small groups of these feathers will
be seen floating on the aviary pool or scattered throughout the bird's habitat.
Upon close examination of the birds, open feather follicles can be seen very
clearly. The jaganas' tail feathers, which can be difficult to see, moult out at
the same time as the flight feathers or within the following 24 hours. The
result is a very stumpy looking bird moving about on its long legs and toes.
The primary wing-coverts are soon moulted, exposing the underwing-coverts,
which are dropped later in the moult cycle. The area of the metacarpus, or
wrist joint just above the manus, may show marked feather loss, giving the
impression that the bird has worn the feathers from this area. New pin-
feather growth is recorded to erupt from the follicles within three days.
During the synchronous moulting stage adult ja#anas at DAK have shown
weight increases of 10g-25g. This slight increase in weight may be due to
the increased mass of heavy fluid-filled growing pin-feathers.
Because they are flightless during the moult, adult jaganas will swim
when necessary in order to reach other land areas or to escape danger. The
birds quickly move through the water paddling with their large feet in the
manner in which ducks swim. They are rarely observed to swim in this
manner outside of the moulting cycle. When the flight feathers are partially
grown the birds have been observed to flap their wings and run across the
surface of the water rather than swim.
The replacement of the flight and tail feathers, from the time the old
feathers are seen to drop until the new feather shafts have opened completely,
occurs over the course of 10-15 days, with the bird fully capable of flight by
day 20. Stress during the moult may slow the growth of the new feathers.
The varying types of stress that may affect feather growth include changes
in temperature and photoperiod, dietary deficiencies and interference from
other animals or humans. Once the stresses have been removed or relieved
the birds resume the proper rate of feather growth.
Juvenile moult
The juvenile jaganas at DAK have been recorded entering their first
synchronous moult - moulting their flight and tail feathers - at eight months
of age. Prior to this moult, their body contour feathers are replaced gradually,
when the juveniles are three to six months of age. The feathers of the head
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.406891" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266209" page_num="119" year="" vol="">
BOCKHEIM - AFRICAN JA#ANA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999476" page_id="56266209"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
119
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9741217" page_id="56266209"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
and neck are not replaced completely until after the birds complete their
synchronous moult, which occurs from the age of nine to 12 months. By
the time they have reached 12-14 months of age, aside from the blue of the
bill and frontal shield, the birds have acquired the coloration of adult jananas.
The black on the crown extends from the end of the frontal shield to the
base of the nape. The rich brown on the back, wing-coverts, rump and
abdomen becomes deeper in colour, and the white on the chin becomes
purer and extends to the upper part of the chest. An iridescent caramel
coloured band, mottled with black, occurs before the start of the rich brown
of the rest of the body. With many of the young birds at DAK the white on
the neck has extended in a broken pattern down the chest to the vent area. It
has taken up to one year for these white feathers to be replaced by the rich
brown feathers of the adult plumage.
The juvenile's second moult occurs gradually after one year. The second
synchronous moulting of the secondary, primary and tail feathers occurs
when the birds reach about 16 months of age. It is after this second moult
that they are likely to mature and appear more robust, with sleek plumage
that shimmers in the sunlight. The frontal shield above the bill develops its
blue-silver colour throughout the juvenile's first year and by the time of the
second moult, at 16 months, the colour reflects that of the adult.
Adult moult
At DAK all three wild caught African Ja#anas, one male and two females,
have undergone a synchronous moult just weeks prior to the onset of the
breeding season (in October and November). The breeding pair moulted
again in this manner in early spring following the breeding season (March).
Eggs have been laid in December, January and February. Initially, other
aviary inhabitants predated the eggs and this led to the replacement clutches
being removed for artificial incubation and hand-rearing, as described by
Congdon and Zima (2000).
Aggression
The African Jagana can in most circumstances be described as a placid
bird which resides by the water's edge. However, on occasions during the
rearing and maturing periods, birds at Disney's Animal Kingdom have had
to be permanently separated. We found that adult females cannot be kept
together in the same aviary during the breeding season and there is a bit of a
risk in trying to keep them together even outside of the breeding season. If
the aviary is very large and has water features at opposite ends, two females
may co-exist.
Juvenile females need to be separated at the first sign of aggression, as
the dominant female will cause any cage or aviary mates, including siblings,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.977757" page_id="56266210"  page_num="120" year="" vol="">
120
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.777623" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266210" page_num="120" year="" vol="">
BOCKHEIM - AFRICAN JA#ANA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993886928571429" page_id="56266210"  page_num="120" year="" vol="">
to cower. At DAK dominant females have been seen to prevent other jaganas
getting access to food bowls and keeping them away when livefood is being
distributed. These other ja 9 anas frequently crouch motionless amongst the
bushes or in corners of the aviary, prompting human intervention to ensure
their well being. At DAK we found that when female jaganas reach six
months of age they often need to be separated into male/female pairs or
placed in their own habitat.
One of the telltale signs that ja 9 anas have been fighting is the development
of what appears as dark, almost black, freckling on the bill and frontal shield.
These are sites of tissue trauma caused by pecking by an adversary. Males
will occasionally suffer this as a consequence of not giving their mate the
amount of space she desires. The pre-copulatory behaviour of the male
African Ja 9 ana explicitly reveals his respect and submissiveness toward the
female.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.434597" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56266210" page_num="120" year="" vol="">
References and bibliography
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.729181333333333">
Carrascal, L. M, Mozetich, I., Senar, J. C. &amp; Domenech, J. 1998. Interactions between
environmental stress, body condition, nutritional status and dominance in great tits. Auk 115,3:
727-735.
Congdon, S. &amp; Zima, B. 2000. Breeding African Jacanas Actophilornis africanus at Disney's
Animal Kingdom. Avicultural Magazine 106,1: 62-73.
del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A. &amp; Sargatal, J. (eds.). 1996. Handbook of the Birds of the World Vol.3.
Hoatzin to Auks. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona, Spain.
Fry, C. H. 1983. Brooding and a Structural Character of the African Jacana. Ostrich 54,3:175-
176.
Hodgson, R. 1983. Rearing the African Jacana Actophilornis africana at the Wildfowl Trust,
Slimbridge, Glos. Avicultural Magazine 89,2:67-68
Tarboton, W. R. 1992. Aspects of the Breeding Biology of the African Jacana. Ostrich 63,4:141-
157.
The Moulting Cycle of the African Jacana Actophilornis africanus was
written by Greg Bockheim when he was working at Disney's Animal Kingdom,
Florida, and his observations were made on birds living in the collection
there. Greg is now General Curator at Potawatomi Zoo, South Bend,
Indiana, USA. E-mail:Ernieaves@aol.com
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.884909" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266211" page_num="121" year="" vol="">
COLLATED DATA ON THE TIMOR SPARROW
</sectionHeader>
<copyright confidence="0.164931">
Padda or Lonchura fuscata
</copyright>
<page confidence="0.997192" page_id="56266211"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
121
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.979609833333333" page_id="56266211"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
by Neville Brickell
The Timor Sparrow is also known as the Brown Ricebird, Brown
Mannikin, Brown Padda or Timor Dusky Sparrow. It measures 13cm (5in)
in length. The crown and nape are black, as are the chin and a narrow line
dividing the upper and lower breast; the cheeks are white. The mantle,
back, rump and upper tail-coverts are dark chocolate brown, the wing-coverts
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.8398535">
Neville Brickell
Timor Sparrow
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996154875" page_id="56266211"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
are blackish chocolate and the tail is deep rich brown. The breast and
underparts are white. The irides are dark brown and the orbital skin is bluish-
grey. The bill is silvery-grey and the legs and feet are pale brown. The male
is described as inseparable from the female, but Restall (1996) is of the
opinion: 'it seems that males are darker and glossier, the females browner
on breast and mantle'. Immature birds have the crown dusky brown, the
cheek patches whitish, the mantle and wings dark brown, and the belly pale
whitish cinnamon. The bill is slate-grey.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997171" page_id="56266212"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
122
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.656109" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266212" page_num="122" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - TIMOR SPARROW
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.966519047619048" page_id="56266212"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
Field characteristics
A large mannikin with white cheek patches, chocolate brown upperparts
and white underparts. Its large bill is silvery-grey.
Distribution and status
It is restricted to East Timor, West Timor and its outlying islands of
Semau and Roti, where it is widespread, but generally sparsely and patchily
distributed. It is locally moderately common, but often difficult to find and
appears to have declined. BirdLife International (2000) lists is as vulnerable
fearing that it is likely to suffer a rapid decline in the near future, as the
result of increasing exploitation for the cage bird trade and habitat loss.
Targets include surveys to clarify its distribution and ecological requirements
and its population size and trends, so that effective conservation measures
can be implemented. There is also the need to monitor and regulate trapping
and trade, and devise and enforce effective legislation.
Habitat and general habits
It occurs mainly in lowland areas, where it feeds on or near the ground
in grassland, lightly wooded cattle pasture, scrub, overgrown gardens,
deciduous or degraded monsoon forest and the edges of cultivation. It usually
occurs singly or in small groups of three to five birds, occasionally in the
company of other seed-eating species such as the Red Avadavat Amandava
amandava and mannikins Lonchura spp.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.584652">
Feeding
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995621466666667" page_id="56266212"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
The Timor Sparrow feeds principally on the inflorescences of grasses,
including those of weeds and, apparently, thistles (Clement et al. 1993;
Restall, 1996). It appears that insect food plays little or no part in its diet
(Burkard, 1980; Restall, 1996). Birds trapped in the field were fed solely
on a diet of dry, plain paddy rice. On receiving three pairs, consisting of
adults and immature birds, in a shipment from Jakata, Restall (1989) offered
the new arrivals a finch mixture consisting mostly of millets, along with
paddy rice and millet sprays. Also favoured were lettuce, orange slices and
mealworms. Later as their diet widened, they no longer accepted the
greenfood, orange or mealworms, but would still nibble at apple and pear.
The ARU (Avicultural Research Unit) fed its seven pairs a similar seed diet
to that described above, plus the inflorescences of Guinea Grass Panicum
maximum , which its birds preferred. Some individuals would also accept
chickweed, broken decorticated (dehusked) sunflower seeds, split peanuts
and termite alates.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.519474" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266213" page_num="123" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - TIMOR SPARROW
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997912" page_id="56266213"  page_num="123" year="" vol="">
123
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.471528">
Housing
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970766815789474" page_id="56266213"  page_num="123" year="" vol="">
One pair in the UK was housed in a breeding cage about lm (3ft 3in)
cubed (Restall, 1989 ). The dividing panel of a double-breeder should be
removed to allow access to both sides. The ARU housed all 14 birds in a
compartment cage which measured 3m long x 70cm wide x lm high (approx.
9ft 9in long x 2ft 3in wide x 3ft 3in high). Plants included potted ferns,
palms and indigenous grasses. Each pair had access to two nests in the open
or concealed beneath foliage. A colony may be housed in an ornamental
garden aviary with, if preferred, other mannikin species as company. Avoid
the Java Sparrow P. oryzivora though as I have observed bullying by this
larger species when selecting nest sites.
Voice
In the Avicultural Magazine Restall (1989) described his first impression
of the undirected call as: ' clik clik clik diklikliklikW. Noting that the bird
performing the advertisement song, stood clear of the perch and moved
slightly from side to side but did not point at any other bird in the vicinity.
On another occasion, he noted that a bird stood on top of a nest-box and
nearby cage and performed a full advertisement song - &apos;chip chip chip
chipchipchipchip (gurgling, gargling, chip)&apos;.
Display
The male twists his head and tail towards the female while bobbing up
and down on the perch, jumping clear of the perch with each bob (Restall,
1996).
Breeding
A single reference exists in which it states that the nests are constructed
of various fibres and grasses, and are placed in tree holes, clinks in walls
and in small, dense shrubs (Restall, 1996). In captivity they have accepted
lovebird nest-boxes packed with coconut fibres and half-open-fronted finch
nest-boxes, and have included raffia and white cotton threads as lining
(Restall, 1989). A UK report by Martin (1961) referred to them having
utilized a Budgerigar nest-box, which was lined with hay, moss, bits of paper
and feathers. The ARU found that of all the nesting receptacles offered, a
Gouldian nest-box was their first choice. Nest linings offered were the
inflorescences of Natal Red-top Rhynchelytrum repens , lucerne, wheat straw,
Pampas Grass Cortaderia selloana plumes and dried, finely cut Kikuyu
Grass Pennisetum clandestinum , used in lawns in South Africa.
Both sexes participate in nest building. The clutch size can vary from
two to nine eggs, with five being the most usual number (Restall, 1996).
The ARU recorded clutches of four to six eggs, with five being the most
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999287" page_id="56266214"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
124
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.824112" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266214" page_num="124" year="" vol="">
BRICKELL - TIMOR SPARROW
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993275875" page_id="56266214"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
usual number. The eggs are white and measure 18mm x 12mm. Both sexes
share the incubation which Restall (1996) recorded as taking 13 days, while
the ARU found that among seven pairs it varied from 12-14 days. Newly
hatched nestlings are naked and pink, but after a few days become darker.
Restall (1996) recorded the fledging period as 21 days, but the ARU found
strong flighted young emerging after up to 26 days. In Germany, Burkard
(1980) bred this species to the fourth generation. Clutch sizes varied from
two to nine eggs. One pair reared 19 young in three consecutive broods.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.548481">
Hybrids
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.817156333333333" page_id="56266214"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
I know of no records of captive mutations, but a hybrid male Timor x
normal Java Sparrow and Timor x white Java Sparrow have been benched
at local bird shows here in South Africa.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.624672" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56266214" page_num="124" year="" vol="">
References and bibliography
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.828652368421053">
BirdLife International. 2000. Threatened Birds of the World. Lynx Edicions in association
with BirdLife International, Barcelona, Spain.
ARU. 1999. Feeding/Breeding Record Cards. KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa.
Burkard, R. 1980. Von einigenseltneren Psittaciden und Prachfinken. Gefielderte Welt 1-2.
Clement, P, Hams, A. &amp; Davis, J. 1993. Finches &amp; Sparrows - An Identification Guide.
Russel Friedman Books cc, Halfway House,South Africa.
Goodwin, D. 1982. Estrildidfinches of the world. British Museum (Natural History), London.
Martin, A. 1961. Breeding of the Brown Mannikin. Avicultural Magazine 67,3:89-90.
Restall, R. 1989. Reminscences of Rare Mannikins Part II. Avicultural Magazine 95,4:192-
209.
Restall, R. 1996. Munias and Mannikins. Russel Friedman Books cc. Halfway House, South
Africa.
Verheigen, J. A. 1976. Some data on the avifauna of the island of Roti, Lesser Sunda Islands,
Indonesia. Zool. Meded. 50:1-21.
White, C. M. W. and Bruce, M. D. 1986. The Birds of Wallacea: Sulawesi, the Moluccas and
Lesser Sunda Islands, Indonesia. B.O.U Checklist No. 7.
Neville Brickell, 100 Innes Road, Durban 4001, KwaZulu-Natal, South
Africa. Tel/Fax:031-3129701 (from outside of South Africa replace 031
with 27-31 )/E-mail:ainvests@global.co.za
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.839206" genericHeader="references" page_id="56266214" page_num="124" year="" vol="">
CORRECTION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.73478475" page_id="56266214"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
In notes on behaviour and ecological requirements of Rothschild's
Mynahs Leucopsar rothschildi by Walter A. Sontag Jr. in Avicultural
Magazine 107,1:10-20 (2001), one number was altered in the editorial process
in Graph D on page 15: R 2 = 0.7481 is correct (not 0.8532). Thus, this
coefficient of determination of the linear regression analysis (for the juvenile
Rothschild's Mynahs in Group 3) was clearly lower than that in Graph A
(R 2 = 0.8532 for the adult Rothschild's Mynahs in Group 1). This in no way
affected any of the conclusions of the paper.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993104" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266215" page_num="125" year="" vol="">
ADDITIONS AND CORRECTIONS TO UK FIRST BREEDING RECORDS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.961615" page_id="56266215"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
125
</page>
<figure confidence="0.971980302325581" page_id="56266215"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
C/P
CD
&apos;o
U
&lt;D
&gt;
a
Q
73
CD
&apos;Sh
a
o
C D XI
U # 7
i-- 1 -*--&gt; O
^ * C
c -o &apos;H
" s?
" -g .2
&lt;d *rJ
&gt; 3 .2
&lt;-; *Cd ^Cd
C rt
&amp; 73
S X ^
G W)
o G z
&apos;c75 &gt;
,3 cS 13
*3 X &lt;d
n ^ -G
u -r) "
&lt;D 5 c
Sou
73
c
cd
CD
8 o #
35 c o
.2 c o
00 T3 &lt;N
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.79192494117647" page_id="56266215"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
. 8 .2
#2H-o
g CD &lt;D
# $ S
.g C/5
c o " -1
U &lt;D O
CT Oh X
Oh &lt;D
CD 2
X o
-*-&gt; &lt;Z5
C &lt;D
" "
cd
73 'a
gH g
C/3
S 73
S 1
+_&gt; co
C/3 ^
O DG cd
^ -- -G
73 cd
&lt;D C (D
S :a S
s
x&gt; o c
o -S o
CD
o 03
c
73 *- -q
</equation>
<figure confidence="0.990626381944444" page_id="56266215"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
&lt;D &lt;D ,
O on '
CO&apos;!
cd
C/3 03
2 s-h
-G CD
c \0x25A0a
.2 *
^ S
2 CD 73
g C CD
# 2 "&gt;
.2 2 k!
, &lt;3 ^
so Q/ O
"&quot;&apos; t/3
*
73 ,C
&lt;D
C/3
CD
1/3
2 CD
-5 tofl
.2 S
2 &quot;o
'-G VH
H *S&gt;
T E
w CD
^ 2
C/3 O
*c #?
o #
C/3 73
cd C
c 3
cd c n
Jg
03
73 73
&lt;D 5--i
\0x25A0S S
CD Gh
CD O
s--
Oh G
O .2
Cd 03
-HH O
IS
&lt;D
CD
cd
CD
CD
&lt;D
CD
M
#
2
CD (D
OO
OS
&apos;-- 1 'S ^
.2 ~
C/3
,-, C/3
O cd
.2 73
&lt;D
o ^
2 73&quot; &apos;G
CD cd
G ^
\0x25A0rH g Cd
--; &lt;D Vn
-O CD od
G X &gt;
Oh &lt;d CD
# G --
G ^ O
G
&quot;G c/3.2
S " s
&apos;2|iS
CD &gt; c
GUO
C/3 Oh3
&lt;D
-G
C/3
CD
cd
cd &lt;D
73
CD
CD
G D 73
c/3 .g
C/3
G G
O Oh
b/j oo
2 cd
g *
8 .2
73 "
2 ^
&amp;;S&gt;
#* o
, &lt;G
CD 73
G
CD
(3D
+-&gt; cd
G G
&lt;D C
G
cd
,&lt;D
Qh fD;
a %&gt;
o
CM
OO &lt;u
22 "
00 PD
s w
CD Dc!
03 y CO
\0x25A0 * o
cn in
03
30 03
D D &lt;
D5 O S&apos;! OO
M y co ^
C cn rc
* -23*2
N ffl .^N m -
di D &lt;! " D U
c o
(D
o g
s s
S #
o o
CN
CN 30
03 03
03 --
G CN
03
32 03
PQ ^
U &lt;
o
cs .y
V, =
" X
s o
^ tS
S S
t&gt;0 73
c e
o o
J J
5 0,1
 |^ |
K 7b o
#1 -s
W) &gt;
HUM
j-H C"
o
ft, o
!"
t-8
c
c
N
&gt;, 5
73 0Q
VI VI
C C
d3 S
c3 c3
s s
X) 03
# ^
W) T3
uwqSS^mS
inCN3OCN3OC^O3(N(Nc&lt;3t^O3O3C30(NCN
30 03 03 00 03 00 03 03 03 00 00 03 00 00 03 03
03 03 03 OO 03 03 03 03 03 03 03 03 03 03
OJ
S) ft, 2
K ^ I
^ &amp;, "
vj
r s ^2
I Z Z
l**
W
CD
DC
tu 9
c a
i I
a
V.
CJ
.cn
S7
S w
# CD
3 G
73 cd
^ O a O
pi CD U
'\0x25A0a ^
t .2
(c) ~Di
(c)H S
CvT sr
#
.00
#
a ^
'# ^ S
r~ M 22
* o m
^ ^
S 5 5
O L) ^
H n j
^ 2 &lt;
w 3 m
U 2 H
&lt; 5 K
Sh
(c)
a
I
11
a
(c) (c)
S |
# ^
^ -2 (c)
2 ^ j O
&amp;#2 S O
s a g g
sS2^
2 ^ S5 j
&lt; ^ 5 S
S ^ u w
A ^ H S
0 &lt; Dcj C/p
&lt; J Uh W
&gt;1
11
&lt; U
W " -
00 U *H
O O * #
O O co
o
^ a
(c) 73
a _
S *S.
-a&quot;
(c) (c)
Oo
(c)
a
&amp;
(c)
w &gt;H ^ ,
H 5 U =a
S o 5 ^
O # Q W
D CD fl a
^ 5 S o
</figure>
<page confidence="0.987488" page_id="56266216"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
126
</page>
<figure confidence="0.988197373770492" page_id="56266216"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
OQ
p p p
Oh Oh Oh GO
o 52
O &quot;
&lt;u M
# #
&lt;u
U
Oh&apos;
O
03
p V
03 ^
fi tS
*S s
&gt;.
o
c
03
E:
O &lt;D
o S
N o
e U
O C&gt;
T3 P
C &gt;
O Oh
^ o
i2 pq
ts
&lt;D
&gt; i-i
&quot;O &lt;o
01 c
ca &lt;U
is a:
i3 [-i d
** &gt;&apos; IS
u !&gt; ti
a " ' 2
S J
I Ja
p U
e g
&lt;u .5
p -o
$*S
S d
00
s
TO c"
-G &lt;U -
s " |
TO ^ P
a oo pq
&lt;
S
*-5
TO
X
TO
z
y
03
Z
O
y
O
P
TO
X
O*
2
TO 03
z y
O
03
Z
PQ
d
2
2 5
O
y
&lt;
y
00
in
00
0
&lt;N
NO
&lt;N
t&quot;-
_ _.
0
00
NO
_ _ _
NO
r~
NO
NO
00
t-~
ON
NO
NO
00
ON
ON
ON
ON
OO
ON
ON
00
ON
ON.
o&gt;
00
OO
On
OO
ON
ON
OO
ON
ON
OO
00
On
ON
On
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
On
ON
ON
ON
Os
ON
ON
ON
On
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
On
a
TO T3
G #
# " g
w " &gt;
IE &gt;. p g 52
x&gt; &lt;U Z 1 O .2
3 'o o&gt;&lt; PC 45
P4 P -a K
d U S O CQ
c"
O H VO t*- VO
a s
S g,
*S &amp;
2
p
tn *3
UJ
2 K
m 00
fc E
a z
S &lt;
tc y
^ o
p &lt;
^ w
w ^
&apos; X
3 g
^ s
&lt; d
u a
2 #
P&apos;S Oh
W D
&gt; #*
0 a
s P
P $s
I
11
Oh X
g* *H
S .8
B^s
# ?
Co O&apos;.
*g Z
18
&lt;50 p
&lt;3 &lt;
00 fc
Q &gt;H p
d 2 *S
"S S
S y a
&lt; z y
H *&lt; s_|
gum
M # o
00 &lt;1 X
" 3
3 c
1 Sp s
s ^ 2
^ ^ o
8 8 #
P &quot;&lt;3 &lt;3
y y is
J W r "
W Z ^
&amp; s w
#og
sal
s* a p
p!;&gt;
H 5 &gt;H
g y a
&lt;#g
2 H
2 o
o
w
3
* a
&lt; *
u
&lt;
# g
O 8
cz2 y
a
P
y
o
w
H
H
S w
* s
^ H
w P
o: o
O 00
Q
M y
P PQ
W CO
ffi o
z S
#
s J
5 O
6 y
15
x ^
y pp
p 00
P &lt;3
P P
P P
to g.
'c 8
o P
^ PQ
pi o
&lt;3 p
^ g.
&lt;3 p
Jy
g. H
Z
S ffi
&gt;H
P 3
d 2
X o
Oh 00
&lt;c d
5 1
a "
S H
1 a
S y
i 0^
</figure>
<page confidence="0.93124" page_id="56266217"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
127
</page>
<figure confidence="0.755544355140187" page_id="56266217"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
s ^
is
(c)
(c) &amp;0
. 0)
u
ft&apos;s
a 2
Js m
i Pi
M PQ
c/5 PP
11
" s
"5
ess
s s s
o o o
o u o
t/3 fcifci&apos; z3iz3&lt;/:i &apos; z3,_H
Dh
Oh Q.
o o
-C J3
o (c)
-- Oh
&amp; Oh
O o
C/2 22
pq aa S pq
.22 .22 .22
t/i w cc vi
Oh Oh Oh .
O O O [V
-C JO -C *
c/3 C/3 c/3 PQ
PQ PQ PQ oq
op co oo &lt;j
s s
s s
1
CN
Pt
&lt;N
Tj-
&lt;N
Tt\0x25A0
ON
ON
wo
in
CN
ON
ON
rP
rP
cn
\
ON
ON
ON
cn
04
ON
ON
ON
\0x25A0--.
(N
--\0x25A0
&gt;n
S
s
s
PQ
PQ
&lt;
&lt;
&lt;
U
U
S On
S 00
ON
r-&quot;
ON
ON
oio
o
SP
TO
\0x25A0 o"
j On N
S 2 n
w&gt;(c)n
&lt;2 a
5 to
6 8
^ o aa JS c5
o fri
X CQ
X e
P2
#
0^-3
5 I
s s
s s
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.969082551724138" page_id="56266217"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
o o
o o
C/3 C/3 &lt;Z2 C/3
S-l ^H S-H l_
&lt;D &lt;D &lt;D &lt;D
PLh Pu Pu Oh
!/3 C/1 CO C/3
TO TO TO t3
o
o
3
PQ
1 |
X ss
TD -O
o o
o
&quot;O -a
S- --
5 S
o o
11
s s
&lt;u 0)
o o
o o
PC PC
&apos;O TO
o o
o o
&apos;H V,
pq pq
&lt;u &lt;u
o o
PC PC
TO TO
O O PS
o &apos;c,
Z 43
T3 X
&gt;&lt;
c3
#
&lt;U
bfl
g S3
&gt;N
i
&amp;Q
. o
SIS
* s
00 C"
PQ
CeQ P^ PQ PsQ PeQ
X ?
. cS
PQ U
</equation>
<figure confidence="0.981702549132948" page_id="56266217"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
2*
u
CS
&lt;u ^
T3
*22 jU
# * s a
o
o
N
c
a, "-&gt; o o o o
s tii! S S S c
* - &lt;u a&gt; . o
Xo.PQo-DQHUUUi--1
a&gt;NO rr, ^ OnnO ^ NO Ifi -- r 1 Oh&apos;tN(Nr, NiTiiTiOOir, h5N^CX--(NT
9iOnOn^^OnOnOnOnooOnoOOOOnO&apos;OnOnOnOnnOooOn^^O&apos;OOOOnOnOnOn
^OnOnONOnOnOnOnOnOnOnOnOnOnOnOnOnOnOnOnOnOn^^OnOOnONONONOn
ts
si
s s
a
-a
o&apos;
X
PS
U
&lt;
PQ
X
as
a&apos; ^
5 #
a a
-a a
t* Sh
P-3
a a a a
H
Z
&lt;c
C/5
w
PC
On
as
w
00 X
y&gt; So
N C/5
2 5/5
s I
X X
PQ X
a c^
sc &lt;
K H
as #
^ u
c/5 X
So Z
S o
Z 7
O "
^ as
H H
Z Z
&lt; &lt;
00 00
&lt; -&lt;
X X
X X
PU PLh
Q Q
as
u u
X X
z z
6 6
z z
5 2
s ^
'5, -S
a^ -2
&lt;&gt;a a
U O
O Z
p
W U 2
PS PS
o o
&lt;
5 a
&lt; u
co s: co
, a ^ ^
 |8 s
S &apos;o &lt;&lt;
^ a ^
PP ^
m c a
9 s .s
6 OQ ^
*r a o
w 3 z
x #
H W &lt;
Z u J
&lt; DC o
&gt; H W
1 --N Tt&apos;I hh
S S sg
Sul
S\0x25A0
a
-2 .22
^ o
o
a
J Z
j*.
*2 &lt;3
^ c ^
-2 .2
Cl, a
c&lt;5 ^
cd up
&gt; &gt;
*2
a, r
2 2 ?
# M
^ .ts
^ Cl,
^ a
Cd -a
O Z
Q P
o w
Z S ~ -
o h z ^
* 5 g o
u z
S 2
S-1
^ a
&gt;! ^
g, S
11
O
"-" r-H 5S
O ^ ^ h
g g g P
pii
J Ld
Cd
Z
O
w
o
dS
H
U
OS
pp
J
D
u-
H
X
&lt;
w
PQ PQ
</figure>
<page confidence="0.958123" page_id="56266218"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
128
</page>
<figure confidence="0.80397525" page_id="56266218"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
" g
U CL,
DO
&lt;D
</figure>
<page confidence="0.67818" page_id="56266218"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
04
</page>
<equation confidence="0.820224729166667" page_id="56266218"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
# #
# #
o o
in
rn t-&lt;
6s o
oo Os
# # S S
# # c?
O O 30
o o -- 03
" " cri pq
0) &lt;D * *
CU Oh U U
- Tt d
gj # #
o o
On Os
O s Os
00 00
&lt;U &lt;D
(Si 04 "n S
. &apos;-- 1 o
T3 T3 7^ d
&lt;D &lt;D c-5 g
&lt;U D O
Vh s-h O&apos; c/3
P5 PQ ^ M
to tC ^ o
03 03 ^ &apos;S
Oo Pu &lt; &gt;
&lt;N Os
OS oo
Os Os
03 03
pu ou
o
o
" N
0 0 3
SS|
u u " u
o
03
&lt;u =0 &lt;u ~ _c -C
.s a do 3 a # #
 |2? #*  |3 3
Q " ^ ^ ^
</equation>
<figure confidence="0.998768086206896" page_id="56266218"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
2 H &lt; &lt; H &lt; &lt;1
a q
(U W
u "3
03 NH
X) 00 00
&lt;D 3 3
D O O
# o o
+3 u o
s s s
#
cD
c d
&lt;D 3
c" .CD
.2 &gt;
00 c/3
&lt; n O. I 2
m^ooNoo^^oomoaoo"\o^OMONM(N"D-ooo&apos;OOi&gt;D , oo\o
Os Os oo Os Os OO OO OO Os OS OO CO Os Os Os Os OO OO OO OS ^ os OS OS Os oo Os 0C Os oo oo
Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os
S. S&apos;
c&gt; 2
a: ^
z z
o o
W W
o 2
cu
h b
D Z&gt;
# a
a
&lt;3
a,
a
a
j3
a
a
Q
Z,
o
w
a
a
CO
l 5
"s
a
Cj
a
Q
Z
O
w
a
#
j
&lt;
2
uj
0^
s &lt;
R 2
03 w
hJ Oh
p
00 j#j
03 03
X c4
OUO
't, s
*2
a a
S&apos; S
E, 1
o S\0x25A0
H 60
O o
04 bq
* H
03
Oh nj
O 3
# 5
a 3
03 i--I
cn
03 pq
03 U
o
Q
&gt;3
S 00
S&apos; a
O hs;
*n 3
"3 -a
-2 #
^ H
H 03
03 03
03 2
S #
03 03
04 03
o m
48 3
# pt
o o
J J
J J
03 03
&gt;"
Q IJ
5 a
W a.
2 a
*S!
s ?
&gt;2
a
to
a
*2 s
a 5
e -SP
a "
|p
a
a
^ t?
*2
5 a
11
1 s
2 S
S
Q
?
a
^ a
\0x25A0I ^
Q a
s O
Co
H
IS
I*
H
O
04
04
#
04 O
04 ^
O
s &lt;
# 1
h3 00
W W
3 "
A W
Q hJ
03 03
04 U
03
Q
04 g
a z
z &lt;
U U
</figure>
<page confidence="0.959149" page_id="56266219"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
129
</page>
<figure confidence="0.950015071428571" page_id="56266219"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
&lt;N
^t
Os
so
Os
cn
Os
Os
#
g
&lt;u
c
in
OS
#
a
ro
CO
Os
ci
&lt;N
00
g
&lt;u
o
\0x25A0s.
c3
Os
c
o
Os
O
Os
Vh
3
XI
o
PQ
U
i A
S
Cq
&quot;S
H
s
&lt;
03
CJ
CU
PQ
pq
s
&lt;
o
&gt;&gt;
X
</figure>
<page confidence="0.904108" page_id="56266219"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
13
</page>
<equation confidence="0.932201142857143" page_id="56266219"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
e3
Cd
CL c *5
r/l r*i
03 03 03 03 03 03 O)
#######
o o o o o o o
I I I I I I I
^ C/3
PQ PQ CQ PQ PQ PQ PQ " S
voinioininfriiDoo
OOONOOOOOOaNONO(c)
Os Os Os Os Os Os Os Os
s" 71 *-&gt;
4)
&quot;O
\0x25A0o
I #
O
o
S #
</equation>
<page confidence="0.216891" page_id="56266219"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
00
</page>
<figure confidence="0.971706447470817" page_id="56266219"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
&gt;&gt;
&lt;D
JD
#3
^3
c
O
o
o
o
o
or&gt;
or&gt;
c &amp;
s s
&lt;3 d3
^ *s
d
"3
o
T3
*--
.$" m
ffib^SSSSEpg
00C0N0NDOOOOC-&quot;
#
M
d)
p
1
03
03
X
Cq
#
&lt;o
c
u
Z&apos;
u
#
#
Sh
o
K
c"
&lt;D
&lt;U
o,
u
o
*3
OT
pq
GO
i-- 1
Z
Cq
Os
O
i
oo
CM
00
o
ON
00
OO
Os
ON
ON
ON
ON
s qs
.ft 'a
^3 ^ ^
&lt;*&gt;
s
s s
.3 .3
5, '5,
3 3
pq u
Pd Cd
3 3
s s
3 3
2 3
s
t 3
*2 1
r I
-I
5 ^
J S&apos;
m w
H H
Z Z
2 2
Cq Cq
ft, ft,
w w
cd Pd
D p
z z
o o
u u
Q Q
pq pq
Pd Pd
pq pq
pq pq
E E
u u
z z
pq pq
pq tq
cd Pd
O O
pq
ft, &amp;
m ^
&amp; z
D O
z u
O Q
U pq
Q ftn
w w
" o
pq J
pq L&gt;
ffi O
pq cd
s a
O E
-ft s -
3 ^3
41
3 SS
So Oo
ft 3
\0x25A0C 3
2 ;s
^ fej
pq w
s ^
D ^
Z
o
u
oo
E
u
3
a |.S
 |d &amp;
%'S S
3 .2 2
3 3 3
*, 3 C
5 Oo 3
Jg 3 3
3 $ e
ft 3 2,
^CQ g
gHS
Igz
"3?0
H 2 y
pq S &lt;
a &lt; s
o
u
n
&lt;
cd
f-H
# c/P
S #
pq &lt;
a &lt; z
* K &lt;
3 Q Q
SUM
^ Z I
|5S
^ z u
E pq
g q 2
^ q c
o o u
S O 00
3 '---
N ft
It
So 3*
3 2
3
1-s
3 o
&lt; K
pq &lt;
S S
*2
&apos;ll
s ^
3 I
Oo "ft
Q 3
s ft
3 ft
t3 &amp;
ft 2
S J
,&gt; ^ ^
&lt; z g
S o o
&lt; N N
aid
U Z z
u &lt; &lt;
^ H Q
^ Z W
&gt; pq J
35^
3 &gt; Q
pq h pq
&gt;H oo Pd
*3 e
4#
.5 -S
3
"C
3
h -iS
ft 2
S" &quot;3
-ft
3
18
o*
R ^
&lt;R
^ **
S1
00 2
Pd 00 -
WO w
8|b
co &gt; X
qq^
PURPLE-CRESTED TOURACO Tauraco porphyreolophus 1988 Mrs F. Raison Pers. comm.
BLACK-BILLED TOURACO Tauraco schuetii 1994 Old House Bird Gardens S. Bishop pers. comm.
GREAT BLUE TOURACO Corythaola cristata 1999 Old House Bird Garden C.B. 14/8/1999:3
ROADRUNNER Geococcyx californina 1994 Banham Zoo D. Armitage pers. comm.
GREATER COUCAL Centropus menbecki 1992 Rode B.G. F.B. 1996:35
</figure>
<page confidence="0.768815" page_id="56266220"  page_num="130" year="" vol="">
130
</page>
<figure confidence="0.906075707792207" page_id="56266220"  page_num="130" year="" vol="">
# ^
B ts
o &lt;d
o &gt;&gt;
. cd
U (TM)
CD
Oh CQ
#
# o-
o g
c /3 cn
J-l
# g #
# # *
&lt;D O
o o
cd . *
CO # "
03 &lt;D
PQ cq cq &gt; Oh
CQ #
# M
# 2
O 'g
CJ C
&lt;
|S
&amp;b 60
&lt;D &lt;D
QC 0C
-d &quot;d
&lt;D &lt;D
&lt;D &lt;D
pq m
c/a c/3 c/3
PQ CQ
PQ pQ
Ob "
#
DC
g ^ o
O CQ CQ -H
J ^ ^ ^
# CQ CQ N
Cq Pq pci 1--1
#
#
o
o
c/3
&lt;D ^
S-E
o * \0x25A0
c/3 VO
3 oo
ON
OO oo
00 00
ON ON
ir, OC 60
Ti &lt;d &lt;d
r- 0C PC
ON
as -a ~a
-\0x25A0 &lt;L&gt;
&lt;u &lt;u
M PQ PQ PQ
o o --- ~ 1
&gt; *Q *
^ S CQ cq pQ
pd &lt; U PQ PQ
Id
Pd
&lt;Z)
c
&lt;D
"CC
&lt;d
60
jo
To
jo
#
(c)
C/3
c
c/3
c
#
o
#
#
o
g
C/3
(U
(D
C/3
3
o
U
&lt;Z)
&lt;D
O
c
N
S
C/3
&lt;D
T3
#
3
C/3
&lt;D
3
&amp;
C/3
3
o
o
N
3
C/3
CD
C/3
&lt;D
o
o
N
U.
rd
n
CD
&quot;O
g
pQ
&lt;5
(c)
60
60
In
3
m
--
n
a.
s
c
n
&gt;.
#
W)
C/3
"S
OJ
Q
cd
CQ
#
a
(D
PC
&lt;D
PC
a
O
3
Q
c3
00
%
cd
cd
00
-3
3
cd
cd
DO
cd
PQ
cd
DO
#
o
CD
T3
3
o
cd
DO
cd
DO
C/3
CD
-3
w
u
J
PQ
d
&lt;
z
PQ
PQ
CQ
PQ
CQ
X
PQ
CQ
PQ
U
CQ
c^*
O&quot;
#
PQ
o-
O&apos;*
J
PQ
PQ
u
cd
pd
00
IT;
in
00
00
.
ON
ts
00
(N
&lt;N
co
oo
in
On
\0x25A0d-
m
VO
&apos;d-
VO
oo
oo
vo
&gt;n
T d-
NO
NO
oo
ON
ON
(c)N
oo
OO
OO
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
oo
ON
OO
ON
ON
OO
O&apos;
O&apos;
ON
VO
C&quot;
ON
ON
OO
ON
ON
ON
On
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
Ov
On
ON
ON
ON
Ov
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
</figure>
<page confidence="0.974471" page_id="56266221"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
131
</page>
<figure confidence="0.972860628571428" page_id="56266221"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
S
. a
p o
H O
8 i
e S&apos;?
g O N
CU go ON
S # s
s J &lt;
&lt;N
r-
d
ON c
ON ^
S
8 d
(c) s
o g
(" O
fc- O --I
(c) . * *
rv &lt;/&gt; O
S as
Jog
a &lt;8
&gt; PQ
&lt; d Q U
8
s
8 is
. o(c)
.2 on 2 00
&quot;Q cn (c) ON
(c) ^ &amp;, &apos;
S vb e c3
^ on o --\0x25A0
2 2 ^ ^
d ^ s
2&lt;So
CN
A on
OO ON
(c)5 2
&lt;N
PQ S
U &lt;
C/3
S s o ON
^ ^ ^ ON
S!SS
CQ ^ ^
U Pu &lt; &lt; I&gt; U
(c) ^
o ~
oo ^
CO 00
8 &quot;
&apos;C PQ
00 ..
O --I
ON ON
r-&lt; ON
S 5
&lt; PU
(D
ON
OO
ON NO
I s ?
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.891379821428571" page_id="56266221"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
P -H CO
s2g
8 m -"
Pu U Pu
o -
os a
s S
O ON
Pc PQ
&lt;u \0x25A0
&amp;H U
C&gt;0
# g
&lt;n r-
T3*ON
QJ ON
(c)
in
PQ ON CO
S - 55
PQ PQ PR
PU pLi U
PS -Z3 O O
(c) cd
**r rjft
o o o
N oj) N
e
</equation>
<page confidence="0.199461" page_id="56266221"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
"3
</page>
<figure confidence="0.853314038216561" page_id="56266221"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
u
c" (c) (c) -d (c)
&quot; tfl M M M
u (c)
b -d Q
bfi
S ^
(c) TQ
a I
s I
(c) DU
jg
js
oo U
" o N u " w G
 |# S % * &apos; &quot;
8 rS &apos;S #
(c)
# # .5 Oh .5
^ ^ ^ o -
.2 oo r Jd
H
Cd ."* W GQ
W W W M
e
8 TO
(c) (c)
(c) (c)
PQ OP
pd
0$
(c)
H-l
hJ
x:
U
U
J5
U
.c
U
s
a
u
o
-C
U
c.
PQ
pd
PQ
At
pd
O
_]
s
&gt;ld
pd
pd
PQ
Mi
PU
o*
pd
-
oo
r-
o
oo
in
in
ON
ON
NO
m
00
t&gt;
ON
ON
in
&lt;N
00
r-~
&lt;N
o
ON
cn
o
oo
(N
t&quot;
(N
J
in
NO
ON
ON
ON
ON
00
On
ON
OO
OO
ON
ON
OO
oo
OO
ON
ON
O
ON
oo
o
o
OO
o
oo
00
o.
o
o
On
o
o
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
On
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
On
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
On
ON
On
o
o
o
o
o
o
ON
o
o
</figure>
<page confidence="0.975725" page_id="56266222"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
132
</page>
<figure confidence="0.968399428571429" page_id="56266222"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
On NO
oo on
2 so
X. Os
On
PQ PQ
U P
CN t-- \0x25A0 *
as os o
ON ON ON
--&apos; -- On
&lt; &lt;
!"
PQ PQ
P P
CO V &lt;
01
&lt;u
Pi
&quot;6
On 5
NO U
as pq
p
oo
On
ON
- #
ex #
0 &gt; o
Pi W
nh r-
&lt;U ON
Oh
S #
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.951391365591398" page_id="56266222"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
P ON
O --&lt;
U "
Pi Q P
# #
i la
o o ..
. . ON
$" "&gt; oo
QJ &lt;U ON
Oh Oh ^
C/5 CO l/~)
ja js ^
OO--I
^ &lt;-&gt; PQ
6 6 u
S S
# o
o *
o ^
e &amp;
&lt;u ^
I Oh f-~
*I - #
I* I
eS .2
Srag
M P PLh
O --I
ON ON
ON ON
Pi Pi
o
ON H
ON CO
PQ PQ ^
t p; &quot;!
PQ PQ "
P P O
2* fS
_* r--
QT ON ON
^ os as
ex ex
o&gt; 0&gt;
PS PQ
PQ PQ
P P
PQ PQ
P P
&lt;u &lt;u
# *S
# p
&gt; ^
:&gt; oo
# c T3
&gt; o
\0x25A0 &gt; H
o3 h
c 1 ^
C T3
P ^ PQ pd
o
~a
o
pi Q oi j
00
ffi s
p p p
s- SO H nh
c3 2o W c3
Oh co Qh PU
O ^ O
13 2
0) .(DO
c^. CQ PQ PQ PQ
jd ^ OQ --&lt;
03 o
u ta
\0x25A08 #
&lt;D P
&lt;D
od P P p pS
_c3
' 5 b O Oh
3 DC
E # S
cl 3
PLh oo pu
u od ^
e^.
oono^h(NOnnoo ^tcnooQOQOcn--imNOoO&apos;-- (N--&apos;mo--&apos;ONONoo^r^t^
OO Os On On GO On On COO\\0^0"0\OnO\OnMOnOnO\OnO\OnoOOOOOON^O\
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.815442" page_id="56266222"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
as as as as as as as ononon^^onono\onononononononononononon^on
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.981081705128205" page_id="56266222"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
(c) a
a g
S S 3
*S (c) a
*2?
^ a
a
g S I
a b #
* rl
K g O
rN ^ ^7
2 o #
^ S m
S S "
H P
g on p
R Q PQ
oa S Q
00 02 PQ
g ^ J
5 Z &lt;
r-i PQ
U ^ &gt;s
W O H
SSh
31 &gt;
PLh X &gt;
&lt;o ~
a |
a S
*2? i
k a
S 3
"* K
co cn
II
&apos;X x
, oo oo
u D D
S g g
* H H
# &lt; &gt;H
PJ o ^
d y cq
J O D
PQ U Q
K *3 (j
S S S
-Cj -a -Ci
C 3,0
on ?? to
III
C S S L S
E~h O, hn
x 3 ffi
00 &quot;ts 00
p b D
Pi ^ DP
H oo ^
U P D
Z Pi PQ
&lt; Si ^
X H 5
UqS
0^ 2; PQ
M w
D I--J !&gt;h
*c
w w
Z J
&lt;n C"
aj
5 W
11
II
o 8
I 83
oo -a cu
P # K
gif
g % I
E 3
H DP
o X
Z H
_ 2 o
"eg
^ P X
^ &lt; o
P IZ)
O W
o 5
w
9 S
o
Nj
%
kQ
&lt;
p
X
u
u
o
p
^ w
P oo
Pi P
P z
p K
H P
oo U
Pi
P
P ,
PQ jy
PQ tj
&lt; 'I
PQ O _
pi ^-5
r&lt; " ^
fc!  |&lt;
s|h
u 3 W
^ &gt;
Q m d
p 5/3 9
Q O #
53 # S
ob ^ g
p 6 z
o ^ g
&amp; Q 8
I
*g J-
^ &apos;S,
a "
ex "
.a S|
C3 O \0x25A0S
3 a (c)
\0x25A0S S S-
.S. ^ ^
~ ^ Pi
3
*S&apos;WS
^ p g
2 g &quot;
^ (R) "
h " z
P ^ w
Spg
# S PQ
p # w
X C/N
</figure>
<page confidence="0.991999" page_id="56266223"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
133
</page>
<figure confidence="0.947680777777778" page_id="56266223"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
f 2
CQ
CQ
oo
B ?!
II
PQ
NO
ci
#
"s
U
cn
66
o OO M
* NO ON O
5 t \ * *
P ON On 00
S 2 2 S
C/D CZ) C/D CZ) C/3
Hh* &lt;3 U CLi tin&quot; On &lt;C P5
3 S
&lt; U fa
CQ PQ
too
&lt;D
cs
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.980271727272727" page_id="56266223"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
M -- (N
rC 66 t&gt;
9\ 0\ ON
Ov Ov Ov
O
j -d (c) *
# u on -
P # r- &lt;n
o CQ 25 2^
5 ^ On On
^ fa
g " PQ PQ
CL PL fa fa
CQ CQ
U PL
OD
cu
as
S&apos;d
-- o&gt;
. . OJ
r-~ !=
</equation>
<figure confidence="0.868485481481481" page_id="56266223"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
00 CQ
ON .
T_l fa
PQ PQ
fa fa'
M OJD
0 &gt; lU
as as
\0x25A0d -d
CU Ol
at &lt;u
u
PQ PQ
fa' fa
PQ PQ
fa' fa
S 2 S
s
OX)
C/3 i/3 C/3
C/3 C/3 C/3
&lt;U &lt;D &lt;D
&lt; &lt; &lt;
fa fa fa
^
c &amp;.2 a
, C S3
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.969975" page_id="56266223"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
&lt;D 0) &lt;0
(U
,3.*P H 5V ) .S H N2&apos;T3T3'0&apos;0&apos;0
P T! C3 03 CDS Ctf
CQ O
PS PS
^ c3 c3 ..
.n 1) 1) 1) 1) 1)
^ S S S S S
Cl fa S PL PL
=# oo fa
fa &lt;u IP
E O #
^ fan
oo PC
PL PL PL PS PS
&lt;D
CL
O 5"
fa ^
o O
# U
&gt;N D
. " CL
# 2
c" ^ 1:3 O
PL PS J #
</equation>
<table confidence="0.854608666666667" page_id="56266223"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
&lt; PQ fa PL
In CD
&lt;P &lt;D Ph
^ # o
# 2 2
&lt; PS fa 5-. 5-. e-. os Q fa
m m n h o\ h h
ON ON ON OO OO OO ON
Ov On On On On on On
</table>
<figure confidence="0.993989237410072" page_id="56266223"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
XrH\ovOOONONOOOOminhrirf)rtO-ihh"h(NONtN|
ONONNONOt^r-OOOOOOONONOOONONONONONOOONONONONOOON
^OnOnONONOnOnOnONOnONOnOnONOnOnOnOn^v^^OnON On
2 to
'f. -I
s &amp;
&lt;43
up &lt;43
&lt; ^
PQ
s
g I
#1
It
^N (3
*a ."*
&quot; I
(c)
I
s
s
&lt;
z
55
D
&gt;H
. Q
on fa
D b
o &lt;
# *
PS oo
J s s S
d ? s
# 8
&lt;P fa
z OS
s fa
fa J
8 "
55 PS
^ PS
PQ
CL
CL
o
sc
00
00
^ PL
fa fa
g#
3 a
PQ &amp; &lt;!
fa DC cs
^ u o
tS
&gt;1
11
. 1.2
CS o
W fa
fa rjj
OQ 3
PS OQ
&lt; s
fa &gt;
Z 00
2 b
e h
n w
" u
I s
S ^
.a ^
L. ~Q
8
OS #
fa as
fa fa
C fa DC
-g
e
00 Q
^ PS
PQ
11
a s
Q ^
g Q
CQ PS
z
&lt;3 H
Si P
B, ^
a ^
p &lt;
^ 9
Q %
PS PQ
Z
SIS
e fa
" H
oj tr
Q
fa
H
&lt;
O
OS
X
H
a
N
c n
fa
O
OS
fa &gt;H
xn fa
O os
S so
II I
PS S g
H f ^
fa ^
^ ^ fa
zg 1
opz
X # fa
Q D 3
fa CQ
y 5 g
fa fa fa
fa &amp; @
D W z
fa PS fa
CQ U U
</figure>
<page confidence="0.996901" page_id="56266224"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
134
</page>
<figure confidence="0.948713613636364" page_id="56266224"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
&lt;D
Oh
C ^
o tp.
to m3
&gt; 00
% ON
DC 2
PQ
Z PC
rO o o
g m
a m3
o S
PQ pq pq &gt;
U Uh Pp od
t&gt;0 00
&lt;u (U
C4 04
On U g
SO
oo
c- os
OO i&quot;H
00
&lt;u
34
-d on
aj
&lt;u oo
i- oo
* ON
00
4)
04
24 24 on cm . .
03 ffl 5? r 03
vB r *
pp pp ^ . (Sj -
pq PQ PQ W pq 2
a Pu cl U Hi &lt;
Pp &lt;
o g
24 I
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.937594043478261" page_id="56266224"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
pq o
. o
 |- L ! to
cq #
PP CP
00
4) r -
P4 4)
. o
\0x25A02 I
(U O
i_i CO
PQ CO
. 3
PP o
pq 5
Ph &gt;
CO
p
H 9
# &lt;2
o3 23
00 2
</equation>
<page confidence="0.719793" page_id="56266224"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
03
</page>
<figure confidence="0.998244603399433" page_id="56266224"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
DC
d
&amp;
q
2
S-3 iii
s r S
dc cn
2^1
r? # O
Xi 'g
03
h
oo
&gt;" 2 q
2 w) "
00 3 2
n B
S 2 "
J U S
C3 &gt;
2 2 o
# q t3
2 DC PQ
a
a
#
C--i
l--5
6
U
-C
u
a
d
i-3
a
a
a
H
Q
a
C^-
C^-
a
C-
S&apos;*
a
a
f
c-
C^-
2
c-
&lt;
(N
"n
CO
r-
NO
ON
NO
CM
CM
CM
in
o
o
oo
ON
ON
&apos;n|-
On
NO
00
o
o
NO
&apos;nT
ON
\0x25A0*fr
NO
Os
oo
oo
00
ON
OO
ON
OO
t-&quot;
ON
ON
O&apos;
ON.
00
ON
ON
OO
O&apos;
ON
OO
OO
ON
00
ON
OO
ON
00
ON
00
On
ON
ON
ON
ON
On
ON
On
ON
ON
On
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
ON
On
ON
ON
On
ON
On
a a
I s
p 4 pq
pq o
P &lt;
c*4
U
Q O
W !D
34 o
% p4
3 p
Z H
&lt;
Z
eS
S
Q
&lt;
a a
5 s
|5
PQ PP
'S^
^ 34
3 P4
S &lt;
-a &gt;
o
s
-2 --
S a
9 S
a o
PP w
O PQ
H3
a
^ .3
2 ^
Co
CO
1
a &quot;3
a #
(so -CS
1 ^
a ^
&quot;S
S&lt;2
'" a
&gt;} 5
B
2 ^
g ^
ll
*a l.
|
Co
.a f
a g
&gt;S oa
a
o
|3
*B S
Cl Cj
t I
C a
a
CcO
a
a
yx ^
S
a ^
S3 00
a a
. " ^
a
CL
m S
Q
O
O
DC
2
U
&lt;
PP
34
U
&lt;
J
PQ
PQ
D
04
U
oo PP
I
a
-a
op
DC
U
z
pp
5
pq
00
pq
Q
oo pq
S o
pq P4
6 S*
co a
3 SJ
" DC
Is
*S pp
|l
DC
Q
W
S
34
U
&lt;
J
PP
a
6
34
&lt;
W
m PQ
ro CO
* O
P4
o
p
a
E
p
&lt;
&gt; .&lt;="
34 a
&lt; I
PQ H
pq O
a pp
IP co
, P
M S S
igf
&gt;3 \0x25A1 &gt;H
pq K co
o4 (j O
O 3o 04
S a
1
of (R)
s S
u 2
S z
pp #
9 &lt;
a s
pp j
o DC
Q pq
&lt;#
S a
^ s
&lt; DC
PP
c a
s -a
-s; p&gt;
^ 5
s; a
o ^
^ Z
34 S
Z
s
K Q
a c
S ^
3- ^
I S
^ PQ P4 &gt;
Q ^ P&gt;
b K a
j g o
13 a 2
a -a ^
a cj o
^ S #
Z *4 3
2 Z a
Ibi
e &lt; S
o s g
a q z
g w z
04 W ^
U DC g
w pq pp
H H pq
</figure>
<page confidence="0.983704" page_id="56266225"  page_num="135" year="" vol="">
135
</page>
<figure confidence="0.943444333333333" page_id="56266225"  page_num="135" year="" vol="">
^ Tf o
Os Os Os
Os Os Os
biD 60 t&gt;0 vr,
&lt;D &lt;D 0&gt; ,
&amp; Pi &amp; g
\0x25A0d t 3 ti ^
(D 0) &lt;D ON (u
0) CD &lt;D &lt;d
ffl m ffl t ffl
Ph Ph' PP ^ PQ
CQ CQ ffl CQ CQ
OP pp PQ u OP
CN e CN
Os S3 Os
Os O Os
&amp;i&gt; g oi&gt;
&lt;d g &lt;D
Qd OnOd
T3 S ~6
0) S5 CD
P e &lt;o
3 PQ 25
S#s
Od PQ &lt;
O * *
c/3 CO
C ON
*J2 os
Si
Cd &lt;
W)
&lt;u * *
* 3
&lt;u l . . ~
&lt;D y-&gt; &lt;N
Jd ON --
S-S
CQ PQ (R)
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.930191839285714" page_id="56266225"  page_num="135" year="" vol="">
PP pp U
jS *&quot;&apos;
bfi Ei
cd ^
3 VO
s
g
o OO
* 3
e S5
0) --&lt;
CP -x
;r^
U Os
O
o " u "
od u d u
o
o
o
o
o
O
o
o
c
N
N
&lt;D
N
N
o
#
a) k&gt;
cd
&lt;v
o
c
o
u
o
PQ
s
C/3
OJ
C/3
o
X
Vi
&lt;u
C/J
o
Vi
&lt;u
&lt;D
T3
</equation>
<page confidence="0.734371" page_id="56266225"  page_num="135" year="" vol="">
45
45
45
</page>
<figure confidence="0.989964278350515" page_id="56266225"  page_num="135" year="" vol="">
4C
45
O
&lt;
"\0x25A0
o-
o-
O
o-
U
o-
d
"*
U
U
U
#\0x25A0*
c^
m
\0x25A0^t
O
Os
Os
O
cn
(N
Os
Os
(N
OO
Os
Os
OS.
Os
OO
OS
OO
Os
Os
Os
OO
f-
OO
On
Os
Os
Os
Os
os
Os
Os
Os
Os
OS
OS
Os
ON
ON
ON
c ^
O hP
3
cd
CP
CQ
h-; h
CQ O
i 5d
Cl ?
^ a
U
\0x25A0S3
#
as
z 2
a
s
z
&lt;
&lt;3
#
&lt;P&gt;
"s
s
s
s
-#
L&gt;
\0x25A0 #
i-3
Is
z z
pq
_l
#2
od
, w
*S &gt;
S0 &lt;
^ pq
^ &gt;
s ^
a 9
-# J
|l
Z PQ
Q
pq
Q
&lt;
pq
X
pq
H
X
#
pi ^
^ #
2 a*
# *
z&quot; w
II
-S
s
8
"a
I
&lt;3
s
8^1
J8o
s S Z
hJ S3
Pd # |
&lt; # |
-\0x25A0., H o -c
CL 00 .&lt;4 Co
Od # -x
 |Z pq
w H 2
S o g!
8 2 w
ffi ^ o
^ E #
S|l
Cu h o
cl cl
o o
z z
es es
t/3 OO
o a
S #
a z
# x
OO 00
pq
-Q O
o Z
pq
*N
iS
\0x25A1 hj z n 00 J 3
d ^ H u P O M
00
d!
&lt; G
&lt;
_q
O
u ^
V pq
g CQ
H pq
It! J
pq
^ u
in
w
u
P4
P
o
C/3
w
U
z
0&lt;
w
W
z
o
Q
Q
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.9965">
F.B.F Breed. Reg. Annual Breeding Register of the Foreign Bird Federation
Psittascene Newsletter of the World Parrot Trust
Proc. of Owl Symp. Proceedings of U.K. Owl Symposium (B. Sayers)
Columbidae Magazine of the Pigeon and Dove Society
Beak and Claw Magazine of the Foreign Bird Association
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999385" page_id="56266226"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
136
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.910357333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266226" page_num="136" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
POPULAR CONURES
Australian Birdkeeper's A Guide to ... series has established itself as
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990635580645161" page_id="56266226"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
probably the leading soft cover series of avicultural books. The books have
great visual appeal with generous amounts of colour, excellent illustrations
and quality glossy paper throughout. For the latest title, Popular Conures,
Canadian authors Ray Dorge and Gail Sibley were chosen.
Bearing in mind that this book was written mainly for the Australian
market, the conures covered are restricted to those available in that country
- five species of Aratinga (including the Sun), Patagonian and Queen of
Bavaria's, Nanday and five species of Pyrrhura , including the popular Green-
cheeked and the colourful Crimson-bellied Conure.
The text is divided into sections: Conure behaviour (including loudness
and nippiness), Obtaining a conure, Husbandry, What's on the menu? and
Entertaining conures, followed by information about the 13 species.
Australian avian vet Bob Doneley wrote the excellent chapter about diseases
and Terry Martin, a specialist in mutations, the page on mutations in Australia.
This 112-page book is full of good basic information gained from various
keepers and breeders whose experiences are described. Occasionally there
are statements which would have been better omitted, such as that of one
breeder who believes that female Queen of Bavaria's Conures pluck out
their tail feathers 'to make it easier for the cock to copulate with her.' My
main criticism is that Dorge and Sibley did not write this book from personal
experience, as evidenced by such statements as: 'We took a few wrong turns,
even venturing up some blind alleys and dead ends, while researching the
species discussed in this book.'
Nevertheless, this does not mean that it will not be extremely useful to
conure keepers and potential pet owners, especially as with each species
there is a discussion of its - pet quality.
For me the highlight of this book is the 13 species illustrated by full-
page colour photographs by Peter Odekerken. Their clarity, against plain
blue, uncluttered backgrounds, is outstanding. A Guide to... Popular Conures
is priced A$30.75 plus postage in Australia, and is available in the UK priced
#13.95.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.28403">
Rosemary Low
</subsectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909697" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266227" page_num="137" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995992" page_id="56266227"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
137
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.973492" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56266227" page_num="137" year="" vol="">
WILDLIFE GUIDE TO ALASKA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995762933333334" page_id="56266227"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
The Ecotravellers' Wildlife Guide to Alaska is the sixth in this series of
guides, endorsed by the Wildlife Conservation Society ( founded in 1895 as
the New York Zoological Society), and all written or co-written by Les
Beletsky. Denis Paulson is co-author of this sixth guide. The format (which
is similar in each guide in the series) consists of chapters on the area in
question, covering geography, habitats, the national parks and reserves, with
the bulk of the guide divided into sections on insects, marine invertebrates,
fishes, amphibians, birds and mammals. The detail on individual areas is
fairly brief, but various internet sites are suggested as sources of further
information. The chapter on environmental threats and conservation in
Alaska seems fairly superficial, and might rapidly become inaccurate given
the recent change in attitude to environmental issues of the US government.
It is not clear if this book is trying to be a location guide, or a very basic
general purpose natural history book. It appears to be aimed at readers who
are new to the study of wildlife, given the reminders to remember to take
binoculars, and to be careful on the slippery rocks when investigating rock
pools. In each section there is a lot of information not specific or necessarily
relevant to Alaska. For example, there are three pages of general text about
hummingbirds, including the statement: There are only two regularly
occurring species and two rare species in southern Alaska', but it names
only one of them, the Rufous Hummingbird. Despite these criticisms there
are a number of good points. The habitat photos give a good impression of
this enormous state, and the colour illustrations are detailed and appear
accurate. In the bird section (plates 17-59 by John Sill) just over 175 species
are illustrated .
The Ecotravellers ' Wildlife Guide to Alaska by Denis Paulson and Les
Beletsky is published by Academic Press, Harcourt House, 32 Jamestown
Road, London NW1 7BY, UK and 525B Street, Suite 1900, San Diego,
California 92101-4495, USA. It is priced #19.95 in the UK, US$29.95 in
the USA and $44.25 in Canada.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.552529">
Shirley Ellis
</subsectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998618" page_id="56266228"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
138
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.978972" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266228" page_num="138" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
SWEET SUCCESS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986646571428571" page_id="56266228"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
Within weeks of being introduced into a 5,000sq ft (approx. 465sq m)
glass house at The London Butterfly House, Syon Park, west London
(website:www.butterflies.org.uk), a pair of Golden-winged Sunbirds
Nectarinia reichenowi nested just 30cm (1ft) from the visitor walkway and
fledged a single chick. It is almost certainly the first recorded breeding
success with this species in Great Britain or Ireland, and may even be a
world first.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.77106" page_id="56266228"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.735854" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266228" page_num="138" year="" vol="">
LONG LIVED MACAW
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.905705142857143" page_id="56266228"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
Ken Dolton, Parklands, Hallow, Worcestershire, writes: 'On the 9th July
this year my Hyacinth Macaw Anodorhynchus hyacinthinus died, it had been
poorly for about two days and did not seem to be coming through the moult
satisfactorily. I purchased this bird in 1958 from a bird dealer named Jack
Indge. It was already an adult when I obtained it so it could have been about
60 years old when it died. I provided it with two females and although I saw
feeding I never had any eggs from them.'
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.688294" page_id="56266228"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.532679" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266228" page_num="138" year="" vol="">
SPANISH QUAKERS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.953109833333333" page_id="56266228"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
According to comment in British Birds 94,4:208-209 (April 2001), the
Monk or Quaker Parrakeet Myiopsitta monachus is now widespread
throughout most of Barcelona. Seven-hundred and seventy-nine nests were
counted in 1999. The increase of the Rose-ringed or Ring-necked Parrakeet
Psittacula krameri has been much less spectacular, and although it is well
established and breeding there, it remains localised and always occurs in
small numbers only. The Mitred Conure Aratinga mitrata and the Blue-
crowned Conure A. acuticaudata may also be established there. Other species
recorded sporadically include the Nanday Conure Nandayus nenday. The
situation regarding exotic additions to the Spanish avifauna is being studied
by the GAE (Grupo de Aves Exoticas) and the results will be published and
also made available via the Internet.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.510701" page_id="56266228"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.98455" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266228" page_num="138" year="" vol="">
LONGEVITY OF WHITE PELICANS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99659925" page_id="56266228"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
In Ostrich 72, 1 &amp; 2, March 2001 (p.123), Emil K. Urban and J. S. Ash
report the recapture of a (Great) White Pelican Pelecanus onocrotalus in a
gill net at Lake Zwai, Ethiopia. The bird was ringed at Lake Shala, Ethiopia
in June 1974,70-80 days after it hatched, and therefore at the time of recapture
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700176" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266229" page_num="139" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999111" page_id="56266229"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
139
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.987" page_id="56266229"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
was known to be 23 years and five, or possibly, six months old. They remark
that how long pelicans live is poorly documented and not well known in
Africa. They go on to record two recoveries of White Pelicans in South
Africa, one aged 17 years and the other 16 years, as well as mentioning an
unmarked bird which may have been at least 28 years old.
In the Avicultural Magazine 73, 2: 62, John Yealland reported the death
of London Zoo's oldest inhabitant, a White Pelican. It had arrived at the
zoo on May 2nd 1922 and died January 11th 1967, so was likely to have been
over 45 years old. Urban and Ash conclude by mentioning an unidentified
pelican, reported to have reached the age of 54 years (del Hoyo et al. 1992).
Does anyone know of records of pelicans which have lived longer?
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.79767" page_id="56266229"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.916733" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266229" page_num="139" year="" vol="">
RECENTLY APPOINTED CURATOR
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996257529411765" page_id="56266229"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
The dates that the White Pelican (above) arrived and later died at London
Zoo were checked by recently appointed Curator of Birds John A. Ellis. In
News &amp; Views on the opposite page of the same magazine (p.63), A. A.
Prestwich referred to the oldest inhabitant having been an Australian Pelican
P. conspicillatus. So as to avoid any confusion, John also checked the records
of Australian Pelicans and found that four arrived on June 19th 1924. One
died November 4th 1940, the casualty of an air raid. The others died October
30th 1950, February 24th 1962 and March 25th 1963. By 1966 no Australian
Pelicans remained in the collection.
At the time that John faxed the above information, the highlight of the
year on the bird section was the successful breeding of the Seven-coloured
or Superb Tanager Tangara fastuosa. John will be more than happy to write
an end of the year report on what has been happening on the bird section at
the zoo. In the meantime he is hoping to persuade the Bird House staff to
write reports of the breeding of the Black Hombill Anthracoceros malayanus
and Blue-crowned Lory Vini australis that occurred there during 2000.
Hopefully, there may also be a report about the breeding of the Purple-tailed
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.763779" page_id="56266229"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
Imperial Pigeon Ducula rufigaster - an earlier UK first breeding.
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.852646" genericHeader="method" page_id="56266229" page_num="139" year="" vol="">
UGANDAN PROCEEDINGS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993288375" page_id="56266229"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
What is likely to have been the first of many workshops concerned with
the status and health of vultures was held in April, at Kampala, Uganda.
The objective of the two-day workshop was to focus attention on the well-
being of East African vultures and to develop protocols for monitoring their
populations, in the light of the current concern about the decline of vulture
populations in India (see News &amp; Views, Vol. 106, No. 3, p. 134 (2000)).
The first day there were formal lectures by biologists, veterinarians and
a lawyer, as well as practical sessions. The emphasis in these sessions was
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995276" page_id="56266230"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
140
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.927623" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266230" page_num="140" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.948668333333333" page_id="56266230"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
on monitoring populations, the use of minimally invasive methods of study
of live birds and correct sampling procedures. On the second day the
participants, most of whom work in East Africa, divided into four groups in
order to formulate protocols and codes of practise for work with vultures.
These have now been finalised and together with the course notes form part
of the Workshop Proceedings , copies of which are available from:- Dr
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.820149833333333" page_id="56266230"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
Christine Dranzoa, Department of Wild Life &amp; Animal Resources
Management (WARM), Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Makerere
University, PO. Box 7062, Kampala, Uganda, or Prof. John E. Cooper and
Mrs Margaret E. Cooper, Wildlife Health Services, PO. Box 153,
Wellingborough, Northants NN8 2ZA, UK.E-maikNGAGI@compuserve.com
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.967736" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56266230" page_num="140" year="" vol="">
BIRDS AND AVOCADOS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9951311875" page_id="56266230"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
It seems to be generally agreed that both the flesh and stone of avocado
pears are toxic to parrots, and therefore should not be fed to them. Is this
true of all varieties of avocado and does it apply to all species of parrot, and
what about other birds?
As a young keeper working in the Bird House at London Zoo, I was told
how the quetzals Pharomachrus sp. kept there in the 1930s were fed on
avocado pears (which at that time must have been incredibly expensive and
difficult to obtain). Recent studies at Monteverde, Costa Rica (where quetzal
and other wildlife research and conservation projects are being funded by
the British Embassy there) have revealed that the Resplendent Quetzals P.
mocinno living in the cloud forest of Monteverde eat the fruits of at least 18
different species of wild avocados, and these make up about 80% of their
diet. The small fruits are plucked on the wing and gulped down whole,
rather like a 'snake eats a frog', wrote Charles Bergman in Wildlife
Conservation Vol.102, No.5:42-49. The stones are regurgitated later. The
fruits are also eaten by other birds, including the Three-wattled Bellbird
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.42400875" page_id="56266230"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
Procnias tricarunculata. Bare-necked Umbrellabird Cephalopterus
glabricollis and Black Guan Chamaepetes unicolor.
* * *
NEW BARRET'S HABITAT SAVED
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.99125125" page_id="56266230"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
For hundreds of years the Cordillera Azul in north-central Peru remained
virtually uninhabited by humans, the forests of these isolated mountains
being protected by their rugged terrain and their great distance from the
waterways of Amazonian commerce. Then, as John W. Fitzpatrick describes
in Birdscope Summer 2001/ Vol.15, No.3, the forests began to be logged.
Local and international conservation organisations acted quickly to save
the Cordillera Azul, where in 1996 biologists from Louisiana State University
discovered the previously unknown Scarlet-banded Barbet Capito wallacei.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700134" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266231" page_num="141" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998634" page_id="56266231"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
141
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.996553" page_id="56266231"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
Thanks to their prompt action, on May 21st 2001, the President of Peru,
impressed after touring the region by helicopter, signed a decree to establish
the 1,353,190 hectares (approx. 3,343,750 acres) Parque Nacional Cordillera
Azul Biabo, thereby, hopefully, safeguarding the barbet and the wealth of
other biological specialities of the Cordillera Azul.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.818792" page_id="56266231"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.877435" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56266231" page_num="141" year="" vol="">
CHANGES AT WALSRODE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993485285714286" page_id="56266231"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
The Vogelpark Walsrode Bird Inventory 2000 records that last year was
a difficult year. The park ran into financial difficulties and in September
was taken over by a group of three companies. Falling attendances had
made it obvious that considerable investment was needed to make the changes
required to halt the fall in the number of visitors and add attractions for
younger visitors. Immediately following the change of ownership, plans
were developed to make the park more attractive and to add a public 'baby
station', a flight show, a children's zoo, and to consider the possibility of
allowing visitors to feed some of the birds such as pelicans and penguins.
Aviaries, particularly those of the parrot section, have been made into
larger units to house flocks of birds rather than single pairs, the aim being to
display birds in what are closer to natural communities. It is also planned to
include a few small mammals and reptiles in some enclosures. Vogelpark
Walsrode hopes to continue to maintain its excellent reputation within the
zoo world and will continue to participate in international captive breeding
programmes, maintain off-public breeding facilities and cooperate with other
collections in establishing viable captive populations of rare species. Despite
the difficulties, it enjoyed a better breeding season than in the previous year,
rearing not only more young birds (1,083 vs 841 in 1999), but also of a
greater number of species (210 vs 184 in 1999).
Unfortunately, the most noteworthy breeding attempts were unsuccessful.
One of two pairs of Kagu Rhynochetos jubatus laid an egg in December.
The shell was damaged, but was repaired and the embryo developed to the
age of four weeks, only to die just prior to hatching. A Greater Bird of
Paradise Paradisaea apoda laid one egg and a Red Bird of Paradise P. rubra
laid a clutch of two eggs. However, they missed the right time to introduce
the females into the males' aviaries and as a result all three eggs were infertile.
Vogelpark Walsrode also has examples of the Twelve-wired Bird of Paradise
Seleucidis melanoleuca. King Cicinnurus regius and Lesser Bird of Paradise
P. minor. Last year Walsrode's female Bulwer's Pheasant Lophura bulweri
laid 25 eggs! However, the male is too old to breed, and all were infertile.
Earlier this year a new male was acquired from Antwerp Zoo. Since 1995,
Vogelpark Walsrode has kept a large group of the spectacular Montezuma
Oropendola Gymnostinops montezuma. The females built numerous huge
bottle-shaped nests and the males established display territories, but it was
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998661" page_id="56266232"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
142
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.924976" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266232" page_num="142" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.930979612903226" page_id="56266232"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
not until last year that this species reared two chicks and another four were
hand-reared after being rescued from their nests following a heavy rainstorm.
After experiencing difficulties rearing young Asian Openbill Storks
Anastomus oscitans, experiments were made which concentrated on the
digestive enzymes added to the food of the chicks. Two chicks were reared
artificially. It is the first ever captive breeding of this species. One of the
pairs of African Openbills A. lamelligerus again succeeded in rearing a chick.
The Southern Bald Ibis Geronticus calvus were successful again, and reared
seven chicks. Riedel's Eclectus Parrot Eclectus roratus riedeli, the smallest
subspecies and very rare in captivity, raised seven young and Vogelpark
Walsrode now has 15 of these birds, the only examples outside of Indonesia.
Two pairs of Cornelia's Eclectus Parrot E. r. cornelia reared three young.
Vogelpark Walsrode now has five pairs of Blue-headed Macaws Ara couloni.
These are confiscated birds which it has on loan .
In 1998 it started a cooperative programme with Tsimbazaza Zoo,
Madagascar. One of the aims of this is to establish viable captive populations
of endemic Madagascar birds. Last year witnessed the first success of this
programme with the rearing of five Crested Couas Coua cristata (a non-
parasitic cuckoo or coucal). It has received further Madagascar Crested
Ibis Lophotibis cristata and Sickle-billed Vangas Falculea palliata and now
has sufficient founder stock for breeding programmes for these species.
Several species of passerines bred in the Nusantara Rainforest Exhibit,
which was opened in 1999. Among these were the Blue-tailed or Borneo
Banded Pitta Pitta gujana schwaneri, Large Wren-babbler Napothera
macrodactyla and Chestnut-backed Scimitar-babbler Pomatorhinus
montana. All three successfully reared young, but Sunda Blue Robins
Cinclidium diana failed to raise their offspring. Other species which hatched
young included Wattled Crane Bugeranus carunculatus, Sclater's Crowned
Pigeon Goura sheepmakeri sclaterii. Whiskered Lorikeet Oreopsittacus
arfaki, Blue-naped Parrot Tanygnathus lucionensis, Muller's Parrot T.
sumatranus , Desmarest's Fig Parrot Psittaculirostris desmarestii, Salvadori's
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.833202" page_id="56266232"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
Fig Parrot P salvadorii , Knobbed Hornbill Aceros cassidix, Red &amp; Yellow
Barbet Trachyphonus erythrocephalus and Guyana Aracari Selenidera culik.
* *
LONG LIST OF BREEDINGS
</table>
<reference confidence="0.782723714285714">
Chester's Zoo Life , Autumn 2001 - Issue 7, has on the front cover colour
photos of a pair of White Storks Ciconia ciconia with three young in the
nest, a Blue-winged Kookaburra Dacelo leachii and a young Great Grey
Owl Strix nebulosa. They are just a few of the young hatched during May,
June and July at Chester Zoo. Others hatched during this period include 10
Humboldt's Penguins Spheniscus humboldti, one Eurasian Spoonbill Platalea
leucorodia, three White-headed Ducks Oxyura leucocephala, one Congo
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.694282" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266233" page_num="143" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.989586" page_id="56266233"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
143
</page>
<table confidence="0.423548916666667" page_id="56266233"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
Peafowl Afropavo congensis, one Vietnamese Pheasant Lophura hatinhensis,
two Satyr Tragopans Tragopan satyr, one Pink Pigeon Columba mayeri,
two Mount Apo Lorikeets Trichoglossus johnstoniae , three Red-tailed
Amazons Amazona brasiliensis, two Yellow-collared Macaws Ara auricollis,
three Tarictic Hornbills Penelopides panini , one Yellow-throated Laughing
Thrush Garrulax galbanus, two Red-tailed Laughing Thrushes G. milnei,
one Emerald Starling Lamprotornis iris and two Azure-winged Magpies
Cyanopica cyana.
* * *
NATIONAL EXHIBITION
Stewart Pyper writes 'Last year's National Exhibition of Cage and Aviary
Birds was held December 2nd - 3rd at the NEC (National Exhibition Centre),
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.992702892857143" page_id="56266233"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
Birmingham. It was dedicated to the memory of our late Chairman Ken
Lawrence, who died just prior to the event. Ken and the National Exhibition
went together. Over the years Ken did much to ensure its success and was
returning home from working on the arrangements for last year's exhibition
at the time of his death.'
'Best bird in the show was a Yellow Bunting or Yellowhammer. Best
foreign bird was an Abyssinian Lovebird owned by Dave Phillips from
Cornwall. This came as a great surprise, for it was the first time a lovebird
has won this award and perhaps only the fourth time a parrot species has
been judged best foreign bird. It went on to be runner-up to the bunting as
best bird in the show, pressed by the White-breasted Amazilia (hummingbird)
which was the subject of the article by Ivor Grogan (of Essex Birds) in the
Avicultural Magazine 106,4:157-164.
Others birds to take the eye included two individual Rothschild's Mynahs
or Bali Starlings , one an adult and the other a current year bred bird. They
were exhibited by Sayers and Booth. R. Beeson's male current year bred
Japanese Robin took the award for the most artistically staged exhibit. There
were two examples of what I took to be Black-and-Crimson Orioles, a species
I do not recollect having seen before. The crimson of one had faded.'
The society again had a stand where members could meet and exchange
news and views and renew their subscriptions. Only two new members
were enrolled, which was disappointing. The cost of the stand was met by
a generous donation from Scott Appleton, a relatively new member, and the
society is most appreciative of his help .
The 2001 National Exhibition of Cage and Aviary Birds will be held
December lst-2nd, once again at the NEC, and the society will again have a
stand. Anyone willing to help run the stand, even if only for an hour or two,
is asked to contact Stewart Pyper - Tel: 01373 836293.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999557" page_id="56266234"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
144
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9580965" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266234" page_num="144" year="" vol="">
ROB HARVEY SPECIALIST
FEEDS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.824421142857143" page_id="56266234"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
Seed mixtures - Straights - Berries - Nuts - Dried fruits -
Supplements
Nectars - Eggfoods - Softbill diets - Livefoods - Frozen foods
Rearing formulas - Pelleted diets - Plus much much more
We supply over 50 zoos and birdparks in the UK plus
hundreds of private breeders with our vast range of quality
feeds and supplements imported from all over the world.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.914719166666667" page_id="56266234"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
Try our livefood at unbeatable prices!
Mealworms
lkg (2.21bs) #14.95 2kg (4.41bs) #26.95
5kg (1 libs) #41.96 10kg (221bs) #72.34
Mini Mealworms
500g(l.libs) #13.95 lkg (2.21bs) #24.95
Livefood prices include delivery
www.robharvey.com
Kookaburra House, Gravel Hill Road, Holt Pound,
Farnham, Surrey, GU10 4LG
Tel: 01420 23986 Fax: 01420 23078 E-Mail
Rob@robharvey.com
</table>
<figure confidence="0.665277864864865" page_id="56266235"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
DONATIONS RECEIVED IN 2000
The society is most grateful to the following members for their generous
support:-
S. Appleton
J.R. Padgett
D.R. Bayliss
A. Perkins
Dr M.S. Bourne (deceased)
P.J. Phelby
R.A. Callaghan
A.J. Pitman
N.H.R. Dodds
R.C.J. Sawyer
L.J. Driver
D.P. Shearing
Mrs W. Duggan
J.G. Thurlow
K.W. Dolton
J. Trollope
M.E. Fidler
J.K. Watson
I.T. Forbes
N. Kapyla
A.W. Gibbard
Dr H. Quinque
D. Goodwin
Jan Louwman
A. Griffiths
Ivo Lazzeroni
R.L. Henshaw
J.L. Pappas
Prof. J.R. Hodges
R. Restall
J.J. Mallett
Miss R. Ezra
N. O'Connor
* * *
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.823691" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266235" page_num="" year="" vol="">
HELP WITH THE WEBSITE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.843171" page_id="56266235"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The society is seeking a member with the appropriate computer skills to
help run the website. If you would like to help, we will be pleased to hear
from you.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.489802" page_id="56266235"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.783714" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56266235" page_num="" year="" vol="">
OMEI SHAN LIOCICHLA STUDBOOK KEEPERS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.957032166666667" page_id="56266235"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Nigel Hewston is now British Isles Studbook Keeper for the Omei Shan
Liocichla. He has promised a progress report in the near future for the Avicultural
Magazine, and will be pleased to hear from anyone interested in this species.
Tel/Fax: +44 (0)1453 826944/E-mail: nigelhewston@supanet.com.
The European Studbook Keeper is: Theo Pagel, Cologne Zoo, Germany.
E-mail: tpagel@zoo-koeln.de
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.98859" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56266236" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION LIBRARIES
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.6503888" page_id="56266236"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
3 9088 01769 6436
Notes from Cobham
by R. C. J. Sawyer.97
Pathology ^nd Diseases of Touracos
by J. Waine ..100
Last of the Great Collectors
by Malcolm Ellis.105
The Omei Shan Liocichla Liocichla omeiensis
by Nigel Hewston. 109
The Moulting Cycle of the African Jagana Actophilornis africanus
</table>
<figure confidence="0.826480083333333" page_id="56266236"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
in Aviculture
by Greg Bockheim.115
Collated Data on the Timor Sparrow Padda or Lonchura juscata
by Neville Brickell.121
Additions and Corrections to UK First Breeding Records
by Dave Coles.125
Book Reviews
Popular Conures.136
Wildlife Guide to Alaska.137
News &amp; Views.139
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</figure>
</algorithms>
