<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.8396166" page_id="56261266"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 116
No. 2
2010
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990753" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261267" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.959550875" page_id="56261267"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2010 as for 2009: British
Isles #18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please).
The subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the
Society later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of
the AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.658685666666667" page_id="56261267"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, SHERATON LODGE, STATION ROAD, SOUTHMINSTER,
ESSEX CM0 7EW, UK..
</construct>
<bodyText confidence="0.9376471" page_id="56261267"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TNI 3 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail: otusscops@talktalk.net
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have not
been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of a
particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history. Articles
should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the scientific
names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given. References
cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line drawings,
black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular point in
the article will be used where possible and should be clearly captioned. If
authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when submitting the
article and write their name on the back of each photograph. Tables and
graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be aware of
the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of the page
which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997594" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56261267" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982475333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7819005" genericHeader="method" page_id="56261268" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.293381" page_id="56261268"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 116 - No. 2 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2010
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9272475" genericHeader="method" page_id="56261268" page_num="" year="" vol="">
IS THE PIN-TAILED WHYDAH Vidua macwura A BROOD-
PARASITE OF THE BLACK-FACED GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.93249851724138" page_id="56261268"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Tiaris bicolor ON PUERTO RICO?
by Robin Restall
Summary
Several species of African weaverbirds (Ploceidae) and waxbills
(Estrildidae) have become established on the Caribbean island of Puerto Rico.
One of these, the Pin-tailed Whydah Vidua macroura , is a brood parasite
whose African host species are common waxbills of the genus Estrilda. It is
also known to occasionally use other estrildid finches and is reported as using
species from other families as hosts (see e.g. Friedmann, 1960). A formal
agricultural report that listed the exotic species established on Puerto Rico,
included a list of species used as hosts by the Pin-tailed Whydah (Camacho
Rodriguez et al. 1999). The list included the native Black-faced Grassquit
Tiaris bicolor. This appeared to confirm anecdotal but unconfirmed reports
from local birders. Despite the apparent similarities between the Neotropical
grassquits and the estrildid finches of the Old World tropics, it is not logical
and ought not to be possible for the Pin-tailed Whydah to successfully
brood-parasitize the grassquits. Jurgen Nicolai (1964) in a seminal paper on
the subject stated baldly that it is, "impossible for (a viduine) to parasitize
other bird groups." The present paper deals with the avicultural techniques
and resources used by the author to test the hypothesis of the Pin-tailed
Whydah using a Neotropical non-estrildid species as host, together with
the conclusions.
Introduction
The Pin-tailed Whydah is the commonest and best known of the parasitic
weaverbirds. It occurs across most of Africa south of the Sahara in grassland
and almost any other habitat where grasses are growing. It is about the size
of a grassquit or Sporophila seedeater, with the adult male in nuptial plumage
being easily recognised by his black-and-white plumage, sealing wax-red
bill and long trailing rectrices (up to 20cm (7 3 /4in) in length). The female
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.88621" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261269" page_num="50" year="" vol="">
50 RESTALL - PIN-TAILED WHYDAH/BLACK-FACED GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998853" page_id="56261269"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
and male in non-breeding plumage are buffy-brownish with black lines
along the head and blackish striations on the upperparts, but the juvenile's
plumage is not striated, and is rather similar to that of an estrildid finch.
During the breeding season in Africa the Pin-tailed Whydah is usually
found in small groups that consist of a dominant, constantly singing and
displaying adult male in full nuptial plumage, together with several birds
that may be juveniles, immatures, females, and males is delayed plumage
maturation. Outside the breeding season, flocks are larger and may contain
several adult males in various stages of plumage development. On Puerto
Rico it seems that the population level is too small for groups of significant
size to assemble - undoubtably a reflection of the population densities of
the waxbills. The Pin-tailed Whydah is a tame bird that shows little fear
or apprehension in the vicinity of man and may even be seen foraging on
garden lawns (Rafy Rodriguez pers. comm; pers. obs.).
The female Pin-tailed Whydah lays a single white egg in the host species'
nest, and this can be identified by its slightly larger size. The host estrildid
usually raises the nestling alongside its own young without any problems.
Once fledged and weaned to independence, the young whydah leaves the
company of the estrildids to join the company of the whydahs. The female
whydah apparently ovulates upon watching the selected host species nest
building. She is stimulated by the song and display of the male estrildid
(Friedmann, 1960; Restall, 1975), but mates with the dominant male of a
whydah group in response to that bird's song and display.
The Pin-tailed Whydah's commonest host species across its range in
Africa is the Common Waxbill Estrilda astrild. Unlike other parasitic
whydahs, it also often lays in the nests of other Estrild waxbills. It appears
that other species are chosen mostly in response a scarcity or absence
of the Common Waxbill (MacDonald, 1980; Mines, 1989; Payne 2005;
Schuetz, 2005). Those whose nestlings have palate markings most similar
to those of the Common Waxbill nestling are the preferred substitutes.
The Black-rumped Waxbill E. troglodytes , Orange-cheeked Waxbill E.
melpoda, Crimson-rumped Waxbill E. rhodopyga, Fawn-breasted Waxbill
E. paludicola , Swee Waxbill E. melanotis, Red-billed Firefinch Lagonosticta
senegala and Bronze Mannikin Lonchura cucullata are most commonly
listed as hosts in Africa (Roberts, 1984; Borrow &amp; Demey, 2001; Stevenson
&amp; Fanshawe, 2002; Redman et al. 2009). The percentage of non -Estrild
hosts is extremely small compared to that of Estrild waxbill hosts. Species
from other families have occasionally been recorded as hosts, and there is
little doubt that the female whydah can be quite catholic and opportunistic
in her choice of host, even occasionally indiscriminate, but it is extremely
doubtful that any of these apparent non-estrildid hosts ever succeeded in
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.676032" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261270" page_num="51" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - PIN-TAILED WHYDAH/BLACK-FACED GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997335" page_id="56261270"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
51
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.995546366666667" page_id="56261270"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
hatching and rearing a whydah chick.
The use of various host species is consonant with the songs of the male.
Other parasitic whydahs are usually host-specific and the song of the male
whydah contains elements of the song of the host species. This has proved
very helpful to field workers in the past when host species have been
identified by analysis of the song of the whydah in question (Payne, 2005).
In the case of the Pin-tailed Whydah, however, the song is not like that of any
particular waxbill, and the female responds to the song of several different
wax bills (Nicolai, 1964). "The species associations of Vidua and estrildid
hosts result from histories of host shifts by the Vidua " wrote Payne (2005).
This sugggests to me that the Pin-tailed Whydah has an above expectation
built-in propensity to use alternative species, a supposition supported by the
lack of host species song mimicry.
Of the known estrildid host species, the Black-ramped and Orange-
cheeked Wax bills. Bronze Mannikin, Tri-coloured Munia L. malacca and
Nutmeg Finch or Spice Bird T. punctulata vary from common to uncommon
on Puerto Rico (Raffaele, 1989). No fewer than nine estrildids are established
on the island, of which six are established in the locality where the Pin-tailed
Whydah is commonest. It is likely that the two Estrild waxbills are favoured,
but it is quite possible that all may be used as host species, including the
munias L. malacca and L. punctulata (Rafy Rodriguez pers. comm.).
There are two species of grassquit commonly found on Puerto Rico,
the Black-faced Grassquit T. bicolor and the Yellow-faced Grassquit T.
olivacea. The former is widespread and commonly found in scrub, loose
open woodland and in gardens - even trespassing into open kitchens to forage
on the floor for fallen crumbs. The Yellow-faced Grassquit is less widely
distributed on the island. Both species are common in the area where the
Pin-tailed Whydah is found. In other parts of the Yellow-faced Grassquit's
range in Central and northern South America, it can be as common and
confiding as the Black-faced Grassquit.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.875419">
Hypothesis
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9993851" page_id="56261270"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
The hypothesis is that for a chosen host species to successfully hatch the
eggs of and rear the nestlings and fledglings of the brood-parasite species,
it must have similar breeding behaviour to those host species known to be
continually and habitually successful. The Estrild waxbills obviously fit that
description, and the mannikin squeezes In. Superficially, the Tiaris grassquits
also appear to fit the bill - they forage and feed in a similar manner to the
estrildid finches in the same habitat and I have seen them foraging together
in the south-western part of the island. They build a covered nest and lay
two or three eggs and go on to rear the young on a similar diet to that of the
waxbills. If the report is accurate, it implies that a grassquit can incubate,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.852546" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261271" page_num="52" year="" vol="">
52 RESTALL - PIN-TAILED WHYDAH/BLACK-FACED GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990074166666667" page_id="56261271"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
hatch and raise whydah chicks and, therefore, it must be equally possible
that it could brood, hatch and raise estrildid chicks. So placing estrildid eggs
(as legitimate substitutes for whydah eggs) and/or nestlings (as legitimate
substitutes for whydah nestlings) under breeding grassquits would be a valid
test. In addition, placing estrildid Bengalese eggs under a canary would
provide a distinct additional dimension to the experiment.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.817026">
Methods
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985727" page_id="56261271"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
From personal experience of studying grassquits in the field on Puerto
Rico and similar projects elsewhere, I knew that an investigation which
required detailed and prolonged observations of both the Pin-tailed Whydah
and the various host species in the field would have required time and
resources not available to me. However, combining some 60 years of
experience with estrildid finches and 15 years with grassquits, both in the
field and in captivity, with the full avicultural resources at my disposal,
allowed this hypothesis to be constructed and tested. The purpose of the
experiment was to introduce eggs and/or estrildid nestlings into the nest of
a breeding pair of grassquits to see whether they would be accepted and, if
so, whether the nestlings would be reared successfully.
I had successfully bred the Black-faced Grassquit several times in the
garden aviary adjoining my birdroom laboratory, and the species is common
in my garden and the neighbourhood. I therefore established a breeding pair
of grassquits in the aviary and another in a Terenzani breeding cage measuring
1m x 0.5m x 0.5m (approx. 3ft 3in x 1ft 7%in x 1ft TAm). To represent
the estrildid/viduine group I used pairs of Bengalese, the domesticated
descendant ofL. striata swinhoei (Restall, 1996), which were also placed in
Terenzani breeding cages. I also had a free-breeding pair of small canaries,
the Timbrado breed, which is similar to the Roller canary in Europe, and is
normally used to supply the pet trade here in Venezuela. I included these
as a control.
During the following year (in the rainy season, when local finches and
others breed), I was able to place a fertile egg of the estrildid Bengalese in
the nest of the grassquits in the aviary (those in the cage failed to breed).
On another occasion I was able to exchange newly-hatched grassquits with
newly-hatched estrildines. As a control I placed Bengalese eggs in the
canary nest.
I was able to find an active grassquit nest in the neighbourhood and as
soon as both of the eggs had hatched, was able to take the nestlings and
replace them with two recently hatched Bengalese.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.865152">
Results
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999524" page_id="56261271"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
The canary incubated and hatched the Bengalese eggs, but failed to rear
the nestlings past the second day. The Bengalese incubated and hatched
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.675968" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261272" page_num="53" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - PIN-TAILED WHYDAH/BLACK-FACED GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998374" page_id="56261272"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
53
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998918923076923" page_id="56261272"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
the first clutch of grassquit eggs, but also failed to rear the nestlings past
the second day. The grassquits in the aviary deserted their nest when the
Bengalese egg was added. The local grassquits in the park deserted their
nest and I found the Bengalese nestling dead and overrun with ants. The
Bengalese deserted the nest in which I had replaced their own young with
grassquit nestlings. It was not possible to tell whether the desertion caused
the death of the grassquit nestlings, or if it was their death that caused the
Bengalese to desert. Desertion of any nest by Bengalese is rare. Like Zebra
Finches Taeniopygia castanotis , they are quite likely to simply add some nest
material on top of the dead nestlings and lay a fresh clutch of eggs.
The Bengalese when left alone subsequently raised a healthy and strong
brood of four young. The grassquits in the aviary eventually built a new
nest and raised both chicks from a second clutch of two eggs.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.88684">
Discussion
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999606962962963" page_id="56261272"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
The adult birds used in the experiment were healthy and subsequently
bred perfectly normally. During the experiment though, it was painfully
apparent that they were unable to feed the other birds' nestlings. I sat and
watched the canary feed herself and then go to the nest, looking in on the
Bengalese nestlings and even making head movements that led me to think
that the chicks were being fed, but on examining them later I found that she
had not fed them.
A characteristic of estrildid waxbills is that the nestlings have a contorted
sideways twist to the neck when begging for food. The more hungry the
nestling, the more it contorts and twists its head, shows its palate and
increasingly moves its tongue from side to side. Freshly-hatched estrildids
beg like other small passerines, but soon begin the neck-twisting behaviour,
apparently on the second day in the case of Estrild waxbills (although the
Zebra Finch does not begin to do so until the fourth or fifth day (Zann, 1996)
and the Cut-throat Finch Amadina fasciata does not develop the behaviour at
all (Goodwin, 1982)). The neck-twisting is most easily seen when fledgling
Zebra Finches beg for food from their parents.
No doubt this eccentric behaviour is an adaptation enabling the brood
of nestlings to obtain food from the attendant parent within the confines
of the small, enclosed nest. The adult enters from the side of the speroid
and stands in a horizontal position and the nestlings twist around in order
to present their gape in the most inviting position possible. In contrast, it
is a characteristic of nestlings hatched in open, cup-shaped nests, to reach
directly upwards, the strongest or hungriest nestling reaching the furthest and
getting first attention from the food-bearing parent. In the case of estrildid
nestlings it seems that the hungriest bird - the one with the widest gape
showing the most palate markings - is the attention-claiming equivalent of
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.845665" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261273" page_num="54" year="" vol="">
54 RESTALL - PIN-TAILED WHYDAH/BLACK-FACED GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99907331707317" page_id="56261273"  page_num="54" year="" vol="">
the upward-reaching nestling.
Tiaris grassquits make a covered nest that superficially resembles an
estrildid nest and it would be easy to assume that the nestlings beg in a
similar manner to estrildid nestlings. However, this illusion was shattered
by a photo Rafy Rodriguez sent me showing a female Puerto Rican Black-
faced Grassquit standing at the entrance of her nest and feeding a clutch of
hungry nestlings. The entrance was actually a loose and fairly large opening,
almost as so a slice had been cut at an angle from the upper front of the
spheroid, rather than having a porch, tunnel-like opening at the side, typical
of the waxbills. Furthermore, the grassquit nestlings were at the front edge
of the opening and begging directly upwards, just like nestlings in an open,
cup-shaped nest. The forward edge of the roof of the nest was above and
slightly behind the heads of the gaping nestlings. A careful examination
of the design of several Black-faced Grassquit nests in the vicinity of my
home showed that the nest in the photo was a typical example of a nest built
by this species.
Much has been written about the role of the luminous spots and globules
in and at the gape edges of estrildid nestlings, and that every species has
its own specific pattern of markings. The palate markings of the waxbills
in the genus Estrilda are usually similar, with the palate markings of the
Pin-tailed Whydah mimicking those the Common Waxbill perfectly. The
palate markings of the two common Estrilda waxbills on Puerto Rico, the
Black-ramped and the Orange-cheeked species, are similar to those of the
Common Waxbill. The whydah nestlings behave just like estrildid nestlings,
complete with twisting begging motions, as can be seen from newly-fledged
whydahs twist-begging from their waxbill foster parents. It is interesting
that the palate markings of the Bronze Mannikin are different from those
of the waxbills. It has a horseshoe-shaped bar instead of five spots and it is
significant that this species is only occasionally used as a host in its native
Africa (22 times out of 79 parasitized nests in one field study (Mines, 1989)).
The palate markings of the Tri-coloured Munia are different yet again and,
in simple design terms, are possibly midway between those of the Bronze
Mannikin and the Common Waxbill.
Tiaris grassquits do not possess palate markings, neither is the gape
luminous, there is no need for it to be, as the nestlings gape in clear, open
light, whereas the estrildid and viduine nestlings do so in darkened, enclosed
nests. The palate and gape flanges of the grassquit nestling are a uniform
pale creamy colour.
The main function of the palate markings is to signal to the parent, "feed
me", and the hungrier the nestling, the more it will contort, open the gape
wider and increasingly move the tongue from side to side. It follows that
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.675992" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261274" page_num="55" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - PIN-TAILED WHYDAH/BLACK-FACED GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994644" page_id="56261274"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
55
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.986072804878049" page_id="56261274"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
in a comparative situation, when a food-carrying parent is confronted with
two kinds of gaping palates, it will respond to the gape that it is genetically
conditioned to respond to.
What about reports that the whydah has been seen entering and laying in
the nests of grassquits? Jack Clinton Eitniear and Lucie Salwiczek have both
mentioned this (pers. comm.) and the late lan Hinze also raised this matter
when we last met. All three commented on the disputes that such reports
provoke. It seems that my experience of the grassquit deserting the nest after
a Bengalese egg was added to the clutch is probably typical of what occurs
in the wild. Nests of Black-faced Grassquit have indeed been found with a
whydah egg amongst the grassquit's eggs, but these nests had either already
been deserted or were subsequently deserted. Furthermore, individual
fledgling whydahs have been seen with fledgling waxbills following adult
waxbills, but have never been seen with fledgling grassquits attended by
their parents (Raul Perez-Rivera pers. comm.).
Conclusion
The apparent inability of a Tiaris grassquit to accept and feed nestling
estrildids argues strongly that any attempt by the Pin-tailed Whydah to
brood-parasitize the Black-faced Grassquit would be doomed to failure. As
a concomitant reciprocal, were it possible for a grassquit to rear an estrildid
nestling, then it would be possible for an estrildid to rear a grassquit nestling.
In this trial, the estrildid finch was the Bengalese. This domesticated
form has been bred for centuries in China, with particular emphasis on its
unquestioning willingness to foster more delicate and colourful waxbills.
The Japanese long ago used Bengalese to virtually "factory breed" Gouldian
Finches Erythura gouldiae. (The newer variants of the Bengalese developed
in recent decades in Europe by crossing the Bengalese with the Black Munia
L. stygia (which have not yet reached Venezuela) are far less efficient as
foster parents.) Field experiments with parasitized waxbills in Africa have
shown that the hosts will usually accept nestlings with different gape patterns
(Schuetz, 2005), inviting the inference that closely related Estrilds will show
a similar degree of tolerance. Various instances of fostering among different
Lonchura species reported in the cage bird and aviculture literature over the
years and, personal experience, suggest a greater foster-flexibility on the
part of munias, with the Bengalese the most open-hearted foster mother of
them all. This super-foster ability loaded the dice in favour of the Bengalese
succeeding, but proved to no avail, as they apparently failed to cope with the
directly upward-reaching begging behaviour of the grassquit nestlings.
In the report that prompted this study, the Yellow-faced Grassquit was
not listed as a host species of the whydah, but as its breeding behaviour is
virtually identical to that of its congener, it is equally valid, or invalid, as the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.873284" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261275" page_num="56" year="" vol="">
56 RESTALL - PIN-TAILED WHYDAH/BLACK-FACED GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997245" page_id="56261275"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
Black-faced Grassquit, as a possible host for the Pin-tailed Whydah.
There are clearly two questions that require answers:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.980360666666667" page_id="56261275"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
1. Why would a grassquit not accept the egg of, nor rear a nestling of a
viduine/estrildine?
2. Why would an estrildid not rear a grassquit nestling?
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.998347205882353" page_id="56261275"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
It is the first question that should be answered as unequivocally as
possible.
a. The egg of the whydah is white, whereas the eggs of the grassquit are
pastel greenish-grey, speckled lightly with various browns and greys,
which tend to be denser at the rounded end; the whydah egg is also
larger. The cavity of the grassquit nest is open to the light, even when
a bird is standing in the entrance, so that the contrasting usurper egg
would be noticed immediately. In the dark interior of an estrildid nest,
the only noticeable difference is the larger size of the whydah egg, and
that is apparently not enough to prompt rejection. Grassquits commonly
lay two eggs, or more rarely, three eggs. Waxbills lay four to six eggs,
therefore an additional egg is less noticeable.
b. Neotropical small passerines generally have shorter incubation periods
and the two, or occasionally three young, fledge earlier than those of
small passerines in the Old World tropics. This is an adaption to deal
with the fact that food is less abundant (Skutch, 1949) and nests are more
heavily predated. Estrildid finches have clutches of four to six eggs
and nestling periods of up to three weeks. This means that the natural
advantage that all "cuckoos" have of being slightly larger, with more
voracious appetites and fledging slightly earlier than their host species'
nestlings, is invalid. Waxbills begin incubation after the third egg has
been laid, whereas grassquits begin incubation after the second egg has
been laid which means that, on average, compared to an Estrilda-Vidua
combination, the Tiaris eggs would commence incubation a day earlier,
further reducing the whydah's advantage.
c. The parent grassquit is adapted to face its nestlings as they reach
directly upwards, with their wide open, unmarked pale gapes, being the
stimulus for it to regurgitate food into the maw; the behaviour in effect
saying, "I'm hungry, feed me." If, alongside the (usually) two "normal",
upward-reaching nestlings, there was another nestling, perhaps a little
larger and begging more strongly, but with a strangely spotted and
coloured gape, twisting around, with a wagging tongue and, lower in
the nest than the grassquit nestlings, then it would be quite remarkable
were that nestling to be fed.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.675855" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261276" page_num="57" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - PIN-TAILED WHYDAH/BLACK-FACED GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996767" page_id="56261276"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
57
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99652112195122" page_id="56261276"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
d. A further factor arising from the point I just made about differences
between small passerines of the Old World tropics and those of the
Neotropics, is that the latter seem to be far more sensitive and responsive
to nest invasion and desert more readily. Laying small clutches means
they can begin a second or third nest with far less effort than a waxbill
that has built a complex nest and laid five eggs.
e. An important difference between estrildid and viduine nestling begging
behaviour and that of other passerine nestlings, is that estrildid and
viduine nestlings do not swallow the food brought to the nest - the parents
thrust it deep into the open maw. I witnessed the sheer puzzlement of
the canary as she was poised to feed the Bengalese nestling, for it was
almost impossible for her to delicately place the food she had regurgitated
into the twisting, waggling gape, and she left without trying. Her own
chicks would have quickly swallowed the morsel and then begged for
more. In contrast, an estrildid nestling that had a morsel of food placed
in its open gape could, because of the wagging of the tongue and the
movement of the head, easily shake it out. From observations of the
Volatinia grassquit and Sporophila seedeaters feeding nestlings, the food-
placing movements are very quick and light, and I am sure those of the
Black-faced Grassquit are the same. It is therefore virtually certain that
the faster, lighter and more delicate feeding technique of these ^normal"
passerine species is inadequate to sustain an African estrildid or viduine
nestling adapted to having food pumped down its throat.
Nicolai (1964) suggested that the feeding method used by estrildids
requires a specialised adaptive breathing technique. Parent estrildids place
their bills deeper into the maw of the nestling and pump up more food at a
time. In contrast, a canary is a delicate and light feeder. He pointed out that
there have been many attempts to rear carduelid finches (e.g. the Red Siskin
Carduelis cucullata) under estrildids (the Zebra Finch can be just as efficient
at fostering as the Bengalese and was often used in such experiments) but
these have always failed because the nestlings are choked. This reverse of
the grassquit feeding -estrildid produces exactly the same result.
When considering reports of non-estrildid species being used as hosts
by the whydah, it is important to recognise that the act of laying an egg
in a nest, does not necessarily mean that the egg will be accepted by the
owners of the nest, let alone incubated successfully and the chick fed and
raised to independence. In the absence of confirmed evidence of successful
acceptance, brooding and rearing, the appearance of an alien egg in any nest
is simply that, and no more. One final point: I have elaborated on several
factors that could militate against a grassquit successfully rearing a Vidua
nestling, because the sample of birds used in this experiment was too small to
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996064" page_id="56261277"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
58
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.916317" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261277" page_num="58" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - PIN-TAILED WHYDAH/BLACK-FACED GRASSQUIT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99894075" page_id="56261277"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
be statistically valid. However, I am convinced that the collective evidence
summarized here shows that the successful use of the Black-faced Grassquit
as a host by the Pin-tailed Whydah on Puerto Rico is, effectively, impossible.
This fully supports Nicolai's original statement.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.941701" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56261277" page_num="58" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999018" page_id="56261277"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
My profound thanks to Lucie Salwiczek and Jack Clinton Eitniear for
their constructive critical comments and suggestions, to Rafy Rodriguez
for his interest, information and many photographs, and to lan Hinze, who
engaged in several animated discussions on the subject at the genesis of
this paper.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.883026" genericHeader="references" page_id="56261277" page_num="58" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.829566576923077" page_id="56261277"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
Borrow, N. and Demey, R. 2001. Birds of Western Africa. Helm, London.
Camacho Rodriguez, M., J. Chabert Llompart y M. Lopez. 1999. Guiapara la Identificacion
de las Aves Exoticas en Puerto Rico. D.R.N.A., Division de Recursos Terrestres. San Juan,
Puerto Rico.
Friedmann, H. 1960. The Parasitic Weaverbirds. Bull. 223, Smithsonian Institution. United
States National Museum, Washington, D.C.
Goodwin, D. 1982. Estrildid Finches of the World. British Museum (Natural History).
MacLean, G. L. 1985. Roberts' Birds of Southern Africa. John Voelcker Bird Book Fund,
Cape Town.
MacDonald, M. A. 1980. Observations on Wilson's Widowfinch and the Pintailed Whydah
in southern Ghana, with notes on their hosts. Ostrich 51:21-24.
Mines, B. M. 1999. Hosts of the Pintailed Whydah ( Vidua macroura) in southern Africa.
Avian Demography Unit: Bird Numbers 8(1) Article 06.
Nicolai, J. 1964. Der Brutparasitismus der Viduinae als ethologisches problem. Zeitschrift
fur Tierpsychologie 21,2:129-204.
Payne, R. B. 2005. Nestling mouth markings and colours of Old World finches Estrildidae:
mimicry and coevolution ofnesting finches and their Vidua broodparasites. Misc. Pub. No. 194.
Museum of Zoology, University of Michigan.
Raffaele, H. A. 1989. Birds of Puerto Rico and the Virgin Islands. Princeton University
Press.
Redman, N., Stevenson, T. and Fanshawe, J. 2009. Birds of the Horn of Africa. Helm,
London.
Restall. R. 1975. Finches and other seed-eating birds. Faber &amp; Faber, London.
Restall. R. 1996. Munias and Mannikins. Pica Press, London.
Schuetz. J. G. 2005. Reduced growth but not survival of chicks with altered gape patterns:
implications for the evolution of nestling similarity in a parasitic finch. Animal Behaviour
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.92510875">
70:839-848.
Skutch, A. F. 1949. Do tropical birds rear as many young as they can nourish? Ibis 91:430-
455.
Stevenson, T. and Fanshawe, J. 2002. Birds of East Africa. T &amp; A D Poyser, London.
Zann, R. 1996. The Zebra Finch. A synthesis of Field and Laboratory Studies. Oxford
University Press.
Avicultural Society Vice President Robin Restall lives in Caracas,
Venezuela. E-mail:robinrestall@gmail. com
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.988053" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261278" page_num="59" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE MOUSTACHED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.470494" page_id="56261278"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
lanthocinda cineracea AT WADDESDON MANOR
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995421" page_id="56261278"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
59
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.976732891891892" page_id="56261278"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
by Simon Matthews
The Moustached Laughingthrush, also known sometimes as the Ashy or
Black-capped Laughingthrush, is one of seven species of laughingthrushes
housed at Waddesdon Manor, near Aylesbury, Buckinghamshire. The
Moustached Laughingthrush was formerly grouped along with a number
of other babblers in the genus Garrulax , which has now been split into
11 genera. The genus lanthocinda contains eight species. These can be
characterised as having white or pale tips on at least the secondary and tertial
feathers, strong colours on the wings and a cap-like effect on the head.
The Moustached Laughingthrush is a medium-sized species measuring
21cm-24cm (approx. ^Ain-Wiin) from head to tail and weighing 43g-55g.
It is sandy brown in colour, with a black cap, moustache and wing-tips. Its
underparts are a huffy grey-brown, there are large grey panels on the wings
and the tail is mainly grey-brown, with black subterminal markings and
white tips to the feathers (see photo p.60).This laughingthrush has a loud
call but is not as vocal as some of the other laughingthrushes. It produces a
high-pitched "pr'r'r'r'ip", which is repeated quickly and sometimes contains
hard, chuckling, disjointed notes.
There are currently three recognised subspecies: /. c. cineracea in north-
east India and western Burma (Myanmar); L c. strenua in north-east Burma
(Myanmar) and south China; and I. c. cinereiceps in central and eastern
China. They inhabit a range of different habitats, including scrubland on
the edge of broadleaf forest, mixed broadleaf coniferous forest, disused
agricultural land, bamboo forest, and can be found living close to villages
(Collar &amp; Robson, 2007).
BirdLife International consider the Moustached Laughingthrush to be
a species of Least Concern, due to its large range and believed population
size. The population is thought to be declining in size, although it has never
been surveyed. The Moustached Laughingthrush is kept by aviculturists,
but not in large numbers. ISIS (International Species Information System)
shows that Waddesdon is the only public collection holding this species. In
addition, there are a few pairs in private collections around the UK.
Waddesdon obtained an adult pair of Moustached Laughingthrush from
Peter Moore in September 2008 and got a second pair in March 2009. The
first pair is housed alone in an off-show aviary. The second pair, consisting
of two 3008 bred birds, is on show to visitors in one of our main aviaries.
Housed with the second pair is a pair of Mindanao Bleeding Hearts
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.988078" page_id="56261279"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
60
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.753953" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261279" page_num="60" year="" vol="">
MATTHEWS - MOUSTACHED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9705886" page_id="56261279"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
Gallicolumba criniger which bred well in 2009, and a pair of Pekin Robins
Leiothrix lutea. It is thought that the Pekin Robins were disturbed by the
laughingthrushes and for that reason were not successful in their breeding
attempt. The second pair of laughingthrushes made no attempt to breed in
2009.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.529631">
Simon Matthews
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.973357944444444" page_id="56261279"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
Adult Moustached Laughingthrush.
The off-show aviary housing the first pair of laughingthrushes (see photo
opposite), is a wooden framed structure measuring 2.8m x 5.3m (approx. 9ft
x 17ft Bin), covered with ^in x lin (13mm x 25mm) wire mesh and has a
large, unheated shelter at one end. Approximately 60% of the entire structure
is covered with Corolux. The aviary has several perches and is planted with
bamboo, a young yew tree Taxus sp. and box shrubs Buxus sp.
In the wild the Moustached Laughingthrush consumes beetles and
other insects, along with seeds, berries and fruit and, at Waddesdon, we
try to duplicate the Moustached Laughingthrush's natural diet as closely as
possible. All our laughingthrushes receive a similar diet, consisting of a fruit
mix, an insectivorous mix and livefood. The fruit mix contains 11 different
kinds of fresh fruit and T16 softbill pellets. The insectivorous mix is made
from four different commercial softbill foods, to which we add grated carrot,
hard-boiled egg, raisins and apple. The birds also receive two livefood feeds
a day, as well as receiving insects on their main food dish. These consist
mainly of mealworms, but they also get waxmoth larvae and crickets.
On March 18th 2009, the first pair of Moustached Laughingthrushes
</bodyText>
<address confidence="0.353694">
MATTHEWS - MOUSTACHED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</address>
<page confidence="0.998316" page_id="56261280"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
61
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999864529411765" page_id="56261280"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
housed in the off-show aviary was seen carrying nest material, so extra
cover was provided in the form of yew tree branches, along with hay and
coconut fibre and two small wicker nest baskets. One was placed quite low
down in the young yew tree and the other was placed in some fresh yew
cover at the back of the aviary. No fu r the r activity was noticed until March
30th, when the pair began to build a nest in the wicker basket low down in
the young yew tree. This nest was never really lined or completed. Just
over two weeks later on April 14th, a nest with two eggs in it was found in
the box scrub on the left-hand side of the aviary. The laughingthrushes had
built this nest entirely on their own about 6in (15cm) in from the outside
of the scrub, using mainly coconut fibre. The nest was never measured but
looked to be no more than 4in (10cm) in diameter. The pair began incubating
the following day. The female may have laid another egg before then, so
that there was a clutch of three eggs. The eggs of this laughingthrash are
a wonderful turquoise colour with tiny brown spots. As that part of the
aviary was not under cover, we gently slipped a sheet of Corolux onto the
roof above the nest to protect it from the elements.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.644214">
Simon Matthews
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999251333333333" page_id="56261280"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
Off-show aviary in which the laughingthrushes bred.
On April 27th the pair began to carry livefood, suggesting that the
incubation period was 12 days. The following day three healthy chicks were
seen in the nest. The parents were provided with white mealworms (those
that had recently shed their skin) and home-produced waxmoth larvae four to
five times a day, beginning at 7,00am and ending at about 6.00pm (18.00hrs)
each day. There were no concerns during the rearing of the chicks, which
fledged on May 9th, i.e. after 12 days. All three reached independence a
few weeks later.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996109" page_id="56261281"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
62
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.776049" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261281" page_num="62" year="" vol="">
MATTHEWS - MOUSTACHED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9941858" page_id="56261281"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
The pair lined the nest made previously in the yew tree and on May 30th,
there were two eggs in this nest. These hatched on June 12th, the following
day though one of the chicks was found dead on the aviary floor. The female
continued to care for the remaining chick which fledged on June 24th. During
the second nesting the three previous fledglings remained in the aviary but
were not observed assisting with the rearing of the fourth chick. Later in
the breeding season two broken eggs were found on the aviary floor and an
infertile egg was found in an old nest. This could, we think, have been due
to the four fledglings continuing to be housed in the aviary with their parents,
even though we did not see any aggression between any of the birds.
Lionel Currie, one of several private aviculturists holding this species
in the UK, has an unrelated pair and was successful breeding this species
in 2009. Lionel's pair began nest building in February and March and, in
June, settled in the top of an old treefem. Two eggs were laid and the pair
successfully hatched them and reared the chicks. As we did at Waddesdon,
Lionel left the juveniles with the adult birds without any problems, except
that in his case, the pair made no further attempt to breed in 2009.
If any members have experience of breeding this species or are currently
keeping Moustached Laughingthrushes, I would be very interested in hearing
from them. E-mail:Simon.Matthews@nationaltrust.org.uk
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.923449" genericHeader="references" page_id="56261281" page_num="62" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.8007792">
Collar, N. J. and Robson, C. 2007. Family Timaliidae (Babblers): In:del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A.
and Christie, D. A. (Eds.) Handbook of the Birds of the World Vol.12 (Picathartes to Tits and
Chickadees). Lynx Edicions, Barcelona.
BirdLife International. 2009. Species factsheet: Garrulax cineraceus. Downloaded from
http://www.birdlife.org (04/01/2010).
</reference>
<table confidence="0.407235" page_id="56261281"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
*
* *
NEW SECRETARY AND TREASURER
</table>
<reference confidence="0.919374">
Peter Stocks is the new Hon. Secretary and Treasurer of the Avicultural
Society, replacing Paul Boulden who relinquished the position on June
30th. Peter's contact details can be found on the inside of the front cover
of this issue.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999072" page_id="56261282"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
63
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.492978" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261282" page_num="63" year="" vol="">
THE BIRD COLLECTION AT TAIPEI ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997740552631579" page_id="56261282"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
by Pierre de Chabannes
The island of Taiwan (formerly named Formosa) is well known amongst
zoologists and birdwatchers for its amazing number of endemic species of
animals, especially species of birds. Taiwan has a subtropical climate and is
homo to a wide array of birds, including both tropical and temperate species,
as well as migrants from colder regions. There are lowland and mountain
forests, as well as grasslands, swamps and other humid areas. I was in
Taipei, capital city of Taiwan, from December 26th-Becember 29th 2009.
The winter (like that of Hong Kong) is usually drier and colder, although the
temperature stays mostly between 10*C-2O*C (50*F-68*F). The summer is
hot, very humid and often accompanied by tropical rains, storms and even
typhoons. These factors help explain the incredible diversity of the avifauna
found on Taiwan, which is such an attraction to bird enthusiasts like me.
During my stay in Taipei, I was fortunate enough to visit Taipei Zoo
twice, on each occasion for a full day. The weather was mostly good, apart
from a little rain, which lasted for about two hours during my second visit.
During the highly enjoyable two days, I obtained a good overview of the
zoo's very nice bird collection and also found time to do some birdwatching
in the forested area of the park.
The zoo, located in hilly forest in the district of Muzha, a few metro
stations away from the city centre, occupies an area of more than 160
hectares (approx. 395 acres). Despite the numerous enclosures, aviaries and
buildings housing the impressive collection of animals, most of the original
vegetation has been preserved and one third of the site remains completely
wild, allowing many of the local bird species to live in complete freedom
in the zoo grounds. Taipei Zoo is heavily involved in the protection of
the island's endemic species of animals. Captive breeding programmes
for species such as the Formosan Serow Capricornis swinhoei, Swinhoe's
Pheasant Lophura swinhoii and Taiwan or Formosan Blue Magpie Urocissa
caerulea , have been proposed by Taipei Zoo, which has been joined by other
Taiwanese parks concerned about local species.
I have set out to give members an insight into what to expect should they
be fortunate enough to visit Taipei Zoo's bird collection and how to maximize
the time spent in this huge park in order to miss as little as possible. The
zoo is divided into geographic zones and there are a few thematic buildings
and exhibits. The bird collection is spread throughout the different sections,
which are all well worth visiting, and one can appreciate the way the park has
been well landscaped and the conservation efforts of the zoological team.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.989217" page_id="56261283"  page_num="64" year="" vol="">
64
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.406367" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261283" page_num="64" year="" vol="">
CHABANNES - TAIPEI ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.949907928571428" page_id="56261283"  page_num="64" year="" vol="">
Pierre de Chabannes
The Taiwanese or Formosan subspecies of the Chinese Bamboo Partridge
is darker coloured.
A standard visit begins at the Formosan animal area, which is especially
interesting for foreign visitors. There are many rarities such as the Formosan
Serows, Formosan Macaques Macaca cyclopis and deer and, one can get the
first glimpse of the shy but beautiful Swinhoe's Pheasant. There is a male
and three females in a dark aviary without, unfortunately, any vegetation.
Taipei Zoo has chosen to concentrate its efforts on this species and leave
the other zoos and bird gardens on the island to work with the Mikado
Pheasant Syrmaticus mikado. In Europe, Swinhoe's Pheasant, although
not particularly common, is more frequently seen in public bird collections
than the Mikado Pheasant. In Taipei Zoo they live with one of two breeding
groups of Formosan Bamboo Partridges Bamhusicola thoracica sonorivox
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.374339" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261284" page_num="65" year="" vol="">
CHABANNES - TAIPEI ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.975223" page_id="56261284"  page_num="65" year="" vol="">
65
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.94624652631579" page_id="56261284"  page_num="65" year="" vol="">
Pierre de Chabannes
Taipei Zoo's last remaining Black-faced Spoonbill,
displayed in the Formosan animal area. This subspecies of the Chinese
Bamboo Partridge, easily differentiated by its much darker general coloration,
is not currently exhibited in any public collection in Europe.
The final two avian representatives living in this zone are the local
subspecies of the Brown Wood Owl Strix leptogrammica calligata , a species
of owl which is common in Asian zoos, and a lone specimen of the Formosan
Crested Serpent-Eagle Spilornis cheela hoya. This lovely species of raptor is
to be seen in almost every large Asian zoo, from Indonesia to China, but most
exhibit their own local subspecies and, as there are 21 different subspecies,
it is difficult to establish successful a breeding programme.
Next comes a huge building housing nocturnal animals. It houses mostly
mammals, along with a few birds. Most of the cages are quite outdated,
space is strictly limited and there is no landscaping. This old building will
though soon be totally renovated and transformed into a tropical greenhouse.
Until then it is home to a small colony of Black-crowned Night Herons
Nycticorax n. nycticorax , a Eurasian Eagle-Owl Bubo bubo of unknown
origin (it may be one of the Chinese subspecies, perhaps B. b, swinhoei or B.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.980823" page_id="56261285"  page_num="66" year="" vol="">
66
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.672108" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261285" page_num="66" year="" vol="">
CHABANNES - TAIPEI ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998353658536585" page_id="56261285"  page_num="66" year="" vol="">
b. kiautschensis), an Eastern Grass Owl Tyto longimembris pithecops (lumped
together sometimes with the African species and, as in this collection, listed
as T. capensis), a pair of Formosan Collared Scops Owls Otus lettiaglabripes,
a single specimen of the rarely seen Tawny Fish Owl Ketupa flavipes and
a group of scops owls identified as Indian Scops Owls O. bakkamoena but
which are, I believe, Formosan Collared Scops Owls, not only because they
look absolutely identical to the above pair, but also because O. bakkamoena
is now generally considered to be restricted to the Indian subcontinent, which
has led to several south-east Asian, Chinese and Taiwanese collections having
to rename many of their scops owls.
After taking a quick look at the Ring-necked Parakeets Psittacula
krameri borealis in the Children's Zoo, it was time to move on to the huge
south-east Asian geographic zone. The landscaping of the enclosures is
really interesting, as is the tropical forest atmosphere that has been created.
Mostly mammals are exhibited in this zone, but there are also some birds,
beginning with a pair of Sarus Cranes G. a. antigone, which is the most
common species of crane kept in south-east Asian zoos. I think that the
only specimen of Purple Swamphen (Gallinule) Porphyrio porphyrio I
saw belongs to the subspecies P. p. poliocephalus, mostly because of the
amount of grey on the head and the light blue underparts. The aviary, set-
up to resemble a mangrove, has thick cover which renders observation of
the birds difficult. A smaller aviary houses a breeding group of Nicobar
Pigeons Caloenas n. nicobarica, a species which is now a common sight in
collections across Asia, as well as in Europe. A huge aviary housing a pair
of Great Hombills Buceros b. bicornis and Asian Brush-tailed Porcupines
Atherurus macrourus has been built in front of the elephant enclosure. At the
end of the Asian zone is a lake surrounded by forest, which can be viewed
from an observation deck on which are small pay-telescopes for visitors to
watch the birds and try to spot local wild waterbirds. Black Swans Cygnus
atratus were the most common species, but I also saw Chinese Pond Herons
Ardeola bacchus. Cattle Egrets Bubulcus ibis coromandus and Little Egrets
Egretta g. garzetta. Although the endangered Chinese Egret E. eulophotes
no longer breeds on Taiwan, it continues to visit the island as a passage
migrant and sometimes is a winter visitor. Its conspicuous bright yellow
bill, coupled with its black legs and yellow feet, make it easily recognisable
and I consider myself very lucky to have seen one by the lake even though,
unfortunately, it was quite a distance away.
Two species of ratite, the Emu Dromaius novaehollandiae and Southern
Cassowary Casuarius casuarius, are to be found living in the Australian
zone. The origin and subspecific status of the latter is, unfortunately, not
known, which is also true of almost all of those living in European and
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.382105" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261286" page_num="67" year="" vol="">
CHABANNES - TAIPEI ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998669" page_id="56261286"  page_num="67" year="" vol="">
67
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999097170731707" page_id="56261286"  page_num="67" year="" vol="">
mainland Asian zoos (although it should be noted that Clement (2007) did
not recognise any subspecies of cassowary at all). Another rathe, the Ostrich
Struthio camelus, is showcased in one of the enclosures in the African zone.
With its light grey coloured neck and head, the male looked to me to belong
to the southern subspecies S. c. australis.
An air-conditioned building at the end of the temperate animal area,
houses two species of penguin, the African (Jackass) Penguin Spheniscus
demersus and the impressive King Penguin Aptenodytes patagonica. Both
species have been bred in the glass-surrounded enclosure, which has a deep,
cold water pool.
The final section of the park is, for me, the best, for it is dedicated entirely
to tropical birds. There is a large collection of waterbirds housed in large
enclosures, each with a large pond. A tight mesh is stretched across the top
of each enclosure to keep out wild birds which may be carrying viruses,
including the dreaded avian flu, which is still common in most parts of
eastern Asia. The waterbirds include the Asian subspecies of the Cattle
Egret, which in breeding plumage is recognisble by the large amount of
buff coloured feathering on its head, neck and back. There are also breeding
groups of Lesser Flamingo Phoeniconaias minor and Chilean Flamingo
Phoenicopterus chilensis. (A third species, the Greater Flamingo P roseus ,
is showcased in a smaller enclosure by the main entrance to the park.) Other
waterbirds include Pink-backed Pelicans Pelecanus rufescens , which are not
uncommon in Asian zoos, Saras Cranes and Common Moorhens Gallinula
c. chloropus, the latter a bird more often seen living wild than in captivity
in Europe and Asia.
Every large Asian zoo has at least one huge walk-in or walk-through
aviary, and Taipei Zoo is no exception. In places the thick vegetation renders
bird spotting quite difficult, but with a little patience, some of the rarer species
can be seen. Visitors can look out over most of the area from an elevated
walkway that follows an S-shaped path between the trees and close to the
pond in the central area of the exhibit. Three smaller aviaries, high but not
very wide, house a Wattled Crane Bugeranus carunculatus , a species almost
never seen in Asian zoological collections, another pair of Saras Cranes and
a beautiful male Green Peafowl Pavo m. muticus.
The first part of this huge aviary is sparsely planted with rather short trees
and there is minimum ground cover, allowing the terrestrial species to forage
more efficiently over the rocky ground. There is a colony of Nicobar Pigeons
and various different domestic mutations of the Rock Pigeon Columba livia.
There are also a pair of Grey Crowned Cranes Balearica r. regulorum ,
Common and Victoria Crowned Pigeons Goura cristata and G. victoria
respectively (of unidentified subspecies), both of which are very common in
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.990649" page_id="56261287"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
68
</page>
<table confidence="0.514242" page_id="56261287"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
CHABANNES - TAIPEI ZOO
Pierre de Chabannes
The Taiwan or Formosan Blue Magpie has yellow eyes and blue underparts.
Asian zoos, Pied Imperial Pigeons Ducula b. bicolor and starlings, the latter
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.998844333333333" page_id="56261287"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
perched alongside each other up in the trees. The starlings include species
such as the very common, large, Black-necked Starling Gracupica ( Sturnus )
nigricollis and the attractive Asian Pied Starling G. (S.) contra jalla. The
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.379328" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261288" page_num="69" year="" vol="">
CHABANNES - TAIPEI ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.989419" page_id="56261288"  page_num="69" year="" vol="">
69
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.972237636363636" page_id="56261288"  page_num="69" year="" vol="">
Pierre de Chabannes
The Hooded Crane is rarely seen in European collections.
last named being, I believe, the subspecies found on Sumatra, Java and Bali,
which has more extensive bare orange skin around the eyes, a clear white
belly and a black crown. The zoo also has at least one Black-winged Starling
Acridotheres (S.) melanopterus, a species which is becoming increasingly
scarce and is now classified as Endangered. It was trapped mainly for the
local cage bird trade on the Indonesian islands of Java and Bali, which (with
Lombok) it is native to and on which it is considered lucky to keep a white
bird. Most individuals kept in captivity in Asia, including those at Taipei
Zoo, are the progeny of different subspecies (not recognised by Clements
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.992817" page_id="56261289"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
70
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.675706" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261289" page_num="70" year="" vol="">
CHABANNES - TAIPEI ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.988817487804878" page_id="56261289"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
(2007)) which have been allowed to hybridise with each other and some
are even hybrids with other closely related species. (In the Avicultural
Magazine Vol.l 14, No. 3, pp. 97-100 (2008), Andrew Owen described the
establishment of a captive breeding group of Black-winged Starlings at the
Cikananga Wildlife Animal Rescue Centre on Java.)
A marshy area in the exhibit is occupied by a pair of Lilford's Cranes G.
g. lilfordi and a mixed colony of Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber and African
Sacred Ibis Threskiornis aethiopicus, both of which are often seen in Asian
collections. Eastern Asia is home to three threatened species of ibis, namely
the Giant Ibis Pseudibis gigantea , White-shouldered Ibis P. davisoni and
Japanese White Ibis Nipponia nippon but, unfortunately, almost no breeding
programmes have been created for these, apart that is for the Japanese White
Ibis, which is kept and bred in some Japanese and Chinese zoos, including
the zoological gardens in Beijing. Most Asian zoos prefer to focus on non-
native species such as the Straw-necked Ibis T. spinicollis , Scarlet Ibis,
African Sacred Ibis and sometimes the Black-headed Ibis I melanocephalus ,
a south-east Asian ibis which is not currently threatened.
The end of the walkway passes through a small area of denser vegetation
frequented by two species of pheasant, the Silver Pheasant L. nycthemera ,
one of the commonest Galliformes in captivity in Asia, and the Greater Argus
Pheasant Argusianus a. argus. Concealed amongst the vegetation was also
a small group of the of the rarely kept Ashy Wood Pigeon C. pulchricollis
and a pair of the equally rare Formosan Green Pigeon Treron f formosae ,
which was not listed on the exhibit's identification panels.
Having come out of the huge walk-in aviary, visitors come to a row of
tall and deep aviaries designed for storks and raptors. These are currently
occupied by Eurasian White Storks Ciconia ciconia, African Marabou Storks
Leptoptilos crumeniferus , a pair of Black Crowned Cranes B. pavonina, a
beautiful specimen of the rare Mountain Hawk-Eagle Spizaetus nipalensis
orientalis , the Japanese subspecies identifiable by its shorter crest and
lighter coloured face, a group of Formosan Crested Serpent-Eagles and some
Brahminy Kites Haliastur i. indicus. Most Asian zoos that keep storks -
apart from some of those in Cambodia, Vietnam and Laos - tend not to show
local endangered species such as the Greater Adjutant L. dubius and Oriental
White Stork C. boyciana. The Oriental White Stork is though being bred in
one or two Chinese zoos and some European collections.
A covered path later splits into two parallel pathways by the sides of which
are two rows of beautifully landscaped aviaries for smaller tropical birds.
There are species from Taiwan, south-east Asia, Africa and South America,
in some instances mixed together and others kept in geographically themed
exhibits. Amongst the most eye-catching are the Toco Toucans Ramphastos
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.380821" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261290" page_num="71" year="" vol="">
CHABANNES - TAIPEI ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994146" page_id="56261290"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
71
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.97592632" page_id="56261290"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
Pierre de Chabannes
Covered walkway past aviaries housing toucans, turacos, the Red Bird-of-Paradise,
Taiwan or Formosan Blue Magpie, Argus Pheasants and other tropical birds.
toco and Keel-billed Toucans It sulfuratus, species which are not all that
rare in big Asian bird collections, despite which they are almost never bred
there. The Phasianidae family is represented by Greater Argus Pheasants,
Silver Pheasants, of unknown origin, Swinhoe's Pheasants, the seldom seen
Grey Junglefow! Gallus sonnerati , some Vieillot's Fireback Pheasants L
ignita rufa , the Blue Eared Pheasant Crossoptilon auritum and a female of
the Taiwanese subspecies of the Ring-necked Pheasant Phasianus colchicus
formosanus. A female Greater Curassow Crax r rubra is displayed in a
separate aviary. This is the only species of curassow seen in south Asian
zoos. One of the most unusual exotic birds I saw in Taipei Zoo was (Buffon's)
Green Turaco Tauracopersa buffoni , a bird which is hard to find in European
zoos but is not rare in Asian collections.
Asian species housed in these aviaries include the Black-winged
Starling, the endemic Taiwanese subspecies of the Large-billed Crow Corvus
macrorhynchus colonorum , a male Red Bird-of-Paradise Paradisaea rubra , a
group of Jungle Mynahs A.fuscus , a pair of the endemic Taiwanese subspecies
of the Rufous or Rusty Laughingthrush Garrulaxp. poecilorhynchus and the
Taiwanese Common Magpie Pica pica sericea , a subspecies rarely if ever
seen in zoological collections.
Lastly, and in my opinion the most interesting species housed in these
aviaries, is the endemic and beautiful Taiwan or Formosan Blue Magpie,
of which the zoo has a breeding group. Immature and unpaired birds assist
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996321" page_id="56261291"  page_num="72" year="" vol="">
72
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.683339" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261291" page_num="72" year="" vol="">
CHABANNES - TAIPEI ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996183048780488" page_id="56261291"  page_num="72" year="" vol="">
the breeding pairs raise their young. It has been shown that without their
assistance, the parents are usually unable to successfully rear their chicks.
Taipei Zoo is probably the only collection in the world in which this species
can currently be seen living in a breeding group.
Next is a set of tall aviaries, each nicely landscaped and providing hiding
places for a few larger species of birds. First to come into sight are some more
Sams Cranes, quickly followed by a pair of White-naped Cranes G. vipio ,
some beautiful Blue (Paradise or Stanley) Cranes Anthropoidesparadiseus, a
small group of Demoiselle Cranes A. virgo and a female Wattled Crane. Two
species housed in the last aviaries captured my attention. The first was an
old Black-faced Spoonbill Platalea minor , easily recognised by its entirely
black bill and large area of exposed black skin on the forehead and around
the eyes. This lone bird has lived in the zoo for a very long time and is the
sole survivor of a large group of these spoonbills. Nowadays, this species
is hardly ever seen or bred in Asian zoos and is almost never seen outside
Asia, except at Weltvogelpark Walsrode in Germany, which has two females.
The last aviary in this section houses a pair of Hooded Cranes G. monacha.
This species breeds in several Chinese zoos and also in some American
collections. In Europe, only two collections keep the Hooded Crane and
only one of these, Weltvogelpark Walsrode, breeds it.
My visit to the Taipei Zoo bird collection ended with the parrots. There
are a few aviaries, each of them nicely landscaped and with behavioural
enrichment provided for these attractive and active birds. Most of the
species on display are common in captivity. These include the Blue-and-
yellow Macaw Ara ararauna, Green-winged Macaw A. chloropterus.
Military Macaw A. militaris, Moluccan Cockatoo Cacatus moluccensis ,
Lesser Sulphur-crested Cockatoo C. s. sulphured , White Cockatoo C. alba ,
Blue-fronted Amazon Amazona aestiva and Yellow-fronted Amazon A.
ochrocephala. Of the others, the Palm Cockatoo Probosciger aterrimus
remains quite common in Asian zoos, but is rarely bred, whereas the beautiful
Hyacinth Macaw Anodorhynchus hyacinthinus , which is a common sight in
Europe, although rarely bred, is very rare in Asian zoos.
That concludes my account of my visit to the bird collection at Taipei
Zoo. I would encourage anyone visiting this zoo to see the entire collection,
which is large and varied and includes animals from all around the world.
In the grounds of the park there are many wild birds. Some of them, such
as the Black-browed Barbet Megalaima oorti nuchalis , often remain hidden
in the forested hills surrounding the zoo and can be difficult to see. Others,
such as the Red Turtle Dove Streptopelia tranquebarica humilis , are more
conspicuous and, depending on the time of the day, good views of them can
be obtained. Great numbers of Red Turtle Doves roost on the trees in the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.382138" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261292" page_num="73" year="" vol="">
CHABANNES - TAIPEI ZOO
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998632" page_id="56261292"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
73
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.975328333333333" page_id="56261292"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
African area. Cattle Egrets and Chinese Turtle (Spotted orNecklaced) Doves
S. c. chinensis are a common sight throughout the park and quite close views
of them can often be obtained by the restaurants and other food outlets.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.94194" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56261292" page_num="73" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.980268866666667" page_id="56261292"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
My deepest thanks to the staff at Taipei Zoo, who welcomed me and
ensured that I had such an enjoyable visit. Their kindness and lovely gifts
really touched me. Particular thanks to Carol Hsin-I Hsieh, without whose
help I would not have had the opportunity to go behind the scenes and obtain
sufficient detailed information to write the above account. I would also like to
thank Chun-Fu Chen (Jeff), who guided me around the Reptile Conservation
Centre and Wetland Ecological Park. His kindness and guidance were as
enjoyable as his knowledge of the local species. I would also like to thank
Dr Shiang-fa Chen, Ming Hsung Chang PhD and Hwa Ching Lin, who each
provided me with very useful documentation and information, as well as
guiding me around the park. Thank you all for making it such a memorable
visit. Finally, I would like to thank Josef Lindholm for his guidance and
assistance during the writing of the above account.
Pierre de Chabannes lives in Le Chesnay in France. E-mail:
pedroyayadrums@yahoo. com
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998091" page_id="56261293"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
74
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.991794" genericHeader="method" page_id="56261293" page_num="74" year="" vol="">
THE SUCCESSFUL BREEDING OF THE BLUE-NECKED
OR AZURE-HEADED TANAGER Tangara cyanicollis
AT WELTVOGELPARK WALSRODE, GERMANY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996483611111111" page_id="56261293"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
by Simon Bruslund Jensen and Kerstin Kirchoffel
The breeding of tanagers is a relatively rare occurrence and these birds
are becoming more and more uncommon in aviculture. The main reason
for the scarcity of good breeding results probably lies in the fact that not
enough attention is given to their needs. Far too often tanagers are kept
in mixed species groups, in which they amaze us with their vivid colours
and get into quarrels, albeit usually not serious quarrels, with other birds.
Tanagers, however, do best when they are kept on their own in pairs or with
other bird groups that do not cause disturbances.
The Blue-necked Tanager, as it is most commonly known, or Azure-
headed Tanager, which is perhaps a more suitable name, has regularly been
kept at Weltvogelpark Walsrode since the park first opened. It was kept
mostly in the Paradise Hall in pairs or small groups, either in aviaries or in
the large free-flight section. It was frequently kept with other tanagers such
as the Golden T. arthus. Paradise T. chilensis and Masked Crimson Tanager
Ramphocelus nigrogularis. The Blue-necked or Azure-headed Tanager was
previously bred in the park in 1994 and 2001.
It is one of the few species of tanager that has been studied in some detail.
It has a fairly large distribution in western and central South America. It
is found principally in open scrubland and on the edge of forest, but has
also adapted well to secondary habitat and is frequently found in gardens.
It is fairly abundant within its preferred habitat and is currently not under
threat. It frequently lives in pairs, but single birds and family groups are
also encountered. When feeding in fruiting trees it may gather with other
species for a short while. Observations suggest that it eats mainly fruit but
examination of its stomach contents have revealed that it also consumes
insects, particularly caterpillars. The most reliable data on its breeding
biology comes from captive birds. According to the literature available it
usually has two eggs, which are incubated for about 15 days. The chicks
remain in the nest for 20 days and after they fledge, the parents continue to
feed them for a further three weeks.
Until recently few zoos kept small tanagers even though, thanks to their
vivid colours, they are popular both with the general public and small softbill
enthusiasts. Over the past few years, however, as smaller softbills have
become increasingly difficult to obtain here in Europe, more zoos have begun
to show a growing interest in keeping and breeding tanagers. Currently the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.797115" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261294" page_num="75" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND JENSEN &amp; KIRCHOFFEL - BLUE-NECKED TANAGER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996244" page_id="56261294"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
75
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999272146341464" page_id="56261294"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
Blue-necked or Azure-headed Tanager is bred only sporadically in a few
zoos and by some private breeders, in numbers far from sufficient to build
up a sustainable captive population.
Our current pair, established in 2009, consists of an older male and a
very young captive-bred female. The pair was given an aviary to itself, but
during the first year did not show any signs of breeding behaviour. As is
typical with tanagers, the two showed few obvious signs of affection, such
as mutal preening, and it was very difficult to determine the quality of the
pair bond. The two did, however, continually keep in contact with each other
through subtle contact calls, which kept up our hopes that the two would
become a successful breeding pair.
Earlier this year the pair was moved to an aviary in the Paradise Hall.
Here the pair shared the 10m sq (approx. l,076sq ft) accommodation with
a pair of Pink-headed Fruit Doves Ptilinopus porphyreus and a pair of
Harlequin Quail Coturnix delegorguei. In early April, only a few weeks
after being transferred to this aviary, the pair began nest building. During
this period the male was occasionally seen displaying when he would, for
example, lower his wings and arch his back to show off his colours to the
female for a few seconds at a time. We barely noticed his song. Apart from
this, the pair paid little attention to each other; at best they would occasionally
follow each other around the aviary.
The pair nested about 0.5m (approx. 1ft 8in) above the ground, in an
open bamboo nesting basket 12cm (approx. 3!/2in) in diameter, placed in a
small fig tree. The material used consisted mainly of different plant fibres,
including coconut fibre and fine ariel rootlets from the fig trees. The pair
also used small amounts of animal hair and moss. Only the female was
observed incubating the eggs and scarcely ever left the nest. The pair was
wary around the nesting tree and took a detour, so as not to reveal the location
of the nest. It contained two eggs and after 14 days the parents became more
nervous than usual. A few days later begging calls confirmed the presence
of chicks in the nest. When they were approximately two weeks old the
male began carrying nesting material and was apparently looking for a new
nesting site. Just short of two weeks after they hatched, the two young
tanagers fledged and during the first day remained on the ground. At this
point the fruit doves suddenly and surprisingly became aggressive towards
the newly-fledged young tanagers, to such an extent that the fruit doves
had to be removed. Unfortunately, one of the young tanagers succumbed
to the related stress, but within a few days the remaining young tanager
was perched in the open, mostly waiting at a certain location to be fed. A
week later the young tanager actively pursued the nearest parent, begging
to be fed. During the nestling period both parents fed the chicks and were
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.959219" page_id="56261295"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
76
</page>
<table confidence="0.7014304" page_id="56261295"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND JENSEN &amp; KIRCHOFFEL - BLUE-NECKED TANAGER
Joao Marco Rosa
The male of the breeding pair.
Joao Marco Rosa
Two weeks after fledging the young tanager actively pursued its parents for food.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.796497" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261296" page_num="77" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND JENSEN &amp; KIRCHOFFEL - BLUE-NECKED TANAGER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994138" page_id="56261296"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
77
</page>
<author confidence="0.33563">
Simon Bruslund Jensen
</author>
<bodyText confidence="0.988614125" page_id="56261296"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
Juvenile awaiting the return of its parents
with food.
themselves offered fresh food by the keepers, initially six times a day and,
two weeks later, four times a day. After the young tanager fledged the male
fed it slightly more frequently than the female.
After a few weeks the pair showed renewed interest in the original nesting
site and refurbished the nest and shortly afterwards produced a second clutch
of eggs. Again there were two eggs and both hatched. Shortly after this the
young tanager from the first clutch was no longer being fed by the parents
and was removed from the aviary well over four weeks after fledging. There
was exactly 56 days between the first clutch and the second clutch.
The main diet consisted of various fruits, with banana and papaya
being particular favourites. Versele Laga pelleted hill mynah diet soaked
in fruit juices was readily taken by the parents and was also fed to the
young. They were also given a high quality dry insect food that is mixed
with small quantities of ground (minced) beef heart, the meat of day-old
chicks and finely grated carrot. Livefood consists primarily of white-
skinned mealworms that are still soft and easily digestible. Water seems
to be particularly important, as they are frequently observed drinking and
bathing, often on wet leaves.
The most recent edition of the Foreign Bird Federation Breeding Register
of Birds Bred in the UK under Controlled Conditions, covering the period
2005-2008, lists five of these tanagers as having been bred in the UK in
2005, one in 2006, five in 2007 and three in 2008 -Ed.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.988213" page_id="56261297"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
78
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.414583" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261297" page_num="78" year="" vol="">
THE WHITE-NAPED CRANE Gms vipio
by Derek Gibson
Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9881128" page_id="56261297"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
While maybe not as striking as the Red-crowned Crane G.japonensis and
lacking the flamboyance of the Black and Grey Crowned Cranes Balearica
pavonina and B. regulorum respectively, and though not continuously
drawing attention to itself by its loud raucous calls, the White-naped Crane
is nonetheless a fascinating gem of a bird. It stands 120cm-130cm (approx.
3ft 11 in-4ft 3 in) tall and has red facial skin, surrounding an intensely orange
eye, and white feathering on the back of the neck extending up onto the
crown; the face and foreneck are black. The overall body plumage is subtle
shades of grey and the wing colour ranges from white to dark grey. The
red legs flush with colour when the bird is in breeding condition. Males
tend to be slightly larger than females. As with other species of crane, the
White-naped is omnivorous, feeding on small insects, seeds, roots and all
manner of wetland plants.
Distribution
It frequents cultivated fields of rice, marshes and estuaries, as well as
lowland steppes and mixed forest steppe areas (Meine &amp; Archibald, 1996).
Its breeding grounds are in Mongolia, north-east China and areas of south-
east Russia and its wintering grounds are in North and South Korea, eastern
Siberia, eastern China and southern Japan. The population numbers some
4,900-5,300 individuals. In common with other species, it has suffered as
a result of habitat destruction and the encroachment of civilization. The
Second World War and the Korean War in particular, damaged many of its
stopover points and wintering areas.
Together with other habitat changes, for instance changes in agricultural
practices, there is illegal shooting, which occurred on at least seven occasions
in the spring of2005 in the Spassky District of eastern Siberia (von Treunfels,
2006), which makes the fact that the White-naped Crane is protected by
law a bit of a sham. All have contributed to the decline of the population
throughout its range. The White-naped Crane faces additional threats on
its wintering grounds. The wintering populations of White-naped and
Hooded Cranes G. monachus are highly concentrated, increasing the risk
of an outbreak of disease (Meine &amp; Archibald, 1996). The artificial feeding
area at Izumi, Japan and the 103,000 hectares (approx. 255,000 acres)
Dagurian Nature Reserve on the Uldza River in the Mongolian province
of Domod (part of the Mongolian-Chinese nature sanctuary that is home to
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.593233" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261298" page_num="79" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-NAPED CRANE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997611" page_id="56261298"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
79
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.974106076923077" page_id="56261298"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
the largest colony of White-naped Cranes) offers some protection, as does
the Khinganski Nature Reserve in Russia, where chicks are raised from
eggs provided by American zoos, to help bolster the population (Wikipedia,
2008). The White-naped Crane is classified as Vulnerable by the IUCN and
is on CITES Appendix 1.
Housing
Exmoor Zoo has had White-naped Cranes since 2001, when a breeding
pair was received from The Tropical Bird Gardens, Rode, which has now
closed. Both the male and female are pinioned and were considered to be
adults when they arrived. They were placed in a paddock-style enclosure
measuring approximately 35m x 18m (115ft x 60ft) which is enclosed by
a 2.5m (approx. 8ft) high perimeter fence. A house/shelter is positioned
at the top of the enclosure by the keeper's main gate, so that feeding and
watering can be carried out with the minimum of disturbance to the birds.
The house/shelter provides the cranes with protection against the more
unpleasant weather that occasionally engulfs North Devon. A freshwater
stream runs lengthways through the enclosure, the bottom half of which is
very wet and has many all-year-round naturally-occurring pools. The grass
is left uncut and the native plant species are allowed to grow unhindered.
These include Cow Parsley Anthriscus sylvestris , Flag Iris Irispseudacorus.
Stinging Nettle Urtica dioica. White Clover Trifolium repens , Red Clover
T. pratense , Sow-thistle Silybum sp., Greater Plantain Plantago lanceolata
and DeviTs-bit Scabious Succisa pratensis. In the top half of the enclosure
the grass is shorter (the lawnmower is dusted off twice a year just before
and just after the breeding season) and it is planted with various plants and
there is a wonderful Tree-of-Heaven Ailanthus altissima.
Diet
The adult birds are fed twice a day, at 9.00am and 3.30pm (15.30hrs).
The first feed consists of400g of mixed com, 400g of waterfowl maintenance
pellets, two slices of wholemeal bread that has been cmmbled and four
day-old chicks dusted with a vitamin supplement. Once a week 400g of
oystershell grit is added to the food. At the second feed each bird gets a
chick and a fish and the morning feed tray is removed to discourage vermin.
Twice a year, in March and October, the birds are routinely wormed. We
use Panacur 2.5% oral suspension.
The cranes spend a large part of each day probing with their bills into
the soft earth and into the flowering heads of various plants. Exmoor Zoo
is blessed with a seasonal abundance of a wide variety of invertebrates,
which coincide with the crane's rearing season. These include crane fly
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.648762" page_id="56261299"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
80
</page>
<figure confidence="0.830187125" page_id="56261299"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-NAPED CRANE
Derek Gibson
Adult at nest with two eggs.
Tipulidae sp., May Bug or Cockchafer Melolontha melolontha , Common
Green Grasshopper Omocestus viridulus, thousands of Arachnids and over
80 species of moths, all of which feed and breed in the zoo's paddocks, as
do numerous other species of Lepidoptera (Devon Moth Group, 2006).
Breeding
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.9874385" page_id="56261299"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
It seems that the White-naped Crane was first bred in the UK at Woburn
Park in 1908 (Coles, 1986). The first sign of a potentially good breeding
season, is when the birds begin to call in unison. The female seems to initiate
the display and utters two calls for each of the male's calls, with the male
always lifting his wings up over his back and the female keeping her wings
folded at her side (Johnsgard, 1983). Again, as with other cranes, the White-
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.593113" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261300" page_num="81" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-NAPED CRANE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998056" page_id="56261300"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
81
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.969070352941176" page_id="56261300"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
Three day old chick.
naped engages in complex dance displays, which consist of synchronized
dips, bows, head swings, wing spreading, leaps and flaps. Bits of grass and
twigs and even sods of earth are picked up and tossed into the air. They
certainly seem to enjoy themselves.
Our first egg was laid on February 23rd 2002, but unfortunately proved
to be clear. We had to wait until May 31 st 2003 before our first chick was
hatched, which unfortunately succumbed after only one day (see below).
Our breeding record is as follows:
2003 One chick being reared by the parents failed to survive. It was
found dead in the enclosure and is thought to have died due to one or
both parents having been inexperienced and having failed to care for it
correctly.
2004 Two young hand-reared and one parent-reared.
2005 No young.
2006 Three hand-reared, one of which did not survive, due to a
protruding yolk sac.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995612" page_id="56261301"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
82
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.906903" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261301" page_num="82" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-NAPED CRANE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9935728" page_id="56261301"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
2007 Five were hand-reared but the one being raised by the parents
died due to heatstroke.
2008 Two hand-reared.
2009 Three chicks were hatched and reared.
We make every effort to let the parents rear their young. However,
being a zoo situated in the countryside, we have a major problem in that
we attract a number of unwelcome nocturnal guests. In 2008, we lost our
female, who was killed on the nest and the two eggs rolled away, when
she was almost certainly, we believe, attacked by a very aggressive Stoat
Mustela erminea.
When the first chick begins to hatch, the second egg is removed and
artificially incubated and the chick is hand-reared, leaving both parents to
care for just a single chick. The dedication of both the male and female to
the chick is an amazing sight to behold. It is constantly fed insects and we
have witnessed the parents with the chick in between them, first being fed by
one parent and then the other. Not surprisingly, parent-reared young seem
to grow at an amazing rate. Again, both parents seem to be in continual
contact with the young crane. A series of low frequency rumbles are emitted
and, if the young one disappears in the long grass, much louder whistles are
emitted. Of course, when danger threatens, both parents mantle and begin
to shout and call, and will even rush at the intruder, standing as tall as they
can and with their wings out, indicating that the intruder's presence is not
welcome.
Over the years various species have shared the enclosure with the
White-naped Cranes. These have included Australian Shelduck Tadorna
tadornoides , Cape Barren or Cereopsis Geese Cereopsis novaehollandiae ,
Bar-headed Geese Anser indicus and Parma Wallaby Macropusparma. Apart
from the male Cape Barren or Cereopsis Goose, a bird far too aggressive
for his own good, none of the others interfered with the cranes. At four to
five months of age, the young White-naped Cranes are placed together in
a communal crane enclosure measuring 35m x 26m (approx. 115ft x 85ft)
with a netting roof, which at its highest point is 5m (approx. 16ft) high.
Housed with them in the enclosure have been European G. grus , Demoiselle
Anthropoides virgo, Saras G. antigone and East African Grey Crowned
Cranes. The birds are of assorted ages and are both male and female. The
young cranes are always placed in the enclosure in twos, in order to avoid
out-and-out aggression. All have, to date, mixed together with little or no
trouble. Within a few days it is apparent that they know which species they
belong to, and birds of the same species stick together. An exception was a
young male (DNA sexed) White-naped Crane, which would not be tolerated
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.59303" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261302" page_num="83" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-NAPED CRANE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998863" page_id="56261302"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
83
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.980247789473684" page_id="56261302"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
by either of the other two young White-naped Cranes, one of which was his
sibling, or by any of the other young cranes.
Nesting
Observations of White-naped Crane nests in the wild, indicate that they
are flat structures made of dry grass and situated on an elevation amongst
reeds or marsh (Soothill &amp; Soothill, 1982). Both the male and female
incubate the eggs. Here at Exmoor Zoo, the cranes nest either on an elevated
small island in the middle of the pond or at the edge of it. Again, as in the
wild, the nest is made from various reeds and grasses and, again, as in the
wild, incubation duties are shared by the male and female. Interestingly,
the pair never re-use an old nest site.
Incubation
A clutch of two eggs is laid each season and, of course, if the eggs are
removed, the female will lay again. Nine is the most eggs laid in a season by
a female here at Exmoor Zoo. Eggs that are taken to be artificially incubated
are carefully measured. The average measurement is 88.61mm x 60.35mm.
They are mottled brown on a cream base. Any dirt is removed with a moist
cloth and the eggs are then placed in an incubator set at 37.5*C (99.5*F) and
50%-55% relative humidity.
The eggs are candled at 10 days to determine that they are fertile and
not again until the external pipping has begun. They are then transferred to
a hatcher set at 37.2*C (99*F) and as high a humidity as possible. If an egg
takes longer than 48 hours to hatch, following the initial pip, we intervene.
Luckily this has happened only once and, in that particular case, roughly
2cm ( 3 / 4 in) of shell around the pip was gently removed and the membrane
was moistened. Cheeping and purring sounds were made by the keeper and
the chick responded and, luckily, hatched successfully.
Chick management
Upon hatching the chicks are weighed and then transferred to a brooder
set at 32*C (89.6*F). The humidity is kept as low as possible to allow the
chicks to dry out and recover from the stresses of hatching. All of the White-
naped Crane chicks have, with one exception, hatched between 7.00am-
9.00am. The exception was the chick that had to be helped from the egg.
When chicks need to be pinioned, it is done within the first 24 hours and
it is very important that they are kept calm. After they have been pinioned
they are placed back in the quiet of the brooder.
The chicks spend the first 24 hours in the brooder. No food is given to
them during this time, thus letting them absorb the yolk sac. Boiled water that
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.920379" page_id="56261303"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
84
</page>
<figure confidence="0.466939" page_id="56261303"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-NAPED CRANE
Derek Gibson
Juvenile White-naped Cranes aged between six and seven months.
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.7738008">
has been allowed to cool, with a water soluble probiotic added, is offered at
regular intervals. The floor of the brooder is covered with a non-slip rubber
material, so that the chicks can get a good foothold and this helps prevent
problems with splayed legs. A small, cuddly toy, is given to act a 'mum'
which they can cuddle-up to.
</figureCaption>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.587334" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261304" page_num="85" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-NAPED CRANE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.985089" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
85
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.995981">
Fig. 1. Frequency of egg laying according to season.
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.982802545454545" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
White-naped Crane eggs laid
No. of Eggs
\0x25A02002
13 2004
02005
\0x25A02006
\0x25A02009
I
Jan Feb Mo
ir Apr May Jun Jul Aug Sep Oct Nov Dec
Month
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.814958">
Fig. 2. Weight gains in grams over the first 14 days.
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.8366516" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10
</figure>
<page confidence="0.8509775" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
11
12
13
14
</page>
<note confidence="0.32621">
Cree 2004
</note>
<page confidence="0.950334571428571" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
116
113
109
114
120
129
138
144
163
197
229
257
264
278
</page>
<table confidence="0.266111" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
Pawnee 2004
</table>
<page confidence="0.984348785714286" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
119
109
115
127
136
152
168
184
196
222
237
249
263
279
</page>
<figure confidence="0.276635" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
Apache 2006
</figure>
<page confidence="0.936316769230769" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
116
112
110
117
122
136
145
149
171
209
221
237
257
</page>
<figure confidence="0.705065" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
270
Crow 2006
</figure>
<page confidence="0.951872071428571" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
115
105
117
124
130
151
172
196
223
242
275
292
319
347
</page>
<figure confidence="0.354971" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
Shawnee 2006
</figure>
<page confidence="0.933902333333333" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
129
108
105
</page>
<figure confidence="0.43774625" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
120
113
Abenaki 2007
129
</figure>
<page confidence="0.7832798" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
108
115
121
128
135
144
151
161
177
186
</page>
<figure confidence="0.847141" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
200
211
232
Sauk 2007
126
110
</figure>
<page confidence="0.753706416666667" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
119
127
136
141
149
157
166
181
199
217
229
241
</page>
<figure confidence="0.606809333333333" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
Ioway 2007
131
121
</figure>
<page confidence="0.798947090909091" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
125
132
139
149
155
162
170
179
188
198
215
</page>
<figure confidence="0.8417995" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
230
Beothuk 2007
</figure>
<page confidence="0.871600857142857" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
129
112
115
126
133
141
156
</page>
<figure confidence="0.6643065" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
160
170
</figure>
<page confidence="0.7275474" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
181
201
213
229
242
</page>
<figure confidence="0.8456055" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
Choctaw 2007
127
117
120
</figure>
<page confidence="0.845635090909091" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
129
141
152
166
183
189
222
240
256
260
273
</page>
<note confidence="0.41004">
Navajo 2008
</note>
<page confidence="0.921443071428571" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
126
112
112
119
127
138
153
169
193
219
250
281
314
336
</page>
<figure confidence="0.4018855" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
Beaver 2008
110
</figure>
<page confidence="0.648930666666667" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
98
96
110
119
132
148
</page>
<figure confidence="0.745286394736842" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
160
180
199
210
224
243
269
23 May 2009
no
99
95
104
117
130
140
160
171
194
220
241
274
281
23 June 2009
110
97
97
100
111
123
143
169
178
190
221
235
276
310
25 June 2009
</figure>
<page confidence="0.649292142857143" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
117
109
99
108
121
129
134
</page>
<figure confidence="0.8199392" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
150
171
187
200
212
</figure>
<page confidence="0.862322" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
239
259
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999568909090909" page_id="56261304"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
The chicks are weighed the following morning and on average have lost
10g-12g. When handling the chicks, we place their body in the palm of
our hand and place the other hand gently over the chick's back; the legs are
held between the fingers to afford an added degree of control. This method
is used each day when we weigh the chicks during the first 14 days. After
this the chicks are too large to be handled safely in this way and from then
onwards are carried (like adults) under the arm, facing backwards, with the
legs 'folded'.
The young cranes are then moved to the rearing pen, which measures
lm x 0.6m x 0.5m (approx. 3ft Sin x 2ft x 1ft 8in). At one end is a heat
source set at 30*C (86*F). Over the course of the following two weeks the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994047" page_id="56261305"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
86
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.911125" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261305" page_num="86" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-NAPED CRANE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998429487804878" page_id="56261305"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
temperature is lowered gradually until it reaches room temperature. Again,
it is important to have a non-slip floor covering. We use carpet tiles, as we
find these easy to keep clean. A small glass bowl 5cm deep x 8cm wide
(approx. 2in deep x 3 l A in wide) contains water, with a calcium supplement
added to it. We use a glass bowl because the livefood that is dropped into it
is clearly visible to the chick and encourages it to eat and at the same time
take a good gulp of water. Each young crane is given a companion. A day
old Helmeted Guineafowl chick Numida meleagris seems to make a very
good companion. Other birds we have tried, such as domestic chickens
and bantams are, of course, good but a guineafowl chick tends to be as
'bright as a button' and soon begins to eat and drink, thus encouraging the
young crane to do likewise. We have tried keeping two siblings together,
but because of aggression, we have had to intervene and separate them at
as young as three days old.
Food is provided in bowls placed as far apart as possible to encourage the
young cranes to take exercise. They are offered an insectivorous mix and
get crushed and soaked Diet A and chick crumbs. There is also a scattering
of food cast onto the floor. Livefood fed to the young cranes consists of
waxworm larvae Achroia grisella , small crickets Gpyllus assimillis and
mealworms Tenebrio monitor. The livefood, which has first been submerged
in water, is held with tweezers and presented to the chicks. The first feed
tends to consist of just two waxmoth larvae, then throughout the day the
quantity of food is increased gradually and the chicks receive seven to eight
feeds a day with the last feed, using tweezers, happening at 6.00pm-6.30pm
(18.00hrs-18.30hrs). Normally the young cranes get the hang of feeding
themselves quite quickly and, as early as two days old, are picking up food
from the floor, but continue to be fed by tweezers until day 10 when each
chick, along with its companion, is eating sufficient food on its own. The
food bowls are refilled throughout the day and livefood is scattered in
the pens at regular intervals, so that the young cranes have access to food
whenever they require it.
By the end of the first day the chicks are usually able to struggle to their
feet and are beginning to take their first rather hesitant steps. Exercise is so
important: here at Exmoor Zoo the chicks are encouraged to take exercise
by being walked in our children's playground that backs onto the zoo's
Incubation and Rearing Station. When the chicks are walked when the zoo
is open, quite an audience gathers (after all who can resist a young crane?)
and it provides keepers with an ideal opportunity to chat to the public about
cranes - not just the White-naped but also the other six species we keep here
in North Devon. The young cranes seem to enjoy this time out of the rearing
pen and continually probe in the long grass, looking for insects and having
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.59308" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261306" page_num="87" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-NAPED CRANE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998603" page_id="56261306"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
87
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999214352941176" page_id="56261306"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
a good old stretch of their wings.
Legs problems can occur. We have had a couple of problems in the past,
with slight bowing of the leg just below the ankle joint. In 2008 we had a
youngster with this very problem. He was just as mobile as the female and
did not seem to be unduly hampered by it. It was only noticeable when he
walked towards us head-on.
A useful recent addition to our crane rearing facility is a small elevated
pool which provides us with another means of exercising our young cranes.
It measures 117cm x 60cm (approx. 3ft lOin x 2ft) and when filled with
water, the maximum depth is 22cm (approx. 8 Van) and the minimum depth
is 10cm (approx. 4in).
Young cranes grow extremely quickly and by the time they are three
weeks old have outgrown the first of the rearing pens. They are then moved
to larger pens measuring approximately 180cm x 70cm (6ft x 2ft 3in). They
remain in these until they are eight to 10 weeks old, at which time they are
moved to larger enclosures and remain in these until they are ready to be
housed with other young cranes in our communal crane enclosure.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909347" genericHeader="references" page_id="56261306" page_num="87" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.893159">
Coles, D. 1986. First Breeding Records for Birds Reared to Independence under Controlled
Conditions in the United Kingdom. Published by the author. Website:www.dcbooks.co.uk
Johnsgard, R A. 1991. Crane Music. University of Nebraska Press.
Meine, C. D. and Archibald, G. W. (eds.) 1996. The Cranes: Status survey and conservation
action plan. IUCN, Gland, Switzerland and Cambridge, UK.
von Treunfels, C-A. 2006. The Magic of Cranes. Abrams, New York.
Derek Gibson, Head Keeper, Exmoor Zoo, South Stowford, Bratton
Fleming, Barnstaple, North Devon EX3J 4SG, UK. E-mail:Exmoorzoo@
btconnect.com &amp; Derek.r.gibson@btinternet.com
</reference>
<page confidence="0.997366" page_id="56261307"  page_num="88" year="" vol="">
88
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9765094" genericHeader="method" page_id="56261307" page_num="88" year="" vol="">
GREY PARROT REPORT II
SOME CONSERVATION ASPECTS CONCERNING
THE AFRICAN GREY PARROT Psittacus erithacus IN
KAKAMEGA FOREST, KENYA: ASSESSMENT OF THE
EFFECTS OF TRADE AND HABITAT DESTRUCTION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.967712709677419" page_id="56261307"  page_num="88" year="" vol="">
by Ireene Madindou and Ronald Mulwa
Summary
The main focus of the second part of this project 1 was to assess the
involvement, attitudes and awareness of the local community concerning
the trade in Grey Parrots, as well as developing a monitoring protocol for
Grey Parrot population trends and habitat quality.
Market surveys were conducted in the communities living in the border
town of Busia and its environs. A questionaire was distributed informally so
as not to arouse suspicions. An illustration of the Grey Parrot taken from a
field guide was shown to those who were interviewed. Government officials
at the Kenya-Uganda border were also interviewed, as well as bicycle and
taxi operators and brokers. Extensive surveys were conducted of preferred
Grey Parrot habitat in Kakamega Forest during the course of searching for
the birds. The habitat surrounding the sites visited was surveyed to document
any disturbance caused by human activities.
Introduction
The African Grey Parrot occurs in Kakamega Forest, Kenya and is
among 30 bird species that are confined (in Kenya) to this forest. Kakamega
Forest is a mid-altitude tropical rainforest, the easternmost outlier of the
Congo Basin forests. Kakamega's avifauna is unique not only nationally,
but continentally. It is a complex and fragmented forest, one that has been
under resource utilization pressure, from inside and outside, for many years.
Continuing forest fragmentation and destruction appear to have taken their
toll on the avifauna (Bennun &amp; Njoroge, 1999) and this has affected one of
the world's most traded birds, the Grey Parrot.
Based on the most recent assessment (in 1994) by BirdLife International
of globally threatened parrots, 86 (26%) of the 332 Psittacidae in the world
are at risk of extinction, with a further 36 Near Threatened. It is a proportion
unmatched in any other large family of birds and testifies to the vulnerability
of parrots both in environmental terms and as an economic resource. The
birds suffer from the combination of habitat destruction (www.birdlife.org.ke)
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.6718395">
1 Copies of the first report are available from Steph Tyler. E-mail:
conservation@africanbirdclub.org
</footnote>
<equation confidence="0.285989" page_id="56261308"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
MADINDOU &amp; MULWA - GREY PARROT REPORT II
</equation>
<page confidence="0.995042" page_id="56261308"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
89
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999523315789474" page_id="56261308"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
and trapping for trade, which are responsible for the exceptionally high
number of threatened members of the family (del Hoyo et al. 1997).
The Grey Parrot has been heavily traded: from 1994-2003 over 359,000
wild-caught individuals were reportedly exported from range states. It is
one of the most popular avian pets in Europe, the USA and the Middle
East, due to its longevity and unparalleled ability to mimic human speech
and other sounds. Demand for wild birds is also increasing in China and,
the increased presence of Chinese businesses in central Africa (particularly
in mining, oil and logging), may increase the illegal export of this species.
Whilst there has been some domestic demand within range states, the main
impact seems to be due to international trade, probably owing to the high
value of this species. Habitat loss is also thought to be having a significant
impact throughout West and East Africa. Proposed conservation measures
include the monitoring of wild populations, ascertaining the extent of trade
and thus implementing appropriate trade restrictions (www.birdlife.org.ke).
The main objectives of this study were to develop a monitoring protocol
for Grey Parrot population trends, habitat quality and trade activities and to
assess the involvement, attitude and awareness among the local community
concerning the trade in Grey Parrots.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.514247">
Objectives
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.933443" page_id="56261308"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
The main focuses of the second part of this project were:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.943625428571429" page_id="56261308"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
1. To assess the involvement, attitudes and awareness among the local
community concerning the trade in Grey Parrots.
2. To assess the status of rescued pet Grey Parrots in Kenya.
3. To survey populations of the Grey Parrot and identify existing pockets
of suitable habitat in Kakamega Forest.
4. To develop a monitoring protocol for Grey Parrot population trends
and habitat quality.
</listItem>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.835825">
Methodology
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.973943181818182" page_id="56261308"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
Informal questionaires were distributed among members of the
communities living in the border town of Busia and its environs. Interviewees
included former trappers of lovebirds Agapornis sp. and quail Coturnix
sp., members of the local site support group, retired civil servants and
immigration officials at the Kenya-Uganda border, as well as bicycle and
taxi operators and brokers. The illustration of the Grey Parrot from Birds of
Kenya and Northern Tanzania (Zimmermann et al. 1996) was used to help
repondents recognise the Grey Parrot.
Status of rescued Grey Parrots
Essentially our visit to the Kenya Society for the Protection and Care of
Animals (KSPCA) was to establish how the parrots came to be in its care and
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.990126" page_id="56261309"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
90
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.96453925" page_id="56261309"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
MADINDOU &amp; MULWA - GREY PARROT REPORT II
to consult the staff on the best ways to rehabilitate the parrots and habituate
them back into their original environment - the forest.
Field surveys
Extensive field surveys were conducted in search of Grey Parrots in
their preferred habitats and at sites where they had been sighted earlier.
These were the Agrocarpus fraxinifolia plantation behind the Rondo Retreat
Centre, Liranda Hill and by the Shitiya River. The particular tree species
preferred by the parrots were scanned for their presence and whenever they
were sighted their activities were recorded. On December 25th 2007 the
team camped near the Yala River in order to ascertain the roosting place of
the Grey Parrots. As parrots must drink water at least once a day (Collar et
al. 1997) attention was focused on the Shitiya and Yala Rivers. The status
of the habitat and levels of disturbance at spots where parrots were sighted
was documented based on the detailed monitoring form and photographs
were taken.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.49594">
Monitoring
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9987488" page_id="56261309"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
The monitoring of the Grey Parrot will be incorporated into an already
ongoing detailed monitoring of birds and habitat at Kakamega Forest IBA
(Important Bird Area). This scheme is being implemented by the Site Support
Group (KEEP), which will incorporate protocols for monitoring the Grey
Parrot along the same and additional transects and seasons.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.961992">
Results
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999000833333333" page_id="56261309"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
Bird trappers confirmed that during the 1970s and 1980s, they used to
trap birds to sell to customers mainly of Asian origin. They trapped mostly
lovebirds and the Brown Parrot Poicephalus meyeri. They also used to trap
Common Quail C. coturnix for food and to sell to other members of the
community. This, however, no longer occurs, as they claim that changes in
weather patterns have caused a downward trend in the number of Common
Quail. They reported that they had never trapped the Grey Parrot.
Members of the local community who have crossed the Kenya-Uganda
border several times, attested to the fact that illegal crossing points exist
that are seldom patrolled by customs officials. At these points, goods are
smuggled across the border and may even pass through inspection units
undetected. They did not commit themselves as to whether birds are ever
smuggled across the border. They were though quite knowledgeable about
members of the parrot family found in Western Kenya. The Red-headed
Lovebird A. pullarius and Brown Parrot are quite abundant in patches of
forest and wooded farmland around the border town of Busia, and are not
shy. Older members of the community confirmed that the Grey Parrot was
abundant several years ago and attributed its decline to changes which may
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.28624" page_id="56261310"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
MADINDOU &amp; MULWA - GREY PARROT REPORT II
</equation>
<page confidence="0.994281" page_id="56261310"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
91
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.996003481481481" page_id="56261310"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
have led to the destruction of its preferred habitat and the species of trees
in which it fed.
The research team met with the local administration police, who
confirmed that birds are trapped and are sold in the local market. They had,
however, never seen Grey Parrots offered for sale. Customs officials reported
that they only inspect vehicles crossing the border to ensure that passengers
have the correct documents and the relevant taxes have been paid. They do
not carry out rigorous inspections because they would not suspect anyone
would try to smuggle animals or plants across the border. They believe this
only happens at airports. Immigration officials at the border said they lack
sufficient knowledge not just of birds, but also of other animals and plants
as well. Customs officials appreciated the information we provided them
with and promised to pay more attention to passenger's luggage and be on
the look-out for the possible illegal trafficking of birds and other animals.
Field surveys
The Grey Parrot's preferred tree species were recorded, as well as the
parrot's activities. The habitat around these spots was also assessed. At the
plantation behind the Rondo Retreat Centre, four Grey Parrots were seen
flying in from the direction of the Yala River. They settled on 30m (approx.
98ft) high Agrocarpus flaxinifolia which were flowering and were observed
licking the nectar and were making whistling and squeaking sounds. There
was a lot of deadwood in the plantation, but not much human activity or
disturbance was observed. After camping at the Yala River on December
25th 2007, early the following morning we saw five Grey Parrots flying from
the tall trees across the swollen Yala River and heading towards Liranda Hill.
Human activities leading to the deterioration of Grey Parrot habitat were
documented and photographed.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.6397715">
Monitoring
Kakamega Environmental Education Programme (KEEP) members
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.992860727272727" page_id="56261310"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
have incorporated monitoring of the Grey Parrot alongside other globally
threatened species they look out for in Kakamega Forest (e.g. Chapin's
Flycatcher Muscicapa lendu and Turner's Eremomela Eremomela turneri )
during their biannual detailed IBA monitoring of species and habitat.
During KEEP'S dry season monitoring in February 2008, members failed
to spot any Grey Parrots. Monitoring will continue to be carried out twice
a year but in future more sites will be monitored. Data collected during the
current study has been included in the monitoring database for Kakamega
and forms the initial baseline information on the probable population status
of the Grey Parrot in this forest, against which future census results will be
able to be compared.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.985156" page_id="56261311"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
92
</page>
<note confidence="0.230214">
MADINDOU &amp; MULWA - GREY PARROT REPORT II
</note>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.718674">
Discussion
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99929735" page_id="56261311"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
The fact that the Grey Parrots occur in a group in which the number of
individuals varies has raised a number of questions. For instance, during the
first phase, three birds were seen on one day and two the following day at
the same location (Rondo Retreat Centre Road into the forest). During the
second phase of the project a group of seven parrots was seen in December
2007 at Rondo Retreat, but in March 2008 there were only four birds in the
group. This could mean that the group of seven seen in December 2007 had
later split into smaller groups of four and three birds, due possibly to a change
in food abundance or as a result of breeding activity. Or could the seven
have been just a loose association of two different families? Apart from the
single plantation of Agrocarpus flaxinifolia at Rondo Retreat Centre, none
of the other sites sampled has a similar monoculture that has been recorded
as a preferred site for the Grey Parrot. Other areas where the birds were
recorded, included sites with particular species such as Maesopsis eminii or
Ficus sur , but only when they were fruiting.
Because of the distances the parrots covered it was impossible to
accurately determine their home range. The food trees were scattered and
the birds had to fly all over the forest, stopping at suitable foraging locations
and watering points. Nectar-feeding demands wide-ranging behaviour, as
the flowering times of the trees varies and the birds have to move around a
good deal in search of new sources of food (Collar et al. 1997).
The habitat at sites sampled was noted as satisfactory - in size at least.
Apart from the Agrocarpus plantation at the retreat centre, other sites
exhibited signs of disturbance. Hence places where the Grey Parrot was
seen regularly in the past are now devoid of the species due to logging and
especially the removal of the huge tall trees, in which it prefers to roost.
The vegetation on Liranda Hill was only just recovering from forest fires
in late 2007 that consumed virtually everything. The site is visited mainly
by thatching grass collectors, who may have started the fires accidently
while preparing meals. The fires burnt key fruit-bearing tree species, such as
Maesa lanceolata , Alhizia gumifera and Syzygium spp., known to be visited
by feeding Grey Parrots. Charcoal kilns at various stages of production
were seen. Thin smoke indicates a freshly-lit kiln while thick smoke with
particles of dust in it is a sign that a kiln is being dismantled. Six smoking
sites were counted in the proximity of approximately 1km (0.6 miles). Such
disturbances can make these sensitive birds fly further in search of food.
It was quite apparent that immigration officials at the border lacked
adequate information concerning the the trade in wild birds and the passage
of animals to and fro across the border, and who were the dealers. The
local community knew about the trapping and selling of birds. This, they
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.285292" page_id="56261312"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
MADINDOU &amp; MULWA - GREY PARROT REPORT II
</equation>
<page confidence="0.996196" page_id="56261312"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
93
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.991858666666667" page_id="56261312"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
confirmed happens, but said that those involved are extremely careful and
it would not be easy to penetrate cartels during a casual investigation or to
conduct interviews.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.520883">
Rescued Grey Parrots
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99813245945946" page_id="56261312"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
Rehabilitating rescued Grey Parrots at the KSPCA centre takes one-
and-a-half years. Apparently 250 baby parrots (including Grey Parrots)
had been impounded at Nairobi's Jomo Kenyatta International Airport on
dates unclear to KSPCA personnel. They were taken to the KSPCA and
only 18 of the Grey Parrots survived. Fifteen of the 18 died later and only
three of the original group survived. These were taken to aviaries built on
Rubondo Island on Lake Victoria. They too died. Most of them had names
and were either pet birds that had escaped or had been abandoned by their
owners when they moved.
When the ornithology research team visited the KSPCA offices on
August 12th 2007, seven Grey Parrots and a Red-fronted Parrot P. gulielmi
were noted. All of these had different case histories. Pishu, a male, had
flown into Wilson Airport at Langata, and staff had called the KSPCA and
arranged for him to be collected. It was not possible to establish where he
had come from. Kaka, a female, had been abandoned in a house when the
owner left Kenya to go abroad. Neighbours heard the bird's cries and on
investigation found the emaciated looking parrot, which they took to the
KSPCA. Sinbad, a dark male from the Congo, almost grabbed a banana
from the hand of Dr Sophie Walker in Karen (another suburb of Nairobi)
and subsequently followed her home. He had probably escaped. A male,
named David, was found in the Giraffe Centre in Nairobi. The staff confirmed
that there used to be three but two had escaped and only David was found.
Nobody knew how the birds came to the Giraffe Centre. Luka, a female,
was released by her owners who did not want her anymore. Another bird,
named Penny, was released by its owner who was leaving Kenya. It was
taken to the KSPCA after a neighbour noticed the distressed bird perched
for many hours near its former home. Mohammed, a male, had an unclear
history, as did another male named Monsieur, that spoke French. Both had
been found flying around in Nairobi.
Dr Sophie Walker a Veterinary Surgeon who is involved in rehabilitating
various birds and other animals, identified them as caged birds because they
exhibited a number of traits, such as eating sunflower seed, green maize
and bananas. Keeping the birds presents a number of challenges, one of
which is the fact that they appear agitated because of the lack of space in
the small aviary in which they are confined. We concluded that they cannot
be released in the surrounding area because of the absence of the species'
preferred feeding trees and the fact that they have never learned how to
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997564" page_id="56261313"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
94
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.976768619047619" page_id="56261313"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
MADINDOU &amp; MULWA - GREY PARROT REPORT II
search for food for themselves.
Conclusions and recommendations
Further research is needed to establish the size of the Grey Parrot
population in Kakamega Forest. So far only seven birds have been recorded.
Attaching radio transmitters/transponders to the birds would enable more
detailed studies to be made of their movements. There is a need for further
studies of their foraging habits and to ascertain their dietary requirements
and the various different trees they prefer for finding nectar, fruits and in
which to roost. An extensive search for flowering trees may be required
and observations made along streams and in riverine forest. This will need
to be carried out with the help of KEEP.
Our initial data has been included in the monitoring database for
Kakamega and forms the initial baseline information on the possible
population status of the Grey Parrot in this forest. The continued gathering
of data on the number of Grey Parrots over a long period of time will provide
important data on population trends.
The KSPCA centre at Karen is actively involved in the treatment and
rehabilitation of Grey Parrots rescued from various sources, but there is no
suitable habitat close by where the birds can be released on an experimental
basis. Therefore, we recommend the establishment of a pilot rehabilitation
programme for the Grey Parrot within Kakamega Forest, where the birds
can be trained to recognise wild fruits, become independent of humans and
eventually be released in the forest. There will need to be consultations
with relevant custodians such as the Kenya Wildlife Service, Kenya Forest
Service, National Museums of Kenya and Kenya Society for the Protection
and Care of Animals (KSPCA) over matters such as fund raising to finance
the venture which will, hopefully, ensure the continuity of the Grey Parrot
population in the wild in Kenya. The research team and Dr Walker have
begun consultations on plans to raise money for an aviary which could
be built at Isecheno. With proper funding, this could be set-up for the
rehabilitation of the rescued parrots and members of KEEP could be trained
how to handle the birds. Radio telemetry could be used to monitor the
movements of the released birds and ascertain whether or not they bond
with the wild population in Kakamega Forest.
Experts at the KSPCA are concerned that most Grey Parrot owners feed
their birds on sunflower seed which is not good for their health. There is,
they feel, the need to educate parrot owners on the need to provide their
birds with a more suitable diet. Owners could also be offered advice on the
general welfare of their birds.
Our work has created an increased awareness among the local community,
provincial administration and police and customs officials, of the trade in
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.286982" page_id="56261314"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
MADINDOU &amp; MULWA - GREY PARROT REPORT II
</equation>
<page confidence="0.990563" page_id="56261314"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
95
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.986508" page_id="56261314"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
wild birds. Consultations are underway to determine the best way forward
to make various government authorities aware of the wild bird trade and
especially to be on the lookout for species listed in the CITES appendices
for Kenya.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.938511" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56261314" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997273222222222" page_id="56261314"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
We wish to express our sincere gratitude to the African Bird Club for
its financial support and patience, as we strove to complete our research
amidst the political difficulties that there were in Kenya at the time. Many
thanks also to members of KEEP, especially site intern Leonard Muhanga
and Wilberforce Okeka a founder member of KEEP, for their support and
hard work throughout the survey. Members were particularly helpful in
conducting the interviews with the local community and at the Kenya-Uganda
border. We also wish to thank the Ornithology Section of the National
Museums of Kenya for providing field equipment.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.898515" genericHeader="references" page_id="56261314" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.460973642857143" page_id="56261314"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
Berinun, L. A. and Njoroge, P. 1999. Important Bird Areas of Kenya. East Africa Natural
History Society.
BirdLife International. 2007. Species Factsheet: Psittacus erithacus. Downloaded from
http://www.birdlife.org (19/09/2007).
Collar, N. J. 1997. Family Psittacidae (Parrots). In: del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A. and Sargatal, J.
(eds.) Handbook of the Birds of the World Vol.4 (Sandgrouse to Cuckoos). Lynx Edicions,
Barcelona.
del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A. and Sargatal, J. (eds.) 1997. Handbook of the Birds of the WorldVoXA
(Sandgrouse to Cuckoos). Lynx Edicions, Barcelona.
Zimmerman, D. A., Turner, D. A. and Pearson, D. J. 1996. Birds of Kenya and Northern
Tanzania. Russel Friedman, Cape Town.
Ireene Madindou and Ronald Mulwa, Ornithology Section, Zoology
Department, National Museums of Kenya, PO Box 40658-00100, Nairobi,
Kenya.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.286507" page_id="56261314"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.940506" genericHeader="general terms" page_id="56261314" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
HARD TO BELIEVE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.983732444444445" page_id="56261314"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
It is hard to believe that the nominate subspecies of the White-cheeked
Turaco Tauraco 1 leucotis, the most commonly kept and frequently bred
turaco, had not been kept at London Zoo prior to 1963. It was first bred in the
UK the following year. It seems that up until then the southern subspecies,
Donaldson Smith's Turaco T. I donaldsoni, which has the tips of the crest
feathers red instead of dull bluish, was the better known of the two. One
lived in the Bird House at London Zoo from 1945-1963, and before that had
been in Spedan Lewis's collection at Leckford, so was likely to have been
at least 25 years old when it died in 1963.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995223" page_id="56261315"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
96
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.973707" genericHeader="method" page_id="56261315" page_num="96" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
GREATER EMPHASIS ON SOUTH AMERICAN BIRDS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.984743681818182" page_id="56261315"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
The Superb Fruit Dove Ptilinopus superbus and the Black-naped Fruit
Dove P melanospila have been added to the bird collection at Chester Zoo.
Over the next few years, the zoo plans to increase the numbers of some of
its South American species. It has recently acquired a pair of Green Jays
Cyanocorax yncas from Barcelona Zoo in Spain, which will be housed with
the zoo's Red-billed Curassows Crax blumenbachii. Dr Roger Wilkinson, the
zoo's Head of Field Conservation and Research, travelled recently to South
America with Phil McGowan, Director of the World Pheasant Association
(WPA), to plan future support for the ongoing conservation of this threatened
species in the Atlantic rainforest of eastern Brazil.
The zoo has increased the number of hombill projects it supports, one
of which is the Mabula Ground Hombill Project in South Africa, which is
attempting to re-establish the Southern Ground Hombill Bucorvus leadbeateri
in areas where it used to live. It also continues to provide financial and
technical support to the Mauritius Wildlife Foundation (MWF). Mauritius
Olive White-eyes Zosterops chloronothos translocated to the He aux Aigrettes
have bred for the first time and over 140 Echo Parakeet chicks Psittacula
echo fledged in 2008/2009 - a record total. The zoo is also continuing to
support work with the Critically Endangered Blue-crowned Laughingthmsh
Dryonastes courtoisi in China and is supporting a project which plans to
conduct a survey in western Yunnan to try to find a species of laughingthmsh
caught on camera, which is thought to be new to science.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.609812" page_id="56261315"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.775192" genericHeader="method" page_id="56261315" page_num="96" year="" vol="">
FAR FEWER THAN STATED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.979095857142857" page_id="56261315"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
Rosemay Low has written to point out that the Cape Parrot Poicephalus
robustus population numbers only an estimated 1,000-1,500 birds, not
" 1,000-15,000" birds, as stated in News &amp; Views Vol. 116, No. 1, p.48 (2010).
The estimate of up to " 15,000" birds, that I quoted from a report in the Bulletin
of the African Bird Club Vol. 17, No.l, pp.7-8, March 2010, was a error. At
the time I suspected it might be incorrect, but it was not until I received
Rosemary's e-mail, that it became obvious how the error had occurred.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998872" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56261316" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985843" page_id="56261316"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The avicultural society is keen to reduce its large stock of back issue.
These have been sorted by year into complete sets and are being offered for
sale at #10 per set/per year, plus postage at cost.
Complete sets are available for the years:
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.565886" page_id="56261316"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
1928
</page>
<figure confidence="0.987653194805195" page_id="56261316"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
1941
1951
1960
1969
1980
1988
1996
2004
1932
1942
1953
1962
1970
1981
1989
1997
2005
1934
1943
1954
1963
1971
1982
1990
1998
2006
1935
1944
1955
1964
1973
1983
1991
1999
2007
1936
1945
1956
1965
1976
1984
1992
2000
2008
1937
1948
1957
1966
1977
1985
1993
2001
2009
1938
1949
1958
1967
1978
1986
1994
2002
1939
1950
1959
1968
1979
1987
1995
2003
Before sending any money, it is advisable to check that the magazines
you require remain available. To do so, please contact Stewart Pyper, 21
Primrose Hill, Nunney, Nr. Frome, Somerset, BA11 4NP UK. Tel: 01373
836293/E-mail:stewartpyper@yahoo.co.uk
*
* *
SERINUS BREEDERS' GROUP
A Special Interest Group has been formed for those who keep birds of
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.962719909090909" page_id="56261316"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
the genus Serinus. It is called the European Society of Serinus Breeders
(ESSB) and like other Special Interest Groups, aims to put keepers and
breeders of these birds in touch with each other to exchange information and
birds in order to maximise breeding results and help establish self-sustaining
captive-breeding populations of as many species as possible, before it is too
late. It has already established contacts with enthusiasts in the Netherlands,
Belgium, France and Germany and has a database with details of which
species respective members keep and breed. It is keen to establish contacts
with other keepers and breeders in these countries and elsewhere. It invites
fellow enthusiasts to visit its website - www.Serinus-Society.eu - and register
an interest in these species and help ensure that this initiative succeeds.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.577011333333333" page_id="56261317"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
3 9088 01510 0449
CONTENTS
Is the Pin-talled Whydah Vidua macroura a brood-parasite of the
Black-faced Grassquit Tiaris bicolor on Puerto Rico?
by Robin Restall.,.49
Breeding the Moustached Laughingthrush Ianthocincla cineracea
at Waddesdon Manor
by Simon Matthews. 59
The bird collection at Taipei Zoo
by Pierre de Chabannes.63
The successful breeding of the Blue-necked or Azure-headed
Tanager Tangara cyanicollis at Weltvogelpark Walsrode, Germany
by Simon Bruslund Jensen and Kerstin Kirchoffel.74
The White-naped Crane Grus vipio
by Derek Gibson .78
Grey Parrot Report II: Some conservation aspects concerning
the African Grey Parrot Psittacus erithacus in Kakamega Forest,
Kenya: assessment of the effects of trade and habitat destruction
by Ireene Madindou and Ronald Mulwa .88
News &amp; Views ...96
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
</table>
</algorithms>
