<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.799381" page_id="56264355"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
GL,
% 4&amp;1
? ^AVICULTURAL
2001
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990772" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264356" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991765142857143" page_id="56264356"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in freedom and captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2001 as for 2000: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.548818" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264356" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.844479" page_id="56264356"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Subscription, changes of address, orders for back numbers etc. should be
sent to:
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, P.O. BOX 47, EDENBRIDGE, KENT TN8 7WP, ENGLAND.
Enquiries regarding membership should be sent to:
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.88044725" page_id="56264356"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE MEMBERSHIP SECRETARY, Stewart Pyper, 21, Primrose Hill,
Nunney, Frome, Somerset BA11 4NP.
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.996379833333333" page_id="56264356"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998437" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264356" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.9972025">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.760372" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264357" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.279559" page_id="56264357"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 107 - No. 4 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2001
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.374462">
The Avicultural Society
</subsectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.976186666666667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264357" page_num="" year="" vol="">
FOR THE STUDY OF BRITISH AND FOREIGN BIRDS
IN FREEDOM AND CAPTIVITY
OFFICERS AND COUNCIL
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.68020475" page_id="56264357"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
As from October 24th 2001
President
MISS R.M. EZRA
Vice Presidents
</table>
<construct confidence="0.429752" page_id="56264357"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
J. M. DOLAN, Jr., Ph.D. (USA) The Rev. R. NOEGEL (USA)
K. W. DOLTON (Britain) Dr. H. QUINQUE (France)
Prof. J.R. HODGES (Britain) R.C.J. SAWYER (Britain)
</construct>
<figure confidence="0.9583386875" page_id="56264357"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
C.J.S. MARLER (Britain)
Honorary Editor
M. ELLIS
Honorary Secretary - Treasurer
L. GARDINER
Members of Council
M. CURZON
J.A. ELLIS
MRS. L. GARDNER
R.H. GRANTHAM
N. HEWSTON
MRS. D. HOLLOWAY
R. E. OXLEY
S. PYPER
P. SCHOFIELD
J. TROLLOPE
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.704312">
Dr. R. WILKINSON
MRS. R. WISEMAN
Chairman C.J.S. MARLER
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999483" page_id="56264358"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
146
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7180855" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264358" page_num="146" year="" vol="">
BLUE-EYED COCKATOOS IN NEW BRITAIN
by Roger Wilkinson
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994764157894737" page_id="56264358"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
Chester Zoo has held Blue-eyed Cockatoos Cacatua ophthalmica since
1966 when five that had been collected on New Britain were received at
Chester together with a larger consignment of birds from Papua New Guinea.
Since then Chester Zoo has successfully reared 40 youngsters and established
an international reputation as a breeding centre for the Blue-eyed Cockatoo.
Chester Zoo holds the European Studbook for the Blue-eyed Cockatoo and
effectively co-ordinates the European zoo population. Young from Chester
have been sent on loan to nine other collections and form the core of a co-
ordinated international breeding programme.
The Blue-eyed Cockatoo is endemic to New Britain; it occurs only on
this one island and nowhere else in the world. New Britain is a mountainous
volcanic island and the largest of the group of islands forming the Bismarck
Archipelago situated off the north-east coast of Papua New Guinea.
Exceedingly rare and highly prized in aviculture there has been uncertainty
over its wild status with contradictory reports received from recent visitors
as to its abundance. Other island cockatoo populations have been heavily
impacted by habitat changes and through these parrots being trapped for the
live bird trade. Both Philippine Red-vented Cockatoos C. haematuropygia
and Yellow-crested Cockatoos C. sulphurea are now critically endangered.
The small number in aviculture suggests that trapping for the bird trade has,
to date, not been a serious threat to the Blue-eyed Cockatoo.
Chester Zoo through a generous grant from Brian and Elizabeth
Livingstone was recently able to fund a field study of the Blue-eyed Cockatoo
on New Britain. John Pilgrim under the supervision of Dr Stuart Marsden
from Manchester Metropolitan University worked in New Britain from
December 1998 to April 1999. John was based in East New Britain and
surveyed two areas around Wide Bay, initially around Mu and later in the
Marunga/Masarou area. Blue-eyed Cockatoos were found to be not
uncommon in primary and selectively logged forest but considerably less
common in forest gardens. At one site a group of 40 cockatoos was observed
on one occasion. In the absence of heavy trapping pressure on Blue-eyed
Cockatoos and given their tolerance of selective logging and the current
extent of forest on New Britain it was concluded that the Blue-eyed Cockatoo
is not currently threatened.
Along with a party of birdwatchers from England I was able to make a
short four day visit to West New Britain in mid-August 2001 and offer some
observations made as a result of that visit. During this period we were
based to the west of Hoskins, at Walinde Plantation Resort, north-west of
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.584566" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264359" page_num="147" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - BLUE-EYED COCKATOO
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.981208" page_id="56264359"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
147
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.728988">
Blue-eyed Cockatoo
Roger Wilkinson
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990166" page_id="56264359"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
Kimbe and on the eastern coast of the Willaumez Peninsula, and mainly
visited areas in the vicinity of Walinde. One day we also travelled some
distance east of Hoskins to the Pokili Wildlife Management Area.
Blue-eyed Cockatoos were not uncommon in what appeared to be
disturbed forest habitat near Kimbe close to the Kulu River. Six birds were
seen there in the late afternoon on August 18th. On the following evening,
August 19th, at Kilu Ridge, again in what appeared to be disturbed forest,
our birdwatching group had at least twenty sightings of single or small groups
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998909" page_id="56264360"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
148
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.847299" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264360" page_num="148" year="" vol="">
WILKINSON - BLUE-EYED COCKATOO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.980433" page_id="56264360"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
of Blue-eyed Cockatoos. It was estimated these sightings represented at
least 15 different individual birds.
One tree held a group of nine birds in a pre-roost gathering. These made
themselves conspicuous by their calls and displays. Their displays were
similar to those I had previously observed in birds at Chester Zoo in that the
crest feathers were raised to expose the bright yellow feathers below. One
displaying bird, whilst perched in this tree, repeatedly rotated forwards on
its branch, bowing as it did this. Additionally, whilst standing upright and
raising its crest feathers it simultaneously extended its wings laterally and
stretched these fully open so exposing the bright yellow under-wings.
On a subsequent evening at the same site on Kilu Ridge, I saw at least 10
Blue-eyed Cockatoos. Again several gathered together in a tree and display
was observed. One bird repeatedly fell backwards clinging to its perch to
momentarily hang upside down before swinging back to an upright position.
Display was also seen to involve not only raising the crest feathers but at the
same time also spreading and extending forwards the cheek feathers to greatly
increase the apparent size of the head.
Six Blue-eyed Cockatoos were seen on August 20th at Pokili Wildlife
Management Area in an area of undisturbed forest and on August 21st three
were seen in selectively logged forest at Garu Wildlife Management Area.
In both cases the reduced visibility of cockatoos in denser and taller forests
in these areas may have resulted in relatively fewer sightings there than in
the more disturbed areas previously visited.
No Blue-eyed Cockatoos were seen during our journeys through oil palm
plantations. West New Britain is Papua New Guinea's biggest timber and
palm oil exporter. Palm oil plantations represent a major source of income
and a poster in Port Moresby airport placed by Pacific Rim Plantations
indicated that palm oil is Papua New Guinea's fastest growing agricultural
success story. It may be predicted that the amount of forest cleared for
planting may be expected to expand in the near future. The long term viability
of Blue-eyed Cockatoo populations in the wild will depend on New Britain
retaining both sufficiently large areas of forest and ensuring that the present
low level of trapping of these birds does not escalate.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.987287" genericHeader="references" page_id="56264360" page_num="148" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.9987905">
Lipscomb, A., Me Kinnon, R. and Murray, J. 1998. Papua-New Guinea , 6th edn. Lonely Planet
Publications, Hawthorn, Australia.
Marsden, S.J., Pilgrim, J.D. and Wilkinson, R. 2001. Status, abundance and habitat use of
Blue-eyed Cockatoo Cacatua ophthalmica on New Britain, Papua New Guinea. Bird
Conservation International 11:151-160.
Wilkinson, R., Pilgrim, M., Woolham, A., Morris, PI., Morris, A. and West, B. 2000. Husbandry
and breeding of Blue-eyed Cockatoos Cacatua ophthalmica at Chester Zoo 1966-1998.
International Zoo Yearbook 37:116-125.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.989796" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264361" page_num="149" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE HOUSE CROW Corvus splendens
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.496023" page_id="56264361"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
by R J. Cleeton
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998873" page_id="56264361"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
149
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.995976052631579" page_id="56264361"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
The House Crow as it tends to be called now, rather than the Indian
House Crow, is normally found in Pakistan, India and Sri Lanka, including
the Maidive and Laccadive Islands, Bangladesh and the Himalayan foothills
of Nepal and Bhutan, eastwards through Burma to extreme southern China,
it is a vagrant to extreme southern Afghanistan (Madge and Burn, 1999), In
addition it has been introduced into or found its way to a number of other
countries, mainly on major shipping routes. It recently bred in the
Netherlands and concern has been expressed that it may reach the UK. It Is
larger than the Jackdaw C. monedula but smaller than the Hooded Crow C.
comm. Its call is a rather harsh 'caaa caaa\ similar to that of the Raven C.
corax.
Five House Crows were imported from Africa about six years ago for
the making of a natural history film. When filming was completed the five
crows went to The Tropical Bird Gardens, Rode, in Somerset, where they
were kept together in a group. As the group showed no interest in breeding,
Mike Curzon decided he would keep just a pair. In 1998, he phoned me and
with his typical generosity, offered me the other three, two males and one
female, for my collection.
The trio is housed in an aviary 20ft long x 10ft wide x 7ft high (approx.
6m long x 3m wide x 2.1m high), one of a row of seven flights all of which
are the same size. Housed on one side of the House Crows' aviary is a pair
of Ravens and on the other side is a pair of Yellow billed Hombills Tockus
flavirostris. A half open * fronted nest-box and a platform covered with
leylandii trimmings were provided as possible nest sites.
In the wild this species feeds on small mammals, insects, young birds
and eggs, fruit, a variety of grains, and any scraps it can scavenge. I find
that chopped chicks, minced (ground) meat, dog chow, fruit and mealworms,
etc. seem to keep them in good condition.
In 1999 a nest was built in the nest-box. It was built using a variety of
twigs and grasses, and two chicks were hatched, but died after one week.
Last year they built a large and impressive nest on the platform and laid five
eggs in it. All five hatched and a variety of livefoods and pinky mice were
provided. However, on the morning of the eighth day I went down and
found all of them dead on the floor. This year they built another nest on the
platform and laid four eggs in it, but as they did not seem very keen on
incubating them I decided to put the eggs in an incubator.
Two proved to be clear, one contained a dead chick, and the other hatched.
The chick was fed approximately every two hours from 7,00am to 9.00pm.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996018" page_id="56264362"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
150
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.982232" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264362" page_num="150" year="" vol="">
CLEETON - HOUSE CROW
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.93575775" page_id="56264362"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
One of the breeding pair
Chris Isles
It was fed rat pups to which were added SA37 or ABEDEC vitamin and
mineral supplements. They were diced very fine and kept in water. The
chick was housed in a brooder set at 37*C (98.6*F) until its pin-feathers
came through, after which the temperature was reduced slowly. It was kept
on astro turf, as I find that keeping young birds on this helps prevent them
developing splayed legs.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997557" page_id="56264363"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
151
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.322894">
Chris Isles
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.793351" page_id="56264363"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
Chick at about 10 days old
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.518454">
Chris Isles
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8896412" page_id="56264363"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
Chick and two unhatched eggs
Mike, as the crow has been named, is fully weaned now and he or she
will later be introduced into the group.
Reference
Madge, S. and Bum, H. 1999. Crows and Jays. Paperback Edition, Helm Identification Guides.
Christopher Helm/A. &amp; C. Black, London .
As described above, the House Crow Corvus splendens, has been bred
by P. J. Cleeton. This is probably the first successful breeding of this species
in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who knows of a previous breeding is
asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999157" page_id="56264364"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
152
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7204595" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264364" page_num="152" year="" vol="">
NECKLACED AND OTHER LAUGHING THRUSHES
by Philip Schofield
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995808026315789" page_id="56264364"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
I can not claim to have any great knowledge about laughing thrushes
having owned only three individuals and not yet tried to breed any. However,
a recent observation of predatory behaviour, referred to below, has fired me
to record a few personal notes about the group.
Gruson (1976) listed 44 species of laughing thrushes in the genus
Garrulax. There may though be 45, as Long et al. (1994) suggested that
one of the subspecies of the Yellow-throated Laughing Thrush G. galhanus
might be regarded as a full species. For many years British aviculture was
effectively restricted to two species, the White-crested G. leucolophus and
the White-throated G . albogularis, with others being imported only rarely.
Boosey (1956), a leading importer during the pre- and immediately post-
Second World War years, gave detailed treatment only to the White-crested
with just a passing mention of the White-throated species. Sclater (1879)
listed eight species (three of which were not then included in the genus
Garrulax ) as having been in the London Zoo collection. However, there
were effectively only the White-crested and White-throated Laughing
Thrushes in UK aviculture when I first encountered this group back in the
mid-1960s. This was at the Norfolk Wildlife Park, where they shared a
planted aviary with Black-winged Stilts Himantopus himantopus and Green-
winged Doves Chalcophaps indica. The overriding impression was how
energetic and noisy Garrulax species are as a group in a large enclosure.
About the same time, I remember seeing a single White-crested Laughing
Thrush that shared a small aviary with a Pagoda Starling Temenuchus or
Sturnus pagodarum. Very much a contact animal, the laughing thrush
invariably roosted with a wing spread over the starling, in the absence of a
more appropriatwe partner.
In July 1978,1 saw Streaked Laughing Thrushes G. lineatus in the wild
on several occasions on the Margalla Hills north of Islamabad, Pakistan. I
remember them foraging on or near the ground in secondary scrub (the area
had been overgrazed at one time by domestic livestock and then allowed to
revert to a more natural state following their removal), and being difficult to
keep in view for any length of time.
In 1987, a friend bought two recently imported White-crested Laughing
Thrushes. These appear to have thrived ever since, and show no sign of old
age 14 years later. They have lived on coarse grade commercial softbill
food, along with fruit and mealworms each day. Aviary companions over
the years have included Golden Pheasant Chrysolophus pictus. Silver
Pheasant Lophura nycthemera, Eastern Rosella Platycercus eximius and
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.716634" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264365" page_num="153" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - LAUGHING THRUSHES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999336" page_id="56264365"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
153
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.989978904761905" page_id="56264365"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
Redrump Parrakeet Psephotus haematonotus, all of which have bred
successfully without any friction, although the pheasants were separated
when they had chicks. At one time there was also a group of Senegal Doves
Streptopelia senegalensis, apparently all females, which likewise were not
molested. Latterly a single Nanday Conure Nandayus nenday has also lived
happily with the laughing thrushes. This sort of co-existence requires plenty
of space. In the early days the laughing thrushes lived in an aviary about
20ft x 15ft (approx. 6m x 4.5m); this has now been trebled in size. The
parrakeets have prevented much plant growth, which may explain the lack
of nesting behaviour by the laughing thrushes, which have flourished through
some relatively severe winters with only overhead cover and shelter from
wind and rain. The only indisposition has been an apparent infestation of
gapeworms Syngamus spp., restricted to one of them and quickly cured with
a game bird worming powder. As one would expect, these are a noisy pair
of birds, whose cackling laughter is at its loudest during a summer rainstorm.
With the shift of bird imports from India to China and other countries in
that region, a much wider variety of species has become available. The
Foreign Bird Federation's Breeding Register listed a dozen (12) species as
having been bred in the UK between 1992 and 1995. I acquired my first
laughing thrush at a local bird sale in February 1998. It is a female Greater
Necklaced G. pectoralis whose mate had escaped through the feeder hole of
the parrot cage in which they were being transported. Left with the single
bird, the owner was pleased to get rid of it. Initially its plumage was rough,
and the bird was very nervous. I removed a metal closed ring, which came
off easily, so was not necessarily evidence of captive breeding. I took it off
because it was sufficiently loose fitting to catch on twigs and endanger the
bird. June of that year found my single laughing thrush sharing an aviary
some 9ft (approx. 2.7m) square with a pair of Indian Ring-necked Parrakeets
Psittacula krameri. Despite the latter, there was a substantial Lonicera nitida
bush in which the laughing thrush spent much of her time. As an importer
was offering this species for sale, I ordered a male, having telephoned first
to ensure that they were indeed Greater Necklaced Laughing Thrushes. When
the bird arrived, it looked a bit small, but it was not until its release into the
aviary that I could see that the new bird was a Lesser Necklaced Laughing
Thrush G. monileger. This was confirmed by reference to King et al. (1975),
to which readers are referred for detailed descriptions (p. 310) and
illustrations (pi. 44). G. pectoralis appears to be about one-third larger,
although only lin (2.5cm) more in overall length (13in (33cm) compared to
G. monileger which is 12in (30.5cm) long). The two other most obvious
distinctive features are the striated grey cheek patches of G. pectoralis and
the iris colour (not mentioned by King et al.) which is dark brown, whereas
that of G. monileger is pale orange. In Grimmet et al. (1999) both species
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999702" page_id="56264366"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
154
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.91995" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264366" page_num="154" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - LAUGHING THRUSHES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998440285714286" page_id="56264366"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
are depicted (p.301) with brown eyes. The two birds were instantly
compatible, and roosted pressed together that night. Having contacted the
importer about his misidentification, he let me have a second G. monileger
at a reduced price, and the three appeared to agree together, although I cannot
remember their roosting behaviour as a trio. I hoped they might attempt to
breed, with the single G. pectoralis helping to feed any young produced.
Such a cooperative effort occurred at London Zoo, where a pair of White-
throated helped feed the single youngster of a pair of Black-faced G.
perspicillatus, both before and after it fledged (Yealland, 1965). Some eight
weeks later upon returning from a short holiday, under a bush I discovered
(unnoticed by the somewhat myopic friend who had kindly cared for the
collection in my absence) the decomposed body of the believed female Lesser
Necklaced Laughing Thrush, with no identifiable cause of death. I have
been unable to obtain mates for the two survivors, and they remain a devoted
couple, never more than a short distance apart. The bird that died had paler,
more yellowy eyes than the surviving G. monileger , which could equally be
a sexual, age or even individual difference.
The aviary has been extended to some 30ft (approx. 9m) long, and is
currently shared by a male Grey Peacock Pheasant Polyplectron
bicalcaratum, a group of young Golden Pheasants and a pair of Fulvous
Whistling Ducks Dendrocygna bicolor. The Ring-necked Parrakeets have
been joined by a pair of young Alexandrine Parrakeets P. eupatria and a
Peach-faced Lovebird Agapornis roseicollis. The only aggression shown
by the laughing thrushes to any of these is an occasional dive at the lovebird
by the female G. pectoralis. This appears to be more playful than anything
else, and is never followed through into an attack. The lovebird, a very
assertive individual which has been seen to bluff the Alexandrines away
from food, does not seem upset by these attentions. I would not trust Garrulax
spp. with anything smaller, despite Lindholm's (1989) reference to a single
White-crested living peacefully with Blue-capped Cordon-bleus Uraeginthus
cyanocephalus at Cincinatti Zoo - significantly perhaps, he did not actually
see the latter. A recent addition to my enclosure, awaiting breeding quarters
elsewhere, is a pair of Common Mynahs Acridotheres tristis. The male G.
monileger will set about these if they approach him too closely, but otherwise
they are ignored. Before the Fulvous Whistling Ducks were introduced, a
pair of Mandarin Ducks Aix galericulata nested in this aviary and on several
occasions one or more of their eggs were found out of the nest-box and with
holes pecked in them, presumably by the laughing thrushes.
Five parrot beaks have drastically reduced the plant life in this aviary, so
plenty of leafy branches are supplied, which the parrakeets strip of leaves
and bark while the laughing thrushes and mynahs search them for insects.
There are logs on the aviary floor which I turn over every few days to expose
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.716736" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264367" page_num="155" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - LAUGHING THRUSHES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999329" page_id="56264367"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
155
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997779285714286" page_id="56264367"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
the insect life underneath. The laughing thrushes are invariably on the floor
snapping-up woodlice and similar prey before I have left the aviary, and
spend a lot of time turning over the litter with their beaks searching for
further food items. My laughing thrushes are fed the same diet as that
described above for the pair of White-crested Laughing Thrushes, and seem
to take anything that is offered in the way of fruit and small invertebrates.
Peanuts are relished, and when I run out of softbill food, poultry chick crumbs
have been equally acceptable. My distrust of them with smaller birds, stems
from an incident at 8.30am on August 27th this year, when I noticed an
adult Common Frog Rana temporaria inside the aviary wire and apparently
looking for a way out. I often see the odd frog in the aviary, and had assumed
they always found their own way out again. On my return to the aviary a
few minutes later, the Greater Necklaced Laughing Thrush was on the ground
killing the frog. Repeated blows were directed at its head, between the
eyes. Considerable force was being used, with the bird leaning back before
striking each blow, standing with its legs apart to get maximum impact.
When the frog ceased to move, the bird began tearing off chunks of flesh
and swallowing them. While doing this, the wings were 'shivered' like
those of a fledgling when being fed, an indication of extreme excitement
perhaps (Harrison ( 1967) referring to courtship feeding by a pair of White-
throated Laughing Thrushes, described wing-shivering by the female). The
frog was not held down at first, until the bird appeared to put her left foot on
it accidentally, and found it made it easier to eat it, and then used the foot
more purposely to hold the frog steady while wrenching bits off. When
some pheasants started to show an interest, the laughing thrush took her
prey into the right angle of some logs, where (still on the ground) she
successfully kept these competitors at bay. During all this, the Lesser
Necklaced Laughing Thrush was very animated, fluffing out his feathers,
singing and jumping up and down, while keeping about lm (3ft 3in) from
his mate.
While not reacting to rain showers in the same way as the White-crested
species, my male Lesser Necklaced Laughing Thrush sings persistently,
particularly early in the morning, a loud, repeated phase of seven notes,
while I have heard only a jay-like scolding from the Greater, in moments of
alarm. As with the White-crested species, my laughing thrushes seem
unaffected by extremes of weather. Although lacking an enclosed shed,
ample protection from wind and rain is provided by a combination of
corrugated plastic sheeting, bundles of reed and growing ivy. Bathing is a
daily activity, usually in the overflow of the aviary pond when the water is
renewed.
With the variety of laughing thrush species available recently, the
opportunity exists to establish self-sustaining populations; with this in mind,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999588" page_id="56264368"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
156
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.906075" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264368" page_num="156" year="" vol="">
SCHOFIELD - LAUGHING THRUSHES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9885484" page_id="56264368"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
I will try to match-up my two birds with more appropriate partners. The
Yellow-throated and Red-tailed G. milnei are two of the 20 passerine species
selected for breeding programmes in British zoos by the Passerine Taxon
Advisory Group. This reflects their desirability as aviary subjects, for both
public and private collections.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.446407" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264368" page_num="156" year="" vol="">
References and bibliography
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.902864285714286" page_id="56264368"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
Boosey, E. J. 1956. Foreign Bird Keeping. Cage Birds, London.
Coles, D. 2000. Management of Laughing Thrushes in Captivity. D. Coles, Lower Basildon.
Coles, D. 1979. Breeding the Red-headed Laughing Thrush at Padstow Bird Gardens.
Avicultural Magazine 85,1:16-17.
Foreign Bird Federation. 1995. Register of Birds Bred in the UK Under Controlled Conditions
for the Years 1992-1995. Foreign Bird Federation.
Gibson, L. 1982. Breeding the White-crested Jay Thrush. Avicultural Magazine 88,3:135-141.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.97059296969697">
Grimmett, R., Inskipp, C. and Inskipp, T. 1999. Pocket Guide to the Birds of the Indian
Subcontinent. Christopher Helm, London.
Gruson, E. S. 1976. A Checklist of the Birds of the World. Collins, London.
Haines, C. 1989. Breeding the Red-tailed Laughing Thrush Garrulax milnei at Padstow Tropical
Bird Gardens. Avicultural Magazine 95,1:10-13.
Harrison, C.J.O. 1962. Observations on Rufous-chinned Jay Thrushes. Avicultural Magazine
68,1:188-197.
Harrison, C.J.O. 1967. Some Notes on Babbler Behaviour. Avicultural Magazine 73,2:28-33.
Hewston, N. 1983. Breeding the White-browed Laughing Thrush. Avicultural Magazine 89,2:63-
66 .
Isenberg, A.H. 1970. Breeding the Rufous Laughing Thrush. Avicultural Magazine 76,4:143.
Jeggo, D. (Chairperson). 1997. Passerine TAG (Taxon Advisory Group) Report - 1996.
Avicultural Magazine 103,1:130-133 .
King, W., Woodcock, M. and Dickinson, E.C. 1975. A Field Guide to the Birds of South-East
Asia. Collins, London.
Lieberman, A. 1984. Breeding the Red-winged Laughing Thrush Garrulax formosus at the
San Diego Zoo. Avicultural Magazine 90,2:87-90.
Lindholm, J.H. 1989. Notes on Aviculture at the Cincinnati Zoo, Ohio, USA. Avicultural
Magazine 95,4:176-191.
Long, A., Crosby, C. and Inskipp, T. A. 1994. Review of the Taxonomic Status of the Yellow-
throated Laughingthrush Garrulax galbanus. Oriental Bird Club Bulletin 19: 41-48.
Mace, M.E. 1994. Notes on Breeding the Black-throated Laughing Thrush. Avicultural
Magazine 100,2:98-100 .
Pasini, A., Arsuffi, D., Micali, G. and Violani, C. G. 1994. Identification and Captive Breeding
of Yellow-throated Laughingthrush Garrulax galbanus. Oriental Bird Club Bulletin 19:49-50.
Risdon, D.H.S. 1955. White-crested Jay Thrushes. Avicultural Magazine 61,1:19-21.
Sclater, PL. (ed.) 1879. List of Vertebrate Animals now or lately living in Gardens of the
Zoological Society of London. Longmans.
Simmons, K. E. L. 1962. Jay-Thrushes and Acorns. Avicultural Magazine 68,1:182-188.
Yealland, J. J. 1965. The Breeding of the Masked Jay-Thrush. Avicultural Magazine 71,1:8.
Ward, B. S. 1975. Breeding the Rufous-chinned Laughing Thrush at Winged World. Avicultural
Magazine 81,2: 68-69.
Yeo Kok Hoe, 1969. The Spectacled Jay-Thrush. Avicultural Magazine 75,3:79-84.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999099" page_id="56264369"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
157
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.971004" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264369" page_num="157" year="" vol="">
BIRDS IN A DESERT GARDEN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.986528" page_id="56264369"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
by Les Gibson
These notes are about the relatively few birds that visited our California
desert garden in the small community of La Quinta in the Coachella Valley,
25 miles (approx. 40km) from Palm Springs and 30 miles (approx. 48km)
from the Salton Sea. Close to sea level, it lies within a horseshoe of hills,
with the opening to the north, and is only V 2 mile (approx. 1km) from the
desert. The average summer temperature for about seven months is 106*F
(41 *C) with 7.6cm (3in) of rain falling erratically in less than seven days,
spread over the year, but with most in late summer. One or two days on
either side of the rain the sky is grey, but the other 265 days of the year it is
cloudless with relentless sunshine, with on one occasion the temperature
going up to 121*F (49.5*C). Global warming affects the desert too, and the
last year we were there, only 3.8cm (lV 2 in) of rain fell.
It was wetter in the past 100 years. Building excavations 2 miles (approx.
3km) away downhill revealed the tops of orchard trees that had been buried
by silt from a flash flood. A long time ago, the valley used to hold a large
lake which was fished by primitive Indians and stone fish traps, now high
and dry, can be seen along the former shoreline. Coachella is a mis-spelling
of Conchella, the Spanish name for the little shells that were found on the
valley floor.
There are three or four small oases in the valley, the largest of which has
a good stand of palms, with the old dead fronds hanging haystack-like, almost
to the ground, around the trunks. These have become home to a colony of
Budgerigars Melopsittacus undulatus, which nest in amongst the old fronds,
rather in the manner of Quaker or Monk Parrakeets Myiopsitta monachus.
The Budgerigar's genetic pool gets refreshed periodically as new escapees
fly in. Palm seeds are a major food. The valley does not sound like a
hospitable place for birds and, was not, until houses and golf courses were
built, with their accompanying sprinklers and ponds. A canal brings water
from the Colorado River, which is used mainly for irrigation while much of
the household water comes from a huge underground lake lying beneath the
surface of the former lake.
The garden's stony soil had no low plants and no weeds! There were
five local Washingtonia Palms, three of them 4.5m (approx. 15ft) tall and
two 9m (approx. 30ft) ones, plus two local Palo Verde (Green Wood) trees.
The latter were 7.5m (approx. 24ft) tall, twice the height and bulk of the
water-deprived ones growing in the desert. An interesting adaptation of
these trees is that all of the wood, including the trunk, is bright green from
chlorophyll, which continues to function after the tiny leaves have dried up.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99923" page_id="56264370"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
158
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.850402" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264370" page_num="158" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - BIRDS IN A DESERT GARDEN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999562738095238" page_id="56264370"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
There was also a dense 3m (approx. 10ft) tall Oleander, a big magenta
Bougainvillea and a miserable, thirsting Grapefruit tree. The piece de
resistance was a 4m (approx. 13ft) tall Saguaro Cactus, with limbs more
than 30cm (1ft) thick. Outside the wall there were masses of Prickly Pear
cacti.
The first birds we noticed after moving in were the Roadrunners
Geococcyx californianus. These large, ground-dwelling cuckoos are shy in
the desert, where their territories are very large, whereas in suburbia they
fiercely defend a mere four or five block square. The male is barely larger
than the female, more noticeable about the head. The area of blue and orange
bare skin behind the eyes is larger and brighter in the male, and he is more
pushy and territorial.
Our two were delighted when we moved in and they came right to the
open glass door, looking for the hand-outs they had become accustomed to
receiving from the previous owners. This had been raw hamburger but we
soon substituted this with soaked dog pellets. At first they were puzzled by
these, but within a week the male was taking them from our hands using the
snatch-and-run method. His mate always hung back but quickly picked up
food thrown to her. All the dog food we used to feed the birds was soaked
first. Often it dried up in the sun, but was never concrete-hard like it is
when taken straight from the bag.
Roadrunners dote on meat, raw or cooked, and are relentless predators.
We watched one chase a lizard under the Prickly Pears then stand like a
statue for two or three minutes until the luckless lizard thought it was safe to
take a look outside. We confess that feeding these birds was in no small part
aimed at saving the lizards. Roadrunners have almost no enemies. They
face down cats and can outrun, at least to the nearest wall, most dogs. They
crouch motionless when a hawk appears, but there never was one big enough
to risk attacking them. The only remote threat to them is from the Coyotes
Canis latrans which roam the streets in the dead of night looking for
everything from dog food to cats and Pekinese.
Pairs of Roadrunners part after nesting and usually disappear for one or
two months in winter. We suspect they go to a common mate-selecting area
for they return around February in pairs. One year, our pair never left and
maintained a close liaison, living about two streets apart, and coming
separately for food hand-outs. If they arrived at the same time, the male
half-heartedly chased away the female, which usually waited over the wall
until he had left. In spite of moderate temperatures, 40*F-50*F (5*C-10*C)
at night but being very pleasant during the day, winter is a hard time for
desert birds. Insects are sparse at the best of times and completely absent
then as are the lizards, which are hibernating. Thin young birds from the
previous season still without a territory, would by hanging around for days
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.590722" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264371" page_num="159" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - BIRDS IN A DESERT GARDEN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999452" page_id="56264371"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
159
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.995868571428571" page_id="56264371"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
hoping to snatch some food, risking injury from the resident male, which
would often chase a youngster at high speed along the middle of the street.
Mating behaviour was noted, perhaps for the first time. The street was
used as a race track and mating ground by the birds which can run at 30kph
(19mph). The female was seen to run slowly or walk quickly for about
1 Oft-12ft (approx. 3m-3.6m) followed closely by the male. His neck was
extended forward and his beak was pointing to the ground and holding a
piece of dog food. His tail was straight up and wagging slowly from side to
side. When the female stopped he jumped 2ft (61cm) into the air and moved
his feet as so he was running. This went on for several minutes with the
female running back the way she came to the end of the property. Then
mating took place. It was not clear which bird ate the dog food, but the male
jumped onto the wall for another piece, which was likely presented to the
'lady'.
Their nests were difficult to find especially as they were on someone
else's property. The pair was extremely cautious and always approached
the nest by devious routes often standing at street comers for a minute or
two until the street was clear, especially if they were being watched or
followed. We knew the birds were nesting not too far away but they always
avoided revealing the exact site, often trotting casually past the nest then
returning to it undercover of vegetation. Finally after the chicks had fledged
we found the nest three houses away. The birds craftily went past it into the
garden and entered the thick Bougainvillea from the house side. The nest
was mainly a 14cm ( 5 V 2 in) thick pad of heavy, thorny twigs, surmounted by
a rimless, shallow grass-lined depression in the 16.5cm ( 6 V 2 in) diameter
top. A new nest is built elsewhere for each new clutch.
Nesting commenced in early spring from February onwards and two
broods were the norm. The first young were brought to the garden on April
1st. The young were looked after for about six weeks then driven away.
Dog food was placed in a dish on top of the wall along with a large bowl of
water which evaporated in two days unless replenished. Because of the
irregularity of the natural food supply, the usual clutch of four eggs rarely
produced four surviving young, two being average.
One year we provided the birds with a large supply of food throughout
the breeding season and just like with the Common or Indian Mynahs
Acridotheres tristis in South Africa (Gibson, 1996), four broods were raised
with four, four, three and two young reaching adulthood. Unfortunately the
pair of Roadrunners never built a nest in our garden so we did not know
how many eggs were laid.
When old enough to leave the nest, the young came to the garden with
one or other parent, mostly it was with the female and sometimes it was
with both parents. Several times a day the young were fed with quantities
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995661" page_id="56264372"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
160
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.848856" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264372" page_num="160" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - BIRDS IN A DESERT GARDEN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.992223785714286" page_id="56264372"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
of dog food then they had a drink of five to 12 sips of water depending on
how hot it was. The adult male was seen to eat 14 pieces of hazelnut-sized
dog food at a sitting but food for the young in the nest was always carried in
the beak. The family returned nightly to the nest or the bush for a period
after the young had fledged, but because the nest was not found until the
birds had left, the exact details could not be recorded. The female laid again
quickly afterwards leaving the male to take care of the young until the second
brood hatched, when he then drove away the young of the first brood.
On one occasion a small scraggy chick was brought to the garden by the
male. It was the youngest of the final brood the others having either gone
off with the female or dispersed. The male took great care of it and it was
fed on the wall for at least two weeks longer than usual. As with all young,
the chick crouched down and begged insistently while next to the food dish.
Later it was driven off rather half-heartedly at first and managed to sneak
back and feed itself for a couple of weeks more before the male got serious
about driving it away.
Roadrunners do not fly high or long distances. We saw the male fly 3ft-
4ft (approx. lm-1.2m) from the wall up onto the eaves of the house and
from there partially glide groundwards over the carport and onto a fence.
This 9ft (2.7m) high and 18ft (5.5m) long sortie was the highest and longest
flight we had seen. To reach the food dish from the ground a bird would
walk to within 1ft (30cm) of the wall and then fly straight up like a helicopter.
They did this even when sitting on the thick branch of a tree and were a
mere skip away from the wall. Rather than fly across they jumped down to
the ground and then flew up.
During the first year we found the Roadrunners interesting but when the
next breeding season arrived something happened that made us go off them
- almost. In the early spring the Cactus Wrens Campylorhynchus
brunneicapillus constructed one of several trial nests in the small palm
immediately above the food dish, while in the nearby Oleander the
Mockingbirds Mimus polyglottos were busily building. A month or so later
we heard the Mockingbirds clamouring in the street. We looked out to see
them dive-bombing an oblivious Roadrunner zipping off with a well-
feathered Mockingbird chick, dead and quite bloodied from being banged
about.
A week later we observed the male Roadrunner in the crown of the small
palm tree where the wrens had built a nest but had not used it. The
Roadrunner dropped onto the wall then ran along it to below the next tree in
which the Cactus Wrens had a nest with chicks. The Roadrunner waited
until he saw one of the wrens by the nest then flew up and clumsily, not
being a perching bird, began to poke about. Both wrens jumped around
hysterically close by but did not dive at the intruder as the Mockingbirds
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.590592" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264373" page_num="161" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - BIRDS IN A DESERT GARDEN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998389" page_id="56264373"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
161
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.995629952380952" page_id="56264373"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
had done. The Roadrunner soon found the entrance to the wren's deep nest
and managed to extract a chick. There followed the most horrendous
spectacle for lacking the beak and claws of a hawk the Roadrunner proceeded
to batter the eight to nine-day old chick on the thick stems of the palm
fronds, spattering blood all over the place. The Roadrunner then dropped to
the large stones on the ground below and as the wrens hopped about calling
frantically proceeded to bash the by then dead chick on the stones until it
was a bloodied pulp though still in one piece. We wondered how it would
be fed to the Roadrunner chicks. Possibly the parents would pull pieces
from the carcass but more likely it would be given to one of the Roadrunner
chicks to swallow whole. After that we stopped feeding the Roadrunners
during the summer but admit to helping them out in the winter when lizards
and insects disappeared for three to four months.
The Mockingbird is the only member of its family to have adapted readily
to living in desert gardens, although unlike the Roadrunner it does not live
in the actual desert. There is little special about the Mockingbird's habits,
which are similar to those of other members of the family. Almost everyone
knows of its singing ability, repeating the same phrase two to five times. It
is also a well-known mimic but there were hardly any other birds in the area
for it to mimic. The only sound that interfered with the male's melodic
repertoire, and then only rarely was a fair imitation from far off of our
Pekinese barking. The one special thing about the Mockingbird is that it
continues to sing on and off all through the night especially when there is
moonlight. Although in the desert there are sometimes wild and windy
though rainless nights, many more are beautiful, warm, still and moonlit.
On such evenings we often slept outside, finally nodding off as the loud,
clear and unhurried song of the resident male Mockingbird echoed around
the garden. The desert is silent during the day and was silent and romantic
on stormy nights, as our bird was answered from all points of the compass
by rivals. The only competing sound was the occasional far-off cry of a
love-struck Coyote in the nearby hills.
In spite of the depredations mentioned earlier, the Mockingbirds
succeeded in raising several young each season and kept the area liberally
supplied with up-and-coming songsters. The bigger birds could not easily
get into the Oleander and the juvenile Mockingbird was probably following
its parents about when it was taken. Our other resident nesters - the Cactus
Wrens - were our favourites. The largest wren and unlike the others in
appearance, it is a handsome bird with its livery of black spots on a white
and orange-tan breast. In spite of the sparsity of vegetation these shy birds
managed to remain hidden most of the time and though we heard their hoarse,
scolding calls daily, it took six months of coaxing before they popped out of
the Bougainvillea to eat the kibbled dog food provided. Even if merely
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99871" page_id="56264374"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
162
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.850536" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264374" page_num="162" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - BIRDS IN A DESERT GARDEN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999679285714286" page_id="56264374"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
watched they dived back into the spiny bush. In other deserts in which
Saguaro Cactus grow the wrens often nest in them. However, our cactus
remained nest-free lacking as it did the old nest holes of woodpeckers, which
these wrens need to nest in.
In our garden, the Cactus Wrens nested only in the small palms. These
had the frond bases left in place all the way down the trunks, giving them an
attractive cross-hatched appearance and the wrens built where the cut fronds
met the growing ones. The nest was a large, untidy mass of long, dry plant
stems and large strap-like pieces of red-brown frond bud covers as well as a
fair amount of plastic bag and some paper. However deep within this debris
was a snug fibre-lined egg depository. After a wind storm the nests were
often found on the ground though usually only when the nesting season was
over and they had loosened. We rarely saw the wrens entering their nest as
they were extremely shy and always moved around the tree out of sight and
also because the nest was placed so that it was not easily observable from
the ground. Because of this secretiveness the first we knew of the presence
of chicks, during the first year, was when the parents appeared with one at
the water dish. Later we found out why there was only one chick. It was
because the pair never succeeded in raising more than two young per season,
one per nest, due to the predation by the Roadrunners. The only other
occasional loss was due to Ravens Corvus corax. These wary birds stuck to
the tall palms when hunting. The Cactus Wrens, like all the birds in the
garden, patronised the water dish all year round and frequently used it for
bathing. Garden sprinklers and drip systems all around provided drinking
water but rarely provided enough water for bathing in.
The common Ground Dove Columbina passerina (whose scientific name
sounds like it comes from a Mexican children's rhyme) was a regular nester
from the end of winter until the heat set in. These birds nested only in the
tallest palms and far from being safe there they were in constant danger. In
early spring all the garden birds froze on hearing a deadly sound save that
was for the Roadrunners which remained alert and ready to take action. The
sound was made by a pair of hunting Ravens as the two birds searched the
crowns of the adjacent palms. Their cawing continued for two to three
months during which time the Ravens took a heavy toll of chicks, mainly
those of the doves, and flew straight to the distant cliff to feed this bounty to
their brood. We watched them comb the palm fronds and estimated that one
in four palms produced a victim during the breeding season. They lacked
finesse and there was a lot of rough scrambling about accompanied by
constant loud cawing as they communicated with each other. The Ground
Dove was one of the very few birds seen in the inhospitable hills with small
flocks of six to 12 moving around eating mainly prickly seeds from a species
of cactus. Prior to local migration, the doves gathered in quite large numbers
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.947152" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264375" page_num="163" year="" vol="">
GIBSON -'BIRDS IN A DESERT GARDEN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999316" page_id="56264375"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
163
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999636" page_id="56264375"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
on the wires outside the house.
The only other species to nest - and then only once - was the tiny tit-like
Verdin Auriparus flaviceps. It hung its prickly little nest at the end of a
willowy but thorny Palo Verde branch outside the wall at the back of the
garden. So we saw little of the Verdins and their young. A later examination
showed the nest to be globular with the entrance just below the top. It was
closed-off with plant material and had a one-way action. It was amazing
how the birds got in and even more amazing how they got out again. The
nest was completely predator-proof and was very like the Common Waxbill
Estrilda astrild nest in our garden in Durban (Gibson, 1996). The Verdins'
nest had the same kind of one-way door, except that it was made of
unapproachable cactus spines. Later, the yellow-headed Verdins were often
seen flitting around the garden seeking insects. The only call they were
heard to make was a quiet peep.
Assorted hummingbirds were non-nesting winter residents that
sometimes stayed longer. These quarrelsome little creatures passed through
in droves but only one at a time was resident, and divided its waking hours
equally between drinking from the feeder by the back door and driving away
other hummingbirds from the feeder. A male Costa's Hummingbird Calyptes
costae always retired to the same perch on a nearby tree from which it could
watch for intruders. To make nectar available to more migrating birds we
hung another feeder by the front door. Within two days, the male had shifted
to a position higher up in a farther-off tree, from which it could see the
original feeder and also watch for hummers heading towards the one by the
front door. However whenever it launched an attack, others took the
opportunity to take a quick sip of nectar from the unguarded feeder. Many
of our neighbours had hummingbird feeders, but a quick check usually found
three-quarters of them were empty at any given time.
A Ladder-backed Woodpecker Picoides scalaris once spent two weeks
in our garden. It drunk the 20% sugar solution from the hummingbird feeder
as did a pair of yellow and black orioles Icterus spp. which stayed for two
days. The woodpecker clung to the underside of a thick limb of a Palo
Verde tree pecking at the place where live and dead wood met. It enlarged
the hole until it could get its beak inside and extracted a small grub. This
took it 17 minutes after which it rested on top of the limb for three minutes
then returned to the underside for a further 20 minutes, apparently pecking
at random without making any obvious attempt to stop and look or listen. It
then flew off and took seven sips of nectar. Five minutes later it returned to
the underside of the limb and pecked for 10 minutes before finding a small
spider that was walking past. It had been clinging beneath the limb and
pecking at it for 42 minutes out of 50. It fell from the underside once
recovering after falling 46cm (LMt) and then flying back to its original
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99958" page_id="56264376"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
164
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.846909" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264376" page_num="164" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - BIRDS IN A DESERT GARDEN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.981562552631579" page_id="56264376"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
position. The fact that it spent 50 minutes during which it captured just the
small grub and spider must say quite a lot for the calorific content of the
nectar, and the fitness of the woodpecker.
We sometimes got birds from the local rescue centre, one of which was
a Loggerhead Shrike Lanius ludovicianus found with a broken wing on the
north shore of the Salton Sea. It was one of four million wintering birds in
the area. The shrike used its lethal bill to destroy bandage after bandage and
its needle-point bill pierced assorted garden gloves, worn when handling it.
It would eat only mealworms. Three weeks later its feathers still looked
good, and though it had a permanently drooped wing, it could fly quite well
and was released.
Another creature which came from the centre, was a very sick White
Pelican Pelicanus erythrorhynchos found on the Salton Sea. This huge
artificial expanse of water, formed from a breach in the Colorado River
canal, is now 3.5% salt, 1.5% more than the sea, and is heavily polluted. In
spite of this there are in it large numbers of African tilapia and these fish
attract large flocks of both White and especially Brown Pelicans P.
occidentalis . There are periodic heavy die-offs in these flocks, the cause or
causes of which remain a mystery at least to government biologists. Our
pelican, which was very thin and weighed about 3.5kg (81bs) was so sick
that it remained outside uncaged all day. It barely ate and died within four
days. Its intestines were a foul mess, and even without the use of laboratory
facilities, it was evident that it had liver flukes which could be seen slithering
about.
Parrot ownership is high in the area and a fair number of escapees passed
through our garden. These included a white cockatoo that stopped by to
screech along with our voluble pet 'Sean Connery', which sat untethered on
a perch outside all through the above events. The two cockatoos were still
competing to find which could make the most din when the owner of the
second cockatoo, who lived a block away, turned up. She was out looking
for her bird, when she heard the two screeching.
The only other creatures seen in the garden apart from the aforementioned
lizards, were the giant blue-black carpenter bee that drilled a 2cm ( 3 Ain)
diameter tunnel in a dead Palo Verde limb and the interesting wind-scorpions,
which pleased us by eating the big red fire ants. Also, we will never forget
the termites that completely ate away all the beams of our bathroom ceiling.
Reference
Gibson, L. 1996. Birds in a Durban Garden. Avicultural Magazine 102,3:124-136.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998885" page_id="56264377"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
165
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.789467333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264377" page_num="165" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE PAPUAN WREATHED HORNBILL
Aceros plicatus AT PAIGNTON ZOO ENVIRONMENTAL
PARK, ENGLAND
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.948624777777778" page_id="56264377"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
by Jo Gregson
The Papuan Wreathed Hornbill, otherwise named Blyth's Hornbill, is an
irregular breeder in captivity. However, as we have begun to learn more
about its avicultural requirements more successes have occurred. Asian
hornbills can be quite a challenge: these species are intelligent and sensitive
to change and take longer to form pairs; young males are vulnerable to
bullying by older females; heated accommodation is necessary and a higher
protein diet is needed for them to rear their chicks successfully. These and
several other factors make them more difficult to maintain and breed
compared to their African counterparts.
The pair of Papuan Wreathed Hornbills came to our collection on
December 20th 2000. They are housed in an aviary which measures 3m x
5m x 4m high (approx. 9ft 9in x 16ft 4in x 13ft high), with an adjoining
inside area measuring 2m x 3m x 4m high (approx. 6ft 6in x 9ft 9in x 13ft
high). In the summertime the outside temperature ranges from 10*C-23*C
(50*F-73*F), with the average being about 16*C (60*F). During the
wintertime the birds are shut in the inside area that at night is heated to an
average 15*C (59*F). In the summertime the inside temperature occasionally
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.656856" page_id="56264377"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
reaches 25 *C ( 77*F).
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.842155" page_id="56264377"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
Two nest-boxes are provided. The one in which the pair bred measures
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.891206">
60cm x 70cm x 60.5cm high ( approx. 2ft x 2ft 3in x 2ft FAin high), with a
15cm x 15cm (6in x 6in) entrance hole 12.5cm (approx. 5in) from the bottom
on the left-hand side of the 60cm (approx. 2ft) side. The box is 2.5m (approx.
8ft 2in) above the floor of the inside area. The other nest-box, which is in
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.988834307692308" page_id="56264377"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
the outside aviary, measures 66cm x 40cm x 50cm high (approx. 2ft 2in x
lft 3 3 Ain x 1ft 7 3 /4in high) and is 3m (approx. 9ft 9in) above the ground.
The entrance hole measures 20cm x 20cm (approx. 8in x 8in) and is at the
centre of the narrow end where there is a small landing ledge. This is the
same type of box used by our Wrinkled A. corrugatus, Trumpeter Bycanistes
or Ceratogymna bucinator and Northern Ground Hornbills Bucorvus
abyssinicus.
The diet consists of a varied fruit mix, along with mealworms, mice,
cooked minced (ground) beef and boiled egg. SA37 is sprinkled onto the
food. When the chicks were due to hatch pinkies were added to the diet,
then after eight days, 'small fluffs', and by day 25 'large fluffs' and small
adult mice were offered.
The pair did not seal the nest-box entrance. The female was often seen
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999399" page_id="56264378"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
166
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.967644" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264378" page_num="166" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - PAPUAN WREATHED HORNBILL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987601666666667" page_id="56264378"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
out of the box and the male was sometimes seen in the box with the female
and chicks. The first chick left the nest-box at 100 days and spent a few
days of the floor before mastering the art of jumping from perch to perch.
Once one chick has fledged it is important to watch for any others remaining
in the nest, and this was the case with our birds. Three days after the first
chick fledged the female began spending less time in the nest-box and, on
inspection, the second chick , still quite heavy in blood quills, was found to
be very soiled. As it probably had some time to go before fledging, we
decided to clean it and then placed it in an open-fronted box of the floor of
the aviary, where it remained for several days and was fed by both parents.
As the first chick to fledge was also soiled and spent some time on the
floor of the aviary, I think that it fledged too soon and may have left the box
at 100 days because the inside of the box was dirty. The chicks would have
been better prepared at 115 days.
Once both were fully feathered, on fine days they were lightly sprayed
with water to help improve the condition of their plumage. Asian hornbills
have a large and very active preen gland and when these birds are handled
they are found to be greasy and have a distinctive smell. The red, yellow
and orange bill colours of some of these species are obtained from the oils
of this gland. As these birds spend much of the day preening and oiling
their feathers, our chicks soon had waterproof plumage. Both chicks when
they fledged had male-type plumage. However, at four months of age, the
head of one of them began to sprout black feathers and this proved to be a
female. The beak of the other bird, a male, had by then grown longer than
that of the adult female. The two were separated from their parents at five
months of age, by which time the female seemed to have tired of their
company.
As described above, the Papuan Wreathed Hornbill Aceros plicatus, also
called Blyths Hornbill, has been bred at Paignton Zoo Environmental Park.
This is probably the first successful breeding of this species in Great Britain
or Ireland. Anyone who knows of a previous breeding is asked to inform the
Hon. Secretary.
/ know that this species has nested at Cricket St Thomas and Linton Zoo,
but so far as I am aware, in neither collection were the chicks reared
successfully. Hornbills in Zoos - a Review by Dr Harm Strehlow published
in International Zoo News Vol. 48/2 (March 2001), reviews the breeding of
hornbills in collections throughout the world and is recommended reading
for those interested in these species. At El Retiro Park, Malaga, the young
Papuan Wreathed Hornbill left the nest cavity after 126 days - Ed.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998697" page_id="56264379"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
167
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993361" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264379" page_num="167" year="" vol="">
DO VITAMINS A AND E HAVE AN IMPACT
ON THE FERTILITY OF HUMBOLDT PENGUINS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.952809205882353" page_id="56264379"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
Spheniscus humholdti ?
by Kelly Rose and Caitlyn Hopkins
Aims of study
To investigate the impact on fertility from adding supplementary vitamins
A (retinol) and E (a tocopherol) to the diet of captive Humboldt Penguins.
To improve the number of viable chicks produced each year.
Introduction
Humboldt Penguin in the wild
The Humboldt Penguin Spheniscus humholdti is native to the coastlines
of Peru and Chile in South America. The birds spend time at their colonies
nesting, rearing their chicks and moulting, but otherwise are thought to spend
most of the year at sea. The species is listed as CITES 1, due mostly to
extensive guano mining in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, for use as
a commercial fertiliser. The continuous disturbance of the birds at their
nesting grounds in the course of its collection reduced the population size
considerably (del Hoyo et al. 1993). Other problems such as intensive egg
collection, Indiscriminate fishing and oil spills (Frost et al. 1976) have also
contributed to the reduction in numbers. The current population is unknown,
however, following El Nino the population is known to have decreased to
below 65% of its former number (Hays, 1984).
In captivity
The captive population of the Humboldt. Penguin is decreasing (6lay,
1995) and therefore many zoos are carrying out research to find out why
this is and what, if anything, can be done about it. In most zoos they are fed
frozen fish, and due to the limitations of this diet, considerable attention has
been given to their feeding as a possible variable/experimental factor (Wallace
et al. 1992). In the wild their diet consists mostly of anchovies and anchoveta
(Blay, 1998) which together with the availability of other fish may mean
that vitamin levels are higher in wild birds. This coupled with the fact that
vitamins A and E have important roles in reproduction were among the major
factors when deciding on this study.
At Bird World
Bird World has kept Humboldt Penguins since 1983. During this time,
data have been recorded on breeding patterns, matings and the number of
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998025" page_id="56264380"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
168
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.477653" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264380" page_num="168" year="" vol="">
ROSE &amp; HOPKINS - HUMBOLDT PENGUINS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997940333333333" page_id="56264380"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
fertile eggs and chicks produced. It has a very successful history of breeding
this species and has produced well over 300 birds. The average production
rate has varied each year, and any decrease in numbers may be due to many
reasons including ageing birds and changing weather patterns. Nonetheless,
it was decided that a research project was in order to determine whether
changing their food could increase the production of penguin chicks.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.7973205">
Methods
Study site
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.872784233333333" page_id="56264380"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
The study was carried out at Bird World, Holt Pound, Farnham, Surrey
GU10 4LD, UK. The captive colony is housed in an open display enclosure,
with a freshwater pool, rocky area and off-show nest-boxes. It comprises
14 adult Humboldt Penguins in seven pairs and various offspring bred there
last year and all hand-reared at BirdWorld. The adult birds' ages range from
13 to 20 years old (the exact hatching dates are to be found in Appendix 1).
Humboldt Penguins are thought to reach sexual maturity at two years of age
but their optimal breeding age is unknown. Because of the small size of the
population, it was decided to use all birds in the experiment rather than have
a control group.
Diet
The birds are fed on a diet of frozen Sprats Sprattus sprattus kept at an
average temperature of -20*C (-4*F), then defrosted in cold water overnight
and/or running water. The Sprats were analysed for vitamin A and E content,
during the course of this experiment. Vita-Zu tablets are added to replenish
any vitamins lost through the freezing process. Many zoos keep fish frozen
for periods of over six months, and prolonged storage can cause depletion
in vitamin E (Gailey-Phillips et al. 1982). Salt tablets are also added to their
diet, to compensate for the salt they would normally acquire from the
seawater. The tablets are fed in about 30 fish (one Vita-Zu and one Salt
tablet per Sprat) every two days. The number of these fish that each individual
penguin receives is random and would vary each time. It is difficult to be
any more precise without causing undue stress to each bird. Vita-Zu tablets
contain 1650 IU vitamin A and 25 IU vitamin E per tablet.
Sprat analysis
Frank Greenslades supplies the sprats; deliveries are normally annual in
October/November. Once the fish are caught they are put on ice and frozen
within 12 hours and upon delivery, BirdWorld store the fish in a freezer and
defrosts the appropriate quantity overnight for the next day's consumption.
They were tested by dry weight analysis for vitamins A and E by Medlab
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.254691" page_id="56264380"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
(MacDonald Exotic &amp; Domestic Laboratories).
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.250796" page_id="56264381"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
ROSE &amp; HOPKINS - HUMBOLDT PENGUINS
</equation>
<page confidence="0.994988" page_id="56264381"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
169
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.94586912" page_id="56264381"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
Blood samples
Initial tests
On January 10th 2001 during routine veterinary health checks all the
adult penguins had 2ml of blood taken from the carotid artery and some of
this was used to analyse for the levels of vitamin A and vitamin E. As much
as possible was done to minimise the stress to the penguins during this
procedure. The penguins were sectioned off from the pool at 8.00am, when
most of them are in their nest-boxes anyway. They had not eaten since
3.30pm the day before.
Re-testing blood
As blood sampling is a stressful procedure, it was decided not to repeat
the analysis after supplementation of vitamins A and E. Instead a comparison
of reproductive performance with previous years was used to assess the
benefit of additional supplementation.
Supplementation
This consisted of injecting 1000 IU (0.02ml) liquid vitamin A (Vitamin
A Palmitate Ampoules - Cambridge Selfcare Diagnostics Limited) into a
Sprat, then adding 25 IU QU tablet) vitamin E (Tocovite 100 tablets - Arnolds
Veterinary Products Ltd.) in tablet form. Each bird was hand fed one fish
each per day for a period of five days. If any bird did not voluntarily eat the
fish, they were not force fed, as it was felt this would be detrimental to the
project and increase stress levels in the birds. The penguins' supplementation
was given regularly through the breeding season daily for five days then
discontinued for nine days. The usual dietary supplementation was continued
as usual.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.967089">
Results
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991677" page_id="56264381"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
Behaviour affecting dosage time
During the early hours of the day (8.00am - 9.30am) the penguins are all
in their nest-boxes and not interested in food. At 11.30am, the penguins
receive their first feed of the day, and there is usually minimal interest,
likewise after 4.00pm when the birds are winding down. However the
3.30pm penguin feed finds most or all the birds in the water and very hungry.
Therefore after some basic experimentation it was found that the best time
of day to feed the supplemented fish was around 2.30pm - 3.00pm so as to
ensure the penguins were hungry enough to eat their tablets/fish. It is worth
noting however that this is not always the case at other times of year, for
example, during moulting most adults have little appetite at all (Williams et
al. 1989).
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.987089" page_id="56264382"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
170
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.383971" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264382" page_num="170" year="" vol="">
ROSE &amp; HOPKINS - HUMBOLDT PENGUINS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.913032" page_id="56264382"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
Sprat testing
The vitamin content of the Sprats compared to other fish (dry matter
comparisons) commonly used to feed captive penguins (Crissey et al. 1998)
is detailed below. The Columbia River Smelt contains significantly higher
levels of both vitamins with Trout also high, whereas all other fish appear to
be on a par with each other.
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.8932585">
Figure 1. Comparison of various fish and their vitamin contents. Sprat
analysis obtained from Bird World sprats and the data of Capelin, Herring,
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.945493888888889" page_id="56264382"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
Trout and CR Smelt having been taken from Crissey et al. 1998.
Fish
Vitamin A (IU g 1 )
Vitamin E (IU kg- )
Capelin
18.2
18
Herring
6.2
5.8
Trout
10.9
70.2
CR Smelt
232
142
Sprat
12.3
</figure>
<page confidence="0.592534" page_id="56264382"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
2.7
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.998826">
Figure 2. This year (2001) has had a marginal improvement on last year but
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.9722408" page_id="56264382"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
still does not compare favourably with previous years.
Mean number of viable chicks per
pairing from 1992 until present
1992 1993 1994 1995 1996 1997 1998 1999 2000 2001
Figure 2 shows the mean number of viable chicks produced per pairing
from 1992 to present (2001). In general, the number produced in 1999
reached a low and since then has improved again. This year there were two
clutches, in the first 11 eggs were laid but three were infertile. Two of those
three came from one pair in which the male, 566, is thought to be infertile as
he has only successfully sired offspring once, in 1992. Unfortunately his
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.252157" page_id="56264383"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
ROSE &amp; HOPKINS - HUMBOLDT PENGUINS
</equation>
<page confidence="0.9973" page_id="56264383"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
171
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.83513525" page_id="56264383"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
current partner, female 718, was a successful breeder with another male up
until 1998 when he died. Due to the lack of 'spare' males she paired with
the infertile male and has not had any offspring since and this may have
adversely affected the mean viable chicks per pairing.
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.934688">
Figure 3. A comparison of mortality of eggs and chicks compared to last
year shows visible improvement.
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.724813" page_id="56264383"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
Comparison of Infertility and Hatchability
for the years 2000 and 2001
Infertile Egg Chick died during incubation Chick Hatched
2000
\0x25A1
2001
In the second clutch, seven eggs were laid, two were dead in the egg and
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.93009025">
two were infertile. Of the three penguins which hatched out of the second
clutch, one died due to an incubator failing.
Figure 4. Vitamin A levels found in each penguin prior to each
supplementation.
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.978478928571429" page_id="56264383"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
1.5
o
E
=L
&lt;
c
E
ro
&amp;gt; 0.5
0
Vitamin A levels in blood prior to
supplementation 10/01/2001
381 566 287 302 387 359 357 385 718 374 383 358 579 558
Penguins
</figure>
<page confidence="0.99599" page_id="56264384"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
172
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.733681333333333">
ROSE &amp; HOPKINS - HUMBOLDT PENGUINS
Figure 5. Vitamin E levels found in each penguin prior to
supplementation.
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.939461333333333" page_id="56264384"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
Vitamin E levels in blood prior to
supplementation 10/01/2001
100 -|-
80 - -.
o
381 566 287 302 387 359 357 385 718 374 383 358 579 558
Penguins
Discussion
Copulation
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.986045047619048" page_id="56264384"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
Over the course of supplementation, it was noted by a number of keepers
that the penguins were observed to be copulating more than previous years.
We believe that, visually speaking, the change in diet increased copulation
(Jenkins &amp; Banks, 2001), therefore improving the chances of reproductive
success.
Observations were made during general keeping duties. These duties
include feeding twice a day, cleaning the pond and checking nest-boxes.
Such duties are performed on a regular basis each year and offer a consistent
amount of observation time.
Normal levels of Vitamins A and E
The nutrient requirements of penguins are unknown especially for this
species as little study has been done in the past. Therefore, estimation of
requirements have been extrapolated in part from knowledge of the nutritional
requirements of domestic birds (Ellis &amp; Branch, 1994). Published vitamin
A requirements are between 1.5 and 4.0 IU g 1 dry diet (NRC, 1994). Excess
dietary vitamin A has been demonstrated to have toxic effects in most species
studied, however, chronic vitamin A toxicity typically results from prolonged
exposure to intakes of 100-1,000 times the nutritional requirement (NRC,
1987) and in formulating the supplementation we were conscious that high
dietary concentrations of vitamin A has also been shown to depress vitamin
E status in birds (Sklan &amp; Donoghue, 1982).
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.251673" page_id="56264385"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
ROSE &amp; HOPKINS - HUMBOLDT PENGUINS
</equation>
<page confidence="0.999107" page_id="56264385"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
173
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.859186" page_id="56264385"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
Another possible problem in apparent fluctuating fertility levels may be
that the size of the population can also affect breeding. In captivity it is
recommended that Humboldt Penguins be kept in groups of at least six but
ideally 15-20 birds (Schmidt, 1978). This is because six birds are the
minimum number required for eggs to be laid. At BirdWorld, although the
number of adults (14) remained constant throughout the experiment, this
year, the number of juveniles fluctuated from eight to two.
Factors affecting the project
1) Problems administering one vitamin modified fish per bird
This was appetite dependable as much as anything else. There were
some days when some penguins did not eat anything and some when the
penguins would fight over a fish and tear it in half.
2) Inconsistency in the amount of vitamin E due to cutting technique
A knife was used to score then halve the tablets but invariably some
would disintegrate and uneven dosages would affect the experiment.
3) External factors affecting mating, e.g. weather, fish quality, water
temperature, public interaction, keeper interaction
This is almost unquantifiable.
4) Interference with nest-boxes and birds sitting on eggs
If a bird was in the nest-box when supplementation was due, the lid
would be lifted and several non-evasive attempts would be made to feed
the bird the fish. If this failed, the fish was left in the nest-box in the
hope that it would be eaten later.
5) Interference of last years ' offspring interacting with adult pairs
There are ten nest-boxes and seven adult pairs, usually each pair sticks
to a particular box, and therefore three are empty. However the juveniles
would often walk into occupied nest-boxes resulting in an aggressive
reaction from the adults.
6) Bird behavioural changes caused by keeping duties, e.g. cleaning
penguin pond
The pond is cleaned weekly and all penguins are kept out of the pool for
approximately 90 minutes. Most of the adults leave voluntarily but this
is not always true of the juveniles, and their presence in close proximity
to the nest-boxes increases the likelihood of (5) occurring.
7) Our own regular salt and vitamin tablets
As detailed previously under diet, it is possible that these regular tablets
could mask the results shown in the blood tests.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999331" page_id="56264386"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
174
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.6158485" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264386" page_num="174" year="" vol="">
ROSE &amp; HOPKINS - HUMBOLDT PENGUINS
Conclusion
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.981418612903226" page_id="56264386"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
One of the main reasons for undertaking penguin research at BirdWorld
was to make a positive impact on the birds, but also to offer recommendations
for other zoos. With this in mind, we suggest that it is essential for zoos to
supplement penguins' fish with vitamin tablets. This supplementation needs
to be vigilant so as to get the best results. Another suggestion may be to
monitor the use of frozen fish and to develop a system (if not already in
place) to limit prolonged frozen storage. Undertaking blood sampling of
the penguins is also a major operation worth mentioning. We found that
such a procedure should be limited to a minimum and planning and practice
is required prior to the commencement of the study.
Future experiments could include re-sampling the blood post
supplementation and looking at hormone levels in the blood as a measure of
fertility and/or adding zinc as a soluble salt to aid vitamin E uptake.
Originally the project was going to be altering photoperiod, but this proved
too difficult at BirdWorld. Another project, which was discussed in the
early stages, was cloacal sampling of post-copulated females to examine
sperm activity. This would have been costly in terms of observation time
required and also would have been an evasive procedure, requiring a license
from the Home Office. This has been performed previously on wild Adelie
Penguins Pygoscelis adeliae (Hunter, 1996).
It has been suggested that vitamin A and E deficiencies may result in
reduced fertility, reduced egg hatchability, birth defects, high chick mortality
and suppressed immune systems (Crissey, McGill and Simeone, 1998). We
believe that vitamin A and E supplementation was successful in our case as
the penguins were observed to be copulating more, the number of viable
chicks produced increased compared to the previous two years and there
was a reduction in mortality rate.
Fertility research performed on Humboldt Penguins has a limited history.
For this reason, we believe that to obtain more valid results, it is necessary
to continue the project over a number of breeding seasons, and encourage
other zoos to try similar studies.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.943989" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56264386" page_num="174" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998289" page_id="56264386"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
Above all we would like to thank Jason Waine B.Vet. Med. MRCVS for
his continued assistance and time throughout the project. Also Edward
Partridge B.Sc for reading related work, original drafts and comments. We
would like to thank the BirdWorld education and keeping staff for assistance,
ideas and encouragement and Dr Peter Hopkins for original ideas and
guidance. Gratitude also goes to Kerry Banks, BirdWorld's Head Keeper,
for her exceptionally well kept penguin history files! Last, but not least, the
generous public, members, family and friends who donated money for the
costs of this project and without whom it would not have been possible.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.251272" page_id="56264387"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
ROSE &amp; HOPKINS - HUMBOLDT PENGUINS
</equation>
<page confidence="0.997425" page_id="56264387"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
175
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.973841" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264387" page_num="175" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.658331695652174" page_id="56264387"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
Crissey, S. et al. 1998. Influence of dietary vitamins A and E on serum a- and y-tocopherols,
retinol, retinyl palminate and carotenoid concentrations in Humboldt penguins. Com. Bio Phy.
Part A 121:333-339.
del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A. and Sargatal, J. (eds.). 1993. Handbook of the Birds of the World. Vol 1.
Lynx Edicions. Barcelona.
Ellis, S., Branch, S. (eds.). 1994. Penguin Husbandry Manual. American Zoo and Aquarium
Association, Bethesda, MD.
Gailey-Phillips, J. and Sladden, W. 1982. Survey on Nutrition of Penguins. J Am Vet Med
Assoc. 181.1305-9.
Hunter, F.M., Davis, L.S. and Miller, G.D. 1996. Sperm transfer in the Adelie penguin. The
Condor 98:410-413.
Jenkins, R. and Banks, K. 2001. Personal communication. BirdWorld.
National Research Council. 1987. Vitamin tolerance of animals. National Academy of Sciences,
Washington, DC.
National Research Council. 1994. Nutrient Requirements of Poultry. National Academy of
Sciences, Washington, DC.
Schmidt, C.R. 1978. Humboldt penguins at Zurich Zoo. Int. Zoo Yb. 26:47-52.
Sklan, D. and Donoghue, S. 1982. Vitamin E response to high dietary vitamin A in the chick. J
Nutr 112.759-765.
Wallace, R. et al. 1992. The effect of dietary vitamin A (retinol) and vitamin E (alphatocopherol)
on serum status of Humboldt penguins. SPN 5:1:14-20.
Williams, G. et al. 1989. Plasa a-tocopherol, total lipids and total cholesterol in wild rockhopper,
magellanic and gentoo penguins before and after moulting. The Veterinary Record, June 3:
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.841190266666667" page_id="56264387"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
585-586.
Appendix 1
Hatch Dates
Males
Females
287
13/04/81
358
20/03/83 !
 |302
03/12/81
374
30/04/83
 |357
09/03/83
</figure>
<page confidence="0.729342666666667" page_id="56264387"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
383
31/05/83
359
</page>
<figure confidence="0.640789807692308" page_id="56264387"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
22/03/83
385
28/06/83
381
30/05/83
558
15/03/88
387
01/07/83
579
14/04/87
566
07/04/87
718
12/12/88
Appendix 2
Current pairs
Male
381
566
287
302
387
359
357
Female
</figure>
<page confidence="0.894834857142857" page_id="56264387"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
385
718
374
383
358
579
558
</page>
<page confidence="0.99413" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
176
</page>
<figure confidence="0.9784634" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
ROSE &amp; HOPKINS - HUMBOLDT PENGUINS
Appendix 3
Pairings and viable offspring 1992 - 2001
1992
1993
1994
Male Female V.O.
Male Female
V.O.
Male Female V.O.
</figure>
<page confidence="0.785775" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
354
</page>
<figure confidence="0.8362745" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
U
1
</figure>
<page confidence="0.818570875" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
287
374
3
287
374
2
302
358
</page>
<figure confidence="0.46364975" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
2
357
U
4
</figure>
<page confidence="0.8836185" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
302
358
</page>
<figure confidence="0.501201" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
1
</figure>
<page confidence="0.8545992" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
359
351
2
357
351
</page>
<figure confidence="0.47458825" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
2
357
719'
1 i
</figure>
<page confidence="0.91001625" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
387
383
4
381
385
3
359
579
</page>
<equation confidence="0.979479" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
i |
</equation>
<page confidence="0.867765" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
357
</page>
<figure confidence="0.546857" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
U
5
</figure>
<page confidence="0.947477" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
387
383
6
381
385
</page>
<equation confidence="0.342841" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
l
</equation>
<page confidence="0.6996688" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
401
579
4
401
579
</page>
<figure confidence="0.696068" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
1
</figure>
<page confidence="0.6720956" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
593
718
4
566
558
</page>
<figure confidence="0.714851" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
1
</figure>
<page confidence="0.6968405" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
593
718
</page>
<figure confidence="0.742341" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
2
596
610
1
</figure>
<page confidence="0.757868" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
287
374
</page>
<figure confidence="0.740647" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
1
U
718
4
U
719
2
U
U
1
u
U
2
1995
1996
1997
287
374
1
302
383
3
287
374
3
302
383
2
357
719
1
302
383
3
357
719
1
259
579
1
359
579
1
359
579
1
381
623
1
357
623
1
</figure>
<page confidence="0.627007" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
381
385
</page>
<figure confidence="0.5146675" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
1
387
358
3
</figure>
<page confidence="0.7520864" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
381
385
3
387
358
</page>
<figure confidence="0.662206" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
1
</figure>
<page confidence="0.640788" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
593
718
4
387
358
</page>
<figure confidence="0.656133857142857" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
2
593
718
1
U
385
2
</figure>
<page confidence="0.655602" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
593
718
4
596
623
</page>
<figure confidence="0.818752018867924" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
3
U
U
1
1998
1999
2001
287
374
1
302
383
3
302
383
3
302
383
2
2000
357
558
2
357
558
4
287
374
2
381
385
2
359
579
2
302
383
2
359
579
1
381
385
1
357
558
1
287
374
1
387
358
1
</figure>
<page confidence="0.80934" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
381
385
3
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.98576575" page_id="56264388"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
Kelly Rose BSc is now doing a PGCE course at Southampton University
and hopes to become a secondary school teacher. Until June 2002 she can
be contacted by e-mail:kjr20l@soton.ac.uk
Caitlyn Hopkins B. App. Sci. H.M.S. Ed has returned to Australia.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998732" page_id="56264389"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
177
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.989662" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264389" page_num="177" year="" vol="">
COUNCIL MEETING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.93878905" page_id="56264389"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
A council meeting was held on Sunday, October 14th at Chestnut Lodge,
Cobham, Surrey.
The following members were present: Miss R. Ezra (President), K.
Dolton, Prof. J. R. Hodges, C. J. S. Marler, R. C. J. Sawyer (Vice Presidents),
M. Curzon, M. Ellis (Hon. Editor), Mrs L. Gardner, R. H. Grantham, N.
Hewston, R. E. Oxley, S. Pyper, P. Schofield, J. Trollope, Ms R. Wiseman.
L. Gardiner joined the meeting following his election as the new Hon.
Secretary/Treasurer. C. J. S. Marler took the chair and was later elected
Chairman.
At the start of the meeting a minutes silence was observed in memory of
our late Chairman Ken Lawrence. Apologies for absence were received
from Mrs D. Holloway and Dr R. Wilkinson, after which the minutes of the
previous meeting were approved and were signed by the Chairman.
Miss R. Ezra, Prof. J. R. Hodges, C.J.S. Marler, Dr H. Quinque, R.C.J.
Sawyer, M. Ellis, M. Curzon and S. Pyper were each re-elected for a further
five-year term. It was agreed to invite J.A.Ellis to join the council, an
invitation which we are pleased to say he has accepted.
The Hon. Editor gave a brief and concise report. The valuable assistance
from Mrs June Sherborne was noted and the Hon. Editor was thanked for
his efforts.
After much discussion, it was decided that the D. H. S. Risdon Award
for the best article in the magazine during 2000, should go to Susan Congdon
and Bill Zima for their account of the breeding of the African Ja#ana
Actophilornis africanus at Disney's Animal Kingdom ( Avicultural Magazine
Vol. 106, No. 2, pp. 62-73).
In 2000, Ken Ashken generously gave the society a sum of money to
create the Dulcie Cooke Award in memory of his late mother. The council
decided that this award, an engraved plaque, should be given annually for
what in the council's opinion is the best photo submitted to illustrate an
article in the magazine. Again there was much discussion, with the majority
of members voting in favour of the award for 2000 going to Theo Pagel for
his photos showing the nest, egg, nestling and newly fledged Elegant Pitta
Pitta elegans at Cologne Zoo ( Avicultural Magazine Vol. 106, No. 4, pp. 166-
167). It noted that the nestling of this species appeared to be undescribed
prior to the publication of his photo.
Five potential first breedings in Great Britain or Ireland were considered
and all approved. The society's medal was awarded to: I. Hinze for the Mali
or Kulikoro Firefinch Lagonosticta virata; R. H . Grantham for the Purple-
bellied Parrot Triclaria malachitacea ; R. C. J. Sawyer for the Blue-bellied
Roller Coracias cyanogaster. The society's Certificate of Merit was awarded
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998869" page_id="56264390"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
178
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.989727" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264390" page_num="178" year="" vol="">
COUNCIL MEETING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994914925" page_id="56264390"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
to: Hillside Bird Oasis for the Lesser Flamingo Phoeniconaias minor ;
Blackbrook Zoological Park for the Marabou Leptoptilos crumeniferus .
We hope to arrange a visit to the Cots wold Wildlife Park on Saturday,
March 23rd 2002, with the President's Garden Party taking place Sunday,
July 15th, and have been invited to visit Ken Dolton's collection near
Worcester on Saturday, August 31st.
After a splendid lunch provided by our hosts, Miss Ruth Ezra and
Raymond Sawyer, the meeting continued into the afternoon. Among the
matters discussed were deciding upon a new delegate to attend NCA
(National Council for Aviculture) meetings and storing the large number of
back issues of the magazine. Lee Gardiner, the newly elected Hon. Secretary/
Treasurer, said he would attend the NCA Annual General Meeting and Laura
Gardner offered to store some of the back issues at Leeds Castle. We can
though no longer store the number we have in the past, and will have to
dispose of some of them. So, if there are back issues you want, now is a
good time to buy them.
The society remains in a sound financial position, thanks largely to the
lower cost of present day printing, generous donations from Vice President
Dr H. Quinque and others and the great generosity of our President, Miss
Ruth Ezra, who each year donates to the society's funds the money raised
by her much looked forward to and greatly enjoyed garden party. Nor should
we forget how Geoffrey Greed and Bristol Zoo stepped in and helped save
the society and get in onto its present sound financial footing following the
death of Harry Horswell. In recognition of this, Geoffrey Greed and Mrs
June Sherborne (who is to continue to do secretarial work for the society)
have been made Hon. Life Members. Following our departure from Bristol
Zoo Gardens, we now have the society's minute books dating back to 1904,
and these may provide interesting material for future issues of the magazine.
Improving how the society promotes itself and aviculture, and whether
it should have a mission statement were discussed. Also considered was
whether or not the society should help fund conservation and research
projects, and it was agreed that the Hon. Editor should ask members and
groups seeking such funding to submit written proposals for consideration
at future meetings.
The Chairman concluded the meeting by thanking Miss Ruth Ezra and
Raymond Sawyer for their kind hospitality.
If you have any views about the above and how the society conducts its
business, how it might enrol more new members, the content of the magazine
or how the website might be improved, we will be pleased to learn your
views.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999072" page_id="56264391"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
179
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996702" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264391" page_num="179" year="" vol="">
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.959788416666667" page_id="56264391"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
Dave Coles' Additions and Corrections to UK First Breeding Records
(Vol. 107, No.3, pp. 125-135) are a very useful addition to avicultural
literature. May I make a few comments? The common name of Eos
squamata ohiensis is the Obi Lory, not Wallace's Lorikeet. A record of the
breeding of the so-called Intermediate Parrakeet apparently appeared in the
Foreign Bird Federation's Breeding Register for 1994. It is now generally
accepted (after the publication of several papers), that the Intermediate
Parrakeet is a hybrid between the Slaty-headed Parrakeet Psittacula
himalayana and the Plumhead P. cyanocephala. Finally, the common and
scientific name Caninde Macaw Ara caninde are invalid. The correct names
are Blue-throated Macaw Ara glaucogularis. I am not being critical - just
trying to avoid the continued (and often confusing) use of incorrect names.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.6616635" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264391" page_num="179" year="" vol="">
Rosemary Low
FROM THE WEBSITE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.981357043478261" page_id="56264391"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
Leonard Enos asks: 'Does anyone have any information concerning the
Crested Jay Platylophus galericulatus in aviculture? I find it hard to believe
that no one has kept this intelligent, personable and fearless corvid outside
my local zoo (San Diego).'
According to the Zoological Society of San Diego 2000 Physical
Inventory, San Diego Zoo began the year 2000 with five pairs of Platylophus
g. galericulatus. During the year three young were hatched but failed to
survive, and at the end of the year the zoo had four pairs on exhibition.
Cologne Zoo (Germany) listed this species in 2000 and Vogelpark
Walsrode (Germany) had three in its collection on December 31 st 2000. I
have no information for 2001.
Roland Cristo asks 'Has the Yellow-breasted Cissa Cissa hypoleuca been
bred in England or Europe?' I know it has not been bred in Britain, but am
not sure about in the rest of Europe, does anyone else know?
Daniel Shearing points out that three Yellow-breasted Cissas were sent
to M. Delacour's collection at Cleres in 1927 where the birds carried sticks
but never attempted to nest. Later that year they were given to Alfred Ezra
and nested on several occasions but always produced infertile eggs. The
eggs were similar in size to those of the Blackbird Turdus merula and coloured
white with brown speckling.
The watercolour painting of these birds by Roland Green, like the birds
themselves, has faded in colour over the years. Hence, the scientific name
hypoleuca, which refers to the white breast of the original museum specimens.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995387" page_id="56264392"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
180
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9643255" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264392" page_num="180" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
NEW GUIDE TO PIGEONS AND DOVES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997225605263158" page_id="56264392"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
Of my three favourite bird families, the pheasants, waterfowl and pigeons,
Jean Delacour's monographs (Country Life, 1951 &amp; 1954) have long
provided completely satisfactory reference works for the first two groups.
Derek Goodwin's Pigeons and Doves of the World (British Museum, 1967)
is of at least equal quality, but has only three colour plates, illustrating
diversity within the family, sexual dimorphism, and some comparisons of
juvenile birds with the adults. Excellent line drawings of many species
within the text give an idea of shape and markings, but have limited use for
identification purposes. This left a vacant niche for a book whose colour
plates could serve the same function for pigeons as do Peter Scott's for
waterfowl and J.C. Harrison's for pheasants.
Now, at last, such a book - Pigeons and Doves - A Guide to the Pigeons
and Doves of the World , published by Pica Press has arrived, and in a form
that complements, rather than supercedes, Goodwin's book. David Gibbs
and Eustace Barnes wrote the text, and John Cox and Barnes painted the
illustrations. I can identify the work of these co-illustrators only by the
signature at the bottom of the page, so uniform are their styles and the quality
of their work. Certainly for the species I am familiar with, not only are the
shapes, colours and markings technically accurate, but the painters have
captured the 'jizz' of each bird so that it looks like a living breathing dove.
There is a sense of movement, either arrested or imminent, aesthetically
very satisfying. The colour printing is overall a little on the dark side. The
wing marking of the Crested Bronzewing, for example, appears a deeper
purple than I have ever seen it in life.
Cox or Barnes might have attempted to paint one of the extinct Raphids,
the Dodo or two solitaires. There should be sufficient contemporary
illustrations of the few living Dodos brought to Europe for this to be possible.
However, it is nice to see their family (Raphidae) given the same treatment
in the text as that afforded to the Columbidae, the surviving family of the
order Columbiformes. The Dodo tends to be regarded as some kind of icon
of extinction, having lost its identity as a bird worthy of individual attention.
Almost all 319 pigeon species (except for a very few probably extinct species)
are shown in full colour, as are subspecific and immature plumages.
Relatively few of these species are common in aviculture, and the variety of
colour and form comes as a revelation. It is not so much the range from the
Diamond Dove to the crowned pigeons, as that there are, for example, 36
species of imperial pigeons when one is used to seeing mainly the Pied and
Green, and there are 17 New World quail doves when one is familiar only
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909721" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264393" page_num="181" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998511" page_id="56264393"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
181
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998785540540541" page_id="56264393"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
with the Mountain Witch, or Crested, as it is called here.
In terms of taxonomic classification, the authors cannot be accused of
being 'splitters' on the one hand or 'lumpers' on the other. What have
traditionally been regarded as three subspecies of the Zebra Dove emerge
here as three distinct species. However, the monotypic genus Aplopelia is
absorbed into the genus Columba with the typical pigeons. More
controversially, the Madagascar Turtle-Dove is also placed in this genus,
while to one who has kept and bred it, it seems very much a Streptopelia, if
a slightly 'different' one. Common names are more open to personal
preference than scientific ones. Thus, the authors rename two of the crowned
pigeons - the Blue becomes the Western and Scheepmaker's the Southern.
At first sight I thought the Brush Bronzewing was now the 'Bush'
Bronzewing, but that is just a misprint on the plate, as the text refers to this
bird by its more customary designation.
Approximately a quarter of the book is taken up by the colour plates, the
rest being devoted to the individual treatment of each species, interspersed
with notes on the characteristics of each genus. The comprehensive coverage
of each species comprises: Identification, Voice, Habits, Habitat, Status and
Distribution, Description, Measurements, Geographic Variations and
(particularly useful) References. Alternative names and classification are
also given.
There is little reference to aviculture, except in so far as trade in live
birds is recognised as posing less threat to this group than to parrots. This
reflects the, regrettable perhaps, fact that few field ornithologists are also
aviculturists. However, to have attempted to include avicultural notes as in
Delacour's treatment of pheasants and waterfowl would have considerably
increased the size of the book. It is pointed out that roughly a third of
pigeon species are in some danger of extinction, making this one of the
most threatened bird families. The authors express the hope that '... this
work will make a small contribution towards highlighting the plight of some
of our most beautiful and relatively neglected birds.' In this they have
succeeded admirably.
None of the points I have made constitute adverse criticism. Negative
comment of this attractive and useful book would be difficult to justify. As
well as being invaluable for identification, the notes on diet and behaviour
provide points of reference for anyone who keeps doves. It should be on the
shelf (or better still open in the hands) of every aviculturist, field ornithologist,
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.6712774">
commercial importer and anyone else with an interest in these birds.
Pigeons and Doves - A Guide to the Pigeons and Doves of the World is
published by Pica Press, The Banks, Mountfield, Nr. Robertsbridge, East
Sussex TN32 5JY, UK. It is priced #38.
Philip Schofield
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998633" page_id="56264394"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
182
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9948875" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264394" page_num="182" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
BIRDS OF EAST AFRICA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9821558" page_id="56264394"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
The new Field Guide to the Birds of East Africa has been a long time
coming, I can remember talking and corresponding about it with Terry
Stevenson, co-author with John Fanshawe, as long ago as 1987 or
thereabouts. More recently I attended an illustrated talk at the County
Museum, Truro, here in Cornwall, given by John Gale who, along with
Brian Small and Norman Arlott, painted the illustrations. I admired Ms
tremendous enthusiasm and marvelled at the fact that he had travelled so
widely in East Africa observing, videoing, photographing and sketching so
many of the species for the plates and knowing what publishers pay for
them, wondered how with all this meticulous preparation he managed to
make a living from it! He then revealed that he is also a veterinary surgeon
and between painting birds works as a locum in Devon.
Conscious no doubt of the fact that there are already a number of bird
books covering East Africa, the publishers or authors, looking I guess for a
way to set their guide apart from the others, cover not only Kenya, Tanzania
and Uganda, but also the birds of Rwanda and Burundi. Following the
dozen (12) or so introductory pages and plate showing seven recently
recorded species (two others were recorded too late for inclusion) are 286
plates illustrating 1,388 species, or as stated on the back cover: '3,400 images
illustrating all plumages and major races likely to be encountered. 5 This we
are told amounts to 80% of the species recorded in sub-Saharan Africa. On
the page opposite each plate is the text about each species illustrated on that
plate and a distribution map for each species, with its range shown in red.
The text about each species usually amounts to some nine to 12 lines,
sometimes more sometimes less, covering recognition, habitat and voice.
The plates are in the main outstanding and of an almost uniformily high
standard. I especially like those painted by John Gale. Therefore, it may
perhaps be over critical to say that I was struck by the fact that a number of
perching birds, including some painted by him, are shown seemingly standing
on the ground, which to the unknowing could be misleading; while some of
those painted by Brian Small are shown standing curiously with one foot on
the ground and the other gripping a branch! One of these is the Black-
headed Gonolek (pi. 234), which is a shame as its coloration is to me more
accurate than that of the same species portrayed in Birds of Africa and is
marginally better than that in Birds of Kenya and Northern Tanzania. The
latter though has more accurately coloured illustrations of the Red-headed
Bluebill, Java Sparrow (introduced onto the islands of Zanzibar and Pemba)
and Black-and-white Mannikin which in western Kenya, or at least on the
Cherengani Hills, has a brownish, not jet black mantle. Interestingly,
Stevenson and Fanshawe describe the Java Sparrow as locally common on
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909695" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264395" page_num="183" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999272" page_id="56264395"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
183
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.893368235294118" page_id="56264395"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
Zanzibar and Pemba, whereas the authors of Birds of Kenya and Northern
Tanzania refer to small numbers on Pemba and make no mention of its
status on Zanzibar. I wonder which of them is correct?
It is difficult not to make comparisons between this and the other two
titles mentioned above. However, one covers just Kenya and northern
Tanzania, while the other will eventually consist of seven huge volumes,
the full set costing several hundred pounds (or dollars). Field Guide to the
Birds of East Africa - Kenya Tanzania Uganda Rwanda Burundi , on the
other hand, costs #29.95 (in the UK) and is an out-and-out field guide, albeit
a fairly thick one (just over 600 pages), that has illustrations and descriptions
of the 1,388 species found in this large area of Africa, as well as other parts
of the continent. Male, female, immature and other plumages, including
those of the main subspecies are illustrated and described where appropriate.
Published by T. &amp; A.D. Poyser Ltd., Harcourt Place, 32 Jamestown Road,
London NW1 7BY, UK ( website: www.academicpress.com), it will surely
became one of the popular standard guides for those wishing to identify
African birds.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.141318">
Malcolm Ellis
</subsectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.615872" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264395" page_num="183" year="" vol="">
PERUVIAN BIRDS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97531675" page_id="56264395"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
The Ecotravellers' Wildlife Guide: Peru by David L. Pearson and Les
Beletsky is similar in style/format to the earlier guides in this series, most of
which have been reviewed in the Avicultural Magazine. Therefore, rather
than risk duplicating what has been written previously, I propose to
concentrate on the bird section of this present guide, which is after all what
is likely to be of greatest interest to members.
Plates 20-80, painted by David Beadle, Daniel Lane, David Numey, John
O'Neil and John Sill, illustrate a wide range of species, beginning with
seabirds, among them the Humboldt Penguin and including other waterbirds,
birds of prey, pigeons and doves, parrots (13 species), hummingbirds (20
species), barbets, toucans and aracaris, manakins, tanagers (25 species) and
small seed-eaters. Although intended primarily for tourists and ecotravellers,
this guide could be useful to aviculturists wishing to identify birds from this
part of South America. In addition, it has excellent illustrations of a wide
range of mammals, amphibians, snakes and other creatures.
The Ecotravellers ' Wildlife Guide: Peru by David L. Pearson and Les
Beletsky is published by Academic Press, Harcourt Place, 32 Jamestown
Road, London NWI 7BY, UK and 525 B Street, Suite 1900, San Diego,
California 92101-4495, USA (website: www.academicpress.com). It is
priced #19. 95 in the UK, US$29.95 in the USA and $44. 25 in Canada.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.460094">
Malcolm Ellis
</subsectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99953" page_id="56264396"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
184
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9699755" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264396" page_num="184" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
UK BREEDINGS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995728210526316" page_id="56264396"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
The Oasis Hummingbird Rhodopis vesper has been bred by Bob McWha,
who lives in Merseyside, here in the UK. According to the report in the UK
weekly journal Cage &amp; Aviary Birds ( November 3rd, 2001), Bob McWha
bought his first pair in 1992, and it is the male from that pair, which he has
had for nine years, and a female that he got from the same dealer five years
ago that have produced the youngster. After a number of infertile eggs over
the past five years, the chick was reared from the pair's third clutch of eggs
this year. Bob McWha puts his success down to the fact that he provides his
birds with a stress-free environment and feeds them on his homemade nectar
which is very similar to that used by Rod Elgar.
It is almost certainly the UK first breeding, though not the first European
breeding, it having previously been bred in 1985 by Maria and Willi Hesse
in Germany, and an account was published in Die Gefiederte 4: 94-96 (1986).
In the same issue of Cage &amp; Aviary Birds , Rosemary Low described the
breeding of the Verditer Flycatcher Muscicapa thalassina at Paradise Park,
Hayle, Cornwall. The pair has been in the collection for over 10 years, but
it was not until last year that four infertile eggs were laid. This year two
young were hatched and hand-reared by Dale Jackson. It seems that this
flycatcher has been bred in the UK at least once or twice before, but the
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.458641" page_id="56264396"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
Paradise Park breeding is the first published account.
* * *
CHICKS OF ENDANGERED OWL REARED
Two Ashy-faced Owl chicks Tyto glaucops have been hand-reared at
Muncaster Castle, near Ravenglass, Cumbria, home of the World Owl Trust.
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.84698975" page_id="56264396"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
The Ashy-faced Owl or Ashy-faced Barn Owl (formerly regarded as a
subspecies of the Barn Owl T. alba ) is an endangered species confined to
Hispaniola and the tiny island of Tortuga in the Caribbean, where habitat
loss and competition for territories and nest sites from the bigger and stronger
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.56589">
North American Bam Owl T. a. pratincola are the main threats to its survival.
The World Owl Trust's birds are part of a breeding programme for T.
glaucops, started in Germany by SCRO (Society for Conservation and
Research of Owls) and supported in the UK by the World Owl Trust and the
International Owl Society. The Dominican Republic Owl Conservation
Project recently completed two aviaries to house this species at the Parque
Zoologico Nacional, Santo Domingo, capital of the Dominican Republic.
* * *
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700196" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264397" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996406" page_id="56264397"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
185
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.979285" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264397" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
ENDANGERED PARROT COUNT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9235624" page_id="56264397"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
On Big Parrot Day 2001 in South Africa, a total of 358 Cape Parrots
Poicephalus rohustus were counted during the morning, and 319 during the
afternoon. Not all of the forests were covered by the census, but in future
years increased coverage of forest patches is planned, especially in parts of
the former Transkei.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.6715665" page_id="56264397"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
* * *
MYNAH PROBLEMS
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.967286444444445" page_id="56264397"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
Concern has been expressed about the increasing number of Common
or Indian Mynahs Acridotheres tristis occurring in and around South Africa's
Kruger National Park, and whether they may be carrying parasites or diseases
that may affect the indigenous species. A 12-month study by the Australian
Museum and University of Wollongong has found that the Common or Indian
Mynah is found now in 80% of backyards and gardens across Sydney,
Australia. Even more significant to the future well-being of smaller garden
birds may be the spread of the native Noisy Miner Manorina melanocephala,
which is found now in 89% of gardens in the northern suburbs of Sydney.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.834621" page_id="56264397"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.971919" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264397" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
ANOTHER FIRST BREEDING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9913238" page_id="56264397"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
In 1994, San Diego Wild Animal Park received from Malaysia's Zoo
Negara two pairs of Storm's Stork Ciconia stormi (previously regarded as
the eastern subspecies of the Woolly-necked Stork C. episcopus). Storm's
is the second rarest stork in the world (the rarest is the Greater Adjutant
Leptoptilos dubius ), with only an estimated 300-1,000 of these elusive storks,
confined to the forest swamps and rivers of Malaysia, Borneo, Sumatra and
Thailand. They were sent to the Zoological Society of San Diego because
of its stork-breeding expertise. Now, after a long wait, four chicks have
been hatched from two clutches of eggs. It is the first breeding of this rare
stork in North America.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.514173" page_id="56264397"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.6092275" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264397" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
EXOTICS CONFERENCE
ICE2002 KEY WEST fourth annual international conference on exotics,
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.660281" page_id="56264397"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
will take place June 19th-22nd, at Wyndham Casa Marina Resort, Key West,
Florida. Further information is available by writing to: PO. Box 541749,
Lake Worth, Florida 33454-1749, USA. Tel: 800-946-4782/Fax: 561-641-
0234/Website: www.EXOTICDVM.com
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999363" page_id="56264398"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
186
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.982634" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264398" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
HIGH-ALTITUDE PARROTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993654818181818" page_id="56264398"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
Emu Vol. 101, No. 3, 2001, Journal of the Royal Australasian
Ornithologists Union, includes a paper by K. David Bishop and Darryl N.
Jones on the montane avifauna of West New Britain, with special reference
to the Nakanai Mountains. Where daily they observed large aggregations
of Rainbow Lorikeets Trichoglossus haematodus massena together with Red-
chinned Lorikeets Charmosyna rubrigularis, feeding at large trees that bore
masses of yellow flowers. The authors heard and/or observed the Red-
chinned Lorikeets in numbers of about 10-60, feeding at the flowering canopy
trees or in noisy parties flying over the canopy, usually towards the summit.
At higher altitudes the Red-chinned Lorikeet appears to generally replace
the Red-flanked Lorikeet C. placentis, which occurs in the lowlands.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.66386" page_id="56264398"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
* * *
PRIDE OF PLACE
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.9896096" page_id="56264398"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
Occupying pride of place at Mareeba Tropical Savanna and Wetland
Reserve visitor centre is an aviary, sponsored by the Australian Geographic
Society, housing a breeding group of 27 Gouldian Finches Erythrura
gouldiae. The Gouldian used to be common across the grasslands of northern
Australia from Mareeba to the Kimberley but, since the 1960s has been in
danger of extinction, and reserve staff hope to some time in the future release
some into the reserve situated 50km (approx. 31 miles) west of Cairns.
Five years ago, this area close to the northern tip of the Cape York
Peninsula was dry cattle scrub, destined to be logged and split into mango
orchards and sugarcane plantations. However, the soil proved unsuitable
for intensive farming, and the local community backed the idea of using
surplus irrigation water to convert the land into a nature reserve, bird
sanctuary and tourist venture.
Twelve lagoons were constructed, connected by creeks and channels set
in 12 hectares (approx. 30 acres) of dry woodland, and the area has quickly
become a wildlife paradise. One hundred and seventy-seven species of birds
have been recorded, including the Great (White) Egret Ardea alba , Black-
necked Stork Ephippiorhynchus asiaticus, Wandering Whistling Duck
Dendrocygna arcuata, Radjah Shelduck Tadorna radjah, Brolga Grus
rubicundus, Sarus Crane G. antigone, Comb-crested Ja#ana Irediparra
gallinacea and Red-tailed Black Cockatoo Calyptorhynchus banksii.
The lagoons are already the most important Brolga roosting and nesting
sites in the region. Freshwater crocodiles breed in some of the channels,
and a release pen has been established for kangaroos and wallabiesnursed
back to health or reared by local volunteers.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.699913" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264399" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995649" page_id="56264399"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
187
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.966778" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264399" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
PIGEON PAIR
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.96631075" page_id="56264399"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
Neville Brickell of the Indigenous Bird Breeders' Research Group in
South Africa, reports what may be the first recorded colour mutations of the
Cape Turtle Dove Streptopelia capicola. Chris Luther, a bird judge and
White and wild or normal type Cape Turtle Dove
pigeon and dove breeder for many years, has bred both white and fawn
mutations of this species. In each clutch, one of the nestlings is of the wild
or normal type and the other is either white or fawn. The white or fawn bird
is always female and the wild or normal type is always male.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.739750666666667" page_id="56264399"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
* * *
TWO IN A NEST
Also from Neville Brickell, the photo below, taken in South Africa by
Brian Buchanan, shows the nest with two eggs of a pair of Three-banded
Plovers Charadrius tricollis, which has been commandeered by a pair of
Brian Buchanan
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.5126085" page_id="56264399"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
Nest containing eggs of Blacksmith Plover (top)
and Three-banded Plover
Blacksmith Plovers Vanellus armatus, which has laid its two eggs alongside
those of the Three-banded species.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998774" page_id="56264400"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
188
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.864412" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264400" page_num="188" year="" vol="">
CONTRIBUTORS TO VOLUME 107 - 2001
BOCKHEIM, Greg
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8760815" page_id="56264400"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
The moulting cycle of the African Jaqana Actophilornis africanus
in aviculture. 115
BOHLMAN, Nicole R.
An examination of potential reasons for variation in egg-laying
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.936203954545455" page_id="56264400"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
cycles of Wattled Cranes............4
BRICKELL, Neville
Collated data on the Timor Sparrow Padda or Lonchura fuscata ... 121
CLEETON, P. J.
Breeding the House Crow Corvus splendens .......... 149
COLES, Dave
Additions and corrections to UK first breeding records.... 125
de RUITER, Maarten
Breeding the Red &amp; Yellow Barbet in captivity ...49
ELLIS, Malcolm
Last of the great collectors. 105
GIBSON, Les
Birds in a desert garden...... 157
GREGSON, Jo
Breeding the Papuan Wreathed Hombill Aceros plicatus at Paignton
Zoo Environmental Park, England.... 165
HEWSTON, Nigel
The Omei Shan Liocichla Liocichla omeiensis . 109
HINZE, Ian
Breeding the Mali or Kulikoro Firefinch Lagonosticta virata ....27
LOW, Rosemary
Breeding the Grey-winged Trumpeter Psophia crepitans ...21
</figure>
<page confidence="0.999018" page_id="56264401"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
189
</page>
<table confidence="0.926657047619047" page_id="56264401"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
CONTRIBUTORS TO VOLUME 107 - 2000 ( Cont'd)
PYPER, Stewart
The Autumn Social Meeting........38
The President's Garden Party ..........36
The Spring Social Meeting.......... 35
ROSE, Kelly and HOPKINS, Caitlyn
Do vitamins A and E have an impact in the fertility of Humboldt
Penguins Spheniscus humholdti . 165
SAWYER, R. C. J.
Breeding the Blue-bellied Roller....... 1
Notes from Cobham .......97
SCHOFIELD, Philip
Necklaced and other laughing thrushes... .152
Observations on seed-eating pigeons........53
SIMPSON, Nigel
Breeding the Victoria Crowned Pigeon at Bristol Zoo Gardens.76
SMITH, Chris
The Andean Tinamou Nothoprocta pentlandii in captivity. 62
SONTAG, Walter A. Jr.
Notes on behaviour and ecological requirements of the
Rothschild's Mynah Leucopsar rothschildi ..... 10
</table>
<reference confidence="0.5646778">
WAINE, J.
Pathology and diseases of touracos ....100
WILKINSON, Roger
Blue-eyed Cockatoos in New Britain...146
Chester Zoo Bird Review 2000 ... 69
</reference>
<page confidence="0.995687" page_id="56264402"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
190
</page>
<table confidence="0.880819148148148" page_id="56264402"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
INDEX TO VOLUME 107 - 2001
Aceros plicatus, breeding . 165
Actophilornis africanus, moult cycle in aviculture. 115
Barbet, Red &amp; Yellow, breeding in captivity...49
Birds, in a desert garden..... 157
Book Reviews
A Guide to. . . Popular Conures... 136
Australian Action Plan 2000.88
Birds of Africa, Volume VI...87
Diseases of Free-Range Poultry.85
Ecotravellers'Wildlife Guide: Alaska ........ 137
Ecotravellers' Wildlife Guide: Ecuador and its Galapagos Islands ... 89
Ecotravellers' Wildlife Guide: Hawaii. ...41
Ecotravellers' Wildlife Guide: Peru... 183
Field Guide to the Birds of East Africa........ 182
Pigeons and Doves of the World...180
Portfolio of Cockatoos.......89
Threatened Birds of the World...39
Who Killed the Great Auk?.......86
Bugeranus carunculatus, variations in egg-laying cycles.4
Cacatua ophthalmica, in New Britain..146
Cobham, notes from..... 97
Cockatoo, Blue-eyed, in New Britain. 146
Collectors, last of the great, Fred Shaw Mayer... 105
Coracias cyanogaster , breeding. 1
Corvus splendens, breeding. 149
Council Meetings...48 &amp; 177
</table>
<reference confidence="0.9591294">
Crane, Wattled, potential reasons for variations in egg-laying cycles.4
Crow, House, breeding. 149
Firefinch, Mali or Kulikoro, breeding.27
Garrulax monileger, pectoralis and others. 152
Goura victoria , breeding at Bristol Zoo Gardens.76
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998748" page_id="56264403"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
191
</page>
<table confidence="0.92321325" page_id="56264403"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
INDEX TO VOLUME 107 - 2001 (Cont'd)
Hornbill, Papuan Wreathed or Blyth's, breeding........165
Ja^ana, African, moult cycle in aviculture... 115
Laughing Thrushes, necklaced and others......152
Leucopsar rothschildi, behaviour and ecological requirements .. 10
Leucopsar rothschildi, correction to above...124
Liocichla, Omei Shan, notes on........... 109
Liocichla omeiensis, notes on....... 109
Lonehura fuseata (see also Padda fuscata below)..........121
Mynah, Rothschild's, behaviour and ecological requirements.10
News &amp; Views....... 42,91,139,184
Nothoprocta pentlandii, in captivity........ 62
Obituaries.......... 47,95
Officers and Council (as from October 24th 2001)..... 145
Padda fuscata, collated data on.......... 121
Penguin, Humboldt, do vitamins A &amp; E affect fertility? .. 167
Pigeons, observations on seed-eating species ....... 53
Pigeon, Victoria Crowned, breeding at Bristol Zoo Gardens ... 76
President's Garden Party 2000 ........ 36
Psophia crepitans, breeding........21
</table>
<reference confidence="0.715696583333333">
Roller, Blue-bellied, breeding ............ 1
Social Meeting, Autumn............ 36
Social Meeting, Spring.......... 35
Sparrow, Timor, collated data on..... 121
Spheniscus humboldti, do vitamins A &amp; E affect fertilty?.. 167
Starling, Bali (see Rothschild's Mynah).....10
Tinamou, Andean, in captivity........ 62
Touracos, pathology and diseases.....100
Trachyphonus erythrocephalus, breeding in captivity.49
Trumpeter, Grey-winged, breeding.....21
UK first breeding records, additions and corrections .. 125
Zoo, Chester, Bird Review 2000 ...... 69
</reference>
<page confidence="0.983902" page_id="56264404"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
192
</page>
<figure confidence="0.970497333333333" page_id="56264404"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
STRAIGHTS
Brown Perilla Seed #2.50 kg #11.50 5kg
Black Lettuce Seed #5.50 kr
Blue Maw
Buckwheat
Canary Seed
Chillies
Chicory Seed
Fonio Paddy
#2.50 kg
#1.50 kg
#1.50 kg
#4.95 5kg
#5.50 5kg
#2.50 500g #5.00 kg
#3.50 kg #15.00 5kg
#6.95 500g #13.00 kg
Fresh Water Shrimps #5.00 500g #9.50 kg
German Thistle #4.50 kg #8.50 2.5kg
#1.50 kg
#1.50 kg
#4.00 500g #15 2.5kg
#1.00 kg #4.50 5kg
Groats
Flemp Seed
Juniper Berries
Linseed
M. Sprays Chinese #1.50 kg
M. Sprays French #2.50 kg
Mountain Ash
Niger Seed
Paddy Rice
Pine Seed Small
Plantain
Safflower
Sesame Seed
Sunflower Striped
#7.00 5kg
#11.75 5kg
#3.25 500g #12.50 2.5.k
#2.50 kg
#1.50 kg
#3.00 500g #6.00 kg
#4.00 500g #8.00 kg
#1.50 kg
#2.50 kg
#1.95 kg
Sunflower Kemals #2.95 kg
Teasel Seed #4.50 500g #9.00 kg
White Penlla Seed #3.00 kg #13.50 5kg
Whole Rosehips #2.50 500g #5.00 kg
STRAIGHTS
EGGFOODS
SOFTBILL DIETS
LIVEFOODS
PARROT MIXTURES
NECTARS
VITAMINS &amp;
SUPPLEMENTS
PARROT PREMIUM (Witte Molen ) or
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.930438" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264404" page_num="192" year="" vol="">
HARVEY'S LARGE PARROT SPECIAL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99678275" page_id="56264404"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
A completely new mix for 2002 which we
formulated for our own birds with over 30
# 12.00 2.5kg ingredients such as: Exotic fruits, nuts out of shell,
#ii.505kg Mountain ash berries, Elder berries, Rosehips,
Cedamuts, Banana pieces, Pumpkin seeds, Blue
raisins but to name a few. Designed for the larger
parrots and does not have so many of the smaller
seeds of the parrot premium mix.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.965555294117647" page_id="56264404"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
lkg #2.00 5kg #8.00 15kg #19.75
30kg for only #35 (Can be 15kg of each)
EGG FOODS FROM WITTE MOLEN
Wimo Moist Eggfood 1kg #3.00 5 kg Tub #14.25
Egg Rearing Food With Herbs 5 kg Tub #15.50
Wimo Eggfood Red lkg # 3.65 5kg Tub #15.50
Egg Rearing Food With Insects 5kg Tub #16.50
SOFTBILL FOODS
Softbill Food With Fruit 5kg Tub #16.25
Universal Food lkg #3.45 5kg Tub #14.25
Softfood with 30% Insects 3.5 kg Tub #19.00
Avi-Plus Softbill Pellets 1 kg #3.95 5kg #13.95
LIVEFOOD (All species available)
Mealworms lkg (2.21bs) #14.95 2kg(4.41bs) #26.95
5kg (11 lbs) #41.96 10kg(221bs) #72.34
MiniM. 50g (1.libs) #13.95 lkg (2.2Ibs) #24.95
All Livefoods prices include delivery
</table>
<figure confidence="0.941200444444444" page_id="56264404"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
#5.00 5kg
#8.00 5kg
#9.50 5kg
#4.95 5kg
#4.95 S kg
#10.00 5kg
#6.00 5kg
#10.00 5kg
P&amp;P only #4.95 up to 45kg. For our advice helpline, free fact sheets or information on
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.7381424">
our ever expanding range ofproducts please contact Rob Harvey Specialist Feeds,
Kookaburra House, Gravel Hill Road, Holt Pound, Famham, Surrey, GU10 4LG.
Tel: 01420 23986 Fax: 01420 23078 E-mail: rob@robharvey.com
Or go to our massive website with over 1100 world wide links!
_ www: robharvey.com _
</reference>
<affiliation confidence="0.535055">
Handbook of the
</affiliation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996443" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264405" page_num="" year="" vol="">
BIRDS OF THE WORL D
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9936755" page_id="56264405"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The first series to cover and illustrate
every bird species.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.484673333333333" page_id="56264405"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Woodpeckers
%
due out in April 2002
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.98485875" page_id="56264405"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
With the publication of Volume 7 (Jacamars to Woodpeckers) all
non-passerines will be covered in the Handbook series.
Over 600 pages, 69 colour plates and more than 300 photographs
depicting all jacamars, puffbirds, barbets, honeyguides, toucans
and woodpeckers.
Great pre-publication offer expires 31 st March 2002
Lynx Edicions, Montseny, 8, E-08193 Bellaterra, Barcelona, Spain
Tel. +34 93 594 77 10 Fax. +34 93 592 09 69 E-mail: lynx@hbw.com
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.861223" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264405" page_num="" year="" vol="">
PROTRACTED PROCEDURE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997608142857143" page_id="56264405"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
According to a report in The Times (December 10th) there have been
several exchanges of letters between the Brazilian Embassy in London and
the British Government and even an official note sent to the Foreign Office,
concerning the extraordinary length of time being taken to return to Brazil
three Lear's Macaws Anodorhynchus leari seized from Harry Sissen in April
1998 (see News &amp; Views, Vol. 106, No.2, p.90, No.3, p. 136 andNo.4, inside
back cover).
Boris Johnson MP raised the matter with the Attorney-General and also
the Treasury Minister responsible for Customs and Excise, and demanded
speedy repatriation of the birds. A customs spokesman said the government
wishes to return the birds to Brazil but does not yet have legal ownership of
them. Adding that Customs has to apply to the Crown Court for custody of
anything that is seized and this can be a protracted procedure.
There is a blue macaws website: www.bluemacaws.org
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.966225" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264406" page_num="" year="" vol="">
SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION LIBRARIES
</sectionHeader>
<address confidence="0.291082">
3 908
01769 6444
</address>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.473356" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56264406" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.966287076923077" page_id="56264406"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society.145
Blue-eyed Cockatoos in New Britain
by Roger Wilkinson.146
Breeding the House Crow Corvus splendens
by R J. Cleeton.149
Necklaced and other Laughing Thrushes
by Philip Schofield.152
Birds in a Desert Garden
by Les Gibson.157
Breeding the Papuan Wreathed Hombill Aceros plicatus at
Paignton Zoo Environmental Park, England
by Jo Gregson.165
Do Vitamins A and E have an impact on the fertility
of Humboldt Penguins Spheniscus humboldtil
by Kelly Rose and Caitlyn Hopkins.167
Council Meeting.177
Letters to the Editor.179
Book Reviews
New Guide to Pigeons and Doves.180
Birds of East Africa.182
Peruvian Birds.183
News &amp; Views.184
Contributors to Volume 107 - 2001 ... 188
Index to Volume 107 - 2001 .190
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</table>
</algorithms>
