<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.9108945" page_id="56256332"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
QL-
Z^VICULTURAL^
MAGAZINE ( " 13 wt2 ).
VOLUME 117
No. 3
2011
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990762" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256333" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.96460475" page_id="56256333"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2011: British Isles #21.00:
Overseas #24.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the
Society later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of
the AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.687655" page_id="56256333"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, SHERATON LODGE, STATION ROAD, SOUTHMINSTER,
ESSEX CM0 7EW, UK.
</construct>
<bodyText confidence="0.94756275" page_id="56256333"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Barclays Bank, Burnham-on-Crouch Branch. Please
quote Account No. 13296954, Sort Code 20 54 30, and ensure you send your
name as the account reference, or else we cannot match payments. In case
of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and Treasurer at the address
above, or e-mail: otusscops@talktalk.net
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have not
been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of a
particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history. Articles
should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the scientific
names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given. References
cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line drawings,
black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular point in
the article will be used where possible and should be clearly captioned. If
authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when submitting the
article and write their name on the back of each photograph. Tables and
graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be aware of
the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of the page
which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997594" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56256333" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982475333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.802296" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256334" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.279434" page_id="56256334"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 117 - No. 3 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2011
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.962737" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256334" page_num="" year="" vol="">
VISUALLY SEXING THE SENEGAL PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<keyword confidence="0.463598">
Poicephalus senegalus
</keyword>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.825872333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256334" page_num="" year="" vol="">
TOGETHER WITH AN EXAMPLE OF SOCIAL
BREEDING BEHAVIOUR BY THIS SPECIES
by Paolo Bertagnolio
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99571352" page_id="56256334"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
A reliable way of visually sexing the Senegal Parrot Poicephalus
senegalus linked to the colour of the under tail-coverts - those of the male
being yellow or almost completely yellow and those of the female being
green or yellowish-green - was, to my knowledge, mentioned first by Silva
(1991), but was subsequently ignored in later ornithological literature by,
for example, Borrow &amp; Demey (2001), Collar in del Hoyo et al. (1997),
Forshaw (2006) and Juniper &amp; Parr (1998), etc.
A few years ago I realised there is another easy way to distinguish
between the male and female adult Senegal Parrot. With the male, the green
of the chest ends in a V-shaped pattern which barely reaches the abdomen 1 ,
whereas with the female the green extends down to the lower abdomen
and between the legs. On the internet, an author wrote recently that: "The
V-shape of the vest is usually longer in females, the green area extending
down over the chest to between the legs, whereas in males the tip of the
green area ends midway down the chest." 1 go along with this, but would
exclude the word "usually."
Here in the northern hemisphere the Senegal Parrot tends to breed during
the winter months. At the Centro per lo Studio e la Conservazione degli
Psittaciformi (CSCP) here in Italy, the female of a pair of the orange-bellied
form P. s. versteri, for years ignored the nest box and laid in December or
January in a hole she excavated in the ground. If not removed just after
hatching, the chicks invariably died when only one or two days old.
l The bird belonging to the nominate form depicted by Bill Cooper in
Parrots of the World by Cooper &amp; Forshaw (Doubleday &amp; Company, Inc.,
1973) fits this description and is shown to be an adult male.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999506" page_id="56256335"  page_num="98" year="" vol="">
98
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.829228" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256335" page_num="98" year="" vol="">
BERTAGNOLIO - SENEGAL PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.983221285714286" page_id="56256335"  page_num="98" year="" vol="">
At the beginning of 2009, the pair was moved to a different flight in
which for the first time the female laid in June in a conventional nest box
and successfully raised four young, which were left with their parents in
an attempt to discourage the pair from nesting again during the winter. In
February 2010, however, much to my surprise there were seven birds in the
flight and, on checking in the nest box, I discovered a further two chicks
ready to fledge. During the following three or four weeks the group was kept
under close observation from some distance, through a pair of binoculars,
and on two occasions I witnessed one of the freshly fledged young, easily
recognised by its almost completely green underparts, being fed by one of
its siblings that had hatched the previous year.
No doubt the presence of so many birds in the nest box during the cold
winter nights (when the temperature occasionally dropped to -1.7*C to
-2.2*C (29*F-28*F) ) helped to generate sufficient warmth to prevent the
freshly hatched chicks becoming chilled. Considering the size of the nest
box, which measured 18cm x 18cm (Tin x Tin) square, the young from 2009
and their parents, must have had to move around very cautiously, so as not
to damage the eggs or trample on the freshly hatched chicks. Whether the
cooperation of the 2009 young extended to assisting with the incubation of
the eggs and/or the care of the chicks while they remained in the nest, must
remain a matter of conjecture.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.796282" genericHeader="references" page_id="56256335" page_num="98" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.981577533333333" page_id="56256335"  page_num="98" year="" vol="">
Borrow, N. and Demey, R. 2001. Field Guide to the Birds of Western Africa. Christopher
Helm, London.
Collar, N. J. Family Psittacidae. In:del Hoyo, L, Elliot, A. and Sargatal, J. (eds.). 1997.
Handbook of the Birds of the World . Volume 4 - Sandgrouse to Cuckoos. Lynx Editions,
Barcelona.
Forshaw, J. M. 2006. Parrots of the World - An Identification Guide. Princeton University
Press, Princeton, New Jersey, USA.
Juniper, T. and Parr. M. 1998. Parrots - A Guide to Parrots of the World. Pica Press, East
Sussex.
Silva, T. 1991. Psittaculture: The Breeding, Rearing &amp; Management of Parrots. Silvio
Mattacchione &amp; Co., Ontario.
It would be interesting to hear from any members who keep and breed
the Senegal Parrot, and also anyone who keeps and breeds the Hawk-headed
Parrot Deroptcyus accipitrinus (see Vol.117, No. 2, p.51 (2011)), whether
their observations confirm the author s findings. - Ed.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997951" page_id="56256336"  page_num="99" year="" vol="">
99
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.797163" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256336" page_num="99" year="" vol="">
LORIKEET EXHIBITS IN UK ZOOS
by Rosemary Low
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.979382783783784" page_id="56256336"  page_num="99" year="" vol="">
I bought my first lories in 1971 and have specialised in these birds ever
since. Indeed, my oldest bird, a Yellow-streaked Lory Chalcopsitta sintillata ,
which has now been with me for more than 35 years, originates from that
decade. As Curator of Birds at Loro Parque, Tenerife, and Palmitos Park,
Gran Canaria, during the late 1980s and 1990s, I was very fortunate to have
in my care almost every species of lory in aviculture, excluding certain
Australian species which were not permitted to be exported.
I have seen the popularity of lories and lorikeets in aviculture rise and
fall like a big dipper. In the late 1970s, when many species were imported
commercially for the first time, they reached the height of popularity.
However, in the late 1980s and early 1990s, when dealers brought in large
numbers of wild-caught birds at low prices, many breeders sold up. The
birds went to dealers who sold them abroad. Gradually the numbers in the
UK fell to the low level of the current decade.
In the early 1990s, some zoos in the USA followed the example of San
Diego Zoo and set up lorikeet exhibits where the public could feed the birds,
which would descend onto their hands to take nectar from tiny pots. The
public bought this food and as a result the idea that money can be made from
such exhibits gradually spread to the UK. New lorikeet exhibits, usually with
Rainbow (Swainson's) Lorikeets Trichoglossus haematodus moluccanus or
Green-naped Lorikeets I h. haematodus , are still being opened.
Unfortunately, some of these leave a lot to be desired. It seems that
lorikeets are being exploited - the commercial aspect apparently taking
priority over proper management. As an example of good management,
Paradise Park in Cornwall can hardly be bettered. Indeed, staff from other
lorikeet exhibits have visited Paradise Park to learn the correct method.
This approach is to be recommended, especially if they act on what they
have learned.
Source of stock
Quarantine methods
There are some important lessons that need to be learned by any zoo that
is considering opening a lorikeet exhibit. At Paradise Park, Curator David
Woolcock had the good sense to set up pairs of Rainbow and Green-naped
Lorikeets wel 1 in advance of the exhibit opening and to breed the required
birds. Indeed, from the initial 10 Rainbow Lorikeets acquired from a UK
breeder in 2004, well over 60 young have been reared. These young are used
in the exhibit, not the breeding pairs. The advantage was that the birds were
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.968693" page_id="56256337"  page_num="100" year="" vol="">
100
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.433358" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256337" page_num="100" year="" vol="">
LOW - LORIKEETS IN UK ZOOS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993424153846154" page_id="56256337"  page_num="100" year="" vol="">
known to be healthy and could be trained to take food from an early age.
The disadvantage was that large numbers were not available initially.
What other zoos have done when seeking to open a lorikeet exhibit is
enquire about how many birds were available from UK breeders and. finding
that sufficient numbers could not be acquired from a single source, at least
three UK zoos acquired birds from a dealer in the Netherlands. These birds
had come from various collections. The result was that these zoos received
birds that tested positive for PBFD (psittacine beak and feather disease)
and/or polyomaviras. One zoo decided to euthanase all these birds. In the
same quarantine space, however, there were at least eight birds from a reliable
breeder in the UK. They were in perfect health, but they too were euthaeased.
The breeder was devastated to leam this. A zoo should know better than to
bring in birds before another group has completed its quarantine.
At another UK zoo
At another UK zoo, when several of its newly arrived birds tested
positive for PBFD, it was decided to manage the flock as if it is in permanent
quarantine. Keepers who look after these birds do not enter the aviaries of
other birds, use foot dips at the entrance and change their boots and overalls
when they clean out the lorikeet exhibit. It is to be hoped that none of these
lorikeets will be allowed to leave the collection. I suspect that even disease
testing is not adequate to identify diseased birds that could unknowingly
be sold, because it depends on birds shedding the virus at the time they are
tested.
Several lorikeets at this zoo died within the first two months and on
autopsy were found to have the adenovirus. The risk involved in bringing
in lorikeets that have not been blood tested for disease cannot be overstated.
Refusal to buy birds that have not been disease-tested does at least send out
a message to the seller that the disease risk is being taken seriously.
Feeding of lorikeets in zoo exhibits
Another serious concern is that relating to the quality of food offered to
the lorikeets. In one case, the manager of a lorikeet exhibit admitted that
the birds were not in good feather and the breeding results were very poor.
On enquiring about the food, I understood why. They were being fed a
commercial product of inferior quality. Unfortunately, many lorikeets are fed
this food because it is one of the least expensive and most readily available
in the UK. Good quality lory foods are not cheap.
At Paradise Park an excellent mixture is made from a variety of nutritious
ingredients and the staff there will readily share the recipe with anyone who
enquires.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.279377" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256338" page_num="101" year="" vol="">
LOW - LORIKEETS IN UK ZOOS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999278" page_id="56256338"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
101
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.977447416666667" page_id="56256338"  page_num="101" year="" vol="">
Does profit come first?
Despite the disease problems, the poor feather condition of the birds and
poor breeding results, the management of one lory exhibit was delighted
because it had proved extremely profitable through the sale of pots of nectar.
I would appeal to all zoos that keep these delightful birds in walk-through
aviaries to consider the welfare of their lorikeets first. Some zoos are doing
a great disservice to lory keeping in the UK and to aviculture in general by
entrusting these birds to the care of inadequately trained staff who often do
not understand their requirements and whose superiors have not taken the
trouble to find out what these birds need.
Warning
Lories and lorikeets are among the most aggressive birds and cannot
normally be kept in a colony. The two subspecies mentioned are exceptions.
Some zoos have, despite advice to the contrary, set up exhibits using several
lory species - because it looks more colourful. This is irresponsible because
it inevitably ends in deaths.
One zoo claims that young birds of various species can be kept together.
This is another myth because even young lorikeets will kill those of another
species. It saddens me greatly at a time when the numbers of lories and
lorikeets in aviculture are declining that they are misused in this way - to
say nothing of terrified birds being hounded and attacked by others and
fatally injured.
Conclusion
Those considering opening lorikeet exhibits need to think long-term.
The recommended procedure is to acquire young pairs and set them up for
breeding - one pair per aviary - and use the young in the exhibit. These
young birds will be much easier to train to take food from the public than
birds (often of unknown age) acquired from a dealer. Even more importantly,
this eliminates the risk of starting the exhibit with diseased birds.
The sixth annual Lory Conference, which was organised by Rosemary
and Ventura Events and held at Twycross Zoo in Warwickshire on June 12th,
was attended by 51 enthusiasts and was a great success. If you have any
questions about keeping and breeding lories and lorikeets and, specifically
about their diets, lam sure that Rosemary or David Woolcockwill be pleased
to answer your questions.
E-mail .-rosemary. low@virgin. net/david@paradisepark. org. uk - Ed.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999011" page_id="56256339"  page_num="102" year="" vol="">
102
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.758722" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256339" page_num="102" year="" vol="">
THE CHESTNUT-BACKED THRUSH Zoothera dohertyi
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.973737552631579" page_id="56256339"  page_num="102" year="" vol="">
by Gary Bralsford
The Chestnut-backed Thrush Zoothera dohertyi is an Indonesian species
found on the Lesser Sunda islands of Lombok, Sumbawa, Sumba and Flores
and in west Timor. It inhabits primary forest, mist forest and woodland, and
can also be found in mountainous regions up to l,050m-2,300m (approx.
3,500ft-7,500ft) above sea level. It is said to be quite common on Flores,
but rare in other areas. It is usually found living alone, with the male and
female coming together only during the breeding season, which is from
August-early September, especially on Flores.
I purchased my first pair of these thrushes in February 2002. I obtained
the pair from Dave Armer in Preston and the following year succeeded in
breeding this species. It was the first time that the Chestnut-backed Thrush
had been bred in the UK. My account of the breeding along with a photo of
an adult bird was published in Vol.109, No.4, pp. 150-153 (2003).
It is not an easy species to sex and DNA sexing is the most reliable way
of ensuring that you have a true pair. Having kept a number of pairs of this
species, however, and having since 2003 bred 26 young, I believe, I can
now spot slight differences between the male and female. Males, I have
noticed, are more brown than chestnut on the back. Females are larger and
have more white on the belly, as well as being more chestnut on the back.
I have heard it said by some breeders that nestlings can differ, with males
being black and females being pink, but I have never noticed this.
There were not many Chestnut-backed Thrushes in the UK in 2002.
There were just a few aviculturists mostly with single unpaired birds.
Apparently, Dave Campbell had brought in several pairs in 2001 and, in
2003, a small number were imported from a dealer in Germany. Through
my friend Bob Jewiss, I managed to obtain a further two birds to pair with
those I had already bred.
I later sold some of my birds to Bob Jewiss and also sold a pair to Jim
Jerrard. The latter described his mixed fortunes breeding this species in
Vol. 113, No.4, p. 156 (2007). One or two zoos and bird gardens had Chestnut-
backed Thrushes, but were often uncertain as to the sex of their birds. Andrew
Owen, when he was at Waddesdon Manor Aviary, bought two of the young
I had bred, to pair with birds they had at Waddesdon. These pairings were
successful and further young were bred there and a Special Interest Group
was established by Andrew, who collated breeding results and put breeders
in contact with each other to arrange exchanges and pair-up single birds.
Andrew is, of course, now Curator of Birds at Chester Zoo and, because of
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.386077" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256340" page_num="103" year="" vol="">
BRALSFORB - CHESTNUT-BACKED THRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999684" page_id="56256340"  page_num="103" year="" vol="">
103
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99255487804878" page_id="56256340"  page_num="103" year="" vol="">
his increased work load, has had to stand down as Coordinator of the Special
Interest Group for the Chestnut-backed Thrush. The Avicultural Society
Special Interest Group is now being coordinated by Jamie Graham, who is
also running an ESB (European Studbook) for this species. I coordinate a
similar group for the Foreign Softbill Society UK (FSSUK).
Several other collections, including Chester Zoo and the Burrell Wildlife
Conservation Trust (Jersey Zoo), along with private aviculturists such as
Raymond Sawyer, Phil Lewis on the Isle of Wight and Bob Jewiss, keep
and breed this species. The Foreign Bird Federation (FBF) Register of Birds
Bred in the UK under Controlled Conditions , covering the period 2005-2008,
shows that six were recorded as having been bred in the UK in 2005, 21 in
2006, 48 in 2007 and 64 in 2008.
There is now a healthy population of Chestnut-backed Thrushes in the
UK and it is to be hoped that this thrush will continue to be bred and a
long-term self-sustaining captive-breeding population will become firmly
established. There are a number of European breeders on the look-out for
surplus birds. I am always getting phone calls from aviculturists wanting
a male or female to make-up a new pair. It seems that every year there is a
surplus of females and a shortage of males.
The Chestnut-backed Thrash spends a lot of time on the ground and, in
the wild, easily blends in with the leaf-litter. It behaves not unlike a pitta,
moving over the forest floor and only flying up onto a branch if it is disturbed.
It is a peaceful bird by nature and can be housed with other species (though
not other thrushes) even when it is breeding, so long as the aviary is large
enough. For the best breeding results, however, each pair should be given
an aviary to itself.
My pairs go to nest about mid-March, or sometimes earlier. I had a
friend whose birds bred in January, but this is not to be recommended. I
pair-up my birds in February, after having kept them apart during the winter
months. I house each pair in a 9ft x 4ft x 6ft high (approx. 2.7m x 1.2m x
1.8m high) flight, with the floor covered with wood shavings. I place a nest
box and a basket in each aviary. I use a parakeet nest box with part of the
front cut away to turn it into a half-open-fronted nest box. This is placed
high in a comer of the flight, well away from the door through which I feed
the birds. A wicker basket, similar to that available from florists' shops, is
fixed to the wire mesh. These are screened from view using plastic Boston
Ferns, which I attach to the outside of the nest boxes and baskets. I always
put the female in the breeding flight first and put the male in the flight in
a show cage at the same time. However, if he is not steady enough in the
show cage, I place him in an adjoining flight (space permitting). I do not
let him in with the female for at least a week.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999629" page_id="56256341"  page_num="104" year="" vol="">
104
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.74001" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256341" page_num="104" year="" vol="">
BRALSFORB - CHESTNUT-BACKED THRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9972368" page_id="56256341"  page_num="104" year="" vol="">
I provide coconut fibre and sisal string or jute as nesting material and
put in some animal hair for finishing off lining the nest. When the pair is
in breeding condition, the female sings a little song, which is not loud, but
which attracts the male's attention. Usually, he then sings loudly and attempts
to feed the female with livefood. I have also noticed that when the pair is
in breeding condition, both the male and female's legs, which are normally
an off-white/pinkish colour, turn a really bright pink.
The female usually lays a clutch of up to three eggs but on the odd
occasion, may lay as many as four eggs, however, often only two of these
hatch. The incubation period is 15 days. The young leave the nest after
about 15-16 days, but it is several more days before they can fly and for
about a week they hide among the undergrowth.
Most of the 26 young bred by Gary, who lives in South Yorkshire, here in
the UK, have gone to zoos and bird gardens, with several of them having gone
to the Netherlands and Belgium. E-mail:gary.bralsford@hotmail.co.uk
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.955441" page_id="56256341"  page_num="104" year="" vol="">
*
* *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.641674" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56256341" page_num="104" year="" vol="">
IMPORTANT NOTICE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9983775" page_id="56256341"  page_num="104" year="" vol="">
Will all members please note that their subscription for 2012 will become
due on January 1 st. Please note that the Avicultural Society account is now
at Barclays Bank, not NatWest. As the NatWest account has been closed,
all future standing orders, subscriptions and other payments should be made
to Barclays Bank (Burnham- on Crouch Branch). Please quote: Account
No. 13296954, Sort Code 20 54 30. Please ensure you include your name
as the account reference otherwise we cannot match payments. In case of
difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and Treasurer whose details can
be found on the inside of the front cover.
Those who prefer to pay their subscription in US dollars can send a
check or money order, US$40 for receiving the magazine by regular mail
or US$50 by air mail, to The Avicultural Society, c/o Jane Cooper, 12650
Hearst Road, Willits, California 95490-9231, USA. All checks and money
orders should be payable to The Avicultural Society.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998892" page_id="56256342"  page_num="105" year="" vol="">
105
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.75731" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256342" page_num="105" year="" vol="">
CAPTIVE CARE OF THE FRIENDLY GROUND DOVE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.911772861111111" page_id="56256342"  page_num="105" year="" vol="">
Gallicolumba stairi IN SAMOA
by Rose Collen, Bronwyn McCulloch, David Butler
and Glen Holland
Introduction
The purpose of this project was to safeguard a number of Friendly Ground
Doves (also known as the Shy Ground Dove) during an operation to remove
Pacific Rats Rattus exulans from the Samoan islands of Nu'utele and Nu'ulua.
It was thought the doves might be vulnerable to the toxins being used (Parrish,
2009). The eradication operation was managed by Dave Butler, a consultant
to the South Pacific Regional Environmental Programme (SPREP). Although
previous trips to the islands over an extended period had resulted in various
counts ranging from no birds to just three birds, we hoped to capture 10-12
birds over a period of 10 days. One bird was caught by Richard Parrish and
staff in Samoa in 2007, which gave us hope that we might be able to catch
enough birds to secure the population during the poison bait drop. In the
event, 26 Friendly Ground Doves were captured on Nu'utele Island and taken
into captivity in two transfers, the first on July 23rd and the second on July
30th 2009. Four doves died while being held in captivity, but the remaining
22 healthy birds were released back onto Nu'utele Island on September 17th
2009, as soon as the poison baits had decomposed.
Capture
We arrived on Nu'utele late in the afternoon and while the holding cages
were being assembled put up three nets shortly before it got dark, but failed
to catch anything on that occasion. At first light the following morning we
headed out to keep an eye on the nets. We decided to split up, with Richard
Parrish watching two nets and one of the authors (G.H.) watching the other
net which was some distance away. As the latter approached the net, he saw
a thrush-like bird take off and as he got closer realised there was a bird in
the net. It was at ground level and as he stood for a moment watching, out
of the grass on the forest floor a second ground dove appeared and walked
into the net. The two birds proved to be a pair and were quickly removed
and placed in suspended holding cages. These were the first of 17 Friendly
Ground Doves caught over a period of 24 hours. Having been so successful,
we decided to pack up and head back to base with them. At our second
attempt a further nine birds were captured over a period of three days. We
had therefore succeeded in capturing 26 Friendly Ground Doves.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999206" page_id="56256343"  page_num="106" year="" vol="">
106
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.219515" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256343" page_num="106" year="" vol="">
HOLLAND ET AL - FRIENDLY GROUND DOVE
Male Friendly Ground Dove.
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97376665" page_id="56256343"  page_num="106" year="" vol="">
Captive husbandry
The post capture holding cages consisted of a row of six cages each
measuring 40cm x 40 cm x 90cm (approx. 1ft 3%in x 1ft 3%in x 2ft 11 Vi in)
and designed to hold a single bird. The floor was 10mm (not quite Vi in) square
weldmesh and the rest of the frame consisted of No. 8 wire frames covered
with green shade cloth. The idea was to provide the birds with privacy but
without making the cages too dark, while at the same time avoiding the
possibility of birds flying against the wire and damaging their beak, cere
and/or skull. As it happened, most of the cages ended up with three birds
in each of them for 24 hours. Seed was placed in a wide but shallow dish
and Omithon soluble vitamin supplement was added to the drinking water
which was provided in hook-on bowls. Handfuls of soft leaf litter collected
from the forest floor were placed on the wire base of each cage. The day
after capture when we removed the birds from the cages to transport them
to the mainland, by palpating their crops it was evident that some birds had
begun to feed, but others did not appear to have eaten anything.
As we had never imagined catching so many birds in such a short time,
we had only eight bird bags. We quickly rallied the troops and a few T-shirts
and a wrap around skirt were sacrificed for the cause and, using string and
makeshift needles for sewing, these were turned into additional bird bags.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.316899" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256344" page_num="107" year="" vol="">
HOLLAND ET AL - FRIENDLY GROUND DOVE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99926" page_id="56256344"  page_num="107" year="" vol="">
107
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.840344857142857" page_id="56256344"  page_num="107" year="" vol="">
Female Friendly Ground Dove.
Once safely in the bags the birds were carefully placed on a bed of soft
leaves in a large plastic container, with the lid slightly open, for the trip to
the mainland in a small aluminium boat.
On arrival at Vailima Botanic Gardens, the birds were housed in large
cardboard boxes in the Parks and Reserves' office. Members of the same
sex were housed together in groups of two or three birds. Each box had
shade cloth on the front to allow in light, a small handful of leaf litter on the
floor and shallow bowls of food and water, as well as seed scattered on the
floor to encourage feeding. The first group of birds captured was housed in
these boxes for seven days - until work on the aviaries had been completed
- and the second group was housed this way for four days.
Confining wild-caught birds this way is a proven method of reducing
losses due to stress. Housing the birds in the boxes helped settle them into
captivity and become accustomed to a captive diet, etc. It worked in the
following ways:
1. By keeping the lights on for 24 hours on each of the first two days
and food and water close by we encouraged the birds to feed on the diet
provided.
2. We prevented them from flying/thrashing around and exhausting
themselves as they were likely to have done in a large aviary.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999651" page_id="56256345"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
108
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.499237" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256345" page_num="108" year="" vol="">
HOLLAND ET AL - FRIENDLY GROUND DOVE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99763636" page_id="56256345"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
Only after they had settled down and were feeding were they moved into
aviaries, with two or three birds of the same sex in each flight.
Aviary set up
The aviary set up consisted of a shed with a concrete floor and concrete
blocks/chicken mesh walls. Twelve internal flights were created within this
structure, using timber framing covered with square mesh welded wire to
rat-proof the flights and with the ceiling and walls lined with shade cloth to
prevent the birds injuring themselves. A corridor, with six flights on either
side, enabled each flight to be easily serviced. A light was set up in the
corridor to provide a little extra light during the day, as there was very little
natural light on the more shaded side of the aviary. Each flight measured
approximately 0.5m wide x 2m high x 2m 3m long (1ft 8in wide x 6ft 6in
high x 6ft t&gt;i n-9ft 9in long).
Each flight had a thin layer of fine gravel on the floor, covered initially
with a thin layer of leaf litter to make it easier for the birds to find the seed
that had been scattered on the ground. Perches were placed at a variety of
heights at either end and in the middle of the flights, so that the birds had at
least two to three perches to move between.
Fresh coconut palm fronds were placed at the two ends and a few
fronds were attached to the sides to provide cover for the birds and avoid
them flying into the ends in panic. Later, tarpaulins were put up around the
outside of the aviaries to block the birds&amp;quot; view of people walking nearby.
The doves seemed to get most stressed by movement and the tarpaulins
made an immediate difference to the amount of flapping around the birds
did when people were nearby.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.504183">
Feeding and servicing
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999658230769231" page_id="56256345"  page_num="108" year="" vol="">
So as not to stress the birds unduly, the amount of time and the number
of people entering the aviaries were kept to a minimum. Fortunately, we
had on record an article by Dieter Rinke who had bred this species many
years previously in Tonga and who referred to them being happy to eat a a
seed mix suitable for Diamond Doves." The Friendly Ground Dove has a
very small bill not unlike that of the Diamond Dove Geopelia cuneata. We
offered our birds a mixture containing white and Japanese millets, buckwheat
and sorghum. Twice a week the birds were given the vitamin and mineral
supplement Omithon in their drinking water at the rate of two small scoops
(4g) per litre (0.22 UK gallons) of water. It was also added to the water
when the birds were particularly stressed such as, for example, after being
handled and moved into the aviaries.
The aviaries were cleaned regularly and any build up of faecal matter or
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.316945" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256346" page_num="109" year="" vol="">
HOLLAND ET AL - FRIENDLY GROUND DOVE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999616" page_id="56256346"  page_num="109" year="" vol="">
109
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99695075" page_id="56256346"  page_num="109" year="" vol="">
mould was removed. The leaf litter was replaced twice during the period of
captivity and fresh leaf litter and invertebrates were provided.
The males, when captured, weighed on average 134.2g (n=6) and the
females 109.#. (n=ll). These figures do not include the birds that died.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.527906">
Losses
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.977083421052632" page_id="56256346"  page_num="109" year="" vol="">
A few losses were expected due to capture myopathy, or "shipping fever"
as it was referred to by the vet in Samoa, but it was hoped to keep these to a
maximum of 10%-15%. Three birds became sick during the first two weeks
in the holding aviaries. In each case the bird was found fluffed up, it was
moving around less than the other birds and was sometimes sitting on the
floor of the aviary. One bird had faecal matter around its cloaca.
The sick birds were removed from the aviary and placed in the cardboard
boxes in which they had previously been housed and were kept in the office
with a lamp shining in day and night. Food was scattered on the floor and
was also placed in a small dish and water was provided in a D-cup bowl.
All three birds were crop-fed 4mls-5mls of a glucose and antibiotic solution.
One that was underweight also received a liquid food supplement (ProNutra
- a complete breakfast cereal formula) and a little added glucose. The bird
that had faecal matter around its cloaca was carefully cleaned to prevent
a blockage. Each of the sick birds died within 24 hours of being found
unwell. Necropsy indicated that the first bird had a high burden of worm
eggs and that all three had likely died as a result of stress and not feeding
adequately. A banding (ringing) mishap on September 7th led to the death
of the fourth bird.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.500871">
Release
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994327615384615" page_id="56256346"  page_num="109" year="" vol="">
On September 7th 2009 the birds were caught using a hand net. They
were checked for injuries, weighed and measured and most of the unbanded
birds were banded (ringed). By midday all of the birds had been placed in
cardboard cat boxes ready for transportation. Cardboard divisions were used
to divide each of the boxes into four compartments and the floor was lined
with a mat of brown fibrous palm material. Each compartment was just large
enough for a dove to perch comfortably - probably without being able to turn
around easily. The journey back to Nu'utele took approximately two hours
by car and boat. On arrival back on the island each bird was removed from
its box and quickly checked for injuries which may have occurred during
transportation (there were none). The doves were then released from the
hand into the area of forest from which most of them were captured. All
flew off strongly into the canopy.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995749" page_id="56256347"  page_num="110" year="" vol="">
110
</page>
<copyright confidence="0.230932">
HOLLAND ET AL - FRIENDLY GROUND DOVE
</copyright>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.849409">
Discussion and recommendations
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98001995" page_id="56256347"  page_num="110" year="" vol="">
In terms of the size of the flights, the aviary was adequate for the
temporary housing of the doves and the best use was made of the available
space. However, had the birds been held in captivity for much longer,
hygiene may have become an issue. Because the birds panicked so much
when anyone entered the confined space, it was difficult to clean the aviaries
and the need to maintain hygiene standards had to be balanced against the
stress caused to the birds. For the same reason it was not possible to observe
the birds closely to check for signs of aggression and whether or not they
were feeding properly, etc.
If a similar project was to occur in the future, ideally each flight in the
holding aviary should be larger so that vegetation can be provided amongst
which the birds can hide and gain greater security and, hopefully, reduce
the stress levels. The vegetation should be replaced regularly to prevent a
build up of faecal matter and mould, which should not be too difficult if
there is enough space in the flights for the birds to retreat to while this is
happening.
Care of the birds
Others involved in the captive care of the birds were Elizabeth Kerstin
and Fialelei Enoka of the Ministry of Natural Resources and the Environment
and Alan Tye of the South Pacific Regional Environmental Programme.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.8584232" page_id="56256347"  page_num="110" year="" vol="">
Reference
Parrish, R. 2009. Report on friendly ground dove capture trip to Nu 'utele Island July 2009.
Rose Gotten, Department of Conservation, Invercargill, New Zealand.
E-mail :rcollen@doc. govt, nz
Bronwyn McCulloch, Threatened Species Team, Healesville Sanctuary.
E-mail: bronwynmcculloch@hotmail.com
David Butler, SPREP consultant. E-mail:d.butler@xtra.co.nz
Glen Holland, Director, Healesville Sanctuary. E-mail :Glen-nat@
hotmail.com
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.955829" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256347" page_num="110" year="" vol="">
WARNING TO PIGEON FANCIERS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998685714285714" page_id="56256347"  page_num="110" year="" vol="">
A paramyxovirus (it is not bird flu) not previously reported in Australia
has been detected by the authorities in Victoria among birds belonging
to pigeon fanciers near Shepparton and in the north-western suburbs of
Melbourne.
A high rate of mortality has been recorded among infected flocks. Strains
of paramyxovirus are generally capable of infecting other avian species, but
at this stage the disease has only been detected in pigeons.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.913259666666667" page_id="56256348"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
Ill
HAND-REARING A GREAT BLUE TURACO
Corythaeola cristaia AT PARADISE PARK, HAYLE,
CORNWALL
by Rebecca Waite
Introduction and background
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.906454" page_id="56256348"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
The Great Blue Turaco Corythaeola crisiata is the largest member of the
turaco family. It measures between 70cm-75cm (approx. 2ft 3in-2ft 6m) in
length and weighs between 820g" 1 ,250g. It has a stout body with quite short
and rounded wings and a long tail The plumage is predominantly blue.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.824763">
David Woolcock
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9191158" page_id="56256348"  page_num="111" year="" vol="">
Young Great Blue Turaco aged 83 days.
Both sexes look identical in coloration and this remains so throughout
the year. This species lives in sub-Saharan Africa, where it inhabits montane
rainforest and gallery forest (forest bordering rivers and streams) from sea
level up to about 2,700m (approx. 8,800ft). It feeds mainly on fruits, but
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999061" page_id="56256349"  page_num="112" year="" vol="">
112
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.812145" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256349" page_num="112" year="" vol="">
WAITE - GREAT BLUE TURACO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999494243902439" page_id="56256349"  page_num="112" year="" vol="">
also favours leaves, shoots and flowers.
The pair of Great Blue Turacos at Paradise Park have been together since
February 2010. Almost from the moment they met they have displayed and
called to each other and now have a very strong pair bond. As soon as we
provided them with a nesting place they began to gather flimsy sticks and
broad-leafed plants to build a nest.
We tried several different types of nesting places, all of them large
platforms with a raised edge or lip to prevent twigs falling off and with
various types of nesting substrate, such as wood shavings, sand and hessian
sacking. The birds would build a nest and the female would even occasionally
lay on these platforms, but after a few days the birds would abandon the eggs.
It was thought that the nests they were building were too flimsy and were
falling apart. We then managed to purchase some very large wicker baskets
one of which we placed in the same area on the existing platform inside the
shelter and we placed another basket outside in a sheltered position. The
birds took to these very quickly and even if the flimsy nest consisted of only a
handful of twigs they would happily sit on it, lay eggs and incubate them.
The first clutch of two eggs was abandoned only three to four days
before the eggs were due to hatch. On inspection, the eggs were found
to be fully formed and contained what looked to be healthy chicks. The
birds laid a second clutch, both eggs of which were fertile, but the same
thing happened again. The next clutch of eggs that was laid was removed
after the second egg was laid and the eggs were artificially incubated in a
Grumbach incubator. One of the eggs proved to be infertile, but the other
egg was fertile and the moment the external pip began, the egg was placed
under a brooding pair of White-cheeked Turacos Tauraco leucotis. We had
successfully used this pair of turacos as foster parents many times before
to rear other turaco chicks. Initially the pair seemed to be rearing the chick
successfully, but by the sixth day it had died. It is thought that the size of
the rapidly growing chick and its demand for food, were just too much for
the foster parents, who simply could not keep up with it.
Following this set back we again gave the Great Blue Turacos the
opportunity to incubate their own eggs and rear the young themselves, in
the hope that they just needed more practise in doing this. Finally, in late
2010, our first chick hatched under the female turaco. This breeding attempt
was monitored via cameras which we had set up to observe the nest without
needing to disturb the turacos. We could easily observe the nest and see
exactly what was happening. The female seemed very attentive and appeared
to be trying to feed the chick. The following day, however, it was obvious
that something was wrong. The chick was not responding to the female&apos;s
attempts to encourage it to feed and after viewing this on the monitor it was
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.461945" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256350" page_num="113" year="" vol="">
WAITE - GREAT BLUE TURACO
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999008" page_id="56256350"  page_num="113" year="" vol="">
113
</page>
<author confidence="0.453302">
David Woolcock
</author>
<bodyText confidence="0.99892816" page_id="56256350"  page_num="113" year="" vol="">
The female sitting on the nest in a large wicker basket on the platform inside the
shelter.
decided to go in and investigate. Upon closer investigation, we discovered
that, unfortunately, the chick had died.
Reluctantly we all agreed that hand-rearing was our most realistic option
and despite the difficulties we were likely to encounter, thought we had
little to lose. Before embarking on a hand-rearing attempt, we carefully
researched all available protocols for hand-rearing this species and after
careful consideration decided to adopt the protocol developed at San Diego
Zoo in California. We already had good links with staff there, namely Pat
Witman and Clancy Hall, and I, together with a colleague at Paradise Park,
had been fortunate enough to visit the zoo in November 2009. I had seen
how its turacos are kept and the diets that are used for hand-rearing these
birds, although it was made clear to us that the zoo's protocol was only
partially successful.
During the winter months all our turacos are locked in their heated shelters
overnight. Because of the extremely cold and prolonged winter in 2010, we
took the decision to prevent the female from continuing to lay and thereby risk
egg binding, by shutting the male and female in separate shelters at night and
allowing them individual access to the main enclosure during the day, with
each bird taking turns outside. Once winter had almost passed, they were
once again let out into the main enclosure together during the day (whilst
still being locked away at night for extra warmth). They immediately began
calling and copulation was frequently observed. Within days the female laid
an egg in her shelter. This egg was removed for artificial incubation.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.9994" page_id="56256351"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
114
</page>
<table confidence="0.690204666666667" page_id="56256351"  page_num="114" year="" vol="">
WAITE - GREAT BLUE TURACO
Day 13.
David Woolcock
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.442781" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256352" page_num="115" year="" vol="">
WAITE - GREAT BLUE TURACO
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.953988" page_id="56256352"  page_num="115" year="" vol="">
115
</page>
<table confidence="0.5643285" page_id="56256352"  page_num="115" year="" vol="">
Day 22.
David Woolcock
</table>
<page confidence="0.999542" page_id="56256353"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
116
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.629986" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256353" page_num="116" year="" vol="">
WAITE - GREAT BLUE TURACO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98617068292683" page_id="56256353"  page_num="116" year="" vol="">
Hand-rearing
The egg was placed in the Grumbach incubator which was used to
incubate the previous eggs and, on February 9th 2011, the internal pip
began. It was followed a day later by the external pip and then finally on
the morning of February 11th the chick had hatched. It weighed 37.14g. We
then followed the hand-rearing protocol given to us by staff at San Diego
Zoo and used it as a guide to what to feed the chick and when. This protocol
had been used to successfully rear chicks there in 2000,2001 and 2003 but,
unfortunately, since then it had not been successful.
After the chick hatched we waited six hours for the begging response
to begin before feeding it. We gave it only a Dioralyte solution for the first
two feeds (using a syringe), then a mixture of Kaytee Rainbox Exact parrot
food soaked in a Dioralyte solution until it was completely hydrated and
soft. This can be kept refrigerated for 24 hours before being discarded.
However, I always placed the food in a metal dish sitting in warm water
to take the chill off the food before feeding it to the chick. I used a pair of
tweezers and tore off small chunks of Kaytee to feed to the chick, which
took it readily. I always removed the chick from the bowl in the brooder (see
below) when feeding it, as it was easier to feed it on a flat surface. I would
feed the chick until it no longer wanted any more food. I was very surprised
by the amount of food such a small chick consumed at one sitting. On the
first day it did not produce any faeces even though we stimulated the cloaca.
The first faeces were passed on the second day. It was necessary to stimulate
the cloaca only until the third day after which, without any stimulation, the
chick would defecate after every meal. The chick's weight was recorded
before the first meal each day and checked against the corresponding weight
recorded at San Diego Zoo.
The temperature in the brooder was initially set at 36*C (96.8*F) and then
decreased by 1*C (~0.6*F) every other day. The humidity was maintained
at approximately 65%-75%. The chick was fed every two hours from
06.30hrs-20.30hrs (8.30pm). It was kept in a metal 'coop cup' bowl with a
small piece of Astroturf on the bottom to help the feet develop properly and
was surrounded with paper towelling which supported the chick and kept
it away from the sides of the metal bowl and prevented it from becoming
chilled. Using this method meant that the matting and towelling could be
changed regularly and the chick kept clean.
For three consecutive days, beginning on the second day, Betamox
palatable drops were given once a day as a prophylactic, in case any infection
had been picked up during hatching. By the sixth day the pin-feathers on the
wings were beginning to develop and the chick became impatient if it was
not fed as soon as it was taken out of the brooder. It would actively try to
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.462117" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256354" page_num="117" year="" vol="">
WAITE - GREAT BLUE TURACO
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999323" page_id="56256354"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
117
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997286585365854" page_id="56256354"  page_num="117" year="" vol="">
move towards the bowl containing the food and the tweezers to encourage
me to speed up. At this stage the chick&apos;s weight was higher than that of
those of the same age successfully hand-raised at San Diego Zoo and this
continued to be the trend until the chick was about 30 days old, when its
weight began to even out and become similar to that of those raised at San
Diego Zoo.
On the eighth day very small pieces of soft, steamed broccoli, dipped
in the Dioralyte solution were given to the chick towards the end of each
feed of Kaytee. The chick seemed to enjoy this so much that by day 12,1
had to begin feeding it the colourful Kaytee first and leave any green bits of
Kaytee until last, along with the broccoli. If I fed it green Kaytee first this
was the only colour food it would eat, presumably thinking that it could be
broccoli - which it loved so much.
On day 10 the Dioralyte solution was discontinued and the Kaytee was
instead soaked in boiled water that had been allowed to cool and the chick
was given access to sunlight for about 15 minutes each day. Day 12 the chick
was observed flapping its wings and beginning to preen itself. At this point
the chick was moved to a flat bowl (with the Astroturf and paper towelling)
so that it could stretch its wings more easily.
On day 14 the feeds were cut down to every two and a half hours from
Q6.30hrs-2Q.30hrs (8.30pm). The diet was also changed slightly with small
pieces of chopped papaya and banana (also moistened in water) being added
to it. As with the broccoli, these new additions to the diet were fed to the
chick after it had consumed the Kaytee and indeed also after the broccoli.
After a day or so I also had to avoid until last, feeding it yellow and orange
pieces of Kaytee - as well as pieces of green Kaytee - as it would not eat the
other coloured pieces once it had eaten these, again presuming they were
banana and papaya.
From day 16a dish of water and a dish containing some food were left
in the brooder with the chick between feeds. The young turaco was standing
well by itself by now. By day 17 it was seen eating small amounts of broccoli
taken from the dish and on day 18 was seen eating small amounts of banana
and papaya. From day 17 it was fed every three hours from Q6.30hrs-20.30hrs
(8.30pm) and was seen attempting to perch on the edge of the food dish.
So, on day 18, perching was placed in the brooder.
From days 21/22 the young turaco vocalised when I entered the room
to feed it. By day 22 the nest bowl was removed as it was no longer being
used. On day 25 the amount of broccoli, banana and papaya was increased
and the Kaytee was not soaked as much, so that it was less sloppy, and was
generally fed to the young turaco in large pieces. It was quickly outgrowing
the brooder, so was moved to a larger brooder on day 27.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998137" page_id="56256355"  page_num="118" year="" vol="">
118
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.638318">
WAITE - GREAT BLUE TURACO
Fig. 1. Comparison of growth rates of Great Blue Turaco chick at Paradise
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.9477781" page_id="56256355"  page_num="118" year="" vol="">
Park and those at San Diego Zoo.
900
0 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 100 110 120 130
Age In days
-Paradise Pk
weight
-San Diego
weight
Day 41.
David Woolcock
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.461709" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256356" page_num="119" year="" vol="">
WAITE - GREAT BLUE TURACO
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997988" page_id="56256356"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
119
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.725661">
David Woolcock
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996936714285714" page_id="56256356"  page_num="119" year="" vol="">
Taken on July 6th 2011, this photo shows the young turaco at 140/141 days of age.
All that is lacking is the orange-red tip to the bill.
From day 28 the young turaco was fed every four hours from OT.OOhrs-
18.30hrs (6.30pm). On day 32, figs were introduced into the diet and were
readily taken. The following day feeds were cut down to every five hours
from 07.30hrs-18.00hrs (6.00pm).
On day 36 the turaco was moved to an indoor pen with perching and
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.977854" page_id="56256357"  page_num="120" year="" vol="">
120
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.808061" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256357" page_num="120" year="" vol="">
WAITE - GREAT BLUE TURACO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999561853658536" page_id="56256357"  page_num="120" year="" vol="">
a heat lamp during the day, so that it could stretch its wings and begin to
try exploring its environment (each eight it was returned to the brooder).
Newspaper was used on the floor in preference to wood shavings, as there
was a potential risk of the young turaco consuming the shavings. Straight
perches were used to limit the risk of the bird becoming caught in a fork
of a branch.
By now the turaco was mostly feeding independently or with just a little
coaxing. On day 45, apple, pear, melon, grapes, blueberries, softbill Kaytee
and a low iron insectile mixture were added to the food bowl which was left in
the enclosure. This was similar to the adult diet and the young turaco seemed
to enjoy the added fruits. Kaytee Rainbow Exact continued to be provided
as the young turaco continued to consume a large amount of this.
The young turaco was later moved to a large outdoor enclosure during
the day and was locked away in a heated shelter at night. The young turaco
continued to be weighed each morning to ensure that it was gaining sufficient
weight. By now it weighed about 1 OOg less than the average weight of a
comparable young turaco at San Diego Zoo, but continued to eat well and
with the added exercise it was getting in the outdoor enclosure, began putting
on weight faster.
On the morning of day 691 noticed that the young turaco had eaten very
little since the previous night and had lost 16g in weight since the previous
morning. Occasionally the young turaco's weight had fluctuated for a day
or so before it began to gain weight once again, but that morning something
did not seem quite right. The young turaco looked fine but was not interested
in food, which was extremely unusual as it had always eaten something
no matter how full it seemed to be. I monitored its condition throughout
the morning. The young turaco took a small amount of food, bet not even
favourite items such as broccoli and the large orange pieces of parrot Kaytee
would tempt it to eat very much. A few times I also observed it drinking
water and it was unusual to see it choosing water in preference to food.
After consulting the park's Curator who had also been monitoring the young
turaco during its development, the vet was called in. The vet agreed that
something was not quite right. The young turaco was slightly fluffed - up by
now and had sleepy-looking eyes, something I had never observed with this
bird before. It was given an injection of Doxycycline and put on a course
of Marbocyl tablets. During that one day it had lost over 90g in weight and
by the end of the day was passing only very watery faeces.
The next morning, with some trepidation, we went to see how the bird
was. To our delight, it was fine. It was almost back to its old self and was
eating lots of food and its weight had remained unchanged overnight.
Since then the young Great Blue Turaco has continued to thrive and
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.462151" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256358" page_num="121" year="" vol="">
WAITE - GREAT BLUE TURACO
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99807" page_id="56256358"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
121
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.996169583333333" page_id="56256358"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
slowly regained the lost weight. At the time of writing (May 2011 ), the
young Great Blue Turaco is 90 days old and weighs 516g, which is about
200g less than the San Diego birds. However, it is very fit, it is boisterous
and is a strong flier, whose adult plumage is almost complete. A DNA test
has shown that it is a female. Since losing weight she has only been given
apple, pear, banana, papaya, blueberries and two new favourites, strawberries
and raspberries. I am hoping to reintroduce the low iron insectile mix and
Softbill Kaytee in the next few weeks, once I am sure she will continue to
gain weight.
Even though this is one of the most challenging species we have reared
here at Paradise Park, it has been worth every minute and I have found it
extremely rewarding.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.856798" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56256358" page_num="121" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.895636" page_id="56256358"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
With thanks to Pat Witman and Clancy Hall at San Diego Zoo and Mark
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.921876066666667" page_id="56256358"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
Stevens and Adam Pollard at Paradise Park for their help and assistance.
Products mentioned in the text
Betamox: palatable drops produced by Norbrook Laboratories Limited, Station Works, Newry,
Co. Down BT35 6JP, Northern Ireland.
Dioralyte: Sanofi-aventis, One Onslow Street, Guildford, Surrey, GUI 4YS, UK.
Doxycycline: Shellmed UK, Loughrea, County Galway, Ireland.
Kaytee Rainbow Exact &amp; Softbill Kayee: Kaytee Products, Inc., 521 Clay Street, Chilton, WI
53014, USA.
Low Iron Insectile Mix: Orlux, Versele Laga NV, Kappellestraat 70, B-9800, Deize,
Belgium.
Marbocyl: Vetoquil UK Ltd, Vetoquil House, Great Slade, Buckinghamshire Industrial Park,
Buckinghamshire MK18 IPA, UK.
Rebecca Waite can be contacted at Paradise Park, Hayle, Cornwall
TR27 4HB, UK. Website:www.paradisepark.org.uk
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.587909" genericHeader="references" page_id="56256358" page_num="121" year="" vol="">
2012 SPRING SOCIAL MEETING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.6909935" page_id="56256358"  page_num="121" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society is planning to visit Chester Zoo on Saturday May
12th. However, the arrangements have yet to be finalised.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997711" page_id="56256359"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
122
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.904642333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256359" page_num="122" year="" vol="">
THE SOUTHERN CRESTED CARACARA Caracara plancus ,
INCLUDING ITS BREEDING AT WELTVOGELPARK
WALSRODE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9361228" page_id="56256359"  page_num="122" year="" vol="">
by Simon Bruslund and Lech Bretschek
The Common or Crested Caracara (formerly Polyborusplancus) has been
split into two species which have been named the Northern Crested Caracara
or simply the Crested Caracara Caracara cheriway and the Southern Crested
Caracara or simply the Southern Caracara C. plancus.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.415233333333333">
Jodo Marcos Rosa/Weltvogelpark
Adult Southern Crested Caracara. There is no obvious visual difference
between the male and female.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.187951" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256360" page_num="123" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND &amp; BRETSCHEK - SOUTHERN CRESTED CARACARA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997522" page_id="56256360"  page_num="123" year="" vol="">
123
</page>
<author confidence="0.43589">
Jessica Rumpel/ Weltvogelpark
</author>
<bodyText confidence="0.9994111" page_id="56256360"  page_num="123" year="" vol="">
The two chicks that were hand-reared. They are four days old.
Changes in the taxonomy of the caracaras have included changing the
name of the genus from Polyborus to Caracara and this is a common and
justified cause of confusion, as this change has not yet been fully implemented
on all applicable databases, including the record keeping databases of ISIS
and the recent CITES Appendixes, where the species is listed in Appendix
II/B.
For this reason the Southern Crested Caracara has several synonyms and
there is some confusion regarding its correct identification. Not least, because
both caracaras look very similar to each other and zoos which keep them
often do not know the precise origin of their birds and, it can be assumed,
that many are wrongly labelled. A particular challenge in future breeding
efforts will be to keep the two forms separate.
A convincing and thorough review of museum specimens by Dove and
Banks, published in a scientific paper in 1999, concluded that the northern
and southern populations of the Crested Caracara should better be considered
separate species. As well as an analysis of their measurements and behaviour,
they provided a practical key to the identification of each form. The chest of
the northern forms is more spotted and that of the southern form is barred,
but the most obvious difference is that the northern forms have a pale patch
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.478091" page_id="56256361"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
124 BRUSLUND &amp; BRETSCHEK - SOUTHERN CRESTED CARACARA
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.97778215" page_id="56256361"  page_num="124" year="" vol="">
on the belly between the legs and in the southern form this area is dark.
Furthermore, there is pale barring on the lower back of the southern form
and in the northern populations the lower back is black. There seems to be
a narrow area in the northern part of South America where the two species
meet or even intergrade. Essentially, however, the Amazon River is the
border between the two. The study has yet to be followed up with genetic
investigations.
Thanks possibly to their high level of adaptability, the Northern and
Southern Crested Caracaras are quite abundant in the wild and neither of
them is currently considered to be endangered (although in Florida the local
population of the Northern Crested Caracara is considered to be threatened).
A third closely related species, the Guadalupe Caracara C. lutosa, is extinct.
It was last seen in 1900, having been persecuted and eventually exterminated
by the human population of this island off Baja California (Mexico). The
Caribbean region was home to some far more ancient caracaras, fossil
remains having been found of what appear to have been terrestrial-living
caracaras, which may even, have been flightless.
Weltvogelpark Walsrode
At Weltvogelpark Walsrode our original Southern Caracaras, consisting
of a single female and a pair from Berlin Zoo, initially proved to be rather
difficult to pair up. All attempts to pair the younger male with the second
female failed and finally the two birds from Berlin ended up forming a
harmonic, but still for some time, non-breeding pair.
It was not until 2010 that the two finally bred. In the cold, early days
of April, the birds were for the first time observed carrying nesting material
in their enclosure which they were sharing with an Andean Condor Vultur
gryphus. The pair was offered a nesting basket measuring 45cm (approx.
1ft 6in) in diameter, which was placed 4m (approx. 13ft) above the ground
in a comer of the aviary where the condor could pose no danger. The basket
was readily accepted by the pair. Unlike their closest relatives the falcons,
which make only a shallow, unlined scrape in the ground or use the old nest
of another species, caracaras build a stocky nest of sticks and dried grass.
By the beginning of May the pair at Weltvogelpark Walsrode had completed
a voluminous nest and the female had begun sitting, but frequently left the
nest if there was the slightest disturbance. The male was frequently observed
at the nest, but did not sit and instead restricted his behaviour to closely
monitoring the surroundings and frequently and loudly proclaimed his hold
on the territory. During incubation the pair seemed to become increasingly
aggressive towards the neighbouring birds and, occasionally even attacked
the mesh, if any bird came too close. As we are not sure exactly when
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.188099" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256362" page_num="125" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND &amp; BRETSCHEK - SOUTHERN CRESTED CARACARA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998502" page_id="56256362"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
125
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.990262275" page_id="56256362"  page_num="125" year="" vol="">
incubation began, we are unable to document the exact incubation period.
It was on May 26th that two chicks hatched just a short interval apart and
developed well in the care of their parents. The regular nest inspections did
not seem to cause excessive stress to either the chicks or the parents.
After adding only a little more material to the nest and with very warm
spring weather compared to the previous year, the pair began breeding
much earlier this year. Also, in comparison to the previous year, the pair
proved to have become significantly bolder and more aggressive towards
the keepers, as well as other birds and, caused considerable stress to the
birds of prey in the neighbouring aviaries, which they even attempted to
grab through the mesh.
For this reason it was decided to intervene and move the breeding pair
from the exhibition aviaries to one of the off-exhibit breeding areas of the
park. The two chicks had to be removed and were placed in a brooder.
Around about the ninth day they were fitted with 11mm sized closed leg-
bands. Hand-rearing the chicks - which were kept on rough bedding to
ensure proper growth of their long legs - proved to be straightforward. The
two are being kept together while they are growing up in order to achieve a
reasonable degree of socialization.
Behaviour and feeding
The behaviour of the caracaras is rather unusual for birds of prey and
particularly for relatives of the falcons. Among the first thing most observers
notice is their high level of activity. Caracaras are very active and move
around a great deal investigating their surroundings. They also indulge in
noisy awkward-looking displays in which the calling bird throws its head
back until it almost touches its shoulders. They are also unusual in that they
spend a large amount of time on the ground - they can fly well but often
seem to prefer to walk. This suits their generalist hunting strategy: they will
eat almost anything and even scratch around in the soil and beneath stones
and branches looking for invertebrates. They eat mainly carrion and even
over ripe fruits and berries. They will search amongst the faeces of large
carnivores looking for anything remotely edible and remove ticks from the
backs of large herbivorous mammals. Caracaras are capable of hunting and
will pursue rodents and reptiles and wait patiently for them to re-emerge from
their burrows/hiding places. They will also follow other birds, swarming
ants, hoofstock, vehicles and humans, in the hope of picking up a meal. In
urban areas caracaras will often wait for the trash to be brought out. At
Weltvogelpark Walsrode, the diet of our Southern Crested Caracaras is not
quite as varied as in the wild, but visitors may occasionally see unusual items
of food, such as fish or fruit, in their aviary.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997181" page_id="56256363"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
126
</page>
<table confidence="0.183553" page_id="56256363"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND &amp; BRETSCHEK - SOUTHERN CRESTED CARACARA
Jessica RumpelfWeltvogelpark
Aged approximately 45 days old, shortly after fledging. By the second year the
Southern Crested Caracara continues to show obvious signs of juvenile plumage, but
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.994460857142857" page_id="56256363"  page_num="126" year="" vol="">
the legs and feet have changed from pale blue to a whitish or pale yellow colour.
The crested caracaras have a low stress threshold when it comes to
contact with other species, so it is surprising to leam that allopreening
behaviour has been observed between a Southern Crested Caracara and a
Black Vulture Coragyps atratus in the wild in the Brazilian Pantanal. In
aviaries this behaviour can prove a rather stressful experience for other even
much larger birds.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.0804318" page_id="56256364"  page_num="127" year="" vol="">
BRUSLUND &amp; BRETSCHEK - SOUTHERN CRESTED CARACARA
127
Jessica Rumpel/Weltvogelpark
The parents and one of the offspring at the nest.
Bibliography
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.974152285714286">
Banks, R. C. and Dove, C. J. 1992. The generic name for Crested Caracaras (Aves: Falconidae).
Proc. Biol Soc. Wash. 105:420-425.
del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A. and Sargatal (eds.). 1994. Handbook of the Birds of the World. Vol.2
- New World Vultures to Guineafowl. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona.
Dove, C. and Banks, R. 1999. A Taxonomic study of Crested Caracaras (Falconidae). Wilson
Bulletin Vol.III,3:330-339.
Ferguson-Lees, J., Christie, D., Burton, R, Franklin, K. and Mead, D. 2001. Raptors of the
World, Helm Identification Guides. Christopher Helm, London.
Mazar Barnett, J. and Pearman, M. 2001. Annotated Checklist of the Birds of Argentina. Lynx
Edicions, Barcelona.
Palmeira, F. B. L. 2008. Allopreening behavior between Black Vulture ( Coragyps atratus)
and Southern Caracara {Caracara plancus) in the Brazilian Pantanal. Revista Brasileira de
Ornitologia Vol. 16,2:172-174.
Ridgely, R. S. and Greenfield, P. J. 2001. The Birds of Ecuador: Vol.l. Status, distribution
and taxonomy. Cornell University Press, Ithaca, New York.
Sazina, I. 1997. The jack-of-all-trades raptor: versatile foraging and wide trophic role of
the Southern Caracara ( Caracara plancus) in Brazil, with comments on feeding habits of the
Caracarini. Revista Brasileira de Ornithogia Vol. 15,4:592-597.
Southern Crested Caracara:http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?oldid=415935418
Weltvogelpark Walsrode is in northern Germany. Website: www.
weltvogelpark. de
</reference>
<page confidence="0.997662" page_id="56256365"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
128
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.6028285" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256365" page_num="128" year="" vol="">
THE MALAY OR BUFFY FISH OWL Ketupa ketupu
by Peter Stocks
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996544324324324" page_id="56256365"  page_num="128" year="" vol="">
The Malay or Buffy Fish Owl Ketupa ketupu , as it is now called, is one
of four species of Asian fish owls - the others being Blakiston's Fish Owl K.
hlakistoni, the Brown Fish Owl K. zeylonensis and the Tawny Fish Owl K.
flavipes - which having previously been reclassified and included in the genus
Bubo with the eagle-owls, are now to be found back in the genus Ketupa.
Currently four subspecies of the Malay or Buffy Fish Owl are recognised:
K k. aagaardi found from southern Assam to southern Thailand and Vietnam;
K k. ketupu found on the Malay Peninsula, Riau Archipelago, Sumatra, Java,
Bali, Borneo and Bangka; K k. minor found on Nias Island (off north-west
Sumatra); and K k. pageli found in north-west Borneo (Clements, 2007).
Size-wise this species measures somewhere between ISin-lS^in (approx.
38cm-47cm) in length and on average weighs about 21b 8oz (1.3kg), meaning
that it is only marginally larger than the Tawny Owl Strix aluco , but some
two-and-a-half to three times heavier. The female is always larger than
the male, with weights of lkg-2kg (approx. 21b 2oz-41b 4oz) having been
recorded.
These birds seem to have the ability to flatten their ear tufts and sink their
head down between their shoulders, giving them what many would describe
as a fierce and frowny-type look.
The Malay or Buffy Fish Owl tends to be a bird primarily of lowland
and coastal areas, but has been recorded living at as high as 5,300ft (approx.
1,600m) on Mount Singgalang on Sumatra. It also seems capable of
living adjacent to paddy fields, provided there are plenty of trees and other
vegetation, amongst which it can seek seclusion during the day, when it
is apparently to be found roosting singly, though not too far from other
roosting birds.
The habitat needs to provide a predominately fish diet along with a smaller
proportion of reptiles, frogs, toads and crabs, etc. Rats, mice and some larger
insects, such as beetles, though readily eaten do not form a great part of the
diet. Because of the relatively small amounts of fur and feathers in its diet,
the fish owl does not cast pellets of the same firmness or consistency as most
other owls, and instead casts any bones or other remains directly below its
roost or feeding site.
Nesting seems to be quite a simple affair, with the birds using a cavity
in a tree or perhaps taking over the abandoned nest of a raptor (something
similar in structure to the nest of a Magpie Pica pica), in which the female
lays a single egg measuring on average 52mm x 48mm. In Boyer &amp; Hume
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.765573" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256366" page_num="129" year="" vol="">
STOCKS - MALAY FISH OWL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998689" page_id="56256366"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
129
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.993607111111111" page_id="56256366"  page_num="129" year="" vol="">
(1991) the egg is described as being white with dusky spots, though I have
yet to visit The Natural History Museum at Tring to confirm this. If this
is the case, I wonder if the eggs of the other three fish owls are similarly
marked!
This owl was first bred in the UK at London Zoo in 1967 and an account of
the breeding was published in the Avicultural Magazine Vol.74, No. 1, pp. 17-
18 (1968). One of the pair had come from John Spedan Lewis's collection
at Leckford in 1945. Its age was unknown, but it was presumed that it had
been living there for some time before the outbreak of war in 1939, so may
have been more than 30 years of age. The other bird had been presented to
the zoo by Dr K. C. Searle in 1954. According to the FBF Register of Birds
Bred in the UK under Controlled Conditions , covering the period 2005-2008,
the last recorded breeding of this species was in 2002 (when one was reared).
The Brown Fish Owl was first bred in the UK at Paignton Zoo in 1985.
Should anyone be fortunate enough to acquire a pair of these beautiful
birds, I believe they would do well in a relatively secluded aviary, probably
in the region of 8ft x 12ft- 16ft x 8ft high (approx. 2.4m x 3.6m-4.8m x 2.4m
high). I would provide an open-fronted nest box roughly 1ft 6in x 1ft 6in x
1ft 6in high (45cm x 45cm x 45cm high) and a tray 1ft 6in x 1ft 6in x 4in
deep (approx. 45cm x 45cm x 10cm deep), both with a substrate of 50%
wood shavings mixed with 50% peat to prevent the egg from rolling around
and perhaps getting broken.
Their diet would, because of its high fish content in the wild, need to
reflect this and contain plenty of protein. So, if the keeper is unable to provide
fish, such as sprats and whitebait, etc., or if the birds will not accept these,
a feeding regime of day-old chicks, mice and rats, should be enhanced with
a suitable supplement or supplements.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.984282" genericHeader="references" page_id="56256366" page_num="129" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.975795833333333">
Boyer, T. and Hume, R. 1991. Owls of the World. Dragon's World, Limpsfield and London.
Clements, J. F. 2007. The Clements Checklist of the Birds of the World Sixth Edition.
Christopher Helm, London.
Peter Stocks is the Hon. Secretary and Treasurer of the Avicultural
Society. His contact details can he found on the inside of the front cover
of the magazine.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.905251" page_id="56256367"  page_num="130" year="" vol="">
130
</page>
<figure confidence="0.535779833333333" page_id="56256367"  page_num="130" year="" vol="">
THE LATEST LIST OF SPECIAL INTEREST GROUPS AND
THE COORDINATORS
Asian starlings and mynahs
Rob Monks - E-mail:rob@pickersleigh.co.uk/Tel:01905 351649
Barbets
Mike Curzon MBE - E-mail:mcurzonmbe@hotmail.co.uk/Tel:01373
</figure>
<page confidence="0.435696" page_id="56256367"  page_num="130" year="" vol="">
824077
</page>
<table confidence="0.952461310344828" page_id="56256367"  page_num="130" year="" vol="">
Blue-crowned Laughingthrush Dryonastes courtoisi
Laura Gardner - E-mail :LauraGardner@leeds-castle.co.uk
Bulbuls and white-eyes/zosterops
Terry Gonsolvis - E-mail:terry@ipage.co.uk
Chestnut-backed Thrush Zoothera dohertyi
Jamie Graham - E-mail:Jamie.Graham@zsl.org
Corvids, hombills and African starlings
Geoff Masson - E-mail:geoffmasson@paultons.co.uk
Fruit doves, ground doves and bleeding-hearts
Rosemary Wiseman - E-mail:ro.wiseman@virgin.net
Laughingthrushes (except the Blue-crowned and Sumatran)
and Fairy Bluebird Irena puella
Ian Edmans - E-mail:Ian.Edmans@nationaltrust.org.uk and Simon Matthews
- E-mail:Simon.Matthews@nationaltrust.org.uk
Liocichlas Liocichla spp.
Nigel Hewston - E-mail:nigelhewston@btintemet.com
Pekin Robin Leiothrix lutea
Chris Dunn - E-mail:chrisdunnl987@hotmail.co.uk/Tel:07413 522485
Seed-eating pigeons and doves
Philip Schofield - E-mail:p.schofield@dorsetcc.gov.uk/Tel:01305 264361
Snowy-crowned Robin-Chat Cossypha niveicapilla
Barry Woodley - E-mail:andrea.woodley@btintemet.com
Sumatran Laughingthrush Garrulax bicolor
Andrew Owen - E-mail:a.owen@chesterzoo.org
Toucans, toucanets and ara^aris
John Ellis - E-mail:John.ellis@zsl.org/Tel:0207 4496436
White-mmped Shama Copsychus malabaricus , Magpie Robin C. saularis
and mockingbirds Mimus spp.
Bob Jewiss - E-mail:bobbyjewiss@blueyonder.co.uk/Tel:07545 958693
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.518426" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256368" page_num="131" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - SPECIAL INTEREST GROUPS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.992595" page_id="56256368"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
131
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.679361" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256368" page_num="131" year="" vol="">
THE SOCIETY'S SPECIAL INTEREST GROUPS
by Malcolm Ellis
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998400783783784" page_id="56256368"  page_num="131" year="" vol="">
The idea of Special Interest Groups - groups of keepers and breeders
of particular species or families of birds, each with a coordinator to put the
keepers and breeders in contact with one another to exchange information and
birds; with the aim of forming the maximum possible number of unrelated
breeding pairs and establishing self-sustaining captive-breeding populations -
was first suggested by Andrew Owen and supported by, if I remember rightly,
other members such as Geoff Masson and Nigel Hewston who were present
at the Avicultural Society meeting held at Waddesdon Manor on March 31st
2007, With the EU (European Union) ban on the importation of birds about
to become permanent, it was vital to establish self-sustaining populations of
as many different species as possible, and the idea received the unanimous
support of the Avicultural Society. Within a few weeks Andrew produced
a list of Special Interest Groups and coordinators, which he forwarded to
me for publication in the magazine (see the inside back cover of Vol.113,
No, 1,2007), I also arranged for the list to be posted on the society's website
(www.avisoc.co.uk) and sent copies of it to the Foreign Bird League (FBL)
and the weekly publication Cage &amp; Aviary Birds (at the time published by
IPC Media and published now by the Kelsey Publishing Group),
Andrew was rather disappointed by the initial response (as were, I think,
many of the other coordinators). Andrew heard from only one person
regarding the Fairy Bluebird Irenapuella and, more surprisingly, did not hear
from any keepers of the Chestnut-backed Thrush Zoothera dohertyi. He was
contacted by a few laughmgthrush keepers and through his own enquiries and
word of mouth, succeeded in locating about 250 laughingthrushes of some
23 species. Andrew was concerned that a lot of the birds had not been DNA
sexed and urged all those with species which are not sexually dimorphic, to
get their birds sexed. Towards the end of 2009, the total number of species
remained at 23, but the number of laughingthrushes had been revised upwards
and the known population was put at 459 birds.
In 2009, the groups received a welcome boost and considerable publicity
amongst the wider bird keeping fraternity, when Nick West of Cage &amp; Aviary
Birds interviewed the various coordinators and based on these interviews,
wrote a series of articles featuring each of the Special Interest Groups in
turn. I am sure members will find these articles of great interest if we can
get permission to reproduce them in the magazine. Nick wrote not just about
the importance of the Special Interest Groups succeeding in establishing self-
sustaining captive-breeding populations and how this might be achieved, but
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998209" page_id="56256369"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
132
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.871329" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256369" page_num="132" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - SPECIAL INTEREST GROUPS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990884804878049" page_id="56256369"  page_num="132" year="" vol="">
also touched upon the careers of the coordinators. I learned, for example, that
John Ellis got his first job aged 16 working at Chester Zoo and went on to
work with birds in the USA, France and Jersey, and left Chessington Zoo for
London Zoo (where he is now Senior Curator of Higher Vertebrates at both
London and Whipsnade) in 2000. John continues to coordinate the Special
Interest Group for toucans, toucanets and ara 9 aris, as well as having recently
taken over the society's website and established our presence on Facebook.
Geoff Masson, Livestock Manager at Paultons Park, previously worked
at Dudley Zoo and Twycross Zoo and Laura Gardner, Curator of Birds at
Leeds Castle Aviary, whose interest in the Blue-crowned Laughingthrush
Dryonastes courtoisi has taken her to China, previously worked at the zoo in
Jersey (what is now the Durrell Wildlife Conservation Trust) and Birdworld,
near Famham, Surrey. Not all of the coordinators are members of the zoo
community - another of the coordinators is a Post Office manager living in
Kent and another has for many years worked for DEFRA's (the Department
for Environment, Food &amp; Rural Affairs') State Veterinary Service.
On the day the first article appeared (and before I had a chance to read it)
I received a phone call from a keeper who has bred Pekin Robins Leiothrix
lutea and Silver-eared Mesias L. argentauris, who asked what I needed to
know about breeding these? Later I received a call from a lady looking
for a mate for her Snowy-crowned Robin-Chat Cossypha niveicapilla , a
man breeding Violet Turacos Musophaga violacea and Emerald Doves
Chalcophaps indica and a caller seeking a male Toco Toucan Ramphastos
toco. He had a female but had lost his previous male with iron storage disease.
I hope he got the diet right before he managed to find a new male. I also
got a phone call from Dick Jaquest, who was trying to locate a female Lilac
-breasted Roller Coracias caudatus. He was obviously successful because
at our recent gathering at Paultons Park he told me he has bred nine, all of
them parent-reared and has written an article about breeding this species
and taken some wonderful photographs.
There have been a few changes since the original list of Special Interest
Groups was drawn-up. Early on Philip Schofield came on board and took
on the Special Interest Group for seed-eating pigeons and doves and more
recently Chris Dunn offered to set up a Special Interest Group for the keepers
and breeders of Pekin Robins. Because of his increased responsibilities on
becoming Curator of Birds at Chester Zoo, Andrew Owen is no longer so
heavily involved with the Special Interest Groups. He will, however, run
the group for the Sumatran Laughingthrush Garrulax bicolor , for which
he is also European Studbook (ESB) holder. The Special Interest Group
for the laughingthrushes (except for the Blue-crowned and Sumatran)
is now in the hands of lan Edmans, Curator of Birds at The Rothschild
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.519957" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256370" page_num="133" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - SPECIAL INTEREST GROUPS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999378" page_id="56256370"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
133
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.993679341463415" page_id="56256370"  page_num="133" year="" vol="">
Collection, Waddesdon Manor, and Simon Matthews, Senior Aviary Keeper
at Waddesdon. Ian fears for the long-term survival of many of the species
of laughingthrushes in UK collections. In some cases because of the low
numbers remaining and in other cases because although there are more birds,
the populations are ageing, with few young birds being bred.
Ian and Simon are also jointly coordinating the Special Interest Group
for the Fairy Bluebird. It is now an EAZA (European Association of Zoos
and Aquaria) monitored species and, lan believes, that the captive population
should be safe. There are an increasing number of private breeders
keeping this species here in the UK, as well as in Europe, where it is now
bred regularly in increasing numbers, lan believes there is little point in
continuing with the niltava groups, as there are now only three holders of
Rufous-bellied Niltavas Niltava sundam in the UK. He fears that unless this
species has a couple of good breeding seasons soon, it may well disappear
from UK aviculture.
Jamie Graham, Corncrake Release Programme Manager and Deputy
Team Leader, HUB/Park Birds, ZSL Whipsnade Zoo and European Studbook
(ESB) holder for the Chestnut-backed Thrush, has agreed to continue to
act as coordinator of the Avicultural Society Special Interest Group for this
increasingly widely kept Indonesian species.
There are, of course, quite a number of species and families missing from
the list - the Orange-headed Thrush Z. citrina, some of the other thrushes
and the majority of seed-eating species, for instance, are all missing from the
list, as are the Lilac-breasted Roller and Blue-bellied Roller C. cyanogaster.
This is not the result of an oversight, but because nobody has come forward
and offered to act as a coordinator for these species. At the recent Council
Meeting we discussed the possibility of setting up a Special Interest Group
for waders (Avocet Recurvirostra avosetta and plovers/lapwings, etc.), but
cannot take this forward until we can find someone willing to coordinate such
a group. Members of the turaco family we tend to leave to the International
Turaco Society (ITS) and other groups such as waterfowl, pheasants, parrots,
owls and birds of prey, are better taken care of by the various specialist
societies.
It would be pleasing to be able to say that the Special Interest Groups
have been a great success, but while coordinators have been able to put a
number of breeders looking for a spare male or female in touch with one
another, there is no denying that the response has been disappointing. As
our previous Hon. Secretary and Treasurer Paul Boulden pointed out to me,
breeders tend to turn to the Special Interest Groups only when they need
a bird to make up a pair and have been unable to obtain it from their usual
contacts. Also, I think it should not be forgotten that in the case of many of
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999493" page_id="56256371"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
134
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.877306" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256371" page_num="134" year="" vol="">
ELLIS - SPECIAL INTEREST GROUPS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9978657" page_id="56256371"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
these species, there are not as many birds about as there used to be - or we
may imagine there are.
The formation of the Special Interest Groups remains a great idea and
such groups are crucial if we are going to build-up healthy, self-sustaining
captive-breeding populations of as many species as possible. However, if
they are to succeed and achieve their full potential it is vital that everybody
gives them their fullest support. This should begin with all those who keep
species for which there are Special Interest Groups, contacting the appropriate
coordinator or coordinators and letting them know which species they keep,
how many and of which sex, and the number they breed each year. This
information will, of course, remain strictly confidential and will not be
disclosed without the breeder's permission.
If there is a species or group of birds for which you feel you would like
to set up a Special Interest Group and act as the coordinator, we would be
pleased to hear from you. There is, of course, no reason why these groups
should not eventually become European (rather than UK) Special Interest
Groups. There are lots of interesting birds being bred in Europe.
Hopefully, breeders will be persuaded to write describing their
successfully breeding methods and this information can be collated and used
to come up with successful breeding protocols.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.411319" page_id="56256371"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.579746" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56256371" page_num="134" year="" vol="">
BREEDING LAYARD'S BLACK-HEADED WEAVER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.924090363636364" page_id="56256371"  page_num="134" year="" vol="">
In Vol.113, No.3, pp. 119-121 (2007), Graham Thurlow described
breeding Layard's Black-headed Weaver Ploceus cucullatus nigriceps
(although some recent field guides use the name P, c. paroptus rather than
P. c. nigriceps , regarding the latter as being restricted to areas south of
Tanzania). It is a distinctive subspecies, but because the "Spotted-backed
Weaver Ploceus cucullatus " was first bred at London Zoo as long ago as
1862 and the Rufous-necked or Village Weaver P. c. cucullatus was bred
there in the 1950s, a note was not included at the end of Graham's account
suggesting that it might be the first breeding in the UK of this subspecies
- which Dave Coles believes it is. If anyone knows of a previous breeding
of this subspecies in the UK please will they inform the Hon. Secretary.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9810155" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256372" page_num="135" year="" vol="">
THE IMPORTANCE OF RECORD KEEPING IN
AVICULTURE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998329" page_id="56256372"  page_num="135" year="" vol="">
135
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.971929" page_id="56256372"  page_num="135" year="" vol="">
by Simon Matthews
Since their earliest days, zoos and other public collections have kept
records of the birds housed in their collections, an example being London
Zoo's (The Zoological Society of London's) Daily Occurrences Books
recording arrivals, births and deaths, its card index system and, in 1927, to
mark its centenary, G. Carmichael Low's Vertebrate List, a large volume
listing every species that had ever been kept in the collection. The records
kept by many zoos were very basic and often recorded only the names of
the species that were kept - some zoos kept barely any records at all. Today,
however, all public collections have to have a well organised record keeping
system and larger collections usually require one or more registrars to enable
them to fulfil the requirements of current legislation.
Before the EU (European Union) import ban, captive populations could
be maintained by the addition of freshly imported birds/fresh blood (new
genetically diverse individuals) coming in from the wild and helping to
maintain the numbers of some of these populations. However, without the
input of fresh stock from the wild, aviculturists have no alternative but to
work with the birds we already have and this is why it is so important that
we keep records of each individual bird we have in our collections.
There are two main ways of keeping records: they can be kept on paper or
electronically. Each of these methods have pros and cons. Paper records are
the cheapest and easiest to keep. Anybody can keep simple written records,
with minimal start-up costs. Electronic records require access to a computer
and, so, are initially more expensive and the record keeper will need some
sort of training on how to input the data. However, large amounts of data
can be stored on a computer and this takes up very little space, as opposed
to storing large amounts of paper. Typed computer records can be read by
anyone, whereas the handwriting of some people can be difficult to read.
Both paper and electronic records can be lost or destroyed, but electronic
records can easily be copied and backed-up, whereas paper copies take up
more space.
Most public collections keep their records on an electronic database
of some description, which may be a spreadsheet or a record keeping
programme. Most zoos, especially the larger ones, use a piece of software
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.774915">
called ARKS (Animal Record Keeping System). This was developed by
ISIS (International Species Information System) and is run by ISIS. ARKS
allows users to keep detailed records of specimens in their collections,
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999338" page_id="56256373"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
136
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.849902" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256373" page_num="136" year="" vol="">
MATTHEWS - RECORD KEEPING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999233652173913" page_id="56256373"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
including everything from the hatch date and parentage to bill length and
weight. The programme can also be used to gather information from different
individuals, on the same or different species, and it is a great tool for gathering
research and for being able to use the data that has been input when writing
articles, etc. ARKS is, however, slowly being phased out and most users
are transferring to ZIMS (Zoo Information Management System). This new
programme, which some UK zoos are already using, will bring together
all the ISIS programmes in one programme, which includes the veterinary
and studbook software, which they already offer. ZIMS will also be a lot
more flexible regarding the data that can be input and will allow the users
to store more accurate and useful information for their collections. ARKS
has worked well, but there have always been areas where record keepers
and registrars have wanted to do more or input data differently and this new
programme will allow them to do this.
Record keeping systems such as ARKS allow users to store massive
amounts of data, but not every collection is able to spare the time and/or
human resources to input data into all available data fields. There are certain
records that are more important to keep than others. However, in an ideal
world every collection, both public and private, should keep every possible
record of their birds, although this can be very time consuming and in reality
is usually only possible in the largest zoos. There are a number of basic
records, however, that should be kept by all individuals to help aid the future
of aviculture. These essential records include:
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.742994" page_id="56256373"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
Name of species
Ring details
Parentage
Age
Sex
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.989233384615385" page_id="56256373"  page_num="136" year="" vol="">
Local ID (specific to your collection, e.g. each
bird can be assigned a number from MOO)
These six essential pieces of information can easily be stored/kept. As
mentioned above, most public collections use a computer programme, but
smaller collections and private individuals can simply use a basic spreadsheet
on a computer, or an even easier method is to keep handwritten records on
lined notepaper in a ring binder kept on a book shelf.
Having physical records of the birds in our collections, means that we
can easily exchange information with other collections, leading to a better
understanding of the birds in our collections and increased standards of
husbandry. It also reduces human error, for we can all make mistakes, and
by having a simple record of our birds we can, for example, easily check that
we are sending the correct bird to another collection and that we are pairing
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.45388" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256374" page_num="137" year="" vol="">
MATTHEWS - RECORD KEEPING
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998937" page_id="56256374"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
137
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.958987" page_id="56256374"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
a male with a female and vice versa. Records also allow aviculturists to
check the parentage of individual specimens before arranging exchanges.
In recent years the parentage of our birds has become even more important,
as the populations of many species have decreased and the availabilty of
fresh stock/fresh blood has been greatly reduced due to the EU ban on the
import of wild birds.
The future of aviculture depends on us keeping accurate records, if we
are to ensure that the populations of the species currently being kept by
aviculturists are to still be around for future generations to enjoy.
Simon Matthews is Senior Aviary Keeper and ARKS representative at
the Rothschild Foundation, Waddesdon Manor Aviary, Waddesdon, near
Aylesbury, Buckinghamshire HP 18 OJH, UK Website:www. waddesdon.
org. uk/E-mail: Simon. Matthews@nationaltrust. org. uk
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.9220525" page_id="56256374"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
*
* *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.689195" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56256374" page_num="137" year="" vol="">
COMING GOOD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9934952" page_id="56256374"  page_num="137" year="" vol="">
It seems as so the 2011 breeding season may have been the best breeding
season yet for the Sumatran Laughingthrush Garrulax bicolor. At the
beginning of September, Andrew Owen, Curator of Birds at Chester Zoo
and European Studbook holder for this species, told me that they had two
chicks in the nest at Chester and this species has also been bred this year at
"Bristol, Waddesdon and Prague." Andrew has promised to write some notes
to bring members up to date on the progress that is being made breeding
this laughingthrush whose chicks had, up until this year, always had to be
hand-reared.
On the subject of whether or not the Sumatran Laughingthrush was once
more common than it is today, and its numbers have declined as a result of
the cage bird trade and/or habitat loss, it is interesting to note that when I
was writing my biography of W. J. C. (Wilfred) Frost (see Vol.l 16, No.4,
pp. 158-183 (2010)), I found no reference to him ever having brought back
this laughingthrush. This is despite the fact that he regularly brought back
birds from Sumatra, including the Long-tailed Sibia Heterophasiapicaoides
simillima , which appears to occupy a similar range and similar habitat to the
laughingthrush. I am unaware of any reference to this laughingthrush in UK
aviculture prior to about 1987 (see Vol.l 14, No.3, p,132 (2008), Vol.l 15,
No. 1, p.40 (2009) &amp; Vol. 115, No.3, p. 159 (2009)).
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998754" page_id="56256375"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
138
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.98301" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256375" page_num="138" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
BRED FOR THE FIRST TIME
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9974985" page_id="56256375"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
I am grateful to my good friend Richard Meyer, who lives in north Devon,
for sending a cutting from our regional newspaper the Western Morning
News, p.6, August 20th 2011, showing one of two recently fledged Toco
Toucans Ramphastos toco at Paignton Zoo, which is apparently begging
for food from the male, who appears to be about to offer it a grape. It is the
first time this species has bred at Paignton Zoo. The male came from Leeds
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.5080515" page_id="56256375"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
Castle Aviary in 2004 and the female from Attica Zoo in Greece in 2010.
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.712038" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256375" page_num="138" year="" vol="">
BRED FOR ONLY THE SECOND TIME
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.891739714285714" page_id="56256375"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
Shortly after I received the above newspaper cutting, our regional BBC
TV news programme featured an item about a Marabou chick Leptoptilos
crumeniferus hatched earlier this year at Paignton Zoo, which included an
interview with Senior Head Bird Keeper, Peter Smallbones. It is believed to
be only the second Marabou ever to be bred in the UK, the first having been
bred at Blackbrook Zoological Park in 1999 (see Vol. 106, No.4, pp. 182-184
(2000); see also Vol. Ill, No.2, pp.56-63 (2005)).
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.916019166666667" page_id="56256375"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
* * *
RECORD NUMBER OF MACAWS BRED
Neville Brickell sent a cutting from a South African newspaper showing
a Scarlet Macaw Ara macao perched on the head of Kimberly Marie
Patrick, described in the picture caption as an adjudicator for Guinness
World Records. The photograph was taken at Xcaret ecological park, south
of Cancun in Mexico, where a "record breaking" total of 105 Scarlet and
Military Macaws A. militaris have been hatched in captivity since 2009.
* * *
LONG-LIVED BALD EAGLE DIES
Avicultural Society Chairman Christopher Marler has lost his female
American Bald Eagle Haliaeetus leucocephalus, which arrived at Flamingo
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.74116475" page_id="56256375"  page_num="138" year="" vol="">
Gardens and Zoological Park from Canada as an injured, brown-headed
immature bird (on a salvage permit) in 1980 and, between 1986-2007, raised
a record breaking 30 young with her partner, a male hatched at Frankfurt
Zoo in Germany.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.699871" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256376" page_num="139" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997097" page_id="56256376"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
139
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.684908" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56256376" page_num="139" year="" vol="">
NEW ARRIVALS AT LORO PARQUE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98954145" page_id="56256376"  page_num="139" year="" vol="">
In August, Simon Braskmd (who is, of course, a Vice President of
the Avieultural Society and a familiar name to readers of the Avicultural
Magazine ) became the new Curator of Birds at Loro Parque, Tenerife. Dr
Matthias Reinschmidt, Zoological Director of the Loro Parque Fundaeion
(LPF), said that Simon brings with him a wealth of practical experience of
bird breeding and will further strengthen the team at Loro Parque.
Over a thousand young parrots had been reared by August. Without doubt
the most important recent highlight had been the rearing of four young Lear's
Macaws Anodorhynchus leari. The two proven breeding pairs each raised
two chicks. These increased the LPF's number of Lear's Macaws to 27.
Four young Red-spectacled Amazons Amazonapretrei had fledged. Two
were reared by their parents and two were hand-reared in the parque's baby
station. There were three pairs of Festive Amazons A. festiva hodini with
between one to three young. These were the second brood of young, those
of the first brood having been successfully hand-reared in the baby station.
The first clutch of eggs laid by the Yucatan Amazons A. xantholora were
infertile, but two healthy chicks hatched from the second clutch and were
easily reared and had already fledged and were flying about in the aviary
with their parents.
A second highlight was the breeding of the Yellow-crowned Amazon
A. ochrocephala xantholaema. It was the third successful breeding season
for this pair, which this year raised a total of four young. This increases the
population of this rarely kept subspecies to 10. The parque has a significant
surplus of males, but believes the chances of building-up a self-sustaining
captive breeding population are gradually improving. Dr Reinschmidt says
that the few breeders holding this subspecies need to work together very
closely, otherwise there is a danger that this attractive subspecies could
disappear from our aviaries.
By September the breeding season was beginning to wind down. Some
species, however, such as the Hyacinth Macaw Anodorhynchus hyacinthinus,
breed relatively late in the year. Three pairs had produced five chicks, while
a further three young were progressing well in the baby station. Two further
pairs were still incubating eggs.
Among Simon's first jobs on arriving at Loro Parque was to take on the
difficult task of hand-rearing a tiny Desmaresf s Fig Parrot Psittaculirostris
desmarestii occidentalis. He took the chick home each evening in a portable
incubator and fed the chick at regular intervals throughout the night and
brought it back each morning. At the time of writing (September 2011)
it was over five weeks old and was well on its way to growing into a fine
young fig parrot.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.940077" page_id="56256377"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
140
</page>
<figure confidence="0.289662" page_id="56256377"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
A Short-tailed Parrot Graydidascalus brachyurus had fledged and could
be seen sitting alongside its parents, as all three preened one another.
* * *
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.980255" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256377" page_num="140" year="" vol="">
NEWS FROM WUPPERTAL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997254" page_id="56256377"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
In mid-August, I received an e-mail from Chris Brack alerting me to
the news that the Brazilian Merganser Mergus octosetaceus has been bred
in captivity for the first time, the breeding having occurred in Brazil. In
Wildfowl: An identification guide to ducks, geese and swans of the world
(Madge &amp; Bums, 1988), it is described as one of the least known of all
waterfowl - a secretive 'sawbill' living on fast-flowing rivers of central
South America (southern Brazil and adjacent regions of eastern Paraguay
and north-eastern Argentina).
A few days after the e-mail, I received by post, Zoo Wuppertal 129 .
Jahresbericht 2010 - the zoo's Annual Report for last year. New arrivals
in 2010 included: 1.0 King Penguin Aptenodytes patagonica, 2.2 Gentoo
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.812859" page_id="56256377"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
Penguins Pygoscelis papua , 0.1 King Eider Somateria spectabilis , 0.1
Harlequin Duck Histrionicus histrionicus , 1.1 Chinese Mergansers M.
squamatus , 1.0 Sunbittem Eurypyga helias , 2.1 Beautiful Fruit Doves
Ptilinopuspulchellus , 1.0 Snowy-crowned Robin-Chat Cossypha niveicapilla,
</table>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.957461">
2.2 Long-tailed Tits Aegithalos caudatus, 1.1 White-lined Tanagers
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.95768085" page_id="56256377"  page_num="140" year="" vol="">
Tachyphonus rufus, 1.1 Paradise Tanagers Tangara chilensis , 1.3 Turquoise
Tanagers T. mexicana, 3.3 Double-barred (Bicheno) Finches Tceniopygia
bichenovii and 1.1 Hawfinches Coccothraustes coccothraustes.
Noteworthy among the species bred were 11 Elegant Crested Tinamous
Eudromia elegans , two King Penguins, four African (Jackass or Black-
footed) Penguins Spheniscus demersus , two Madagascar Crested Ibis
Lophotibis cristata , two Buffleheads Bucephala albeola, a Bateleur
Terathopius ecaudatus , two Red-crowned Cranes Grus japonensis, 34
Avocets Recurvirostris avosetta , five Cape Thick-knees Burhinus capensis , a
Victoria Crowned Pigeon Goura victoria , two Blue-and-yellow Macaws Ara
ararauna , two Toco Toucans Ramphastos toco , two Swallow-tailed Manakins
Chiroxiphia caudata , a Bam Swallow Hirundo rustica, six Dunnocks
Prunella modularis , seven Vermilion Flycatchers Pyrocephalus rubinus ,
five Brazilian Tanagers Ramphocelus bresilius, two Blue-faced Honeyeaters
Entomyzon cyanotis , three Gouldian Finches Erythrura gouldiae, 20 Timor
Zebra Finches T. guttata and three Bali Starlings Leucopsar rothschildi.
There is a colour photo of one of the two young manakins (p.13), a photo
of one of the young Brazilian Tanagers begging for food from the male,
which is not responding (p.16) and also a photo of the Victoria Crowned
Pigeon chick on the nest with one of its parents (p.47).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700222" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256378" page_num="141" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995948" page_id="56256378"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
141
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995996" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256378" page_num="141" year="" vol="">
WORKING WITH THE BLUE-CROWNED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98352924137931" page_id="56256378"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
In Chester Zoo's Z Magazine , pp. 11 -13, Spring 2011, in an article about
the Blue-crowned Laughingthrush Dryonastes courtoisi , illustrated by
several wonderful photographs of this species taken in the wild in China,
Roger Wilkinson the zoo's Head of Field Conservation &amp; Research, wrote
that the zoo first began keeping this species in 1993, when it received a pair
from Leeds Castle Aviary, followed by two further pairs from Raymond
Sawyer - President of the Avicultural Society, These birds bred for the first
time at Chester in 1996 and subsequently bred there regularly each year
until 2001, with Chester-bred birds being sent to Rode Tropical Bird Garden
(which no longer exists), Paradise Park at Hayle here in Cornwall, Jersey Zoo,
Mulhouse Zoo in France and Rotterdam Zoo in the Netherlands. There was
then a gap of four years until, through the European Studbook, a new female
was received from Leeds Castle Aviary. Since then chicks have been hatched
each year and further Chester-bred birds have been sent to Paultons Park in
Hampshire, Belfast Zoo, the Durrell Wildlife Conservation Trust (formerly
Jersey Zoo), Rotterdam Zoo and Koln Zoo in Germany. Chester Zoo is one
of only a few EAZA (European Association of Zoos and Aquaria) zoos which
continues to regularly breed this Critically Endangered species.
A total of 122 Blue-crowned Laughingthrushes were, Roger wrote, listed
on the ISIS international inventory on November 2nd 2010. Ninety-five of
these were in Europe and 27 in the USA. During the previous 12 months,
19 had been hatched in Europe and one in the USA. A further 26 birds
listed as Yellow-throated Laughingthrushes D. galbanus (of which courtoisi
was originally considered to be a subspecies) are likely to be Blue-crowned
Laughingthrushes, as the former remains unknown in captivity in Europe
and North America. Laura Gardner, Curator of Birds at Leeds Castle Aviary
has, since 2003, been the European Studbook holder for the Blue-crowned
Laughingthrush and Mark Myers of Woodland Park Zoo, Seattle, manages
the zoo population in the USA.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.357369" page_id="56256378"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.529557" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256378" page_num="141" year="" vol="">
STUDYING LILIAN'S LOVEBIRD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.822126571428571" page_id="56256378"  page_num="141" year="" vol="">
Last year Tiwonge Mzumara, financed by an award of #960 (approx.
US$ 1,600) from the African Bird Club, made two extended visits to Liwonde
National Park in Malawi, to assess the current status in the park of the Near-
threatened Lilian's or Nyasa Lovebird Agapornis lilianae.
The illegal hunting of birds for food is said to be prevalent in the park,
with the favoured method often being to poison the small pools of water
which the birds visit to drink during the dry season. However, during the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998675" page_id="56256379"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
142
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.928443" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256379" page_num="142" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9836988" page_id="56256379"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
study only one poisoned waterhole was found, probably because of increased
patrols introduced by the park's management. Outside of the park hunting
occurs throughout the year, with local communities regarding the lovebirds
as pests and poisoning and trapping them.
A total of 2,113 lovebirds were counted in the park during the study
(approximately twice as many as had been estimated). They were mainly
observed feeding on the seeds of Acacia xanthophlea and the fruits of
Capparis tomentosa , as well as petals, sepals and immature fruits of
Adamsonia digitata , the fruits of some Ficus spp. and the seeds of herbs
and grasses.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.819057" page_id="56256379"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.739001" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56256379" page_num="142" year="" vol="">
TWO NEW PAIRS OF HORNBILLS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985943888888889" page_id="56256379"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
Having previously adopted a pair of Bushy-crested Hornbills Anorrhinus
galeritus (in 2002) and later a pair of Rhinoceros Hornbills Buceros
rhinoceros , followed by a pair of Great Hornbills B. hicornis , this year the
society has adopted a pair of White-crowned Hornbills Berenicornis comatus
and a pair of Wreathed Hornbills Aceros undulatus in southern Thailand,
as part of the Hombill Research Foundation's, Hombill Family Adoption
Program. This is the program in which local villagers who previously took
hombill chicks from their nests to sell, now guard the nests and collect
valuable research data.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.68782525" page_id="56256379"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
* * *
NEW ARRIVALS FROM NORTH AFRICA
Two juvenile North African Ostriches Struthio c. camelus have arrived
at Paignton Zoo Environmental Park in south Devon, here in the UK, as
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.998164" page_id="56256379"  page_num="142" year="" vol="">
part of a European conservation plan. The two males, described as "feisty
characters", already stand more than 1.8m (6ft) tall and may eventually
weigh as much as 158kg (3501b).
Hannover Zoo in Germany, which is leading the conservation effort,
collected 28 eggs from birds living in Souss Masa National Park near Agadir
in Morocco. Eighteen chicks hatched, but there were only six females. More
females will, it is hoped, be brought in later.
This red-necked subspecies (considered by some to be a full species)
has disappeared from 12 of the 18 countries in which it used to be found
in North Africa. The only significant population outside of Morocco is in
Niger, where there may only be about 60 birds.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.699962" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256380" page_num="143" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997983" page_id="56256380"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
143
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.946585" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256380" page_num="143" year="" vol="">
THE JEWEL HUNTER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.953633307692308" page_id="56256380"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
Chris Gooddie turned his back on a successful job in order to satisfy his
dream of seeing all of the world&apos;s 32 species of pittas in the wild in a single
year. To do so he travelled more than 200,000km (124,275 miles) through
Thailand, Malaysia, Taiwan, Sabah, Vietnam, the Philippines, Indonesia,
Australia, Sri Lanka, Manus (one of the Admiralty Islands and home to the
Superb Pitta Pitta superba ) and the Solomon Islands, as well as visiting the
K i bale Forest in south-west Uganda, where he saw and photographed the
Green-breasted Pitta P reichenowi and Zambia, dose to the border with
Zimbabwe, to find the African Pitta E angolensis - though on that occasion
his camera failed to work at the crucial moment. Chris tells the story of
his pursuit of all 32 species of pittas and some of the other 2,000 species
of birds he saw during his year long journey in his book The Jewel Hunter
published by Wild Guides, Old Basing.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.595701" page_id="56256380"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.712915" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256380" page_num="143" year="" vol="">
AWARDS FOR 2010
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98076725" page_id="56256380"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
At the recent Council Meeting held at Paultons Park on September 24th
2011, members of the council decided that the D. H. S. Risdon Award for
the most informative article in the magazine during 2010, should go to
I. I. Elston, K. Unger and R. Dunn of Fort Worth Zoo for their article on
the reproductive behaviour of the Saddle-billed Stork Ephippiorhynchus
senegalensis and the developmental behaviour of the chicks (Vol 116, No.3,
pp. 100-108).
The Dulcie Cooke Award for the best photographs in the magazine during
2010, was awarded to Pierre de Chabannes for his photographs illustrating
the accounts of his visit to Parc de Cleres (Vol. 116, No. 1, pp. 16-24), Taipei
Zoo (Vol. 116, No.2, pp.63-73) and Weltvogelpark Walsrode (Vol. 116, No.3,
pp. 109-127).
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.2296692" page_id="56256380"  page_num="143" year="" vol="">
* sfs *
ADDITIONAL SOURCES OF INFORMATION
Have you visited the Avicultural Society website - http://www.avisoc.
co.uk - lately or seen us on Facebook - http://en-gb.facebook.com/pages/The-
Avicultural-Society/192426724136286
</figure>
<page confidence="0.999608" page_id="56256381"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
144
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.985174" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256381" page_num="144" year="" vol="">
OBITUARY
STEWART PYPER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997858333333334" page_id="56256381"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
The sudden and unexpected death of Stewart Pyper came as a great
shock to his fellow council members. Stewart will be greatly missed by
the members of the council and all his many friends in the bird world, who
knew him personally or through their dealings with the Avicultural Society
and before that the Foreign Bird League.
Stewart phoned me on Monday morning, October 17th, to discuss society
business and enquire about the progress of the next issue of the magazine.
He invariably phoned me each Monday morning and perhaps once or twice
during the course of the week and on this occasion, as on previous occasions,
he sounded his usual bright and breezy self, and there was not the slightest
hint that anything might have been amiss. Immediately after calling me,
he spoke to the Avicultural Society President, Raymond Sawyer, and called
Raymond again early that evening and talked about writing a piece for the
magazine about Raymond's recent 87th birthday celebration and of visiting
Raymond at Chestnut Lodge the following week. It seems that Raymond
may have been the last person to have spoken to Stewart, because when John
Ellis phoned later that evening, there was no answer.
A few weeks earlier Stewart had been among those manning the society's
stand at this year's National Exhibition, hosted by the Parrot Society UK,
at the Staffordshire County Showground, he had taken part in the society's
visit to Germany and had been largely responsible for organising our Autumn
Social Meeting at Paultons Park.
Stewart had been an Avicultural Society council member for a great many
years and had been closely involved in all aspects of the smooth running
of the society. He is probably irreplaceable and, as I wrote earlier, will be
greatly missed.
We hope to publish a fuller appreciation in the next issue of the
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.619639" page_id="56256381"  page_num="144" year="" vol="">
magazine
Malcolm Ellis
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993416" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256382" page_num="" year="" vol="">
NEW CHAIRMAN OF THE
WORLD PHEASANT ASSOCIATION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.972299555555555" page_id="56256382"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Dr Richard Carden has been elected the new Chairman of the World
Pheasant Association (WPA). He succeeds Prof. Tim Lovel, a co-founder
of the WPA in 1975, who has long played a prominent role in the World
Pheasant Association. Richard Carden is a former career civil servant and
Director General of the Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food (MAFF),
the predecessor of DEFRA (Department for Environment, Food &amp; Rural
Affairs). He is also a member of the BTO (British Trust for Ornithology),
the Norfolk Wildlife Trust and a former assistant warden at Lundy Bird
Observatory off the coast of north Devon.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.4958668" page_id="56256382"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
* * *
NEW CURATOR
Josef Lindholm, who until very recently was Senior Aviculturist at
Dallas World Aquarium, is the new Curator of Birds at Tulsa Zoo and Living
Museum, which occupy an 84 acres (approx. 34 hectares) site in Mohawk
Park, the third largest municipal park in the USA. Tulsa Zoo and Living
Museum, which have nearly 600,000 visitors a year, currently exhibit more
than 2,800 animals, many of these rare and endangered. We look forward
to hearing from Josef, with news of the bird collection.
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.836415" genericHeader="method" page_id="56256382" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.658950916666667" page_id="56256382"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society is keen to reduce its large stock of back issues.
These have been sorted by year into complete sets and are being offered for
sale at the reduced price of #5 per set, per year, plus postage at cost.
Complete sets are available for the years: 1928,1932,1934,1935,1936,
1937, 1938, 1939, 1941, 1942, 1943, 1944, 1945, 1948, 1949, 1950, 1951,
1953, 1954, 1955, 1956, 1957, 1958, 1959, 1960, 1962, 1963, 1964, 1965,
1966, 1967, 1968, 1969, 1970, 1971, 1973, 1976, 1977, 1978, 1979, 1980,
1981, 1982, 1983, 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988, 1989, 1990, 1991, 1992,
1993, 1994, 1995, 1996, 1997, 1998, 1999, 2000, 2001, 2002, 2003, 2004,
2005, 2006, 2007, 2008 and 2009.
Before sending any money, it is advisable to check that the magazines
you require remain available. To do so, please contact Peter Stocks, The
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.841904333333333">
Hon. Secretary and Treasurer, The Avicultural Society, Sheraton Lodge,
Station Road, Southminster, Essex CM0 7EW,. Tel: 01621 772427/E-mail:
otusscops@talktalk.net
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.648605" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56256383" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
</sectionHeader>
<address confidence="0.285921">
3 9088 01661 2624
</address>
<bodyText confidence="0.484033666666667" page_id="56256383"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Visually sexing the Senegal Parrot Poicephalus senegalus
together with an example of social breeding behaviour
by this species
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.797527153846154" page_id="56256383"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Paolo Bertagnolio.97
Lorikeet exhibits in UK zoos
by Rosemary Low.99
The Chestnut-backed Thrush Zoothera dohertyi
by Gary Bralsford.102
Captive care of the Friendly Ground Dove Gallicolumba stairi
in Samoa
by Rose Collen, Bronwyn McCulloch, David Butler
and Glen Holland.105
Hand-rearing a Great Blue Turaco Corythaeola cristata
at Paradise Park, Hayle, Cornwall
by Rebecca Waite.Ill
The Southern Crested Caracara Caracara plancus, including its
breeding at Weltvogelpark Walsrode
by Simon Bruslund and Lech Bretschek.122
The Malay or Buffy Fish Owl Ketupa ketupu
by Peter Stocks. 128
The latest list of Special Interest Groups and the Coordinators... 130
The Society's Special Interest Groups
by Malcolm Ellis....131
The importance of record keeping in aviculture
by Simpn^fatthews.135
Ne&gt;ys.&amp; Views .138
Obituary
Stewart Pyper.144
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
</table>
</algorithms>
