<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<equation confidence="0.4982296" page_id="56264407"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
P^HSO N/a/v&amp;apos;&amp;quot;
m 0 5 2005
^IBRA?!0S&amp;apos;
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 110
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264408" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990578714285714" page_id="56264408"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2004 as for 2003: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.618871" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264408" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE..
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970951409090909" page_id="56264408"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, ARCADIA, THE MOUNTS, TOTNES, DEVON TQ9 7QJ, UK.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TN13 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail: Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998476" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264408" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982477333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.78837" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264409" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.35795" page_id="56264409"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 110 " No. 4 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2004
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9315755" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264409" page_num="" year="" vol="">
STRIGXFORMES AND PSITTACIFORMES:
PHILOGENETIC LIKENESS OR CONVERGENCE?
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.668845">
by Paolo Bertagnolio
Resume
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993207090909091" page_id="56264409"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Can the poorly known feeding habits of captive owls be considered a
circumstantial clue backing up the phylogenetic likeness of Strigiformes
and Psittaciformes?
The basic difficulty in taxonomic analysis of large orders, as pointed out
by Homberger (1980), is distinguishing between similar characters that
indicate a close relationship of two or more taxa (homologous characters
which have been inherited from a common ancestor) and similar characters
which have evolved independently in response to particular environmental
pressures (convergent characters).
The long debated question of which order or orders of birds parrots are
most closely related to is still largely controversial. Peters (1937) placed
the Psittaciformes between the Columbiformes and the Cuculiformes, while
Mayr &amp; Amadon (1951) pointed out morphological similarities with the
Strigiformes, though excluding a phylogenetic link between the two orders.
Based on a comparative study of the egg-white proteins, Sibley &amp; Alquist
(1972) came to the conclusion that parrots are a distinctive group of birds,
whose nearest allies seem to be the pigeons. Burton (1974) also favoured
the view that Columbiformes is the order more closely related to
Psittaciformes and pointed out that several features of the Tooth-billed Pigeon
Didunculus strigirostris show significant trends towards those present in
parrots.
The morphological likeness of the pigeons and the primitive Malagasy
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.5392978">
genus Coracopsis has been stressed by Low (1992). According to Joshua
(1994) both C vasa and C. nigra have a karyotype which is not characteristic
of other African parrots, suggesting their ancestors may have been from
Asia. (Unlike any other parrot, when in breeding condition, the two
Coracopsis spp, undergo peculiar metamorphoses, i.e. eversion of the cloaca
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999463" page_id="56264410"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
146
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.875088" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264410" page_num="146" year="" vol="">
BERTAGNOLIO - STRIGIFORMES AND PSITTACIFORMES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998818651162791" page_id="56264410"  page_num="146" year="" vol="">
and in the case of C. vasa, the head of the female becoming bald and yellow.)
Morphological and behavioural resemblances with Coracopsis can be
observed within the Afrotropical Musophagiformes (or Musophagidae).
Representatives of the genera Tauraco and Corythaixoides formerly at the
CSCP (Centro per lo Studio e la Conservazione degli Psittaciformi) in
compartments contiguous to C. vasa and C. nigra, showed a surprising
convergence in general attitudes, especially when jumping to and fro and
running along perches, and when jerkily moving their heads and necks in a
typical excited manner unlike any other parrot except (as far as I am aware)
Ara chlowptera and A. rubrogenys. Of particular significance could be the
sunbathing postures of the turacos and Coracopsis which lay flat on a perch
with partly spread wings and occasionally perch on the ground with the tail
pointing upwards. Females of both groups (and occasionally macaws and
the Palm Cockatoo Probosciger aterrimus ) can also be observed with the
tail erect when copulating. The harsh guttural sounds and melodic whistles
of Coracopsis are atypical of parrots.
The broad and compact bill of Coracopsis , with no appreciable notches
on the sides of it (vaguely reminiscent of the decurved upper mandible of
turacos) could be considered an unspecialised, primitive psittacine type of
bill. Suggestive of turacos also are the relatively long tarsi, rudimentary
nuchal crest (perceivable in C. nigra), small head, long neck and tail, rounded
wings (with slow wing beats), prominent naked cere, greyish-blue hues and
the colour pattern of the tail, as well as analogies in secondary characters
related to the colour of the bill of C. vasa and Corythaixoides leucogaster.
Fossil turacos have been reported from the late Eocene of Bavaria (Fry,
Keith &amp; Urban, 1988) and early Oligocene and the Miocene of France
(Feduccia, 1980), and show that these birds were once widespread, at least
in the Old World. The earliest fossil parrots are Paiaeopsittacus georgei
from deep clay deposits of the low-middle Eocene near Walton-on-the-Maze,
Essex, England, and Archeopsittacus verreauxi from the upper Oligocene
or lower Miocene of France.
Detailed analyses of DNA by Sibley, Alquist &amp; Monroe (1988) threw
some new light onto the question. Though confirming that parrots stand
alone as a discrete group, such analyses indicate that their DNA shares certain
characteristics with that of other clusters of families, including the swifts
(Apodiformes), trogons (Trogoniformes), owls (Strigiformes) and cuckoos
(Cuculiformes) and that, in spite of shared crop milk and a fleshy cere, the
pigeon-parrot link may be more tenuous than previously considered.
According to Sibley &amp; Alquist (1990), albeit parrots and pigeons share some
characteristics, they differ in so many ways that a close relationship cannot
be supported.
Morphological and ecological convergence towards Strigiformes show
up in the nocturnal Kakapo Strigops habroptilus, though here stress must be
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.563493" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264411" page_num="147" year="" vol="">
BERTAGNOLIO - STRIGIFORMES AND PSITTACIFORMES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999162" page_id="56264411"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
147
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.965419880952381" page_id="56264411"  page_num="147" year="" vol="">
put on convergence. Generally speaking, parrots are considered to be
vegetarians, though there are a few prominent exceptions. In New Zealand
the diet of the Kaka Nestor meridionalis includes grubs, while in the same
country the KeaTV. notahilis , besides grubs, grasshoppers, snails, rats, mice,
rabbits and nestling birds, may occasionally feed on sheep and Red Deer
Cervus elaphus carcasses, and even attack dying animals trapped in the
snow (Diamond &amp; Bond, 1999). The small kakarikis Cyanoramphus
unicolor and C. novaezelandiae hochstetteri of the Antipodes Islands feed
largely on the carcasses of penguins and other vertebrates washed up onto
the shore by the surf, similarly to the now extinct C. n. erythrotis of Macquarie
Island. In Australia cockatoos of the genus Calypthorhynchus eagerly devour
grubs they attain when stripping bark off Eucalyptus and other trees (replacing
woodpeckers not represented on that continent), while insects and insect
larvae are included in the diets of a large number of Australian cockatoos,
parakeets and lorikeets ( Callocephalon, Eolophus , Cacatua , Platycercus ,
Barnardius, Psephotus, Northiella , Trichoglossus , etc.) (Saunders, Rowley
&amp; Smith, 1985; Wyndham &amp; Cannon, 1985; Rowley &amp; Chapman, 1991;
Sindel &amp; Gill, 1996; Higgins, 1999, etc.). Remains of grubs and insect
larvae have been found in the stomachs of Agapornis swindernianus in Africa,
as well as in the stomachs of convergent Micropsitta the diminutive parrots
of New Guinea and nearby islands (Forshaw, 1989). In South America both
the Golden-winged Parakeet Brotogeris chrysopterus chrysosema and the
Hyacinth Macaw Anodorhynchus hyacinthinus are known to feed on small
water snails, molluscs, worms and beetle larvae, and insect larvae are sought
by Scarlet Macaws Ara macao , Red-bellied Macaws Orthopsittaca manilata,
Barraband's Parrots Pionopsitta barrabandi, Aratinga spp. and Pyrrhura
spp. (Roth, 1989). In the Caatinga of Minas Gerais, Brazil, a flock of Golden-
crowned Conure A. aurea was seen catching winged termites on the ground
as these emerged from a terrestrial termite nest (Sick, 1993).
It is very likely that animal proteins are included in the diets of a larger
quota of parrots (if not all of them) than is generally thought. Palm Cockatoos
in West Papua (formerly Irian Jaya) (fide Soendji in Bertagnolio, 1994)
occasionally feed their offspring small reptiles and other small vertebrates.
Attenborough (1980) described how a flock of Quaker Parakeets Myiopsitta
monachus in Argentina flew down and noisily gorged themselves on strips
of meat hanging from a line to dry.
All parrot species at the CSCP relish raw minced meat and Cacatua,
Psephotus, Alisterus, Loriculus spp. and others at breeding time avidly devour
mealworms, at which time their consumption of dry seed drops conversely.
Many of the larger species (Ara, Anodorhynchus, Amazona and Psittacus)
enjoy raw chicken necks and pink mice, and on one occasion I watched a
male Pesquef s Parrot Psittrichas fulgidus in a large aviary dash from the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998937" page_id="56264412"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
148
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.874842" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264412" page_num="148" year="" vol="">
BERTAGNOLIO - STRIGIFORMES AND PSITTACIFORMES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996067" page_id="56264412"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
perch and seize a mouse in its bill, which it then dismembered and devoured,
using the rear part of its tongue to force pieces of the meat back into its
gape. More than once I have noticed two Palm Cockatoos share a mouse
one of them was firmly holding with one of its feet, though I am unable to
say whether the mouse was killed by the birds or was picked up from the
aviary floor when it was already dead. Similar behaviour by a Blue-fronted
Amazon A. aestiva aestiva was witnessed recently, during which a Mitred
Conure A, mitrata in the same enclosure tried to join in the 'banquet 5 .
Breeding Red-capped Parrots P. pileata formerly at the CSCP used to dig in
ant nests searching for stored seeds and insect larvae.
From the above examples one might hypothesize that analogies in beak
morphology in Psittaciformes and Strigiformes are the result of similar
functions in the past rather than mere convergence, and that the two groups
split from a common camivorous/fragivorous ancestor. As pointed out by
Smith (1975), if it did not have such a small gape a parrot's bill would rather
resemble that of a birds of prey.
While a quota of animal proteins are included in the diets of the majority
(if not all) parrots, owls may not be as strictly camivorous/insectivorous as
normally considered. In this context it is of interest to mention a strange
liking for vegetable matter by at least two species of the order Strigiformes.
For more than 20 years (up until 1995) the CSCP also acted as a rescue
centre for birds of prey on behalf of the Italian League for Bird Preservation.
During that time thousands of specimens were temporarily cared for here,
including a number of Scops Owls Otus scops. These were fed day-old
chicks, pink mice, mealworms, crickets, locusts and a little red meat. It was
not until 1990 that I had the opportunity to observe an unusual feeding
behaviour by this species.
At that time the premises were crowded and we were required to put
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.697279">
four Scops Owls in a flight cage (3m x 1m x 2m (approx. 9ft 9m x 3ft 3in x
6ft 6in)), part of a row housing Aratinga conures. One evening at dusk
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.977965307692308" page_id="56264412"  page_num="148" year="" vol="">
when I was checking the flights from some distance through a pair of
binoculars, I noticed one of the owls trying to reach through the wire partition
to peck a piece of apple in the nearby compartment. From that time on
apple became a regular item of food for these owls and was readily sought
after by all of them. Other fruits and vegetables such as water melon, ripe
figs, bananas, cherries and apricots, as well as endive and lettuce, were
successfully tested. The liking for apple, figs and lettuce was confirmed by
Giampaolo Rebecchi, who told me that in midsummer in his former collection
the preferred food of the Scops Owls was vegetable matter and that animal
proteins were only second choice. Lettuce leaves being eaten by captive
adults was quoted by Koenig (in Cramp, 1985) and Dr Giacomo DelFOmo
told me that Tawny Owls Strix aluco in his possession eagerly devoured
ripe cherries.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.563468" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264413" page_num="149" year="" vol="">
BERTAGNOLIO - STRIGIFORMES AND PSITTACIFORMES
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999404" page_id="56264413"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
149
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9963988" page_id="56264413"  page_num="149" year="" vol="">
Fruits and other vegetable matter are rapidly digested and under normal
condition no detectable traces of them are left in the pellets or stomachs of
wild Scops Owls. Plant material has been however recorded by Uttendorfer
(in Cramp, 1985) and plant fibres by Fry, Keith &amp; Urban (1988). Plant
remains in Tawny Owl pellets were quoted by Gruzdev &amp; Likhachev and by
Thiollay (in Cramp, 1985).
Another strange behavioural habit, this one involving Little Owls Athene
noctua , is worth mentioning. Every year when all the rescued Little Owls
(up to 30-40 on average) were released, the perches in their communal flight
(natural branches of different sizes and consistency) looked far thinner or
had been completely destroyed, while the wooden boxes (normally disused
parrot nest-boxes into which the birds used to shoot like bullets when their
enclosure was approached by humans) had been largely reduced to sawdust,
a convergent gnawing behaviour reminiscent of parrots and crossbills Loxia
spp. rather than owls.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.965924" genericHeader="references" page_id="56264413" page_num="149" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.752830379310345">
Attenborough, D. 1980. The Zoo Quest Expeditions. Travels to Guyana, Indonesia and
Paraguay. Lutterworth Press, Guildford, UK.
Bertagnolio, P. 1994. Tool-using by Parrots: the Palm Cockatoo and Hyacinthine Macaw.
Avicultural Magazine 100, 2:68-73.
Burton, P. I. K. 1974. Jaw and tongue features in Psittaciformes and other orders with special
reference to the anatomy of the Tooth-billed Pigeon ( Didunculus strigirostris ). Journ. Zool.
174:255-276.
Cramp, S. (ed.). 1985. The Birds of the Western Palearctic. Vol.IV. Oxford University Press.
Diamond, I. and Bond, A. B. 1999. Kea, Bird of Paradox. University of California Press,
Berkeley.
Feduccia, A. 1980. The Age of Birds. Harvard University Press, Cambridge.
Forshaw, I. M. 1989. Parrots of the World. Blandford Press, London.
Fry, C. H., Keith, S. &amp; Urban, E. K. 1988. The Birds of Africa. Vol.IIL Academic Press,
London.
Higgins, P. J. (ed.). 1999. Handbook of Australian, New Zealand and Antarctic Birds. Vol.4.
Oxford University Press, Melbourne.
Homberger, D. G. 1980. Functional morphology and evolution of the feeding apparatus in
Parrots, with special reference to the Pesquet's Parrot Psittrichasfulgidus (Lesson). In: Pasquier,
R. F. (ed.) Conservation of New World Parrots. Proc. 1CBP, WWGP MeetAl 1-485.
Joshua, S. 1994. Chromosomes solve puzzles of parrot taxonomy. Proceedings III International
Loro Parque Parrot Convention: 69-78.
Low, R. 1992. Parrots in Aviculture. Mattacchione, Pickering.
Mayr, E. and Amadon, D. 1951. A classification of recent birds. Am. Mus. Nov., 1496:1-42.
Peters, J. L. 1937. Checklist of Birds of the World. Vol.IIL Mus. Comp. Zook, Cambridge.
Roth, P. 1989. Reparti^ao do habitat entre Psittacfdeos simpatricos no sul da Amazonia. Acta
Amazonica 14, 1-2:175-221.
Rowley, L. and Chapman, G. 1991. The Breeding Biology, Food, Social Organisation,
Demography and Conservation of the Major Mitchell or Pink Cockatoo, Cacatua leadbeateri,
on the Margin of the Western Australian Wheatbelt Aust. J. Zool
</reference>
<page confidence="0.995156" page_id="56264414"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
150
</page>
<reference confidence="0.88714175">
BERTAGNOLIO - STRIGIFORMES AND PSITTACIFORMES
Saunders, D. A., Rowley, I. and Smith, G. T. 1985. The effects of clearing for agriculture on
the distribution of Cockatoos in the Southwest of Western Australia. In: Keast, A. et al. (eds.).
Birds of Eucalypt Forests and Woodlands: 309-321.
Sibley, C. J. and Alquist, J. E. 1972. A comparative study of the egg-white proteins of non-
passerine birds. Bull. Peab. Mus. Nat. Hist., 39:1-131B.
Sibley, C. G. and Alquist, J. E. 1990. Phyogeny and Classification of Birds. A Study in Molecular
Evolution. Yale University Press, New Haven.
Sibley, C. G., Alquist, J. E. and Monroe, B. L. 1988. A Classification of the living birds of the
world based on DNA-DNA hybridization studies. Auk 105:409-443.
Sick, H. 1993. Birds in Brazil. A Natural History. Princeton University Press.
Sindel, S. and Gill, J. 1992. Australian Grass Parrakeets, The Neophema. Singil Press, Australia.
Sindel, S. and Gill, J. 1996. Australian Grass Parrakeets. The Psephothus and Northiella
Genera. Singil Press, Australia.
Sindel, S. and Gill, J. 1996. Australian Cockatoos. Singil Press, Australia.
Smith, G. A. 1975. Systematics of Parrots. 117:18-68.
Wyndham, E. and Cannon, C. E. 1985. Parrots of Eastern Australian Forests and Woodlands.
In: Keast, A. et al. (eds.). Birds of Eucalyypt Forests and Woodlands: 141-150.
Paolo Bertagnolio, Centro per lo Studio e la Conservazione degli
Psittaciformes, Via Luigi Russo, 78, 00050 Aranova, Rome, Italy.
</reference>
<equation confidence="0.280603" page_id="56264414"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.5394" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264414" page_num="150" year="" vol="">
BEALE PARK DAY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.94310475" page_id="56264414"  page_num="150" year="" vol="">
Members of the Avicultural Society have been invited to join members
of The Parrot Society UK (whose recently elected Chairperson is Cliff
Wright) and members of other bird societies and clubs at Beale Park Day,
Sunday July 3rd 2005. Curator of Birds, Dave Coles, is keen to encourage
bird societies and clubs to join together to view the collection and enjoy the
facilities. There will be a concessionary half-price charge on the day.
The park, in which a number of new aviaries has been opened recently,
including a walk-through Australian aviary dedicated to the late Ron Oxley,
has a good and varied collection of birds including Wonga Pigeons, ground
doves, peacock pheasants, Bali Starlings, laughingthrushes, tanagers,
tinamous and Cobalt-winged Parakeets.
It is located on the A329 north-west of Pangboume, Berks.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999002" page_id="56264415"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
151
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.935461333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264415" page_num="151" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE RED-WINGED STARLING, INCLUDING
AN ATTEMPT TO START A BREEDING COLONY
by Louise Peat
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991482333333334" page_id="56264415"  page_num="151" year="" vol="">
The Red-winged Starling Onychognathus morio is considered to be one
of the more successful species of African passerines. It ranges from eastern
Sudan and Ethiopia southwards through eastern Africa to South Africa. It is
commonly found in urban areas where it takes full advantage of nesting and
feeding opportunities in and around human habitations. It is sexually
dimorphic, the adult male having a black head with an inky-blue sheen, and
the adult female having a grey head and neck with some dark streaking. It
is monogamous and pairs possibly mate for life. If nesting places are limited,
several pairs may nest together in a loose colony. Outside of the breeding
season Red-winged Starlings may gather in flocks of up to 500.
History
Red-winged Starlings first arrived at the Cotswold Wildlife Park, Burford,
Oxon., UK, in June 1993. A related pair was acquired from a private
collection, the female of which was later exchanged for an unrelated bird. A
year later in 1996 after the female had not been seen for a couple of days,
the nest-box was inspected and she was found dead inside. In March 1997
a new female arrived from Cricket St Thomas and two years later she laid
her first egg, which was found smashed. The following year she laid another
egg which suffered the same fate. At that point (July 2000) we decided to
move the pair to a quieter aviary on the pheasant section.
There the pair shared the aviary with a male White Eared Pheasant
Crossoptilon crossoptilon drouynii. The starlings settled in well and appeared
to enjoy their new-found privacy. Both of the birds were hand-reared and
very steady around me, the male would even fly to my hand for mealworms.
That summer no breeding behaviour was observed, in fact the pair seemed
pretty much incompatible; the female would sporadically chase the male,
but this would last for only a few seconds.
Observations and breeding 2002
In 2002 the behaviour of the birds started to change; the male was seen
to be taking more interest in the nest-box and would gather as many
mealworms as he could in his mouth and then parade in front of the female
calling. However, at no point did he offer her the mealworms, instead he
seemed to get bored and swallow them himself Various nesting materials
were made available to the birds, including dried grass, straw, small twigs
and a plastic D-dish filled with mud, which during the peak of the nest
building had to be re-filled three times a day.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998984" page_id="56264416"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
152
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.754416" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264416" page_num="152" year="" vol="">
PEAT - RED-WINGED STARLING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9986335" page_id="56264416"  page_num="152" year="" vol="">
The male did not get involved with the nest building, which to me was
very strange as everything I had read on the subject stated that it was a joint
effort. I thought it might indicate that the birds had not bonded fully, so I
was delighted when I came in one morning and the female was missing. It
was obvious that she had begun sitting. During the first week of incubation
she come off the nest only to eat but during the second week she was off
every time I went near the aviary, no matter how quietly I approached it. I
began to fear that she was no longer sitting, but bearing in mind this is quite
common behaviour with starlings, I gave her the benefit of the doubt.
Disaster struck on June 7th when the female attacked and killed the male.
I can only assume that when the chicks hatched she perceived him to be a
threat. The next day she was seen hitting a dead chick against a rock in the
aviary. Unsure as to whether the chick was already dead when she had
removed it from the nest or whether she had killed it, we decided to intervene
and remove the remaining two chicks and hand-rear them.
They were reared on a diet of waxworms, crickets, mealworms and fruit.
They were fed at two hourly intervals from 6.00am-10.00pm. They fledged
at 25 days old, and at exactly three months old, the shyest of the two began
to show grey flecking on the head and neck, indicating that she was a female.
The other was a male.
After the removal of the chicks, the female began to build a new nest
and laid a second clutch of eggs. She laid the first egg 11 days after the
male was killed and 10 days after the removal of the chicks. On the slim
chance that the eggs might be fertile they were removed for artificial
incubation but unfortunately all four proved to be infertile. Much to my
surprise she then went on to lay a third clutch, and that time I decided to
leave the eggs with her and take the opportunity to observe her nesting
behaviour, without the fear of harming viable eggs.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.371768" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264417" page_num="153" year="" vol="">
PEAT - RED-WINGED STARLING
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999593" page_id="56264417"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
153
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9930321875" page_id="56264417"  page_num="153" year="" vol="">
Once weaned the two hand-reared young were placed in the adjoining
aviary to the adult female. Their arrival was met with much interest from
the female and her initial growling was soon replaced by curiosity. When
we were sure the female had stopped laying and lost all interest in breeding
we opened the slide between the two aviaries. To my surprise there was no
aggression and within half an hour of opening the slide all three birds were
sitting together on the same perch.
Nest-box 1 (outside).
Nest-box 2 (inside).
Forming a colony
At the start of 2002 we had discussed keeping Red-winged Starlings in a
group. I had heard of a private breeder, Peter Horn, who had two nests with
chicks. Two pairs were reserved, which would have allowed us to make up
three pairs. Mr Horn eventually offered us all his birds, three males, two
females and four juveniles, which arrived in October 2002. They were housed
next door to our trio, to give them a change to feed and get used to the
aviary. The next day the pop holes were opened and all 12 birds were allowed
to mix. The two hand-reared birds fitted in instantly, but our adult female
was less sure and began growling and there were a couple of attempts to
chase some of the younger birds. Luckily her behaviour soon changed and
she became increasingly interested in the unpaired male. The two were
often seen perched together, and within a week the female was seen preening
the male.
The next day the birds were more vocal and I was amazed to hear several
vocalizations from the group that I had not heard before. Also interesting
was the bond between the two breeding pairs. I observed behaviour that I
had never seen from our original pair. Each pair was constantly together
and for the first time I observed mutual preening. This made me realise
how unstable the bond had been between our original pair, and how it could
explain the aggressive behaviour of our female towards the male. It also
supported the theory that Red-winged Starlings may mate for life.
Although the flock of 12 birds got on well, I knew that when the breeding
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999639" page_id="56264418"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
154
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.74796" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264418" page_num="154" year="" vol="">
PEAT - RED-WINGED STARLING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99708392" page_id="56264418"  page_num="154" year="" vol="">
season came around, having that large a group of birds together would pose
problems. We did not for example want to take the chance that some of that
year's juveniles might pair up with their siblings. We decided that all the
juveniles would be paired to unrelated birds and placed on loan with other
collections. This would leave the park with three unrelated pairs, two of
which were bonded and proven breeders. These would be the start of our
breeding colony.
To see if the birds would nest in a colony, a natural looking cliff or
rockface was built. It was made from wood and polystyrene, which was
covered with a layer of cement and made to look as natural as possible. It
includes four tunnels and a ledge, each big enough to hold a nest. Three of
the tunnels have observation doors so that we can observe what is happening
inside.
Natural looking cliff or rockface.
The 2003 breeding season
Signs of breeding behaviour began earlier than expected. The blue pair
started nesting on February 1st and by March 1st the pair had completed the
nest and laid the first egg. Even though this pair was by far the more
dominant, there was at that point no increase in aggression. Only the female
incubated the eggs, whilst the male constantly stood guard close to the nest
site. Any disturbance would cause the female to come off the nest and join
him.
On March 15th the first chick hatched, followed by the second and third
on March 16th and 17th. Because we had hand-reared the earlier chicks, I
had never observed parental feeding. Much to my surprise the parents would
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.371793" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264419" page_num="155" year="" vol="">
PEAT - RED-WINGED STARLING
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999378" page_id="56264419"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
155
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999819571428572" page_id="56264419"  page_num="155" year="" vol="">
kill and mash-up the livefood before feeding it to the chicks. This was done
by striking the insects on rocks in the aviary. They also removed the legs
and wings of the insects. As the chicks got older the parents were less
careful about mashing-up the livefood, and after approximately 12 days,
whole and live insects were fed to the chicks. They also showed more interest
in feeding mealworms to them. Both parents took an active part in feeding
the chicks. Livefood was provided every two hours from 7.00am-5.00pm.
Crickets and waxworms were offered initially, then as the chick got older
locusts and mealworms were also provided. The adults also had access to
their usual food, but very little of this was eaten.
The female was observed collecting the chicks' faecal sacs more
frequently than the male. These were collected during feeding periods; she
would carry them to the feeding area (the feeding platform was 4ft (approx,
lm) from the nest), drop them, and then carry on feeding. The male would
then pick up the sacs and take them further away from the nest.
On March 1st the green pair began nest building and by April 8th three
eggs had been laid. At that point this normally docile pair became a lot
more territorial and both the blue and green males began to harass the hand-
reared red male. Disappointingly the latter had not managed to bond with
our original female and showed increased signs of being imprinted and
preferring human companionship. Whenever the keeping staff were servicing
the aviary his behaviour would change and the other two males would chase
him; this stopped as soon as the keeper left. This behaviour was monitored
closely. On April 15th when the blue pair's chicks fledged, the aggression
towards the red male increased, so the decision was made to remove him
from the aviary. At that point the original female became ill and was removed
so that we could monitor and treat her.
The blue pair's chicks first showed signs of fledging on April 13 th (almost
a month after hatching), when one of the chicks came out of the nest for a
short period but then returned for the rest of the day. The parents had begun
reducing the amount of insects fed to them, and whenever they were away
from the nest, judging by their different calls, were possibly trying to
encourage the chicks to leave the nest.
When the chicks fledged on April 15th, they lacked flying skills and
spent a lot of time on the floor of the aviary. It was at that point that we
began to have concerns about the level of aggression within the group. The
green pair was incubating eggs and had become much more territorial and
the blue pair's newly fledged chicks appeared ignorant of the threat the pair
posed, and their clumsy attempts at flying seemed to provoke aggression
from the green male. In order to give the chicks a chance to 'find their
wings' the pop holes between the two aviaries were closed. From that time
onward there never seemed to be a suitable opportunity to re-open the pop
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999502" page_id="56264420"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
156
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.751983" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264420" page_num="156" year="" vol="">
PEAT - RED-WINGED STARLING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993827775" page_id="56264420"  page_num="156" year="" vol="">
holes. One or other pair always had chicks at a stage when it would have
been too risky to reintroduce them.
On April 16th the blue male was seen carrying nest material and displaying
to the female, and was building a new nest on top of the earlier nest. By the
end of the month a second clutch of three eggs had been laid and the pair
was showing signs of becoming aggressive towards the three juveniles
fledged from the earlier nest. These were moved to an off-show aviary in
which they were later joined by our original female, which had made a Ml
recovery.
The three juveniles were very unsettled in their new aviary and we felt
that by putting our original female in with them, she might have a calming
effect on them. This worked better than we ever expected, she took on the
role of surrogate mother, and was in no way aggressive. Their stress levels
decreased dramatically, and because the female was steady around people,
her calmness influenced the behaviour of the youngsters and made it easier
to service the aviary without the young birds panicking. Two juveniles
fledged by the green pair and a juvenile from the blue pair's second clutch
later joined the group.
Slowing them down
Both breeding pairs were focused on producing as many chicks as they
could. No sooner had their chicks fledged than they would set about nesting
again. Such an exhausting process would inevitably begin to take its toll on
the birds, so rather than risk their health, we decided to limit their breeding.
After the two pairs had between them reared a total of eight healthy chicks
we began to encourage them to slow down. This was done by reducing the
protein in their diet and by removing their last clutches of eggs. After
breeding had ended the blue and green pairs were allowed to join each other
again and behaved as so they had never been separated, with no aggression
being witnessed.
General husbandry
When keeping a group of Red-winged Starlings together the most
important factor is the feeding regime. We ensured that within the aviary
there were several feeding stations. It quickly became obvious that certain
pairs were territorial over certain areas of the aviary and these areas included
the feeding stations and the houses. If the number of feeding stations had
been reduced the amount of aggression would have increased dramatically.
It is important to make sure there is always sufficient food available. On the
few occasions that all the food had been eaten, there was a rise in the level
of aggression within the group which resulted in less dominant birds being
attacked.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.371589" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264421" page_num="157" year="" vol="">
PEAT - RED-WINGED STARLING
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998026" page_id="56264421"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
157
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.948999578947368" page_id="56264421"  page_num="157" year="" vol="">
Diet
Through the winter the group's diet consists mainly of finely chopped
apple, pear, tomato and greenfood (lettuce and watercress). This is
supplemented with other fruits that are available, such as pawpaw (papaya),
banana, grapes, melon etc. To add variety to the diet we use one as a treat
each day. The group is also given sultanas that have been soaked and, once
a week, oranges cut in half. Seasonal berries are given and are devoured
with enthusiasm. A small amount of meat is included in the diet, bulked out
by mixing it with soaked Diet A pellets and an insectivorous mixture.
Livefood is offered only infrequently. Neutrobal vitamin supplement is
sprinkled over the food twice a week.
Leading up to the breeding season the diet is changed, with the quantities
of meat being increased and more livefood made available. When chicks
have hatched, livefood in the form of mealworms, locusts and waxworms,
is given up to five times a day.
Water
Water is supplied at each feeding station. This is changed daily. The
starlings love to bathe and during the breeding season use the water to dampen
the mud used in the building of their nests.
Nesting
Large quantities of mud and other nesting materials need to be supplied
during the breeding season. Pairs will sometimes re-use nests built in
previous seasons and it is worthwhile checking such nests to ensure that
they are clean.
Housing
Our starlings have access to two houses, each of which contains a feeding
station and although they are quite hardy birds, the houses have heat lamps
which are switched on during winter evenings.
Identification
Each pair is fitted with colour coded rings and their offspring have
coordinated colour rings, plus an extra colour to indicate which clutch they
were from. These enable us to identify individuals within the group.
Summary of results of observational study
Several conclusions can be drawn from the results. Taking each pie
chart in turn and comparing the different pairs, straight away (Pie chart 3) it
is obvious that the two birds of the red pair had not bonded. It is very
noticeable that they spent the majority of their time vocalising and self-
preening. One can only assume that they were vocalising in an attempt to
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999027" page_id="56264422"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
158
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.25459" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264422" page_num="158" year="" vol="">
PEAT - RED-WINGED STARLING
</sectionHeader>
<tableCaption confidence="0.97779">
Table 1. Outline of observations made during 2002 breeding season.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.82745643902439" page_id="56264422"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
March 2nd
Male seen taking an interest in nest-box, which he entered
a couple of times.
May 7th
Female started building a nest in a food bowl inside house.
May 8th
Female changed her mind and instead started building a
nest in nest-box in aviary.
May 22nd
Female coming out of box only to feed. Both birds are
silent.
June 5 th
Female very interested in insects, so ration is increased.
June 7th
Male killed by female. Late afternoon chicks heard in nest-
box.
June 8th
Female seen hitting dead chick against a rock. Remaining
two chicks taken to be hand-reared.
June 11th
Female building nest in food bowl.
June 12th
Female turns her attention to building in half-open-fronted
box (Nest-box 2) inside house.
June 18th
First egg of second clutch laid between 9.00am-9.30am.
Female silent.
June 19th
Second egg of second clutch laid between 9.00am-9.30am.
June 20th
Third egg of second clutch laid. All three eggs removed for
artificial incubation.
June 21th
Fourth egg of second clutch is laid and is also taken for
incubation.
July 1st
First egg of third clutch laid.
July 2nd
Second egg of third clutch laid.
July 3rd
Third egg of third clutch laid.
</figure>
<tableCaption confidence="0.671294">
Table 2. Weights and measurements of second clutch of eggs, all of which
proved to be infertile.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.946125" page_id="56264422"  page_num="158" year="" vol="">
Egg
Weight
Measurements
1
10g
38mm x 22.3mm
2
lOg
36.9mm x 22.9mm
3
9g
38mm x 22.8mm
4
9g
37.8mm x 22.9mm
Table 3. Information gathered from two nests built by female.
Nest-box
Total area covered
by nest material
Circumference
of nest cup
Depth of
nest cup
1
12in sq
6in
3 V 2 in
(305mm sq)
(152mm)
(90mm)
2
lOin sq
5in
2V2in
(255mm sq)
(127mm)
(63mm)
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.356263" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264423" page_num="159" year="" vol="">
PEAT - RED-WINGED STARLING
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.950979" page_id="56264423"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
159
</page>
<figure confidence="0.806209636363636" page_id="56264423"  page_num="159" year="" vol="">
Pie Charts 1-3
Observations of group outside the breeding season.
Red Pair 24.01.03
2
16%
6
47% \0x25A0 v;
; y 3
37%
Key
1 Social interactions with each other
2 Social interactions with group
3 Self-preening
4 Mutual-preening
5 Physical display
6 Vocalising
7 Male nest interest
8 Female nest interest
9 Inter-male aggression
10 Inter-female aggression
11 Group aggression
12 Inter-pair aggression
</figure>
<page confidence="0.85992" page_id="56264424"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
160
</page>
<figure confidence="0.905813592592593" page_id="56264424"  page_num="160" year="" vol="">
PEAT - RED-WINGED STARLING
Pie Charts 4-6
Observations of group at start of breeding season when blue pair had
laid eggs.
Blue Pair 02.03.03
10 %
- Ipji !0%
7
35%
Green Pair 02.03.03
8
1
B -- 22%
28%
[
KTv&amp;apos; 6%
W 3
7
6 im .
27 %
6%
Key
1 Social interactions with each other
2 Social interactions with group
3 Self-preening
4 Mutual-preening
5 Physical display
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.613262428571429" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264424" page_num="160" year="" vol="">
6 Vocalising
7 Male nest interest
8 Female nest interest
9 Inter-male aggression
10 Inter-female aggression
11 Group aggression
12 Inter-pair aggression
</sectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.331632" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264425" page_num="161" year="" vol="">
PEAT - RED-WINGED STARLING
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.873243" page_id="56264425"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
161
</page>
<figure confidence="0.807557" page_id="56264425"  page_num="161" year="" vol="">
Pie Charts 7-9
Observations of group when blue pair's chicks had hatched.
Blue Pair 19.03.03
10
19% 17%
Key
1 Social interactions with each other
2 Social interactions with group
3 Self-preening
4 Mutual-preening
5 Physical display
6 Vocalising
7 Male nest interest
8 Female nest interest
9 Inter-male aggression
10 Inter-female aggression
11 Group aggression
12 Inter-pair aggression
</figure>
<page confidence="0.997641" page_id="56264426"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
162
</page>
<table confidence="0.496386" page_id="56264426"  page_num="162" year="" vol="">
PEAT - RED-WINGED STARLING
One week old.
Two weeks old.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.371628" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264427" page_num="163" year="" vol="">
PEAT - RED-WINGED STARLING
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998993" page_id="56264427"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
163
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.96506" page_id="56264427"  page_num="163" year="" vol="">
Fourth egg still in nest.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999476" page_id="56264428"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
164
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.718295" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264428" page_num="164" year="" vol="">
PEAT - RED-WINGED STARLING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.978172413793103" page_id="56264428"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
attract a more suitable mate or attempting to bond with each other. The self-
preening could also be interpreted in a number of ways, it could for example
have been to help attract a mate, insecurity (both had a low status within the
group) or perhaps even frustration.
In pie chart 6 it can be seen that at the start of the breeding season
vocalisation and self-preening decreased (the male began to parade around
with nesting material) and both birds were spending more time together. At
that point it was felt that the pair was starting to bond. However, in pie chart
9 it can be seen that the levels of vocalising and self-preening had risen
again. This could have been as a result of aggression from the blue pair,
which at the time had chicks. The red pair was continuing to interact with
each other but all nesting behaviour had ceased. Shortly after this the two
birds were removed from the aviary for the reasons given earlier.
In pie charts 1&amp;2 it can be seen that the birds of both the dominant blue
pair and the green pair spent a lot of time with their partners outside the
breeding season. It is also interesting to note that even outside the breeding
season both pairs were very interested in the nesting areas. The dominant
blue pair spent more time interacting with the red pair and also spent much
more time vocalising than the green pair. Without further study it is not
possible to understand whether this was because the birds of the blue pair
had a strong enough pair bond that they did not need to reinforce it as much
as those of the green pair, or that the opposite was the case and the birds of
the blue pair were not as committed to each other as those of the green pair,
the male and female of which spent almost all of their time together with
very little interaction with other group members.
With such a small study sample it would be wrong to draw any concrete
conclusions from this data. Nevertheless, I feel that our results have raised
several interesting points and I hope that someone else will take up the
challenge and take this study further.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.49127">
Provisional conclusions
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9980999" page_id="56264428"  page_num="164" year="" vol="">
The excitement of breeding this species was easily surpassed by the
experience of keeping the birds in a group. Although they had to be separated
for a short period during the breeding season, I continue to believe it is
possible to keep them in a group.
Had the nesting of the two pairs been synchronized, as a result of which
the chicks had fledged at the same time, perhaps the adults would have been
more tolerant of the fledglings. Also, had the aviary been larger and/or had
denser cover, we may have been more successful. Either way I think that
the quality of life of these birds is much improved if they are kept in a
group, and I would recommend this as being the best way to keep them.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.3718" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264429" page_num="165" year="" vol="">
PEAT - RED-WINGED STARLING
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999058" page_id="56264429"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
165
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9905725" page_id="56264429"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
Pairs though may need to be separated during the breeding season. One
way of doing this is to keep them in an aviary that can be sectioned off
whilst the pairs are breeding.
I am sure they could be kept in a single sex group all year round and
would make a fascinating display for the general public, giving them the
opportunity to better appreciate such a magnificent understated species.
Follow up
There are several other points I wish to follow up. The main one being
whether or not hand-reared birds will breed successfully. Our problems
with the original pair, which did not have a strong pair bond, may have been
as a result of both birds having been hand-reared. I am waiting to hear back
from the collections in which we placed our 2002 hand-reared birds, whether
or not these birds managed to form strong pair bonds with the parent-reared
birds with which they were paired.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.346301">
Afterthoughts
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9968628" page_id="56264429"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
I have learnt so much over the past two years during the course of this
study. I remain convinced that under the right conditions it should be possible
to establish a breeding colony of Red-winged Starlings in captivity. One of
the main benefits of keeping this species in a group is that when kept this
way they appear (and I apologise for being anthropomorphic) to get so much
more out of life. I am an avid believer in displaying group birds in a group,
which I guess is stating the obvious.
The primary point here is improving husbandry. With a little extra effort
we can give many species a more natural lifestyle and vastly improve their
quality of life.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.869541" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56264429" page_num="165" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9976422" page_id="56264429"  page_num="165" year="" vol="">
I would like to thank Christina Wells for her observational studies on
our group of Red-winged Starlings. She spent many days braving the
elements and undertook the study with determination and enthusiasm.
Because I was limited in the amount of time I could devote to the study, a lot
of data would have been missed without Christina's input. Her results are
produced in the very informative pie charts.
I would also like to thank Dave Edgington, who at the start of this
study was my Section Head and is now Curator of the Cotswold Wildlife
Park collection. He allowed me to try out my theories, and without his
backing and support the study would not have happened.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999093" page_id="56264430"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
166
</page>
<construct confidence="0.8677085" page_id="56264430"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
PEAT - RED-WINGED STARLING
Bibliography
Feare, C. and Craig, A. 1998. Helm Identification Guides Starlings and Mynahs. Christopher
Helm/A &amp; C. Black, London.
Louise Peat is a bird keeper at the Cotswold Wildlife Park, Burford,
Oxon. 0X18 4JW, UK. Tel:01993 823006/Fax:01993 823807/Website:
cotswoldwildlifepark. co. uk
* * *
</construct>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.818408" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264430" page_num="166" year="" vol="">
CORRECTION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998078333333333" page_id="56264430"  page_num="166" year="" vol="">
In the previous issue of the magazine (Vol. 110, No.3, pp. 104-107 (2004)),
in Magpie rescuing its mate from a Carrion Crow and other crow versus
magpie encounters by Derek Goodwin, the first sentence of the fourth
paragraph (p. 104) should have read: "I have twice seen Wood Pigeons and
once a feral pigeon grappled in flight by a crow...". This got changed to: "I
have twice seen Wood Pigeons and once a feral pigeon grappling in flight
with a crow...". This was incorrect. As Derek has written to point out,
pigeons do not "grapple" when fighting or trying to escape. I apologise for
this error. Hon. Ed.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.904314" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264431" page_num="167" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE GREEN ARACARI Pteroglossus viridis
</sectionHeader>
<figure confidence="0.346749" page_id="56264431"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
by Chris lies
</figure>
<page confidence="0.998465" page_id="56264431"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
167
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9986664" page_id="56264431"  page_num="167" year="" vol="">
It was the last week in April and I was sure I had heard a slightly different
"chirrup" that morning. I fetched my stepladder and climbed up towards
the nest-box. I remembered deciding that the nest-box was not quite in
Parents and young Green Aracaris.
One of five young bred by the author.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99852" page_id="56264432"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
168
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.803367" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264432" page_num="168" year="" vol="">
ILES - GREEN ARACARI
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97887975" page_id="56264432"  page_num="168" year="" vol="">
keeping with what the birds would have chosen in their natural habitat. The
box had been made quickly from two right angles from an old set of stairs,
Quickly made nest-box in which the pair bred.
Eggs in box.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.508111" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264433" page_num="169" year="" vol="">
ILES - GREEN ARACARI
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999162" page_id="56264433"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
169
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997846390243902" page_id="56264433"  page_num="169" year="" vol="">
with a piece of melamine nailed on the bottom. The inspection lid was a
further piece of recycled melamine held on by a rubber band. It was nearly
2ft (61cm) down to the bottom of the angled box, where on a bed of
woodchips was a pure white egg. My Green Aracaris had laid!
I had acquired them the previous year from Phil Cleeton, a fellow member
of the Avicultural Society. I considered them to be in exceptional condition
and was confident that they would tolerate an outside aviary immediately.
Having watched them in their 'hopping mode', it was decided that they
would be best suited to living in a square aviary. However, they did not
seem to settle at all in the square aviary, so were moved to the aviary next
door which although it covered a smaller area, was 6m (approx.20ft) long.
In this aviary they were able to fly directly from end to end, which they
seemed to enjoy.
The advice in my collection of books was that if they were to survive, I
should feed them nothing but fruit and low iron fare, and from the outset I
followed this path. They never seemed enthusiastic about this diet though,
so I decided to dump the 'rule book'. I provided them with minced beef,
puppy pellets, my homemade softbill mix and grapes. They liked grapes, so
I hung them up by the bunch.
In their first clutch there were four eggs, two of which hatched and both
chicks were reared. They then produced a second clutch and reared a further
three young to independence. The cycle from the first egg to commencement
of the second clutch seemed to be eight to nine weeks. The first two young
were left in the aviary during the second nesting. The parents would "purr"
over their young with obvious delight.
I supplemented their diet with some crickets during the chicks' first week,
though I suspect that most escaped into other aviaries and were consumed
by other birds. They would take a few mealworms, though it seemed that
the male was interested in them as a display item to impress the female,
more than as a regular item of food.
At the time of writing (September), the autumn sunshine has enticed the
family to show-off their lovely colours and sway their impressive bills. They
seem to have enjoyed the summer and I cannot help but wonder whether
they know of their contribution to aviculture in being the first pair of
Pteroglossus viridis to breed in the UK.
As described above, the Green Aracari Pteroglossus viridis , has been
bred by Chris lies. This is probably the first successful breeding of this
species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who knows of a previous breeding
is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
To learn more about Chris lies ' birds you can visit his website:
www. birdtrek. co. uk
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995259" page_id="56264434"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
170
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.725242666666667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264434" page_num="170" year="" vol="">
DUYVENBODE'S LORY: THE HISTORY OF ONE PAIR
FROM 1978-2004
by Rosemary Low
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8272795" page_id="56264434"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
I have kept the Chalcopsitta lories from New Guinea in my own aviaries
since 1971 when I acquired a pair of Black Lories C. atra. As Curator of
Birds at Loro Parque, Tenerife, and later at Palmitos Park, Gran Canaria, I
had many others of this genus in my care, along with up to 200 other species
of parrot. I have found Duyvenbode's Lories C. duivenbodei to be among
the most interesting of all parrots as aviary birds: intelligent, beautiful and
very affectionate towards each other. They are almost unsurpassed in
affectionate behaviour if hand-reared.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.443739">
Copyright Rosemary Low
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9927595" page_id="56264434"  page_num="170" year="" vol="">
Adult pair at Jurong BirdPark, Singapore.
In 1984 the late Bob Grantham and I were awarded the medal of the
Avicultural Society for the first breeding of Duyvenbode's Lory in Great
Britain and Ireland. This breeding was recounted in th q Avicultural Magazine
Vol.90, No.l, pp. 18-26. It related to a female imported in October 1973 and
a male imported in October 1978. Both were probably only a few months
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.369715" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264435" page_num="171" year="" vol="">
LOW - BUYVENBODE'S LORY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.99842" page_id="56264435"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
171
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9156303125" page_id="56264435"  page_num="171" year="" vol="">
old at the time of importation. The male was introduced to the female in
November 1978. The fact that they made no attempt to breed until 1982
also suggests that the male was young, as this species takes about four years
to reach sexual maturity. The young take several years to become fully
coloured; perhaps the plumage continues to increase in intensity of colour
for some years more. The male of this pair, now 25 years of age, is a very
beautiful bird with a remarkable intensity of orange-yellow on the thighs
and a more pronounced crescent-shaped area of yellow on the upper breast
that overlays the brown feathers, than the female. He has a magnificent
4 mane 5 of golden-yellow streaks on the nape - perhaps a badge of his age
(and gender). The female's plumage is only slightly less intense. She is not
quite so bold in appearance or demeanour as the male. She has a brown iris
whereas that of the male is slightly more reddish brown.
Copyright Rosemary Low
The first 2004 youngster aged exactly five months* Note the pale
periorbital skin typical of immature birds.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99815" page_id="56264436"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
172
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.748039" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264436" page_num="172" year="" vol="">
LOW - DUYVENBODE'S LORY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999742952380952" page_id="56264436"  page_num="172" year="" vol="">
The colour scheme of this lory, with its pure daffodil yellow underwing-
coverts, orange-tinged yellow thighs, the remarkable yellow crescents at
the side of the beak, and yellow forehead, blue-violet rump and rich brown
wings and body, is unique in the bird world. It is arguably the most distinctive
of all parrots.
In 19871 went to live in the Canary Islands and this pair of birds remained
with Bob Grantham. Following his death in 2002 I collected the two birds
from the same aviary in which the pair had resided for more than two decades.
Bob had told me that on one occasion the aviary had collapsed and the male
and a young bird had escaped. Unfortunately the young one was never seen
again but the male returned and was caught. This was predictable because
his pair bond with the female is extremely strong. The two are exceptionally
compatible.
I was delighted to once again have this pair in my care. They are in
excellent condition. I placed them in an aviary measuring 15ft long x 3ft
wide x 6ft high (approx. 4.5m long x lm wide x 1.8m high). This is longer
than the aviary in which they lived previously. They had never had access
to a shelter; their aviary was alongside a fence in a sheltered position and, of
course, they always roosted in their nest-box. I housed them in my only
aviary that does not have a shelter attached. The exposed side is protected
by bubble-wrap on wooden frames. The nest-box is situated so that it can
be inspected from outside in the covered corridor. Given the aggressive
nature of these birds when breeding, this is essential.
I always use inverted L-shaped nest-boxes for lories (and most other
parrots) as, in my opinion, they have a number of advantages over vertical
nest-boxes. The box provided for this pair measures 1ft 4in (approx. 40cm)
high, with a 1ft x lOin (approx. 30cm x 25cm) base and the long part of the
box (at the top) 1ft lOin (approx. 56cm) in length. Despite the cold weather,
the pair nested after only five weeks in my care. There were two eggs, the
first of which was laid by February 6th. A chick hatched, probably from the
second egg, on or before March 5th. The parents were extremely aggressive
and trying to change the nest-litter (wood shavings) at regular intervals was
something of a challenge. As usual, the chick was plucked but had feathered-
up by the time it left the nest on May 23rd (it is normal for the young of
Chalcopsitta lories to spend about 80 days in the nest).
The young one was DNA-sexed and found to be a female. She had a
close bond with her father and I intended to leave her with her parents for
some months. However, after a few days the adult female started to behave
as though she was afraid of the young one, so I had to remove the latter to
the next-door aviary. The young lory was extremely distressed at being
separated from her father. She screamed in anguish for some days and would
always hang on the welded wire so as to be as close to him as possible. I felt
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.36509" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264437" page_num="173" year="" vol="">
LOW - DUYVEMBODE'S LORY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999305" page_id="56264437"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
173
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999174166666666" page_id="56264437"  page_num="173" year="" vol="">
sorry for her, as a single Chalcopsitta lory is not a happy bird - but I felt that
my 30-year old female was much more susceptible to stress than the young
one. I was going away on June 3rd for a few days and could take no risks.
On my return on June 9th the female was incubating two more eggs. They
did not hatch. The young female had settled down. I could not acquire
another young bird so she had to remain alone.
In 2003 the pair nested again during the first week in December - unusual
behaviour for Chalcopsitta lories. There was frost most nights during the
incubation period. Nevertheless, a chick had hatched by January 2nd. It
caused me much worry by leaving the nest prematurely on March 5th before
it could even perch. As the weather remained cold and the chick was plucked
on the crown (from where it would lose much body heat), I had no alternative
but to take it indoors at night. Catching up the young one was a procedure
that caused an enormous amount of stress - not least to me. I knew that both
parents would attack me vigorously as I scooped up the young one in a
towel and then I had to try to exit the aviary with the angry male clinging to
my back. I had anticipated this and wore a quilted jacket and quilted hood.
The male is capable of inflicting serious injury.
Once indoors I had the difficult task of trying to feed the growling,
struggling young lory. I returned it to the nest-box each morning. This
procedure continued until, much to my relief, after three or four nights, it
found its way back into the nest on its own. During the second week in
April I began to notice the female behaving nervously and flying in panic
up and down the aviary. Again it seemed as though she was afraid of the
young bird. I was going away on April 15th so had to resolve a potential
problem by catching the young one and placing it with its sister in the next
aviary. Catching it was an unpleasant experience! Fortunately, the young
bird flew out into the covered corridor but the parents were on my back and
head attacking me - and it was very difficult to dislodge them. If I had not
had the quilted hood of my jacket close around my face I would probably
have been scarred for life! Fortunately, the two young birds settled down
together very well and are often to be seen rolling around in play on the
aviary floor. This behaviour accounts for their less than perfect plumage.
The female nested again quite quickly and laid the first of two eggs on
May 5th. Much to my surprise, there were two newly-hatched chicks in the
nest on June 2nd. At the time of writing (June 20th) they are nearly three
weeks of age. The female's behaviour has surprised me as she allows me to
check the nest unchallenged each day when she leaves it. Today I was even
able to change the nest litter without her usual display of aggression or
histrionics! This was a relief because with two chicks in the nest the wood
shavings will need to be changed every few days after the chicks are three
weeks of age. Earlier in the year I was not able to do this and, one morning,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999318" page_id="56264438"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
174
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.5734855" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264438" page_num="174" year="" vol="">
LOW - DUYVENBODE'S LORY
Copyright Rosemary Low
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.856863" page_id="56264438"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
Chicks aged three and five days, weighing 17g and 18g with crops empty.
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.329923">
Copyright Rosemary Low
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.992321166666667" page_id="56264438"  page_num="174" year="" vol="">
Day 20, weighing 75g with crop empty.
when the chick was nearly three weeks of age, the female left the nest with
no intention of returning. I found the chick cold and deserted, warmed it up
in a brooder, fed it, cleaned out the nest, put in several inches (centimetres)
of clean wood shavings and decided to take a chance on returning the chick.
It was a cold day so this was risky but I suspected that the female would
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.364917" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264439" page_num="175" year="" vol="">
LOW - DUYVENBODE'S LORY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997306" page_id="56264439"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
175
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.327324" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264439" page_num="175" year="" vol="">
Copyright Rosemary Low
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991709083333333" page_id="56264439"  page_num="175" year="" vol="">
Day 31, weighing 131g with crop empty.
return to the nest as soon as she heard the chick. Fortunately she did so.
She had deserted the nest because it was too wet. She is an excellent parent.
I feed the pair fresh, warm nectar at least five times a day. Warm nectar
on a cold day is essential as they do not like drinking cold nectar. They also
dislike drinking from nearly full containers because the nectar settles, leaving
a watery layer on top. Whereas my other Chalcopsitta lories take quite a
wide variety of foods in addition to nectar, my Duyvenbode's eat only apple,
pear and celery. My nectar mixture has been modified over the years but
still has malt extract as the base, fed in equal quantity with honey. As out-
of-date baby cereal is no longer available, I feed CeDe Lory, a cereal with
egg and all necessary vitamins and minerals.
A heaped dessertspoonful of these three items (the malt and honey
dissolved first in hot water) make one litre (approx. PA pints) of nectar.
When chicks are in the nest at least one feed consists of Nekton Lory instead
of my own mixture. This is the only proprietary lory food that I have found
to be suitable for Chalcopsitta spp. One well-known brand is extremely
harmful to these birds and appears to cause liver and/or kidney disorders
that result in death. Whereas most Trichoglossus lorikeets, for example,
can take a wide variety of foods in addition to nectar, because Chalcopsitta
lories need a large proportion of nectar in their diet, it must be suitable for
these more sensitive species.
My Duyvenbode's Lories have great presence, perhaps even more so
than most Chalcopsitta lories. The male has a very strong personality and
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999183" page_id="56264440"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
176
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.743543" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264440" page_num="176" year="" vol="">
LOW - DUYVENBODE'S LORY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.988581314285714" page_id="56264440"  page_num="176" year="" vol="">
is extremely watchful and inquisitive. Beneath their swing feeders are two
large plastic trays to keep clean the aviary floor which consists of pebbles.
If the male wishes to attract my attention (such as on the rare occasions
when the nectar pot is empty) he will either grab the tray with his beak and
move it about or throw pebbles into it. Both these actions make a sound
loud enough to alert me. The birds' only fault is their loud voices. The male
can make a faultless imitation of nectar being poured from a jug, also the
sound of a distant human conversation.
I would be interested to know whether any other pairs that were the
subject of a first breeding award 20 or so years ago are still breeding!
Postscript
To my surprise, the female laid two more eggs in mid-November. These
hatched on December 17th and 18th, which coincided with a cold spell with
below-freezing temperatures at night. I checked the nest-box daily at first
light when the female left the nest to feed. On December 28th I found one
chick dead in the nest. The previous day had been fine, cold and sunny and
I had noticed that the pair had used all their bath water. Possibly the female
had been wet when she returned to the nest and the chick had become chilled.
Or perhaps it simply had not received enough food.
I removed the other chick immediately and placed it in the brooder that
had been plugged in since the chicks hatched. On checking the chick's
weight I found that it was below the expected weight for its age - only 29g
at 11 days instead of about 40g. The chick was healthy and fed readily. At
first I fed it only on Nekton Lori. Eight days later I thickened the food by
adding about x h Lory CeDe and a few days later gave it only Lory Cede. On
January 1st, at 15 days, I ringed the chick with a 7.6mm ring (size S), marked
with the year 2005. (At short notice and during the holiday period, Hughes,
the maker's, effort to send me the rings on time was greatly appreciated.)
When ringed, the chick's eyes were slit and the eyes and ears were not
fully open until day 21. The first wing feathers erupted on day 22 when,
incidentally, the white egg tooth was still present as a tiny white dot. By
day 23 the toes were in the correct position. By the age of 30 days the chick
was very alert and aware of everything going on. By day 31, at the time of
writing, the yellow feathers of the throat are just visible and the tail feathers
are starting to erupt.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.978598" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264441" page_num="177" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE GREY SEEDEATER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9465215" page_id="56264441"  page_num="177" year="" vol="">
Sporophila intermedia
m
by Robin Restall
There are several species of grey-coloured seedeaters within the genus
Sporophila from South America, and between them they range from the
Atlantic forest of southern Brazil, northwards, east of the Andes, to Colombia.
One species continues into Central America. The Grey Seedeater S.
intermedia ranges across northern South America, from Guyana in the east
to western Colombia. It is primarily a bird of grasslands, and I have found
it in savannah, meadows and pastures. I have also found it in rice fields,
especially in the tall banks of Panicum maximum that can be found on either
side of the ditches that run between the rice fields and the roads. Thus, as
one drives through the countryside it is fairly commonly seen clinging to
tall seeding heads of the grass. The Grey Seedeater also occurs in parks and
gardens, usually in untended areas where P. maximum grows freely.
It is an accomplished songster, with a loud and attractive roll of warbles
and whistles that are expanded into a rich vocabulary as the bird gets older
and copies familiar sounds in its environment. It is easy to maintain in
captivity, and thus is a favourite for the local bird trade. However, it is too
common, and thus low in price, for it to provide a big business opportunity
and so it tends to be ignored by the professional trappers.
The male Grey Seedeater is about 11cm (approx. TVhn) in length and is
uniform grey above and below to the breast, with the belly and under tail-
coverts white. The feathers of the wings and tail are blackish with grey
edges and there is a white patch at the base of the middle primaries. The
pale, yellowish bill is a heavy, finch-type bill, with a well-curved culmen.
The female is buffy above and cinnamon on the breast, and is pale creamy-
whitish on the belly and under tail-coverts. Her bill is very dark brown and
is on average slightly larger than that of the male. The legs, toes and nails of
both sexes are dark greyish.
It may perhaps be helpful at this point to clarify the characteristics of the
various other males in the grey seedeater group, for there are no satisfactory
comprehensive colour plates illustrating them in the field guides and
handbooks. The Plumbeous Seedeater S. plumbea is a pure French grey,
with a black bill and a white crescent beneath the eyes. The legs, toes and
nails are dark olive. The Slate-coloured Seedeater S. schistacea is very
similar to the Grey Seedeater, but has an orange bill with a very narrow,
scimitar-like upper mandible. It generally has olive-green legs and toes,
with pale straw-coloured nails. Some males are almost identical to the male
Grey Seedeater, and can only be separated by the bill. The species which is
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998785" page_id="56264442"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
178
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.918003" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264442" page_num="178" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - GREY SEEDEATER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997804047619048" page_id="56264442"  page_num="178" year="" vol="">
very easy indeed to confuse with the Grey Seedeater, is the Ring-necked
Seedeater S. insularis. It was described originally from Trinidad as a
subspecies of the Grey Seedeater (Gilliard, 1946), but was subsequently
synonymized under it by Meyer de Schauensee (1952). With the increasing
scarcity of finches on Trinidad, the only people who knew the Ring-necked
Seedeater was a distinct species were the Trinidadian birdkeepers. Very
soon all seedeaters disappeared from Trinidad and field observers and
ornithologists never had the chance to study it. I recently discovered that it
exists happily here in Venezuela and found that it is a distinct species in its
own right (Restall, 2002). The key difference is that the male has a whitish
band across its rump, which the Grey Seedeater never does. Other
differences, like a larger bill, with that of the female on average being smaller
than that of the male, and a longer tarsus, are only meaningful in the context
of a large series of birds being compared in detail.
We used to live in a house that lay within a golf course in Caracas, and
the garden, which was not very large, benefited from the presence of the
fairways and woodland copses, and was a haven for birds. In one year I
logged 98 species in the garden, including 13 species of hummingbird.
Among the seed-eating species that were seen fairly regularly were the Blue-
black Grassquit Volatinia jacarina , Yellow-bellied Seedeater S. nigricollis ,
Grey Seedeater, Saffron Finch Sicalis flaveola and Black-faced Grassquit
Haris bicolor. I built a small birdroom at the back of the house, and in the
garden had a large steel-framed aviary built. This covered a walk-around
area that was paved with flagstones and had small trees in tubs, and a sloping
garden in which grasses and flowering shrubs grew in profusion. There was
a small pond about 1.5m (approx. 5 ft) square, as well as an old washing sink
with a sloping scrubbing ramp that contained water. The enclosure was
irregular in shape, with a floor area of about 5m x 7m (approx. 16ft x 22ft)
and was 5m (approx. 16ft) high. Big baskets, planted with ferns, hung from
the roof. The entrance had a large safety porch and feeding area, which also
served as a trap to catch birds when necessary.
Various finches, in the broadest sense of the word, were kept in this
idyllic aviary, including two pairs of Grey Seedeaters. One male was richer
in coloration than the other. I subsequently learned that Sporophila seedeaters
generally become richer and more intense in colour as they get older. The
older bird moulted into an intense blue-grey and as the rainy season began,
it soon came into breeding condition, and chased the other male relentlessly,
singing passionately all the while. I knew there was a risk of aggression
between them, but thought that the size of the aviary would give both birds
enough cover and room to be able to cohabit. Not so. Before I was able to
trap the less dominant male, it had been harried to death by the other.
Sporophila seedeaters build a small, compact nest of fibres and fine
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.746288" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264443" page_num="179" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - GREY SEEDEATER
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999093" page_id="56264443"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
179
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.997970425" page_id="56264443"  page_num="179" year="" vol="">
straws. It invariably appears to be weak and very fragile, with light showing
through at any angle. The Grey Seedeater builds a nest of fine root fibres,
and will search for these in an aviary. If provided with coconut fibre it will
also use this in the inner lining. The nest site is selected by the female, who
carries a fibre to the site and attempts to tie it to part of a fork of small
branches. She will make cup-moulding movements on the spot and if
satisfied, will bring further fibres and attempt to get the nest started. The
male will excitedly bring fibres as well and also attempt to get the nest
started, but it is the female that drives things along, and may switch to another
site very quickly.
I found the nest in my aviary after it was finished and contained two
eggs. The nest was about 5cm (approx. 2in) across the top and 4cm (approx.
1 V 2 in) deep. It was bound to a set of slender stems forking into the canopy
of a Ficus benjamina that was growing in a tub, and was level with the top
of my head. It was so close to the top of the Ficus , which was well rounded
and had been trimmed regularly to form dense cover, that the leaves were
only a few centimetres (1 in or so) above the top of the nest.
The eggs were pale greyish, spotted and blotched with various browns
and umbers. I have no record of the incubation period, but guess it to have
been relatively short. Two nestlings fledged after about 10 days. They
thrived, being fed by both parents, but a few days later, escaped through the
wire mesh. This had been specially made to order, and I had specified 2cm
( 3 Ain) including the width of the wire, but this proved to be too generous.
The parent birds were retained however.
The feeding station was like a big bird table and held bowls of various
seeds and seed mixtures. In addition I usually offer a bowl of softbill mix
and another with fruit. However, the Sporophila seedeaters were invariably
seen feeding only on the seed. They also ate any growing seeds and fed on
the plants in the aviary. They nipped and ate the emerging buds on the
bamboos and many of the shrubs.
The species adapts well to life under controlled conditions and can be
kept fit and in good feather on an all-dry seed diet. The birds usually welcome
lettuce and may also take apple. I have never managed to interest them in
livefood, however, since then, when I have been able to study other species
of Sporophila I have seen them continually hunting insects. Also, Grey
Seedeaters have been observed catching flying termites. Birds taken as
juveniles adapt to a wider variety of foods much better than do wild-caught
adults. My birds were in their natural climate and kept under near-natural
conditions. I believe they have bred in aviaries in Germany (Sabel, 1990),
and possibly in Denmark. I am not aware of any cage breedings.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995393" page_id="56264444"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
180
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9773135" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264444" page_num="180" year="" vol="">
RESTALL - GREY SEEDEATER
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9927689" page_id="56264444"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
Gilliard, E. T. 1946. Two New Gray Seedeaters from South America. Auk 63:570-574.
Meyer de Schauensee, R. 1952. A Review of the Genus Sporophila. Proc. Acad. Nat. Sci.
Phil. 104:153-196.
Restall, R. L. 2002. Is the Ring-necked Seedeater ( Sporophila insularis) from Trinidad extinct,
or is it a cryptic species widespread in Venezuela? Studies in Trinidad and Tobago Ornithology
Honouring Richard ffrench (Hayes, F.E. and Temple, S.A., eds.). Dept. Life Sci., Univ. West
Indies, St. Augustine, Occ. Pap. 11,2002.
Sabel, K. 1990. Pfaffchen , Ulmer, Stuttgart.
The author, who was recently elected a Vice President of the Avicultural
Society, lives in Caracas, Venezuela. E-mail: restall@cantv.net
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.766684" page_id="56264444"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.877389" genericHeader="introduction" page_id="56264444" page_num="180" year="" vol="">
PLANTING TREES FOR PARROTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985550052631579" page_id="56264444"  page_num="180" year="" vol="">
Indaba Inyoni Newsletter of BirdLife South Africa, Vol.7, No.4, 2004,
included a report (p.6) about a tree planting scheme aimed at increasing the
habitat of the Critically Endangered Cape Parrot Poicephalus robustus. In
August, to kick start the scheme, some 600 Podocarpus henkelii seeds, which
had been donated, were planted in a nursery in KwaZulu-Natal. Further
seeds of yellowwood trees Podocarpus spp. are being collected from various
forests in which this parrot occurs.
Seedlings grown from these seeds will later be planted on the peripheries
of the forests. Seedlings will also be planted on private land to form a series
of corridors linking patches of forest. Several landowners, especially in the
Karkloof area, have expressed support for the scheme. Seeds are also being
collected from forests in the Eastern Cape in order to establish a similar
scheme there.
As a further source of food, pecan nut trees will be planted where forest
destruction has forced parrots to move into built-up areas to feed. The group
behind the scheme is trying to source a quick growing hybrid pecan nut tree
for the scheme and has appealed for pecan nut growers and nurseries to
donate trees.
E-mail:capeparrot@birdlife.org.za for further information.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998386" page_id="56264445"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
181
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9868285" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264445" page_num="181" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE ONLINE INDEX
LETTER FROM THE CHAIRMAN
</sectionHeader>
<figure confidence="0.98802075" page_id="56264445"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
Mr D Coles
Beale Park
The Child-Beale Trust
Lower Basildon
Reading
Berks
RG8 9NH
Dear Dave
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.932548285714286" page_id="56264445"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
At the last meeting of Council it was freely expressed by all members that
the hard work you have put in on the index for the Avicultural Magazine is
thoroughly appreciated and a big vote of thanks was recorded. It really has
been a monumental effort to have undertaken such a task and all aviculturists
can be proud and delighted at the outcome. Well done indeed.
I do hope you are keeping well and all the birds are thriving.
Once again many thanks from us all.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.510744571428571" page_id="56264445"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
Yours sincerely
Christopher Marler
Chairman of Council
Avicultural Society
The index to the Avicultural Magazine 1894-2003 can be accessed on
the society's website :www.avisoc. co.uk
* * *
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.964831" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264445" page_num="181" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.965558" page_id="56264445"  page_num="181" year="" vol="">
A large stock is available including some early issues. Further details
are available from: The Hon. Secretary and Treasurer, The Avicultural
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.452535">
Society, Arcadia, The Mounts, Totnes, Devon TQ9 7QJ, UK. E-
mail: Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998642" page_id="56264446"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
182
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9929325" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264446" page_num="182" year="" vol="">
NEWS AND VIEWS
PROBABLE FIRST EVER CAPTIVE BREEDING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9987436" page_id="56264446"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
In April 2004, a pair of Black-browed Barbets Megalaima oorti nested
in a dead palm and hatched and successfully fledged two chicks at Miami
Metrozoo, Florida, USA. It is probably the first time this barbet has ever
been bred in captivity. This species then known as Oort's Barbet was probably
first imported into the UK by Wilfred Frost in 1930.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.838634" page_id="56264446"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.748669" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264446" page_num="182" year="" vol="">
TWENTY-SIXTH PELICAN HATCHED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990886" page_id="56264446"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
During the 2004 breeding season, four Pink-backed Pelican Pelecanus
rufescens chicks were hatched at San Diego Wild Animal Park. It is the
only North American collection that breeds this species, and brought the
number hatched there to 26.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.856835" page_id="56264446"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.717168" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264446" page_num="182" year="" vol="">
NINETEEN CHICKS HAND-REARED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.974437368421052" page_id="56264446"  page_num="182" year="" vol="">
Staff at World of Birds Wildlife Sanctuary, Hout Bay, South Africa
(website:www.worldofbirds.org.za), having obtained two newly imported
pairs of Guira Cuckoos Guira guira, are now having difficulty
accommodating their numerous offspring. They would be having even more
difficulty had all 50 eggs that have been laid hatched and if all the chicks
hatched had been reared successfully. There were times when there were
up to 10 eggs in the bulky nest, which was regularly reconstructed in new
locations in the well-planted 15m x 15m (approx. 50ft x 50ft) aviary which
they share with a large number of other birds. Within a year 19 chicks were
hand-reared. All were taken from the nest before fledging, because the
chicks have the habit of jumping out of the nest before it is safe for them to
do so. Hand-rearing them is easy and is a pleasure as the birds cooperate so
willingly and immediately become trusting and tame.
Manager Hendrik Louw also reported that following a mild winter there
had been a very promising start to the new breeding season, with a long list
of birds on eggs or rearing chicks. The list included several species of parrot,
pigeons and doves, waterfowl and other waterbirds. Other birds on the
list included the Pied Starling Spreo bicolor , Red-winged Starling
Onychognathus morio. Von der Decken's Hombill Tockus deckeni, Red-
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.86735775">
billed Blue Magpie Urocissa erythrorhyncha, Brown Pelican Pelecanus
occidentalism Saddle-billed Stork Ephippiorhynchus senegalensis, Blue,
Paradise or Stanley Crane Anthropoides paradisea and a number of species
of birds of prey and owls.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.979662" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264447" page_num="183" year="" vol="">
NEWS AND VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998012" page_id="56264447"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
183
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990456" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264447" page_num="183" year="" vol="">
SUCCESSFUL BREEDING SEASON
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.965856791666667" page_id="56264447"  page_num="183" year="" vol="">
Curator David Woolcock reports that they again enjoyed a successful
breeding season at Paradise Park Wildlife Sanctuary, Hayle, Cornwall, with
the undoubted highlights being the breeding of three species which had not
been bred there before. Most important of these was the breeding of the
Blue-throated Macaw Ara glaucogularis. The birds have been in the
collection since 1992, when they were imported from Florida. Never
previously having shown any interest in the nest-box, this year the pair
produced its first clutch at the end of February and laid a second clutch in
March, which was left with the pair but failed to hatch, possibly because the
humidity in the nest had not been quite right. When the third clutch was laid
in April, the eggs were placed in an incubator and two male chicks were
hatched and successfully hand-reared. The park hopes to swap one of them
for a female and establish a second breeding pair.
Blue-throated Macaw chicks.
The park (home of the World Parrot Trust) has a special interest in this
species and through donations and special events has raised #20,000 (approx.
US$36,000) to support a breeding project in Florida. The project has had
considerable breeding success and is about to release a number of these
macaws in their native Bolivia. The second species which was bred for the
first time at the park was also a parrot. Acquired in 1996, the park's pair of
Grey-headed or Cape Parrots, which had not nested before, this year raised
two young. A few authors continue to treat this parrot as a subspecies of the
Cape Parrot Poicephalus robustus, some others treat it as a subspecies of
the Brown-necked and some treat it as a full species in its own right, as a
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999554" page_id="56264448"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
184
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996805" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264448" page_num="184" year="" vol="">
NEWS AND VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.981294272727273" page_id="56264448"  page_num="184" year="" vol="">
result of which it may be listed as P. r. suahelicus, P fuscicollis suahelicus
or P. suahelicus.
Orange-winged Amazons Amazona amazonica raised three lovely young.
Other parrot species bred this year included Roseate Cockatoo or Galah
Eolophus roseicapillus. Lesser Sulphur-crested Cockatoo Cacatua
sulphurea , Rainbow Lorikeet Trichoglossus haematodus , Goldie's Lorikeet
T. goldiei and Blue-throated Conure Pyrrhura cruentata. Golden Conures
Guaruba guarouba were sitting on eggs at the end of August. White-cheeked
Turacos Tauraco leucotis and Livingstones's T. livingstonii were also sitting.
Red-crested Turacos T. erythrolophus raised two young earlier in the season.
Paradise Park also bred the Luzon Bleeding Heart Dove Gallicolumba
luzonica.
The third first for the park, was the breeding of the Avocet Recurvirostris
avosetta. Two pairs were acquired as youngsters in 2000, and this year one
of the pairs succeeded in raising four young. Madagascar Teal Anas bernieri ,
Chiloe Wigeon A. sibilatrix and Common Eider Somateria mollissima were
bred. Baikal Teal A.formosa hatched but failed to survive. Grey Crowned
Cranes Balearica regulorum gibbericeps also nested.
Avocet chick.
Gouldian Finches Chloebia gouldiae bred well earlier in the year and
Nutmeg Finches or Spice Birds Lonchura punctulata did even better. The
numbers of young reared by both species getting into double figures.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.979672" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264449" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
NEWS AND VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996349" page_id="56264449"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
185
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993657" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264449" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
WALLACE'S BIRDS OF PARADISE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.96257119047619" page_id="56264449"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
In The Birds of Paradise by Frith and Beehler (Oxford University Press,
1998), at the end of the Greater Bird of Paradise Paradisaea apoda species
account, it is mentioned that Pennant noted a living bird was sent to England
prior to 1790, but no evidence is offered that it reached here alive. Probably
the first living birds of paradise to arrive in England and the first seen alive
anywhere in Europe were two male Lesser Birds of Paradise P minor
purchased for London Zoo in Singapore by Alfred Russel Wallace and
brought to London by him early in 1862. On arrival they were housed in a
large cage in the Zoological Society's old museum, but immediately had to
be separated because they fought. The sight of one another or even a plume
waved near them was said to have produced great excitement.
The Council Minutes for August 17th 1859, show that the zoo agreed to
pay Wallace #100 (approx. US$180) for the first bird, #50 (approx. US$90)
for the second and #25 each (approx. US$45) for any others (up to 10).
April 16th 1862, it was unanimously agreed to pay him the sum of #307.9s.0d
(approx. US$550). He was to receive #150.0s.0d (approx. US$270) for the
two birds, #137.3s.0d (approx. US$250) for his passage from Singapore to
London and #20.6s.0d (approx. US$36) for sundry expenses.
In 1881, the Zoological Society of London purchased a Red Bird of
Paradise P. rubra , a Twelve-wired Seleucidis melanoleuca and a Crinkle-
collared Manucode Manucodia chalybata , and the following year obtained
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.507269" page_id="56264449"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
a Paradise Riflebird Ptiloris paradiseus.
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.881456" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264449" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
HOW TIMES CHANGE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996677090909091" page_id="56264449"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
In 1871, London Zoo paid #120 (approx. US$220), almost as much as
was paid for the two birds of paradise above, for two male Lady Amherst's
Pheasants Chrysolophus amherstiae. According to Bo Beolens and Michael
Watkins in their recently published book Whose Bird? Men and Women
Commemorated in the Common Names of Birds (Helm, 2003), this species
is named after Sarah Countess Amherst (1762-1838), wife of William Pitt
Amherst, Governor General of Bengal from 1822-1828. Lord Amherst was
responsible for sending the first example of this pheasant to London in 1828.
Unfortunately the bird failed to survive the journey, however, the specimen
enabled Leadbeater to describe this now familiar species. The first live
specimen reached London in July 1869.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.611492" page_id="56264449"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.891274" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264449" page_num="185" year="" vol="">
GULF SUCCESS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97540025" page_id="56264449"  page_num="185" year="" vol="">
Dubai Zoo, a small zoo in the United Arab Emirates, is believed to be
the first collection anywhere in the world to have bred the Socotra Cormorant
Phalacrocorax nigrogularis . It currently has 30 of these cormorants and
has so far raised eight chicks.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999389" page_id="56264450"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
186
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9968545" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264450" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
NEWS AND VIEWS
PROBABLY NAMED AFTER JEAN PECQUET
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9965605" page_id="56264450"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
In News &amp; Views Vol.109, No.3, p.142 (2003), the question was asked,
who was Pesquet after whom Pesquet's Parrot Psittrichas fulgidus is named?
The question was asked on behalf of Bo Beolens and Michael Watkins,
authors of Whose Bird? Men and Women Commemorated in the Common
Names of Birds (Helm, 2003). Members were unable to provide the answer.
Now, Michael Watkins has written to say that after nearly four years of
searching and considerable confusion over spellings and names, they are
99.99% sure that it is named after Jean Pecquet (1622-1674), who was a
famous French anatomist. They believe that Rene Pierre Lesson named the
species Banksianus fulgidus in 1829, so that name has priority, but in 1830
named it Dasyptilus pecquetii and that got corrupted to Dasyptilus pesquetii,
with Psittrichas later being adopted as the generic name. It is a bird that
was illustrated by Gould and the English name possibly came from him as
he used the name Dasyptilus pesqueti on his engraving.
The species was collected during the 1826-1829 circumnavigation by
the French vessel L Astrolabe , which was also known by its previous name,
La Coquille. Rene Pierre Lesson's brother Pierre Adolphe Lesson was on
board during the circumnavigation as the ship's surgeon and naturalist, and
the authors believe he almost certainly collected the parrot and on his return
gave the specimen to his brother, Rene Pierre, who described the species.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.6386475" page_id="56264450"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
* H&amp;lt; *
NEVER PREVIOUSLY BRED
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.992217555555555" page_id="56264450"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
A Great Green Macaw Ara amhigua more than 30 years of age, which
had never previously bred successfully, has done so for the first time at the
breeding centre of the Loro Parque Fundagion in Tenerife. Received last
year from Basel Zoo, the male was paired with a younger female this spring
and the pair produced two young. Yellow-crowned Amazons Amazona
ochrocephala xantholaema bred there for the first time in 2003 and this
year two different parents raised three chicks. Scaly-naped Amazons A.
mercenaria fledged three young and Red-browed Amazons A rhodocorytha
fledged two young.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.622247" page_id="56264450"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.96218" genericHeader="method" page_id="56264450" page_num="186" year="" vol="">
SECOND GENERATION CAPTIVE-HATCHED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998742714285714" page_id="56264450"  page_num="186" year="" vol="">
A pair of Rhinoceros Hombills Buceros rhinoceros which have lived
together since 1994 at Phoenix Zoo, Arizona, USA, last year succeeded in
hatching a chick. It was the first time that this species has bred at the zoo.
The chick is thought to be one of the few hombills - if not the only one - to
have been bred from captive-hatched parents. The 15 year old male has
been at the zoo since 1991, and was paired with the 11 year- old female after
she arrived at the zoo in 1993.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.979657" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264451" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
NEWS AND VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995959" page_id="56264451"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
187
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.989251" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56264451" page_num="187" year="" vol="">
NEWS FROM TEXAS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.960812" page_id="56264451"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
At the end of September 2004, Josef and Natalie Lindholm took up
positions at The Dallas World Aquarium (website:www.dwazoo.com).
Judging by the guide they sent, it is much more than just an aquarium. It has
for example a fantastic collection of birds. These include 22 forms of toucans,
aracaris and toucanets. Josef's work area is a roof garden (surrounded by
skyscrapers), where there are 23 pairs, including Ivory-billed Pteroglossus
flavirostris, Many-banded P. pluricinctus and Curl-crested Aracaris P.
beauharnaesii, occupying cages arranged around a lushly planted flight
which is home to six male and five female Guyana Cock-of-the-Rock
Rupicola rupicola. He also works with Ocellated Turkeys Agriocharis
ocellata and several pairs of North American hummingbirds set up for
breeding.
Natalie cares for nine pairs of rhamphastids, as well as Hawk-headed
Parrots Deroptyus accipitrinus , Pompadour Cotingas Xipholena punicea ,
Yellow-knobbed Curassows Crax daubentoni and Argus Pheasants
Argusianus argus , and was about to take charge of five pairs of Andean
Cock-of-the-Rock R. peruviana. She is also responsible for the Jaguars
Panthera onca , Ocelots Leopardus pardalis and Giant Otters Pteronura
brasiliensis.
Josef has promised to write about the history of the bird collection, from
its beginning in 1995 through to the present, and thereafter submit annual
reports.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.416720666666667" page_id="56264451"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
* * *
AVICULTURE CONVENTION IN IRELAND
Carrigaline &amp; District Budgerigar and Foreign Bird Club, County Cork,
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.9822745" page_id="56264451"  page_num="187" year="" vol="">
is hosting an Aviculture Convention at the Carrigaline Court Hotel. Starting
on the evening of Friday, April 1st, there will be a fun quiz night, then on the
Saturday and Sunday, April 2nd and April 3rd, there will be talks, a pet fair,
which will include a display of birds, as well as birds for sale and trade
stands. For further details e-mail: bird@esatclear.ie or Budgie foreign
@esatclear.ie or contact the Secretary Brendan O'Brien, tel:00 353 (Republic
of Ireland) 21 4371603. There is also a website - www.esatclear.ie/~budgie/
- which has the latest up to date information.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998576" page_id="56264452"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
188
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.663813" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264452" page_num="188" year="" vol="">
OBITUARY
Janet Kear
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.886162652173913" page_id="56264452"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
Janet Kear, whose death was announced in November 2004, was one of
the UK's most respected ornithologists and an internationally recognised
authority on waterfowl. She joined the staff of the Wetlands &amp; Wildfowl
Trust as a research scientist and worked closely with Sir Peter Scott during
the 1960s, during which she played a leading role in the establishment of a
breeding programme for the then endangered Hawaiian Goose.
Janet held a number of important positions including those of Principal
Scientific Officer and Avicultural Co-ordinator with the WWT, later
becoming Curator of its Martin Mere reserve in Lancashire, a post which
she held from 1977-1990.
She served on the councils of the Avicultural Society, British Trust for
Ornithology, Council for the Study of Bird Behaviour, Royal Society for
the Protection of Birds, Jersey Wildlife Preservation Trust and English Nature.
She was the first woman to become Vice President of the British
Ornithologists' Union (1989-1991) and was subsequently President (1991-
1995). Between 1980-1988 she was Editor of Ibis.
In 1990 Liverpool John Moores University conferred on her an honorary
professorship and in 1993 she was awarded the OBE for services to
conservation.
Janet Kear was author of The Mute Swan (1989), Man and Waterfowl
(1990) and Ducks of the World (1991). She was a co-author of Hawaiian
Goose (1980) and Waterfowl (1985). Her sixth book, Ducks, Geese and
Swans , is due to be published in the spring of 2005.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.465305" page_id="56264452"  page_num="188" year="" vol="">
Frank Wooiham
* * *
US BANK ACCOUNT
Those who would prefer to make payments in US dollars are reminded
that the society now has a US bank account. Overseas membership for
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.53986525">
2005 will remain at US$38 for receiving the magazines by regular mail or
US$50 for air mail. Checks and money orders should be made payable to
The Avicultural Society and sent to: The Avicultural Society, c/o Jane Cooper,
12650 Hearst Road, Willits, California 95490-9231, USA.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.994881" page_id="56264453"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
189
</page>
<table confidence="0.59484225" page_id="56264453"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
Contributors to Volume 110 - 2004
Barnicoat, R
Notes on the Red-legged Honeycreeper/
Yellow-winged Sugarbird Cyanerpes cyaneus 59
Bertagnolio, Paolo
Strigiformes and Psittaciformes:
Philogenetic likeness or convergence? 145
Unrecorded heat stress posture and feeding habit in captive
Red-tailed Black Cockatoo Calyptorhynchus banksi 69
Boulden, Paul
Living Coasts 36
Brack, Christopher
The President's Garden Party 2003 38
Bralsford, Gary
Breeding the Red-crested Cardinal Paroaria coronata 97
Breeding the White-eared Bulbul 17
</table>
<figure confidence="0.883716466666666" page_id="56264453"  page_num="189" year="" vol="">
The 2003 breeding season - some disappointments 54
Brickell, Neville
Collated data on the Brown Twinspot Clytospiza monteiri 28
Chaney, Andy
Breeding success with the Brown Twinspot Clytospiza monteiri 32
Goodwin, Derek
Magpie rescuing its mate from a Carrion Crow
and other crow versus magpie encounters 104
He Fen-qi
Report on the implementation of the Wuyuan Project 64
lies, Chris
Breeding the Green Aracari Pteroglossus viridis 167
Jerrard, Jim
The Japanese Waxwing Bombycilla japonica
76
</figure>
<page confidence="0.988849" page_id="56264454"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
190
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.639870166666667" page_id="56264454"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
Contributors to Volume 110 - 2004 (cont'd)
Jones, Marvin L.
A history of the genus Picathartes in captivity, 1948-2002 9
Low, Rosemary
Duyvenbode's Lory: the history of one pair from 1978-2004 170
Lowde, B. N.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.844430157894737" page_id="56264454"  page_num="190" year="" vol="">
My Woodcock Study 82,103
Marler, Christopher
The successful breeding of the American Bald Eagle
Haliaeetus leucocephalus at Flamingo Gardens and Zoological Park 49
Massey, Brian
Breeding the Grey-capped Greenfinch Carduelis sinica 57
Ortiz Merry, Luis J.
The hand-rearing of an Umbrellabird 108
Owen, Andrew
Hand-rearing the Mauritius Fody Foudia rubra 119
Peat, Louise
Breeding the Red-winged Starling,
including an attempt to start a breeding colony 151
Metabolic Bone Disease and general leg deformities in chicks
- causes and preventative measures 71
Restall, Robin
Breeding the Grey Seedeater Sporophila intermedia 177
Tinoco, Herlandes Penha and Faggioli, Angela Bemadete
The behaviour of Struthio camelus australis at
</table>
<reference confidence="0.785563333333333">
Belo Horizonte Zoo, Brazil: evaluating causes of breeding failure 1
Wilkinson, Roger, McLeod, Wayne, Langford, Darren and Morris, Paul
Breeding the Red Bird of Paradise at Chester Zoo 20
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998829" page_id="56264455"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
191
</page>
<table confidence="0.942946954545454" page_id="56264455"  page_num="191" year="" vol="">
Index to Volume 110 - 2004
Aracari, Geen, probable UK first breeding 167
Bird of Paradise, Red, UK first breeding at Chester Zoo 20
Bombycilia japonica, keeping and breeding 76
Book Reviews
Aras 142
Birds of Belize 81
Birds of the West Indies 41
Curassows and Related Birds 141
Fabulous Feathers, Remarkable Birds 80
Handbook of the Birds of the World (Volume 8) 79
Breeding Season, 2003, some disappointments 54
Bulbul,White-eared, breeding 17
Calyptorhynchus banksi, unrecorded posture and feeding habit 69
Cardinal, Red-crested, breeding 97
Carduelis sinica , breeding 57
Cephalopterus penduliger , hand-rearing 108
Chalcopsitta duivenbodei, history of one pair from 1978-2004 170
Clytospiza monteiri , collated data 28
Clytospiza monteiri , UK first breeding success 32
Cockatoo, Red-tailed, unrecorded posture and feeding habit 69
Corvus corone , crow versus magpie encounters 104
</table>
<reference confidence="0.751013">
Crow, Carrion, crow versus magpie encounters 104
Cyanerpes cyaneus, notes on keeping and breeding 89
Disease, Metabolic Bone, and general leg deformities in chicks 71
Eagle, American Bald, UK first breeding and subsequent successes 49
Fody, Mauritius, hand-rearing 119
Foudia rubra , hand-rearing 119
Garrulax galbanus courtoisi (see Report on Wuyuan Project) 64
Greenfinch, Grey-capped, breeding 57
Honeycreeper, Red-legged, notes on keeping and breeding 89
Hornbills in Thailand - 2003 99
Laughingthrush, Courtois' (see Report on Wuyuan Project) 64
Letter from the Chairman, on line index 181
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999261" page_id="56264456"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
192
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.612293" page_id="56264456"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
Index to Volume 110 - 2004 (cont'd)
Letter to Editor, leg deformities in chicks 140
Living Coasts, enormous new aviary of striking, modem design 36
Lory, Duyvenbode's, history of one pair from 1978-2004 170
News &amp; Views 43, 91,144,182
Obituaries, Ken Dolton, Janet Kear 47,188
Onychognathus morio, breeding, attempt to start a colony 151
Ostrich, evaluating causes of breeding failure 1
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.914509615384615" page_id="56264456"  page_num="192" year="" vol="">
Paradisaea rubra , UK first breeding at Chester Zoo 20
Paroaria coronata , breeding 97
Pica pica , crow versus magpie encounters 104
Picathartes , history of genus in captivity 1948-2002 (part 3) 9
President's Garden Party 2003 38
Pteroglossus viridis , probable UK first breeding 167
Pycnonotus leucotis or P leucogenys leucotis, breeding 17
Scolopax rusticola, study 82,130
Seedeater, Grey, breeding 177
Sporophila intermedia , breeding 177
Starling, Red-winged, breeding, attempt to start a colony 151
Strigiformes and Psittaciformes, philogenetic likeness or convergence 145
Struthio camelus australis , evaluating causes of breeding failure 1
</table>
<reference confidence="0.980136714285714">
Sugarbird, Yellow-winged, notes on keeping and breeding 89
Twinspot, Brown, collated data 28
Twinspot, Brown, UK first breeding success 32
Umbrellabird, Long-wattled, hand-rearing 108
Waxwing, Japanese, keeping and breeding 76
Woodcock, study 82, 130
Zoo, Chester, notes from - 2003 116
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998123" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264457" page_num="" year="" vol="">
LORO PARQUE FUNDA^ION COMMITS RECORD
AMOUNT FOR CONSERVATION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.963371583333334" page_id="56264457"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Loro Parque Fundagion, which recently celebrated the 10th
anniversary of its creation in 1994, in October announced that it will commit
a record 500,000 Euros (approx. #350,000 or US$650,000) to conservation
projects in 2005. The aim of most of the projects is to help save threatened
species, especially species of parrot, the group of birds with which the
fundagion has internationally recognised expertise.
The fundagion is advised by international experts such as Professor Ian
Swingland of the Durrell Institute of Conservation and Ecology, Dr Nigel
Collar of BirdLife International, Dr Jorgen Thomsen of Conservation
International, Dr Wolf Iwand of TUI and Dr Tomas de Azcarate y Bang of
the Institute of Responsible Tourism. The advisors assessed the merits of
the many conservation proposals which had been received and gave their
recommendations which led the board to make the momentous decision to
commit more funding than in any previous year.
Loro Parque heads the list of major sponsors. Dr Iwand, representing
TUI, another of the major sponsors, gave an impassioned plea for the business
community to increase corporate responsibility for the environment by
supporting the fundagion. Speaking after the meeting, Wolfgang Kiessling,
President of the Loro Parque Fundagion said, "The Loro Parque Fundagion
has shown 10 years of steady growth, and to date has spent almost 2.5 million
Euros (approx. #1.7 million or US$3.3million) to help save the natural
treasures of the planet."
The 18 main conservation projects which will benefit in 2005 are in
many parts of the world and will involve a diverse range of collaborations
with government agencies, non-governmental organisations, universities and
local community groups. Loro Parque having recently fledged a Spix's
Macaw Cyanopsitta spixii, it is appropriate that the projects include the
Spix's Macaw Recovery Programme. Two of the four most threatened
parrots of Venezuela, the Yellow-shouldered Amazon Amazona barbadensis
and Blue-headed Conure Aratinga acuticaudata neoxema of Margarita
Island, will be beneficiaries of an extensive environmental programme, and
similar activities will take place in the Philippines to help conserve the
Philippine Cockatoo Cacatua haematuropygia. In Thailand, where the Loro
Parque Fundagion already assists with conservation in the Phu Khieo Wildlife
Sanctuary in a special project of HM King Bhumibol, there will be education
programmes in local communities and the training of forest officers.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.929" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56264458" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
</sectionHeader>
<category confidence="0.311797">
Strigiformes and Psittaciformes: Philogenetic likeness
</category>
<table confidence="0.812379571428571" page_id="56264458"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
or convergence?
by Paolo Bertagnolio. 145
Breeding the Red-winged Starling, including an attempt
to start a breeding colony
by Louise Peat. 151
Breeding the Green Aracari Pteroglossus viridis
by Chris lies... 167
Duyvenbode's Lory: The history of one pair from 1978-2004
by Rosemary Low. 170
Breeding the Grey Seedeater Sporophila intermedia
by Robin Restall. Ill
Planting trees for parrots. 180
Letter from the Chairman. 181
News and Views. 182
Obituary - Janet Kear... 188
Contributors to Volume 110 - 2004 . 189
Index to Volume 110 - 2004 . 191
gr --
_3 9088 01140 6709 _
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</table>
</algorithms>
