<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.8496174" page_id="56260869"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 112
No. 2
2006
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260870" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990837" page_id="56260870"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2006 as for 2005: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.5855" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260870" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.972357" page_id="56260870"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, ARCADIA, THE MOUNTS, TOTNES, DEVON TQ9 7QJ, UK.
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TN13 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments. In case of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and
Treasurer at the address above, or e-mail: Paul@pboulden.fsnet.co.uk
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998476" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260870" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982477333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.800952" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260871" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.291977" page_id="56260871"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 112 - No. 2 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2006
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7127835" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260871" page_num="" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE WHITE-BROWED COUCAL
Centropus superciliosus
AT EXMOOR ZOOLOGICAL PARK
by Derek Gibson
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.832047576923077" page_id="56260871"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
On March 24th 2005, 2.1 White-browed Coucals, captive-bred in 2003
in Europe, arrived at Exmoor Zoological Park from the Cotswold Wildlife
Park, Oxfordshire (see Cotswold Wildlife Park Review of 2005 by Louise
Peat, Avicultural Magazine Vol. 112, Nod, pp. 8-9, (2006)). They were placed
in a quarantine aviary in which it became very apparent that we had a matched
pair and an additional male. The odd bird was removed and housed in a
separate quarantine unit.
Aviary
The pair was released into an aviary measuring 3.8m x 2.7m (approx.
12ft 6in x 8ft lOin), which is covered on both sides, the back and a quarter
of the roof, leaving just three-quarters of the roof open to the elements. At
the back of the aviary there is a warm, dry shed measuring approximately
1.3m x lm (4ft 4in x 3ft 4in), that is the same height as the aviary. The
outside area has three large clumps of bamboo, which are trimmed at lm-
1.4m (approx. 3ft 3in-4ft Tin) tall and there are three palms Phoenix
canariensis , which at present are 1.3m (approx.4ft 4in) tall. The floor has
5cm (2in) deep pea shingle. Access is at the rear through a safety porch.
The perches (cut from Beech Fagus sylvatica) are 5cm-15cm (2in-6in) in
diameter and run continuously throughout the length and width of the aviary.
At the rear of the aviary they run the full width to a height of 2m (approx. 6ft
6in) and the full length at a height of 1.5m (approx. 5ft) and 0.8m (approx.
2ft 7in) at the front. The coucals love to run along the perches, often
preferring this to flying. The single nest box is situated at the rear of the
enclosure at a height of approximately 1.7m (5ft 7in). It is 28cm wide x
42cm long xl5cm deep (1 lin wide x 1ft 4&apos;/2in long x 6in deep), with a wire
mesh bottom. The feeding station is also situated at the rear of the enclosure,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.986119" page_id="56260872"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
50
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.828429" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260872" page_num="50" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-BROWED COUCAL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.753874" page_id="56260872"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
at a height of approximately 1.4m (4ft Tin). No artificial heat or light are
provided, as the coucals seem more than capable of thriving all year round
here at Exmoor without artificial heat and/or light.
Diet
Here at Exmoor the coucals receive:
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.903755818181818" page_id="56260872"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
Bogena Insectivorous mix
Soaked crushed Zoo A
Apple, pear, banana, carrot, grapes etc., cut into 5mm square pieces
Raw minced (ground) meat
Crushed boiled egg
Raw sprats
The following livefood is offered:
Large locusts
Field crickets
Waxmoth larvae
Mealworms
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.993251" page_id="56260872"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
All the above are taken readily. At 10.00am-10.30am the birds receive
the softbill mix, then at 3.00pm-3.30pm they are given livefood. This regime
suits us and the coucals well. In the afternoon, the livefood is scattered
about the aviary and enables the keepers to see the birds at their best and
most active. It is a wonderful sight to see the coucals scurrying about on the
floor searching for livefood and observing just how many insects they can
eat before their partner. They then return to perch on a branch and wait for
their next meal. A rotten log (which is replaced twice a year) is placed in the
aviary, and the coucals spend time excavating bugs from it. Clean water is
available for drinking and bathing.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.9195044" page_id="56260872"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
Nesting
23.04.05
09.05.05
12.05.05
19.05.05
</figure>
<page confidence="0.9192" page_id="56260872"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
26.05.05
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999384" page_id="56260872"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
Both the male and the female were observed carrying bamboo
leaves to the nest box. The initial nest was a very loose affair,
with a small depression in the middle.
The first egg was laid, followed by a further four eggs, which
were laid at daily intervals. The eggs were white and fairly uniform
in size. Average measurement 30mm x 22mm (from five eggs).
Both the male and female sat on the nest.
The nest had expanded in size, due to us adding bamboo leaves
and coconut fibre, which were woven into the nest, which now
filled the box.
Broken eggshells were found on the aviary floor and newly-
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.492564" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260873" page_num="51" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-BROWED COUCAL
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997833" page_id="56260873"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
51
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9889923" page_id="56260873"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
hatched coucals were observed. A period of 17 days passed from
when the first egg was laid to when the first egg hatched.
The young
The five young were all very vocal, even when the female was brooding
them. Eight extra feeds of livefood were given throughout the day between
8.00am-6.00pm. The chicks each had an enormous gape and black and
white quills, which made them look like tiny porcupines.
29.05.05 The female was observed feeding the youngsters from the softbill
mix, but took only the minced meat and sprats. The quantities of
these were therefore increased. The parents were at this time very
vocal and protective of the young. The male would "hiss" and
flick his tail from side to side when keepers entered the aviary,
although at no time did he attempt to 'dive bomb' them. The
female sat as tight and as still as she could and only left her
precious brood when the nest was inspected.
07.06.05 One of the chicks was found dead on the aviary floor. Very little
of it was left except the wings and torso. We can only assume
that it died in the nest and was promptly eaten by the others.
Possibly it had been the youngest, as the remaining four chicks
were all very much at the same stage of development. Their eyes
were now open, the quills had turned brown and the gape, that
was previously a very pale pink colour, was a more muted black,
though the tongue remained pink.
10.06.05 Minced meat and fish were no longer being taken, only livefood.
They probably got through 10 locusts, 20 crickets, 20-30
waxmoths and handsful of mealworms each day.
13.06.05 The first two young fledged. They looked very different from
the adult male and female. Their iris was brown, their feathers
were very dark and they had only a short tail.
14.06.05 The male was seen feeding locusts to the two young which had
fledged the previous day, while the female continued to brood
the two young which remained in the nest.
15.06.05 Two bowls of food were now being provided, one at the feeding
station and the other on the floor.
16.06.05 The male was very protective of the two fledglings and seemed
to be encouraging them to feed themselves. When the oldest of
the two begged to be fed, the male appeared to ignore it and fed
the others.
18.06.05 The remaining two young fledged. The two that had fledged
earlier were observed eating minced meat from the bowl on the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995352" page_id="56260874"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
52
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.878289" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260874" page_num="52" year="" vol="">
GIBSON - WHITE-BROWED COUCAL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.976431444444444" page_id="56260874"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
floor. When they begged for food, they were ignored but the
youngest two were fed. The softbill mix was tried, but was quickly
discarded.
21.06.05 All four youngsters were hiding, motionless, in the bamboo. At
no time after they had fledged was the female involved in their
development, instead she preferred to rebuild the nest.
29.06.05 The male was very vocal. He was calling to the female, who was
sitting on the nest. I can best describe his call as a rolling "doodle,
doodle, do".
20.07.05 Nine eggs had been laid.
30.07.05 All nine were clear. Average measurement 32mm x 22mm (nine
eggs).
No further nesting attempts were made. All four youngsters grew to look
identical to their parents. The iris of the eyes slowly turned red and by the
turn of the year the juvenile feathers had become like those of the adults.
The young were removed from the aviary in March 2006, as it was decided
that they might disrupt breeding this year.
At the time of writing (April 2006), Exmoor Zoological Park has 2.1.4
White-browed Coucals, and we have our fingers crossed that another
successful breeding season lays ahead with these most beautiful and
rewarding birds.
Derek Gibson, Exmoor Zoological Park, South Stowford, Bratton
Fleming, Barnstaple, Devon EX31 4SG, UK.
As described above, the White-browed Coucal Centropus superciliosus,
has been bred at the Exmoor Zoological Park. It is believed to be the first
breeding of this species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who knows of a
previous breeding is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.884115333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260875" page_num="53" year="" vol="">
SOME NOTES ON OUR EXPERIENCES OF KEEPING
AND BREEDING THE YELLOW-THROATED
LAUGHINGTHRUSH Garrulax galbanus courtoisi
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998497" page_id="56260875"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
53
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.964414428571428" page_id="56260875"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
by Martina Reul-Schneider and Holger Schneider
The Yellow-throated Laughingthrush is a highly social species. It breeds
in flocks in the wild, which is an exception within the genus Garrulax.
When fonning new pairs in an aviary, it is necessary to take into account the
social behaviour of this species. It is not possible to tell the sex of this
laughingthrush by its appearance or its behaviour. Behaviour amongst birds
of the same sex is the same as amongst pairs. Although you find two birds
of a true pair sitting very close to each other at night, to prove that two birds
really are a true pair, DNA-analysis is necessary. In the case of the 2.2 we
keep, the two males are very closely attached to each other. If you simply
relied upon their behaviour, you would mistakenly place them together as a
pair.
In our opinion G. galbanus courtoisi should not be regarded as a
subspecies of G. galbanus. Their appearances are similar, but their behaviour
is quite different.
Captive management
Because of its social behaviour described above, the Yellow-throated
Laughingthrush can easily be kept with many other bird species, even other
laughingthrushes. However, breeding success is unlikely in an aviary housing
many inhabitants. Young Yellow-throated Laughingthrushes leave the nest
very early and helpless and often fall victim to other birds. Small, ground-
living birds such as ground doves and quail, would probably not unduly
affect their breeding success. The Yellow-throated Laughingthrush will only
begin breeding, if it feels safe in an aviary. Such an aviary needs to be fairly
thickly planted, but with enough space to fly. It loves to take a bath in a
small pond. The aviary needs to have an enclosed shelter into which the
birds can retreat during cold weather, as you sometimes see specimens with
frost-bitten toes. Our two pairs are the sole occupants of a 23sq m (approx.
269sq ft) aviary, with a 9sq m (approx. 96sq ft) enclosed shelter. The aviary
is planted with a Beech Fagus sylvatica , an Apple Tree, hawthorn Crataegus
sp., buddleia and bamboo. A clematis is growing on the wall of the shelter.
The birds are only fed inside the shelter. They roost inside the shelter all
year round and almost always breed inside the shelter.
Diet
Not much is known about their food in the wild. Dependent on the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.898057" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260876" page_num="54" year="" vol="">
54 REUL-SCHNEIDER &amp; SCHNEIDER - YELLOW-THROATED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99485055" page_id="56260876"  page_num="54" year="" vol="">
season and the biotope, they are thought to eat a mixed diet of fruits, berries,
seeds and insects. Outside the breeding season our laughingthrushes get the
usual softbill food and fruit. Then before the breeding season begins (mid-
March-early April) we begin to mix the softfood with a commercial insect
food at a ratio of three parts softfood to one part insect food. The birds
continue to be fed fruit, plus the addition of some mealworms. A vitamin
and mineral supplement (Korvimin) is given all year round.
Nest building
In the wild nest building mostly starts in mid-April or the end of April.
That is when about 200 birds assemble in five known colonies. They always
prefer to breed in the same places in big Cinnamon Trees. The nests are
built close to each other. In aviaries Yellow-throated Laughingthrushes can
be bred in pairs as well as in flocks. The birds build the rather stable nest in
a place of their choosing. In contrast to the wild birds, aviary birds choose
very different nesting places. In aviaries nests have been built in bamboo,
Thuja , conifers, hawthorn and so on. More important is the safety of the
nesting site. The birds like little baskets made of bast as the base of the nest.
Some nests are used a second time for the next brood.
We put the baskets (15cm (almost 6in) in diameter) inside at the beginning
of April, depending on the weather. Our birds prefer to nest inside the shelter.
In the past five years they have built only one nest outside, on that occasion
in a clematis. The inside of the shelter is equipped only with branches. The
bifurcated (forked), leafless branches are arranged vertically like small, bare
trees. The nesting baskets are fixed 1.8m (approx 6ft) high. They become
surrounded by juniper or other coniferous leaves, so that a little cave arises.
There should be one, or better still, two narrowing openings through which
the birds can enter and leave the nest, and a cavity above the nest. We have
tested various different nesting materials and found that our birds prefer dry
blades of grass. Round blades of grass lmm-2mm in diameter and 15cm-
20cm (6in-8in) long are perfect. They must be flexible. Building usually
begins some days after the nesting material has been provided. The birds
seem to fly about the aviary with blades of grass in their bills, without any
sense of purpose, for two to three days; but then the nest is completed in one
and a half to two days. In many cases the first egg is laid the next day.
Egg-laying and incubation
Yellow-throated Laughingthrushes mostly lay three to four clean white
eggs, but can lay as few as two or as many as five. Both partners incubate
the eggs. Apparently the female incubates mostly at night and the male
during the day. When the birds start sitting, they can very easily be disturbed.
Therefore great care must be taken not to disturb them for at least the first
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.520539" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260877" page_num="55" year="" vol="">
REUL-SCHNEIDER &amp; SCHNEIDER - YELLOW-THROATED LAUGHINGTHRUSH 55
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999713292682927" page_id="56260877"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
six to seven days. The chicks hatch after 16 days.
Our two pairs build their nests 2m (approx. 6ft 6in) apart from each
other and there is never any aggressive behaviour between the two pairs. In
one case the first eggs of one pair were infertile. This pair was then attracted
by the calls of the newly-hatched chicks of the other pair and began helping
to care for them. Again this did not lead to any aggressive behaviour between
the two pairs. The four adult birds fed the young and sat on the nest brooding
them. It would have been interesting to have observed them for longer, but
the pairs were separated from each other in order to get a fresh clutch of
eggs from the first pair (the helpers).
A pair may produce up to four more clutches if earlier breeding attempts
have been unsuccessful. The female may also incubate the second clutch
alone, while the male cares for the chicks from the first clutch.
The hatching of the chicks
There is little detailed information available about the hatching of the
chicks and their diet in the wild. In our experience they leave the nest after
just 12 days. It is a very young age at which to leave the nest and they
remain very dependent on their parents. They can climb well and healthy
young birds immediately try to reach the highest branches. They sit close to
their siblings. Other birds in the aviary can pose a danger to them, due to
the young laughingthrashes' clumsy behaviour. It is advantageous if the
birds nest in the inside part of the aviary, where the young birds can stay for
the first few days and are protected from bad weather, such as heavy rain or
long-lasting cold or wet weather, which can be harmful to young birds.
Rearing the chicks presents the greatest problem: in the first three years
only one out of nearly 30 of our chicks survived. All died during the first
five weeks, before they had become independent. Others have experienced
similar problems: the studbook keeper has reported the loss of chicks in the
UK and reading the US studbook, one also finds that only a very small
number of chicks survive. Various zoos and private breeders have confirmed
this. Attempts to hand-rear the chicks had produced the same result, but
recently chicks have been hand-reared in a few zoo collections.
The symptoms we observed, leading to the death of the young, were
always the same with, in most cases, the chicks dying less than 24 hours
after first showing symptoms. The chicks suddenly became lethargic and
then their legs were affected. They became stiff and stretched forward and
the toes clenched into &apos;fists 5 , so that the birds could no longer grip the
branches. In addition, the birds developed diarrhoea, which resulted in the
feathers around the cloaca becoming stuck together. Some birds also had
difficulty breathing. Examination of the birds 5 faeces found no coccidia or
salmonella, only a sparse growth of coliformes. Examination of the dead
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.921959" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260878" page_num="56" year="" vol="">
56 REUL-SCHNEIDER &amp; SCHNEIDER - YELLOW-THROATED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994919692307693" page_id="56260878"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
chicks failed to establish any single, uniform, cause of death.
During these years, the breeding pairs were given different bowls
containing different kinds of food, with which to rear their young. There
was softfood as described earlier, fruit such as papaya (pawpaw), apple and
grapes and livefood (50% mealworms and 50% crickets and waxworms).
They were also given a vitamin and mineral supplement (Korvimin).
Unfortunately the parents took only the livefood to feed to their young and
ignored the other food.
After different attempts to optimize the rearing of the young, we made
two important changes in the 2004 breeding season. First of all, the food
was offered in a different way. The livefood and fruit were cut into very
tiny pieces and mixed with each other. The softfood was finely ground and
mixed with the livefood and fruit from the third day onwards. The result
was that the different elements of food stuck to each other. This meant that
the parents were forced to feed the chicks a mixture of foods, instead of just
the preferred livefood.
The second change we made was that in addition to the vitamin and
mineral supplement, we added a dose of vitamin Bi (using pulverized tablets).
After we made these changes, all the young grew up without any losses
during the following two years.
On reaching independence
The young begin to feed independently at five to six weeks of age, though
the parents continue to care for them for some weeks afterwards. It may be
that young of the first clutch assist with the rearing of the young of the
second clutch. In the wild the young birds probably live in small groups
with their family, and wander around until the next breeding season.
We have observed some especially interesting behaviours during the
development of the young. In one case, a juvenile which was already
independent, took part in brooding the second clutch. It was not clear if the
bird was really helping, or if it was just trying to have contact with its parents,
which mostly brooded at the same time with it.
In another case, a 15 day old hand-reared youngster was immediately
adopted by the adult birds, which were not breeding at the time.
Two seven week old youngsters were housed with a single adult male,
in order to let the parents produce a second clutch, and the youngsters were
adopted by the male.
The above are examples of the extremely social behaviour of this species.
Holger Schneider and Martina Reul-Schneider live in Germany. E-
mail: schneiderholger@t-online.de
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997227" page_id="56260879"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
57
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996527" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260879" page_num="57" year="" vol="">
YELLOW-THROATED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.982346333333333" page_id="56260879"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
Laura Gardner, Curator of Birds, Leeds Castle Aviaries and Species
Coordinator for the European zoo population, has provided the following
facts about the the Yellow-throated Laughingthrush and the Yellow-throated
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.783499588235294" page_id="56260879"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
Laughingthrush Project 2004.
Bjorn Anderson
Yellow-throated Laughingthrush {courtoisi), Wuyuan, China.
History of the bird in the wild in China
1919 Two collected in Wuyuan, south-east China.
1923 Birds described as Garrulax courtoisi.
1930 This was changed to G. galbanus courtoisi.
1956 Three were collected at Simao in south Yunnan, south-west China.
1988 Birds appeared in trade, although until then known only from China as
museum specimens, with no subsequent sightings recorded by either Chinese
or visiting ornithologists.
Aims of 2004 project
To visit six known breeding locations in China.
Make behavioural observations.
Undertake a population census.
Collect DNA samples.
Renew Memorandum of Understanding with Wuyuan Forestry Department.
</table>
<page confidence="0.939094" page_id="56260880"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
58
</page>
<figure confidence="0.946376159090909" page_id="56260880"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
GARDNER - YELLOW-THROATED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
Breeding
Nests in tall trees.
Trees around villages.
Trees adjacent to river.
Population overview
Year
Site 1
Site 2&amp;3
Site 4
Site 5
Site 6
2000
45-50
?
?
50-60
?
2001
about 40
50-60
4
about 50
?
2002
40-45
50-60
-
about 50
?
2003
30-40
60-80
-
40-50
about 20
2004
20+
30-40
_
30-40
20-30
Significance of Site 6
Close proximity of birds to people.
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.891738148148148" page_id="56260880"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
Potential for close sociobiological observations.
Different to other breeding sites (lower trees; not adjacent to river; in yard
of town government offices).
Predators.
Success of colonial nesting.
Partners in conservation
ZGAPS German conservation organisation that initiated support for surveys
in the wild. CEPA French conservation organisation.
Chester Zoo.
Leeds Castle.
Also funding from Mulhouse Zoo, France and UK-based Avicultural Society.
Status of birds in European zoos
Thirty-six birds were held in 11 collections at the end of December 2003.
Doubts exist over the taxonomy of these birds, which may be courtoisi or
simaoensis.
Chick mortality remains a problem.
Further investigation is needed regarding the birds' sociobiological needs,
e.g. are they best kept communally or in pairs.
Proposals for 2004-2007
The use of radio-tracking to help locate wintering sites.
To find a Chinese student to undertake behavioural studies and population
viability analysis.
Continue to search for simaoensis.
Investigate taxonomy - DNA-analysis of simaoensis and courtoisi to be
undertaken.
Circulation of husbandry/veterinary questionaire.
Compile and publish Husbandry Guidelines .
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.323683" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260881" page_num="59" year="" vol="">
GARDNER - YELLOW-THROATED LAUGHINGTHRUSH
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.98073" page_id="56260881"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
59
</page>
<table confidence="0.8546965" page_id="56260881"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
Special thanks to:
The Winston Churchill Memorial Trust.
Leeds Castle Foundation.
Prof. He Fen-qi, Academia Sinica, Beijing.
Wuyuan Forestry Department.
Dr Roger Wilkinson, Chester Zoo.
Dr Roland Wirth, ZGAP.
Bjorn Anderson.
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.999118166666667" page_id="56260881"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
Since the above was written, the Avieultural Society has received a request
for funding for a 10- day visit to Simao by Prof. He Fen-qi, to again search
for simaoensis, which has not been seen for definite in the wild since the
three specimens were collected in 1956.
Prof. He Fen-qi has made several previous visits to the area including
one with Laura in 2004. Hopes were raised early last year when on his third
visit he and his colleagues heard and glimpsed a bird they thought was
simaoensis. Dr Roger Wilkinson, Mary Richardson and Prof. He Fen-qi
visited the area later in 2005; but were unable to find this enigmatic bird.
Most or all previous visits to Simao have been in the spring (the season
when the type specimen was collected). This time though Prof. He Fen-qi
planned to visit the area in August, the main rainy season around Simao.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995004" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56260881" page_num="59" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970688375" page_id="56260881"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
The society has a large stock of back issues mostly from 1935 onwards
but there are also some earlier issues still available. They are priced #3.00
each (including p&amp;p). Please check availability before placing an order.
Overseas members may be able to pay by credit card through a Paypal
invoice, but this service is not available in all countries. All enquiries should
be addressed to: P. Boulden, Hon. Secretary/Treasurer, Avieultural Society,
Arcadia, The Mounts, East Allington, Totnes, Devon TQ9 7JQ, UK or
E-mail: admin@avisoc .co.uk
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.991447" page_id="56260882"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
60
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996361" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260882" page_num="60" year="" vol="">
ON THE EDGE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.983152769230769" page_id="56260882"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
by Jo Gregson
There are about 300 species of pigeons and doves in the world today.
Many of them we see each day and take for granted, hardly giving them a
second glance. This is odd, because the pigeon more than any other bird,
has been important to man in so many ways, e.g. as a source of food, a
message carrier, game bird, aviary pet and even magician's foil. The Dodo
Raphus cucullatus and Passenger Pigeon Ectopistes migratorius paid the
ultimate price for our adventures, but, for the Socorro Dove Zenaida graysoni ,
now extinct in the wild, we have a rare second chance.
The Socorro Dove was last observed on Socorro (off the west coast of
Mexico) in 1972. In captivity, however, this species is thriving and the
captive population is being globally managed by aviculturists in many zoos
and bird collections.
At first glance the Socorro Dove appears to be a rather dull looking bird,
that is an overall ruddy brown colour, but when seen close-up and in natural
sunlight, it is seen to be delicately marked with shades of brown and to sport
a bluish-grey head and nape. This colouring is less pronounced in the female.
The extinction of this species in the wild was brought about by the
introduction to the island of the domestic cat and habitat changes due to
extensive sheep fanning. In recent years, while aviculturists have been busy
managing the captive population, fieldwork has been carried out to eradicate
feral cats and restore the island's plant life.
It seems that many species of pigeon simply cannot wait to burst skyward
in a flurry of feathers, unlike the Socorro Dove which is calm and unfazed
by everyday business. It spends much of its time on the ground quietly
foraging for food, which must have made it easy prey for feral cats and
man. As with most pigeons and doves, this species is fairly undemanding
and is in no way difficult to keep in captivity. It is hardy and is a regular
breeder, making it an ideal aviary bird. Here at Paignton Zoo Environmental
Park on the south coast of Devon, our specimens live outside all year round.
They have access to heated shelters in which they can roost during cold
weather, though most prefer to brave the elements.
Their diet consists of a seed mixture, mixed millets, wheat and cracked
maize. In addition, they are fed a small amount of boiled egg and chopped
lettuce, lightly sprinkled with SA37. Lime and flint grit are always available.
It has been said that these birds can be aggressive to each other and to
other species. We have not found this to be a problem. Our two main breeding
pairs are housed in mixed exhibits, these are though some 30ft and 40ft (approx.
9.1m and 12.1m) high and do contain a lot of natural plant growth.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.677629" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260883" page_num="61" year="" vol="">
GREGSON - ON THE EDGE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995754" page_id="56260883"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
61
</page>
<table confidence="0.949476083333333" page_id="56260883"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
The following birds all live peacefully with our Socorro Doves:
Laysan Teal Anas laysanensis
Californian Quail Callipepla californica
Edwards's Pheasant Lophura edwardsi
Laughing Dove Streptopelia senegalensis
Turtle Dove Streptopelia turtur
Red-crested Turaco Tauraco erythrolophus
Green Turaco Tauraco persa
Bali Starling Leucopsar rothschildi
Azure-winged Magpie Cyanopica cyana
Zebra Finch Taeniopygia guttata
Male Socorro Doves mature in 12-18 months, depending on the time of
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.989119565217392" page_id="56260883"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
the year that they were hatched. We have kept mixed sex groups of young
birds in small holding aviaries without any problems until dominant males
reach about 14 months of age. At this time they start driving the young
females and have to be removed from the aviary. On occasions females
have been aggressive to other females when held in small enclosures.
Females mature at about the same age as the males. The youngest female
here to lay an egg was 12 months old. In an ideal world, young birds should
be paired and placed in a large aviary, before they are two years of age.
A trait that sets the Socorro Dove apart from most other captive pigeons
and doves is its ability to build a nest. Yes, it is true, they build their own
nests - and they are good nests at that! Two eggs are laid and are incubated
for 15 days, very often with both chicks being reared. The favoured height
for nest building is about 6ft-7ft (approx. 1.8m-2.1m) above the ground, in
dense vegetation. We have left young from several broods with their parents
for up to a year without any problems. Some of our young inexperienced
females will use wicker baskets to nest in.
Plans for the reintroduction of this species back onto Socorro are shaping
up well. A block of aviaries has been erected on the island in preparation
for a soft release scheme, due to begin in the near future. Captive-bred
birds to be used in this scheme will be selected following health screening
and DNA testing. Once the reintroduction begins, I am sure it will not be
long before the Socorro Doves 'find their feef and once more become part
of the island's wildlife.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.85044225">
Jo Gregson is Senior Head Keeper of Birds at Paignton Zoo
Environmental Park, Totnes Road, Paignton, Devon TQ4 7EU, UK.
Tel:01803 697500/Fax:01803 523457/Website:www.paigntonzoo.org.uk/
E-mail :jgregson@paigntonzoo. org. uk
</reference>
<page confidence="0.994901" page_id="56260884"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
62
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.909648" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260884" page_num="62" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE WHITE-BELLIED GO-AWAY BIRD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9096285" page_id="56260884"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
Corythaixoides leucogaster AT WADDESDON MANOR
by Andrew Owen
Description
The White-bellied Go-away Bird is a member of the turaco family. It is
50cm (approx. 19 3 /4in) in length, of which approximately 25cm (about
9 3 /4in) is taken up by the tail. The adults have a grey head, breast, back,
wings, upper tail-coverts and central tail feathers, the latter becoming darker
towards the tip. The median and greater wing-coverts have black tips, which
form bars across the closed wings. The white bases of the black primaries
are conspicuous when the birds fly. They have a 6cm (approx 2V2in) long,
black-tipped crest, which can be raised or lowered onto the head. The lower
breast, belly, thighs and under tail-coverts are white. The legs and feet are
blackish-grey. It is the only sexually dimorphic member of the turaco family,
the male having a black bill, whereas that of the female is a pale greyish-
green colour.
Distribution and habitat
The White-bellied Go-away Bird is found in east and north-east Africa,
in north-west, central and southern Somalia, Ethiopia, southern Sudan, north-
east Uganda, northern and eastern Kenya, south through the eastern plateau
of Tanzania. It is a bird of arid habitats, where it favours hot, low-lying
acacia savannah and scrub with scattered trees. It occurs from sea level to
an altitude of 1,700m (approx. 5,475ft) and is generally common throughout
its range (del Hoyo et al. 1997; Stevenson &amp; Fanshawe, 2003).
Food
This species feeds on a diet of fruits, flowers, seeds, leaves and buds of
acacias and other plants, particularly favouring the young green pods of
Acacia tortilis (del Hoyo et al. 1997).
Our birds
Three male White-bellied Go-away Birds were purchased from a dealer
in 2002. Following quarantine, the three were moved to one of the on-show
aviaries, which also housed a small group of Emerald Starlings Lamprotornis
iris. One of the White-bellied Go-away Birds died of septicaemia following
an injury to one of its legs. A female, a bird believed to have been bred at
VogelPark Walsrode, Germany, was bought from a private aviculturist in
September 2003. The female spent the winter months in quarantine and in
late spring 2004 was introduced to one of the remaining two males. The
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.532634" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260885" page_num="63" year="" vol="">
OWEN - WHITE-BELLIED GO-AWAY BIRD
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998925" page_id="56260885"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
63
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.982656208333333" page_id="56260885"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
pair bonded immediately and mating was observed during the pairs' first
day together.
Following her prolonged period in quarantine, the females' condition
improved over the next few weeks, in part due to increased exercise and
access to an outside aviary.
In August 2004, we learned that Birdworld in Surrey had a single female
that was laying eggs regularly, so immediately sent our spare male there on
breeding loan, in the hope of establishing a second pair.
Accommodation
The aviary our pair is housed in comprises of an outside flight 14ft long
x 12ft wide (approx. 4.2m long x 3.6m wide), with a domed roof that is 15ft
(approx. 4.5m) tall at its highest point. Natural branches are provided for
perching and the flight is planted with a number of shrubs including Bamboo
Pseudosasa japonica, Box Buxus sempervirens , False Acacia Rohina
pseudoacacia and palms Trachycarpus fortunii and Spirea. The White-
bellied Go-away Birds often eat the leaves and new buds of the acacia and
Spirea , but ignore the Box. Bark chippings and leaf litter cover the aviary
floor, in the centre of which there is a shallow pool in which the birds often
bathe.
The roof of the flight is partially covered and provides the birds with
protection during inclement weather. In addition the birds always have access
to a large indoor shelter which is heated to approximately 20*C (68*F).
They often spend a considerable amount of time in the shelter and often do
not venture into the outside flight for several days at a time.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.574269">
Feeding
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9992988" page_id="56260885"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
When the males first arrived, they would eat little else other than chopped
lettuce, banana and a few mealworms. However, over time they began to
accept the wide variety ripe fruits offered to our other species of turaco, i.e.
diced apple, pear, grapes, mango, papaya (pawpaw), kiwi fruit, plums,
peaches and nectarines. Other fruits offered when in season, may include,
strawberries, blueberries, apricots, figs and pomegranates. A proprietary
brand of low iron softbill food is also provided, to which is added, soaked
raisins, grated carrot and boiled egg. Low iron softbill pellets are also added
to the mix.
All the above items are taken to a lesser or greater degree, however, the
birds definitely have a pronounced preference for greenfood, as they do in
the wild. This was also noted at Houston Zoo, where this species was first
bred (Todd et al. 1985). Therefore, during the summer of 2004, the birds
were offered romaine (cos) lettuce, spinach, pak-choi (Chinese celery
cabbage), peas and leafy, cut branches of a number of trees and scrubs
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997246" page_id="56260886"  page_num="64" year="" vol="">
64
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.878132" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260886" page_num="64" year="" vol="">
OWEN - WHITE-BELLIED GO-AWAY BIRD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99335743902439" page_id="56260886"  page_num="64" year="" vol="">
growing in the estate grounds. These included Hawthorn Crataegus nigra ,
Lime Tilia sylvatica, honeysuckle Lonicera spp., Cotoneaster spp. and willow
Salix spp., from which the birds ate the tender young leaves.
Breeding
Following the initial flurry of activity, which included mating and a lot
of calling, when the pair was placed together, there were few further signs
of breeding behaviour until July 19th, when the male was seen chasing the
female. A few days later, on July 22nd and 23rd, the female was seen carrying
fine twigs to a wicker nest basket, attached to a wall high up in the aviary
shelter. No further breeding activity was seen until December 18th, when
the male was seen sitting for a brief period in the nest basket. This behaviour
continued for the next five days, during which time the female was never
seen on the nest. On December 22nd the male had been observed feeding
regurgitated food to the female. On December 29th the female solicited
food from the male by fluttering her wings, before and during feeding, much
like a turaco chick would beg for food. An hour later she was sitting in the
basket. Over the next week, the pair was often seen sitting together on the
nest. On February 7th the birds were seen possibly mating and continued to
spend a lot of time in the basket. We were reluctant to disturb them, but
during a brief period on February 18th when they were not sitting, a nest
inspection revealed a single pale bluish-green egg. During this inspection
the birds returned and were calling loudly. After this, disturbance was kept
to a minimum. During the next two days, the male incubated throughout
the day, rarely coming off the nest to feed. We assumed that the female
probably took over incubation during the evening. A second egg was laid
on February 21st, but was laid from the perch and smashed. By the end of
February we felt the hatching of the egg was overdue, but allowed the birds
to continue sitting until March 3rd, when the egg was removed and found to
be infertile. There were a lot of feathers in the shelter and the female began
to moult heavily.
On March 26th the birds were behaving strangely, with both of them
making an unusual continuous croaking call, that was very different from
their usual rather duck-like nasal call. The male was chasing the female
around the aviary floor, but no aggression was observed. On March 28th
the nest was checked and found to contain two bluish-green eggs. These
subsequently proved to be infertile.
From the beginning of April the nest was seldom left unattended and by
April 9th the birds appeared to be sitting again. Often both birds would sit
together in the basket, but with the male continuing to carry out most of the
assumed incubation during the day. Because of our reluctance to disturb the
birds it was not until April 28th that we were able to confirm that there were
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.532627" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260887" page_num="65" year="" vol="">
OWEN - WHITE-BELLIED GO-AWAY BIRD
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998267" page_id="56260887"  page_num="65" year="" vol="">
65
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999673714285714" page_id="56260887"  page_num="65" year="" vol="">
two eggs in the nest. When the nest was checked on May 9th it was found
to contain an egg and a recently hatched chick. The chick's head, neck and
back were covered with sooty brownish-grey down, with paler creamy-white
down on the flanks and underside. Both adults remained on the nest during
the inspection. A close examination of the nest revealed that it had been
heavily lined with bamboo twigs and leaves. On May 11th the second egg,
which was infertile, was removed from the nest. Both parents continued to
take turns brooding the chick during the day and were seen eating buds and
flowers of the acacia tree in the outside flight and feeding the regurgitated
buds and flowers to the chick.
The chick continued to grow well and by eight days of age it had trebled
in size and the dark pin-feathers of the wings and tail were erupting. The
adults were offered a large amount of greenfood, in the form of romaine
lettuce, pak-choi and spinach, as well as the leafy branches of Hawthorn,
Lime, Hazel Corylus avellana, willow and honeysuckle. All of these were
taken, with the tender young leaves of the Lime and Hawthorn being
favoured. Very little fruit appeared to be taken at this time.
By the time it was 15 days old the chick had a small crest and a short tail
approximately 4cm (just over Vhm) long. The wing feathers were grey
with distinctive black barring, similar to that of the adults. The chick left
the nest basket on day 18 and landed amongst a thick layer of conifer branches
that had been placed beneath the nest site a few days earlier. It appeared to
be healthy and both parents were in close attendance throughout the rest of
the day.
The next morning the chick was found on the aviary floor. It was very
weak and was chilled, having apparently been abandoned by its parents,
which until then had been model parents. The chick was immediately placed
in a brooder and after an hour began to warm up. During the day it grew
increasingly stronger, but refused to take food from a dish or from tweezers.
It was therefore force-fed at two hourly intervals with a variety of fruits,
lettuce and soaked T16 turaco pellets. The temperature in the brooder was
reduced to 26*C (78.8*F), after which the chick seemed more comfortable.
It was decided not to return it to its parents, which showed no signs of
distress over losing their chick. The chick, which was placed in a small
cage, was beginning to take food from a pair of tweezers and showed a
strong preference for greenfood such as lettuce and peas. Other food items
had to be hidden behind the lettuce and peas before the chick would eat
them. After five days the young go-away bird would avidly take peas and
bits of mango from tweezers, but would refuse everything else. Over the
following 10 days the young go-away bird's health declined rapidly, it refused
to voluntarily take any food from the dish or tweezers and became
increasingly weak. It had to be force-fed every meal and would often
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.872175666666667" page_id="56260888"  page_num="66" year="" vol="">
66
OWEN - WHITE-BELLIED GO-AWAY BIRD
Andrew Owen
Female sitting on nest.
Andrew Owen
Female, male (with black bill) and chick.
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.394425" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260889" page_num="67" year="" vol="">
OWEN - WHITE-BELLIED GO-AWAY BIRD
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.718521" page_id="56260889"  page_num="67" year="" vol="">
67
</page>
<figure confidence="0.89876675" page_id="56260889"  page_num="67" year="" vol="">
Eight days old.
Andrew Owen
Aged 25 days.
Andrew Owen
</figure>
<page confidence="0.997957" page_id="56260890"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
68
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.876661" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260890" page_num="68" year="" vol="">
OWEN - WHITE-BELLIED GO-AWAY BIRD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999726380952381" page_id="56260890"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
regurgitate the food as soon as it had been given to it. As it was refusing all
food and had become increasingly weak, the decision was taken to euthanase
it at 42 days old. A post mortem showed that apart from a large, fatty liver,
all the other organs appeared to be normal.
On June 8th, four days after the pair had been seen mating, the first egg
of a further clutch was laid. Prior to this a CCTV camera had been placed
above the nest and this allowed us to make detailed observations of the
nesting activity. Incubation commenced following the laying of the first
egg, after which two further eggs were laid on alternate days. Three egg
clutches are often laid by the grey turacos, unlike the green and blue members
of the family, which normally lay only two eggs (del Hoyo et al. 1997).
As with the earlier nesting attempts, the birds shared incubation duties,
with the male sitting for the majority of the day and the female sitting in the
evening. Occasionally both birds would sit on the nest at the same time.
Time spent off the nest was infrequent and usually very brief, with the
incubating bird coming off to feed for 10 minutes or less. Changeovers
would usually take place at the nest and would often involve some quiet
vocalisation and bill touching. When the male arrived at the nest, he would
occasionally regurgitate food to the female, before taking over incubation
duties. Nesting material, usually bamboo twigs and leaves, was added to
the nest throughout the incubation period.
The first egg hatched at 8.55am on July 6th, 29 days after it was laid.
Both parents were on the nest as the egg was hatching and were seen to peck
the shell; presumably they could hear the chick calling inside. Once the
chick had emerged, the parents ate the remaining shell. The second egg
hatched on July 7th, 28 days after being laid and the third egg hatched on
July 9th, again after a 28 day incubation period. The chicks begged for food
one to two hours after hatching and received their first feeds soon afterwards.
The first two chicks to hatch progressed well, but the youngest chick was
found dead in the nest two days after hatching. It was still very small and
presumably had not been able to complete for food with its two older and
stronger siblings.
As with the earlier nesting attempts, the parents were again provided
with a wide variety of green leaves including Dandelion Taraxacum officinale
leaves. The two chicks grew well on this diet and at 18 days old, resembled
miniature versions of the adults, though with short crests and tails. Most of
their plumage was downy, as the body feathers had not yet fully developed.
As the nest basket was relatively high up, a thick layer of wood shavings
was placed below the nest to provide a soft landing and prevent injury to the
chicks when they left the nest. Like the young of other turacos, young go-
away birds are unable to fly properly on leaving the nest, but are able to ran
along the floor and scramble among branches placed below the nest.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.532625" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260891" page_num="69" year="" vol="">
OWEN - WHITE-BELLIED GO-AWAY BIRD
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998134" page_id="56260891"  page_num="69" year="" vol="">
69
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.988590658536585" page_id="56260891"  page_num="69" year="" vol="">
One of the young left the nest at 18 days old, but was returned to the nest
before the end of the day. Both young eventually left the nest at 24 days old,
by which time they were able to perch properly and would sit together quietly
on one of the low branches in the aviary shelter. Unlike with the first nesting
attempt, both parents continued to care for the young after they left the nest,
with one or both of them sitting close to the young, which would solicit
food from their parents in a typical turaco manner, i.e. by flapping their
wings and emitting a high-pitched call.
On August 7th both juveniles, one aged 30 days old and the other aged
28 days old, were seen for the first time eating greenfood from a dish placed
on the aviary floor. However, they continued to beg for and receive food
from their parents, while starting to take larger quantities of food from the
dishes provided. Due to their fibrous, leafy diet, pellets of indigestible
material were regurgitated by all of the go-away birds.
The two young birds grew steadily and after a few weeks began to spend
more time in the outside aviary, where on hot sunny days they were seen
sunbathing. At four months of age they were fully-grown and virtually
indistinguishable from the adult male and like him both possessed black
bills. In November 2005 the adults nested again. Only one egg was laid in
the nest basket, the second egg was laid from a perch and smashed on the
ground below. The juveniles were left in the aviary with their parents to see
if cooperative breeding occurs in this species. Although neither of the
juveniles were seen in the nest basket on their own incubating the egg, one
or occasionally both of them were often seen sitting in the basket with an
incubating parent. They were clearly interested in the egg and all four birds
were in attendance and pecking at the egg as it hatched.
The chick progressed well and on several occasions was observed being
fed by the juveniles. It seemed to be healthy, but sadly, died at only four
days old. There was no indication that the juveniles had played any part in
its death. Unfortunately it was not possible to send it for post mortem.
Perhaps it was lost as a result of having hatched during the English winter,
when we were unable to provide it with a large variety of greenfood,
particularly leaves.
By the end of December, the two juveniles, then aged five months, became
aggressive towards the adult female and were therefore removed to a separate
aviary which, unfortunately, brought to an end our experiment in the
cooperative breeding of this species.
Conclusion
The White-bellied Go-away Bird was bred at Waddesdon Manor during
2005 and we believe this to have been the first time this species has been
bred in the UK.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.988325" page_id="56260892"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
70
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.813759" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260892" page_num="70" year="" vol="">
OWEN - WHITE-BELLIED GO-AWAY BIRD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98501" page_id="56260892"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
The White-bellied Go-away Bird is a charming member of the turaco
family and although not brightly coloured like many of its relatives, it is
nevertheless a beautiful bird. It is confiding and relatively straightforward
to keep, as long as it is provided with plenty of greenfood. In our experience
it has a relatively gentle nature, unlike many other turacos, and apart from
the harassing of the female by the juveniles, no other aggression has been
observed.
Although it is not rare in the wild, it would be nice to establish this
delightful species in captivity. The difficulty may be that there seems to be
very few of them being kept.
A small number of wild-caught birds were imported by a UK dealer
during 2005, but their location is unknown to us. We would like to hear
from anyone who keeps this species. The author can be contacted by
telephone at: 01296 653286 or e-mail:Andrew.Owen@nationaltrust.org.uk
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.866528" genericHeader="references" page_id="56260892" page_num="70" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.992163666666666" page_id="56260892"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A. and Sargatal, J. (eds.). 1997. Handbook of the Birds of the World. Vol.4.
Lynx Edicions, Barcelona.
Stevenson, T. and Fanshawe, J. 2002. Field Guide to the Birds of East Africa. T &amp; A D Poyser,
London.
Todd, W., Grubbs, D. C. and Lahera, H. 1985. A successful breeding of the White-bellied
Touraco Corythaixoides leucogaster at the Houston Zoo. Avicultural Magazine 91,3:120-123.
Product mentioned in the text
Nutribird T16 low iron pellets: Versele-Laga NV, Kapellestraat 70, B-9800, Deinze, Belgium.
Waddesdon Manor (website: www. waddesdon. org. uk), near Aylesbury,
Buckinghamshire HP 18 OJH, was built (1874-1889) by Baron Ferdinand
de Rothschild on a hilltop overlooking Aylesbury Vale. It has one of the
finest Victorian gardens in the UK, at the heart of which are 10 aviaries,
four of which house African birds, including the White-bellied Go-away
Birds, and six of which house Asian species. Mr James de Rothschild
bequested Waddesdon to the National Trust in 1957 and, a family charitable
trust, under the chairmanship of Lord Rothschild, now manages it for the
National Trust.
As described above, the White-bellied Go-away Bird Corythaixoides
leucogaster , has been bred at Waddesdon Manor. It is believed to be the first
breeding of this species in Great Britain or Ireland. Anyone who knows of a
previous breeding is asked to inform the Hon. Secretary.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9555985" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260893" page_num="71" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE GREATER FLAMINGO - THE FIRST
SUCCESS IN 15 YEARS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996837" page_id="56260893"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
71
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.980954" page_id="56260893"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
by Walter Mangold
Here at the World of Birds Wildlife Sanctuary, Hout Bay, Cape Town,
South Africa, the colony of Greater Flamingos Phoenicopterus ruber roseus
consisting now of 58 birds, was obtained when the birds were young chicks
15 years ago, during a dramatic rescue operation, when thousands of chicks
died at Etosha Pan in Namibia, when the water dried up at the crucial
hatching/ development stage.
Greater Flamingo on nest mound.
Greater Flamingos may reach 40-60 years of age; breeding probably
starts at four to six years of age or a little later.
Greater Flamingos are not known to breed in the Western Cape and there
are only isolated, sporadic records of them breeding or attempting to breed
in the Northern Province.
Over the past years there have been many breeding attempts at the World
of Birds, sometimes they have even attempted to breed two or three times in
a year. Every time success seemed to be close though, there was a drastic
change in the weather and their efforts ended as abruptly as they had started.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995899" page_id="56260894"  page_num="72" year="" vol="">
72
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.807622" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260894" page_num="72" year="" vol="">
MANGOLD - GREATER FLAMINGO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998230697674419" page_id="56260894"  page_num="72" year="" vol="">
Was the weather the problem or could it have been that our colony had
no experienced breeding pairs to teach the other birds by example? Having
been obtained when still young chicks, our birds had never witnessed the
collective breeding frenzy in a huge colony of wild flamingos. We tried
everything we could think of to assist them. We added more water to the
potential nesting area. We dug and loosened the soil to make it easier for
them to build their nest mounds and added clay to bind the soil and scattered
leaf litter to help hold it together. We also added rock salt to the water in the
hope it would provide extra stimulation. We even filled buckets with wet
clay and then turned the buckets upside down and tipped it out onto the
ground to create potential nest mounds. It was though all to no avail.
Then in November 2004, summer started much earlier than usual, with
very favourable mild and warm and even hot conditions right through to the
end of December. We found we no longer needed to waste time helping
them, for they were building their first nest mounds on raised land which
was high and dry. It was a mystery to us how they managed to use their
beaks to scrape the surrounding diy soil into small mounds and, we wondered,
if they used saliva to bind it together.
Soon we had fluctuating numbers of very high nest mounds in the small
wetland area through which water trickled from a higher to a lower pond.
Was this activity, we wondered, due to perfect weather conditions or the
change of food, to the commercially prepared, locally produced, Avi-plus
flamingo mash, which had recently become available to us, or was it a
combination of both?
Nests were abandoned and new ones built. There was a maximum of 20
at one time; then the first eggs appeared. Some fell out of the nests and
some were broken by scavenging, free-flying Sacred Ibises Threskiornis
aethiopicus. We collected some of the fallen eggs and put them in an
incubator, and put dummy eggs in those nests to keep the activity going in
the colony.
Most of the early eggs were infertile, but new eggs kept appearing. The
nest mounds kept growing in height and becoming wider around the base,
and we were amazed to see how huge some of them became. The flamingos
incubated the single egg, by balancing on top of the mounds, with their
folded legs sticking out behind.
Every now and then an incubating bird would suddenly rise, examine
and fondle and turn the egg, then cautiously lower itself down again, wriggle
from side to side to get comfortable and then quietly continue brooding the
egg, which rested in a dip on the top of the mound.
There was great excitement just before Christmas when the first dark
grey down-covered chick, with a pink beak and dark pink legs, hatched.
The next morning though it was gone presumably having been snatched
and eaten by ibises.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.475137" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260895" page_num="73" year="" vol="">
MANGOLD - GREATER FLAMINGO
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998566" page_id="56260895"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
73
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999600404761904" page_id="56260895"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
It was interesting to observe the flamingos' reaction when a turkey hen
or a peacock approached. The turkey caused the entire colony to abandon
its nests in fear for a moment, whereas the peacock was collectively
confronted and challenged. The usually very timid and panicky flamingos
also changed mood drastically when staff tried to sneak in to replace fallen
eggs. The birds fearlessly faced the staff and violently pecked at them,
while the incubating birds refused to rise from their nests.
On December 29th another newly-hatched chick was seen. It was on a
nest close to where the visiting public were only a few metres (yards) from
the colony and had the privilege of observing the intimate behaviour of the
flamingo family and other members of the colony, something that would
have been an impossibility in the wild.
In the afternoon the chick had fallen from the nest and was found lying
in the shallow muddy water. It was another critical moment between success
and failure. A member of staff had to go in and rescue the chick and replace
it on the nest so that it was safe from being eaten by the ibises. Later the
same afternoon, another newly-hatched chick had fallen from its nest mound
and was seen trying frantically to scramble back up again. It too had to be
replaced. The continued presence of the Sacred Ibises walking freely within
the colony was a great worry. Our management team of Hendrik Louw and
his wife Claire stayed until late in the evening to make sure that all was well
and returned again very early the next morning.
On January 1st there were three chicks, one of which never seemed to
develop quite as well as the other two. It always looked dirty and clumsy,
so we were not surprised when a few days later, it could not be accounted
for in the morning. The remaining two were monitored each day. They
were often viciously pecked when walking amongst the incubating adults,
but they continued to progress well. In the evenings they climbed to the
tops of their nest mounds to be kept warm and safe. It was the most wonderful
feeling to see their heads sticking out from under or above the parents' wings
and to watch them gently being fed life-giving liquid from the adults' beaks.
After 10 days we stopped worrying about them, as by then they were too
large to be at risk of being eaten by the ibises.
At that stage there were still up to 20 occupied nests and a maximum of
16 eggs were counted. No more eggs hatched though and gradually the
nests were abandoned, with the last two birds remaining with their eggs
until the end of January.
A start has been made and experience gained. We have what we expect
will in future develop into a very productive breeding colony of Greater
Flamingos. Our flamingos have demonstrated that they really cJo not need
our help. We must just provide them with the right food and leave the rest to
nature. That is all that is needed.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997113" page_id="56260896"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
74
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.614861" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260896" page_num="74" year="" vol="">
MANGOLD - GREATER FLAMINGO
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.6951912" page_id="56260896"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
Part of the colony that was obtained as young chicks.
Two chicks were reared during the 2004-2005 breeding season.
The author is Director of the World of Birds Wildlife Sanctuary,
Valley Road, Ho at Bay 7806, Cape Town, South Africa. Website:
www.worldofbirds.org.za/ e-mail:worldofbirds@mweb.co.za
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9349005" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260897" page_num="75" year="" vol="">
BREEDING AND DIET OF THE CROAKING GROUND
DOVE Columbina cruziana
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.992608" page_id="56260897"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
75
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.965420861111111" page_id="56260897"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
by Jack Clinton Eitniear
The Croaking Ground Dove Columbina cruziana is a 15cm (approx.
6in) long sexually dimorphic Columbina ground dove that inhabits arid and
semi-arid areas along the Pacific coast of South America at altitudes of up
to 3,230m (approx. 10,600ft) (Henry, 2005; contra Baptista et al. 1997),
from northern Ecuador to northern Chile and east in northern Pern to the
Maranon Valley (Baptista et al. 1997; Dickinson, 2003; Ridgely &amp; Greenfield,
2001). Typical of ground doves, it can be found on farmland and in gardens
and parks, as well as in scrub and riparian thickets. Breeding is said to be
stimulated by rainfall with nesting starting four to six weeks after the first
good rains (Baptista et al. 1997; Goodwin, 1983). Despite this nesting has
been recorded in most months with multiple nests in a single season likely
(Johnson, 1967). Nests have been located in bushes and trees, on the ground
and on ledges of buildings.
According to egg data slips at the Western Foundation of Vertebrate
Zoology (Rene Corado pers. comm.) nests have been collected from June-
March. They have been discovered from 1.5m-3m (approx. 5ft-9ft 9in)
above the ground in cactus, small trees (acacia), citrus and banana plants.
Eight eggs averaged 3.89g (3.53g-4.52g) with dimensions of 21.5mm x
17.2mm-24.6rnm x 18.3mm (n=9). Nesting in considerable numbers has
been noted in the isolated fruit growing desert oasis of Pica, Chile, Johnson
(1967) gave the average measurement of nine eggs as 23.2mm x 17.9mm.
Captivity
During 2003 a shipment containing Croaking Ground Doves was
imported from Peru into the USA, through the port of Miami, Florida. Three
pairs were obtained during March 2004 and placed in a 1m x 1.5m x lm
(approx. 3ft 3in x 5ft x 3ft 3in) holding cage and fed a commercial dove mix
with a finch mix added, supplemented with fresh diced fruit and lettuce and
with vitamins, water and oystershell also provided.
Breeding
On April 1st 2004 a pair was visually sexed and placed in a planted
aviary measuring 2m x 4m (approx. 6ft 6in x 13ft), that housed a single pair
of Black and White Seedeaters Sporophila luctuosa. On April 20th two
pure white egg, one measuring 23mm x 18mm and the other 24mm x 18mm,
were discovered in a nest lined with grasses in a 24cm (9V2in) wicker basket,
fixed in a comer, 2m (approx. 6ft 6in) above the aviary floor. On May 1st
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.987641" page_id="56260898"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
76
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.886764" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260898" page_num="76" year="" vol="">
EITNIEAR - CROAKING GROUND DOVE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.983576428571429" page_id="56260898"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
the eggs hatched and the two young fledged on May 13th.
In 2005 all three pairs were placed in a large L-shaped aviary (the second
portion of which measured 2m x 4.5m (approx. 6ft 6in x 13ft 8in)) with
Black and White Seedeaters and Elegant Quail Lophortyx douglasii. No
breeding activity was noted in 2005.
This year two pairs were removed in the hope that the remaining pair
would breed. On April 10th a nest was discovered in a dead conifer. The
nest was 1.5m (approx. 5ft) above the ground. The pair had chosen this site
despite having several baskets and nest boxes available. The nest contained
two eggs that were being incubated at the time of the discovery. This nest
was of more significant construction than the previous one. On April 17th
the two eggs hatched and the young fledged on May 2nd (after 15 days). At
the time of writing, the pair has re-nested in the basket. Nest construction is
similar to the previous basket nest. They currently have two chicks in pin-
feathers. Of the four fledged, three were males, which supports the finding
of Bosque et al. (2004), who noted that the wild population contains a higher
proportion of males.
Diet
Upon receipt of the doves they were fed the dove and finch mixes
described above. Concerned that the seeds in these mixes were too large for
this species, I proceeded to review the literature on the subject and
subsequently applied the information to developing a more appropriate diet.
As a precursor to the development of the diet, I obtained samples of the
three most readily available mixes (finch, canary and dove). Dissection of
the mixes indicated that cumulatively they were composed of 14 types of
seeds and grains etc. (Table 1). These were measured using an Alan Gordon
Enterprises(R) hand-held lenscope with a 7 x 1 Div. 0.1 scale. Seeds were
measure to 0.1mm.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.944365">
Results and discussion
Breeding
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9988528" page_id="56260898"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
Jeffrey Trollope (1974) discussed the breeding and behaviour of this
species. I would like to note areas not included in his article, as well as
aspects that contrast with his experiences. In chronological sequence I should
note that even in a large aviary this species appears to breed best in single
pairs and not in group situations. Given that the first pair bred in one section
of the L-shaped aviary, before the dividing door was removed, one could
conclude that a pair would be successful in each section of the aviary, if the
dividing door remained closed, but this proved not to be the case.
Nest site selection and composition varied significantly. Unlike in
Trollope's aviary, no nests or nest sites were re-used. It would seem plausible
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.618579" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260899" page_num="77" year="" vol="">
EITNIEAR - CROAKING GROUND DOVE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.994181" page_id="56260899"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
77
</page>
<author confidence="0.750149">
Jack Clinton Eitniear
</author>
<bodyText confidence="0.997691541666667" page_id="56260899"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
Nest removed from conifer after young fledged. Note faecal material on rim.
that if a nest failed prior to incubation, it would likely be re-used. After the
eggs have hatched and there are growing chicks in the nest, however, faecal
material accumulates on the rim of the nest, and to re-use such a nest would
likely encourage parasites. In my aviary all three nests were newly
constructed. While the nest of this species is generally described as not
being "a substantial structure" or a "flimsy platform" (Ingels pers. comm.)
in my experience nest construction depends on the structure on which it is
built. For example, two of the three nests were built in small, oval-shaped
baskets. In these instances the nests were approximately 11 cm wide x 2.5cm
deep ( 4 V 2 in wide x lin deep) and were made of fine and coarse grasses and
some feathers. The second of the three nests was 16cm wide x 5.5 cm deep
(approx. 6 V 2 in wide x 272in deep). It was a considerable structure. It was
tucked inside the middle of the previous year's Christmas tree, that had
been placed in a comer of the aviary. As the pair constmcted another smaller
nest, after this larger one, it is likely that the nest site chosen, determines the
size and stmcture of the nest. A nest built in a conifer needs to be a much
larger nest than that required when the birds nest in a sturdy basket mounted
on a wall. Evidence of such variation in nest construction was not found in
the literature, although in the account of the closely related Ecuadorian or
Buckley's Ground Dove C. buckleyi, it is stated that it builds a very
"substantial nest" in captivity (Baptista et al. 1997). One has to wonder if
the same variation in nest constmction is found in that species as well.
Trollope (1974) mentioned that the bill was hom coloured at age 21
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995199" page_id="56260900"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
78
</page>
<table confidence="0.2817925" page_id="56260900"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
EITNIEAR - CROAKING GROUND DOVE
Jack Clinton Eitniear
This nest is smaller than the previous nest that the same pair built in a conifer.
Jack Clinton Eitniear
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.9845152" page_id="56260900"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
Recently hatched young.
days. With our birds here, all four had typical adult-like black and yellow
bills at 26 days (see photo opposite). This may or may not be consistent
with Trollope, as considerable development can occur in five days. In
addition, I found considerable differences in the sizes of the nest-mates in
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.606242" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260901" page_num="79" year="" vol="">
EITNIEAR - CROAKING GROUND DOVE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.975876" page_id="56260901"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
79
</page>
<table confidence="0.755040333333333" page_id="56260901"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
Jack Clinton Eitniear
Fifteen days old.
Jack Clinton Eitniear
Twenty-six days old. Note that the iris and bill colour have changed and that the
plumage now resembles that of the adult. This species is also known as the Gold-billed
Ground Dove.
</table>
<page confidence="0.990298" page_id="56260902"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
80
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.875609" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260902" page_num="80" year="" vol="">
EITNIEAR - CROAKING GROUND DOVE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.982836820512821" page_id="56260902"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
all three nests. At day 30, however, both fledglings had reached the same
developmental stage. In the two broods I observed, the young did not
associate closely with the adults after fledging. In fact, the adults went back
to nesting within one week of the young having fledged, requiring the young
ground doves to be quite independent.
Diet
Trollope (1974) stated that the species fed on various millets, hemp,
rape, niger and small canary seed, yet he was able to produce only two
young from six clutches (a total of 12 eggs). To rule out nutrition as a
problem, I investigated the diet of this species in the wild and developed a
captive diet that is as close as possible to the natural one. I was fortunate to
be able to turn to some field data Perez &amp; Bulla (2000) had recently published
in their study of granivorous doves in Venezuela. They studied four species:
Plain-breasted Ground Dove C. minuta, Common Ground Dove C.passerina ,
Ruddy Ground Dove C. talpacoti and Scaled Dove Scaradafella squammata.
They concluded that all four species prefer seeds in the same size range. As
doves do not dehusk seeds, but swallow them whole, seed size is related to
bill and gape size rather than bill shape. With the four species studied, bill
length ranged from 14mm in C. minuta to 16mm in S. squammata. The bill
length of C. cruziana is 15mm (between that of C. passerina 14mm and C.
talpacoti 15.2mm). Given that the Croaking Dove is clearly within the size
range of the ground doves studied by Perez &amp; Bulla (2000), I felt their data
was relevant. In short, they concluded that the ground doves fed on seeds
from over 120 plant species but preferred plants with seeds up to 2.5mm in
length. In fact, the mean seed length preferred ranged from 1.75mm-1.95mm.
The total range of seeds consumed ranged from 0.8mm-6.4mm. Given the
hundreds of different seeds to choose from, the four species of ground doves
preferred seeds approximately 2.0mm in length.
Table 1 shows the sizes of the seeds, etc., in typical cage bird mixes.
The greatest size variation, from 2.0mm-7.0mm, is found in the dove mix.
However, there is only one type of seed in this mix within the preferred seed
size range of ground doves. Surprisingly, most finch mixes commercially
available in the USA contain very little variety. With seeds from 1.7mm-
5.0mm, finch mixes appear to be formulated to provide nourishment for
finches with various seed size preferences. Canary mixes contain the greatest
variety of different types of seeds, with more smaller seeds than the other
mixes. Croaking Ground Doves tend to choose smaller seeds and leave the
larger ones in the dish. Though certainly they would feed on the larger ones
(up to 7mm perhaps) rather than starve.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.618894" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260903" page_num="81" year="" vol="">
EITNIEAR - CROAKING GROUND DOVE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996831" page_id="56260903"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
81
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.999329">
Table 1. Composition and size of ingredients in three standard mixes.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.994972849056604" page_id="56260903"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
Type
Size
Finch
Canary
Dove
Niger 1
1.7mm
X
X
Rape 1
1.7mm
X
Red proso millet 1
2.0mm
X
Yellow millet (small) 1
2.0mm
X
White millet
3.0mm
X
X
X
Sesame seed (hulled)
3.5mm
X
Milo
4.0mm
X
Flax seed
4.0mm
X
X
Hemp seed
4.0mm
*x
Popcorn
5.0mm
X
Canary grass seed
5.0mm
X
X
Rice
6.0mm
X
Oat groats
6.0mm
X
Safflower (hulled)
7.0mm
X
1 Indicates seeds within optimum foraging size of ground doves.
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.996557736842105" page_id="56260903"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
As a result of the above findings, I switched from finch and dove mixes
to a canary mix, which I augment with red proso millet. While cage bird
mixes may vary, the point here is if you purchase or formulate a mix, the
greatest percentage of seeds should be under 2.0mm. The same size rule
should apply to pelleted and granulated diets. As well as getting the size
right, it is undoubtably also important to provide a variety of types of seeds.
In their analysis of the 51 types of seeds available to the (North American)
Tree Sparrow Spizella aborea Kendeigh &amp; West (1965) noted significant
variation in the caloric content of seeds between species within the same
family and between different families. These differences can amount to as
much as 1,000 calories per gram of seed. Optimum foraging theory tells us
that birds feed on the seeds that provide the greatest nutritional benefit for
the least amount of effort. This choice is often passed on to the young
through observing the feeding habits of their parents (Cadieu et al. 1995).
Wild caught birds not only have to adjust to a captive diet but then
communicate the appropriate choices to their offspring. Therefore, providing
a variety of seeds within the proven preferred seed size range seems prudent.
Of course such a mix should be accompanied by vegetative material, vitamins
and grit.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994074" page_id="56260904"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
82
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.842856" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260904" page_num="82" year="" vol="">
EITNIEAR - CROAKING GROUND DOVE
Conclusion
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9765235" page_id="56260904"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
Although Trollope (1974) mentioned that this ground dove could be a
"free breeding species in captivity" his rearing of two chicks from 12 eggs
was hardly a cause for optimism. The advanced age and variation in the
size of the dead chicks in nest three support the theory that his birds lacked
sufficient nutrition. However, considering the small sample size and lack
of details about his dietary regime this statement is, at best, speculative.
In the USA both the Croaking and Ecuadorian Ground Doves were
imported and bred during the late 1960s and early 1970s (Hanover, 1970).
During that time there was little interest in them and they apparently died
out in captivity and were not bred again for another 30 years. A number of
individuals possess them currently, so hopes are high that these interesting
ground doves will finally become established in captivity.
Postscript (August 2nd 2006)
When I was writing the above article, the pair was incubating its second
clutch of eggs this year. Following the fledging of those two young the pair
nested again and fledged a further two young on July 17th. On July 19th the
pair built yet another nest and on August 1 st-August 2nd laid another two
eggs. These are currently being incubated. So far this year, eight eggs have
been laid and six young fledged. However, one chick from the first nest
perished. Upon examination it was found to have a severely malformed
leg. The result of the detailed autopsy is pending.
. Acknowledgements
I wish to thank Lloyd Kiff (Library, World Center for Birds of Prey) for
providing copies of the Handbook of the Birds of the World species account
and Rene Corvocado for egg slip information held at the Western Foundation
for Vertebrate Zoology. I would also like to express my appreciation to John
Pire for information on the history of the species in captivity and to Danny
Gonzalez (Penguin Inter.) for importing these fascinating birds.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.911496" genericHeader="references" page_id="56260904" page_num="82" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.9975039">
Baptista, L. F., Trail, R W. and Horblit, H. M. 1997. In: Handbook of the Birds of the World.
Vol. 4. del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A., Sargatal, J. (eds.). Lynx Edicions, Barcelona, Spain.
Bosque, C., Pacheco, M. A. and Garcia- Amado, M. A. 2004. The annual cycle of the Columbina
ground-doves in seasonal savannas of Venezuela. Journal of Field Ornithology 75:1-112.
Cadieu, J. C., Cadieu, N. and Lauga, J. 1995. Local enhancement and seed choice in the juvenile
canary, Serinus canarius. Animal Behaviour 50:793-800.
Dickinson, E. C. (ed.). 2003. The Howard and Moore Complete Checklist to the Birds of the
World. Third edition. Princeton University Press, Princeton, New Jersey, USA.
Goodwin, D. 1983. Pigeons and Doves of the World. Third edition. Cornell University Press,
Ithaca, New York, USA.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.619307" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260905" page_num="83" year="" vol="">
EITNIEAR - CROAKING GROUND DOVE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998666" page_id="56260905"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
83
</page>
<reference confidence="0.8878809375">
Hanover, D. G. 1969. First importation into the U.S.A. and first breeding of Buckley's Ground
Dove. Avicultural Magazine 75,5:179-180.
Henry, P-Y. 2005. New distributional records of birds from Andean and western Ecuador.
Cotinga 23 (in press).
Johnson, A. W. 1967. Birds of Chile and Adjacent Regions of Argentina, Bolivia, and Peru.
Vol. II &amp; supplement. Platt Establecimientos Graficos S. A., Buenas Aires, Argentina.
Kendeigh, C. S. and West, G. 1965. Caloric values of plant seeds eaten by birds. Ecology
46,4:553-555.
Perez, E. M. and Bulla, L. 2000. Dietary relationships among four granivorous doves in
Venezuelan savannas. Journal of Tropical Ecology 16:865-882.
Ridgely, R S. and Greenfield, P. J. 2001. The Birds of Ecuador. Cornell University Press,
Ithaca, New York, USA.
Trollope, J. 1974. The breeding and behaviour of the Gold-billed Ground Dove ( Columbina
cruziana). Avicultural Magazine 80,5:181-188.
Jack Clinton Eitniear, Center for the Study of Tropical Birds, Inc,
218 Conway Drive, San Antonio, Texas 78209-1716, USA. E-mail:
</reference>
<equation confidence="0.311651" page_id="56260905"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
jce@cstbinc. org
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.94695225" page_id="56260905"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
D. H. S. RISDON AWARD
Preliminary findings on reproduction of captive Marabou Storks
Leptoptilos crumeniferus by C. W. Kuhar, L. M. Heinandez and K. Amos-
Mongiello {Avicultural Magazine Vol. 111, No.2, pp.56-63), based largely
on research carried out at Disney's Animal Kingdom, Florida, USA, was, in
the view of the council, the best (most informative) article published in the
magazine last year, and the worthy winner of the D. H. S. Risdon Award for
2005.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.601956" page_id="56260905"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.924785" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56260905" page_num="83" year="" vol="">
DULCIE COOKE AWARD
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.969202285714286" page_id="56260905"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
The council considered the best photo or photos used to illustrate an
article in the magazine during 2005, to have been the photos of the Red-
and-Yellow Barbet Trachyphonus e. erythrocephalus taken by Colin Scott,
showing a chick aged 15 days, a female chick at 22 days, a 28 day old male
and female and, a juvenile female with the parents, used to illustrate Colin's
account of breeding this colourful East African barbet {Avicultural Magazine
Vol.l 11, No. 1, pp.21-25).
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996805" page_id="56260906"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
84
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.972184875" page_id="56260906"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
A FLYING VISIT TO COSTA RICA
by D. Grenville Roles
In mid-January I was privileged to attend a conference entitled the
Western Hemisphere Migratory Species Initiative (WHMSI) in San Jose,
Costa Rica. The focus of the conference was the development and structuring
of an organisation which addresses the evermore urgent need for safe and
permanent corridors of habitat for migratory species in the Western
Hemisphere; from the Bering Sea to the tip of Tierra del Fuego and beyond.
The needs addressed included those of ariel, terrestrial and aquatic/pelagic
species. So obviously the scope and complexity are huge. My role was that
of an observer of the initiative and to let attendees know that the Disney
Wildlife Conservation Fund can be a source of funding for conservation
projects. These notes do not address the laudable ambition and altruism of
the fledgling organisation and its international partners, but are an account
of my shameless self indulgence in using the trip to view some of the world's
most beautiful bird species in their natural habitat.
Costa Rica is a beautiful, small Central American country, westernised
enough to seem entirely familiar and comfortable, but exotic enough to be
novel and exciting. English is widely spoken and even out in the countryside
I could successfully communicate with my muchopoquito (incredibly small
to miniscule) knowledge of Spanish, with the universally friendly and
attractive people.
With an easy connection from Orlando to Miami and onto San Jose, I
arrived at my hotel early in the evening to find that due to overbooking, I
had been assigned the Presidential Suite for the first two nights (it was such
a tough start to my visit!). The hotel, part of an international chain, boasted
every luxury and, had it not been for the birds in the grounds, I could have
been almost anywhere in the world.
As it was, at breakfast, Rufous-collared Sparrows Zonotrichia capensis
were on crumb-pick-up duty around the dining area, while a Rufous-tailed
Hummingbird Amazilia tzacatl sampled the chilly early morning nectar from
the flowers in front of the dining table. A Great Kiskadee Pitangus
sulphuratus awoke in the courtyard and started shrilly yelling its name while
high overhead Black Coragyps atratus, Turkey Cathartes aura and Lesser
Yellow-headed Vultures C. burrovianus were already into the morning patrol
looking for road kill. White-winged Doves Zenaida asiatica , still sounding
drowsy, were calling from a partially completed nest in a nearby small palm
tree.
I had planned to keep my first day free to acclimate myself somewhat
and get used to driving in Costa Rica. However, I discovered there was a
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.774078" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260907" page_num="85" year="" vol="">
ROLES - COSTA RICA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995723" page_id="56260907"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
85
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998125023255814" page_id="56260907"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
zoo in town and decided to try to visit it. It was much easier said than done.
With a paucity of street signs, alternating roads of one-way traffic, huge
congestion and defective drivers, I feared my life was at risk, so found a
hotel close to the zoo, parked, and walked the rest of the way.
With an interesting topography, the zoo was clearly not flush with funds,
but was definitely trying hard with very limited resources. The animals all
looked healthy and well cared for. The broken concrete floors were all
spotlessly clean as were the battered tin dishes from which the animals ate.
The most remarkable feature of the zoo, to my mind, was the seemingly
disproportionate attention focused on the education programme. Clearly of
huge concern to the staff is the need to convey information and appreciation
for wildlife and wild places, which is entirely appropriate and encouraging.
It seemed disproportionate only in the amount of attention lavished on it. I
do not wish to diminish the effort, but it would have been nice to have seen
a few exhibits that were equally well developed.
My best moment occurred when, as I was admiring the Green-winged
Macaws Ara chloroptera , a Blue-crowned Motmot Momotus momota flew
down onto their perch, wagged its tail a few times, posed for me like a
catwalk model, and then flew off. I was flabbergasted-it was so casual. Of
course it did not know it was spectacular, beautiful and gorgeous and was
the first wild motmot I had ever seen and, it had left me, breathless. The zoo
is, by the way, close to the city centre, so that particular motmot, at least,
was an urban dweller.
So common that I almost forgot them, were the superabundant Clay-
coloured Robins Turdns grayi , whose name just about says it all. These
drab greyish-brown birds, which look like a washed-out version of a female
European Blackbird T. merula, raided the animals' food bowls for fruit.
Another superabundant species was the Blue-grey Tanager Thraupis
episcopus. It seemed as so every street tree had at least two of these birds
searching the branches and chasing each other through the foliage. My
second ornithological treasure du jour was a White-eared Ground Sparrow
Melozone leucotis, a pretty, greenish little bird, with a blackish face and
chest and striking white 'ears'.
Two days later I made day-long field trips to two locations. The first
entailed a long drive through an elevated national park to the Research Station
at La Selva. Up on the side of a volcano, through the constant rain and mist
of the early morning, we spied precipitous drop-offs at virtually every turn.
The landscape seemed utterly devoid of bird-life, but nonetheless I could
appreciate the monstrous ferns and immense leaves of Gunnea insignis
growing at the ends of astonishing snake-like trunks, and the virtual cascade
of palms and grasses which covered the steep slopes. This disappointing
visit was compensated for by our next location, the Sueno Azul Hotel in
Sarapiqui.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.993726" page_id="56260908"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
86
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.944239" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260908" page_num="86" year="" vol="">
ROLES - COSTA RICA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998874380952381" page_id="56260908"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
The weather cleared as we left the mountainside and descended to a
lower altitude and I was thrilled to see first, five Northern Jaqanas Jagana
spinosa at a little pond at the side of the road ; then, tumbling and swooping
over a hillside nine or more Chestnut-headed Oropendulas Psaracolius
wagleri , their golden outer tail-feathers flashing as they twisted and turned
over the hill. Things were definitely looking up. Next I caught a glimpse of
a male Military Starling Sturnella militaris in a patch of stubble. It was
accompanied by a number of fossicking Inca Doves Columbina inca. The
cryptically plumaged doves were almost invisible on the bare ground, in
contrast to the Military Starling whose scarlet chest flashed like a beacon as
he stretched up on his toes. As this is a social species, he was probably
accompanied by others of his kind, but any males with their backs to me
would have been utterly invisible, as would any of the sparrowy-feathered
females.
We eventually lurched to a stop at an unimpressive driveway, from where
we set-off on a 1 / 2 -mile (approx. 1km) hike to our next destination. My
choicest moment en route was seeing a flawless pair of Ruddy Ground Doves
C talpacoti sitting on a piece of deadfall. It looked like a Robin Hill portrait.
The brightly coloured brown male contrasted nicely in the midday sun with
the duller female. I unfailingly get 'choked up' when I see a species, relatively
common in aviculture, free in its native habitat. I have been a professional
aviculturist all my working life and love the close-up and personal experience
of working with my charges, but nothing equals the thrill of viewing a
flawless wild bird 'behaving' in its natural habitat. I also have a special
admiration for Columbiformes, so that particular moment in time was
especially beautiful.
Balancing upon a fence post was a Smooth-billed Ani Crotophaga ani,
black and featureless as a silhouette, only its profile giving it away. In the
distance Great-tailed Crackles Quiscalus mexicanus paddled at the edge of
a small pond. At the buffet lunch, surrounded by a wonderful collection of
extraordinary Heliconia spp. and cultivars, Blue and White Swallows
Notiochelidon cyanoleuca together with Mangrove Swallows Tachycineta
albilinea could be seen swooping over a large retention pond upon which a
pair of Northern Jaqanas were busily chasing bugs. A White-ringed
Flycatcher Coryphotriccus albovitatus looking like a miniature kiskadee (it
has cinnamon upperparts, is buttercup yellow below and has a stripey head),
perched upon the telephone wires alongside neighbourly Grey Kingbirds
Tyrannus dominicensis.
After lunch we toured part of the property, many of us as we did so
brushing against a shrub at the side of the path in which a pair of Olive-
backed Euphonias Euphonia gouldi could be observed feeding chicks. Then,
as we approached a stand of large trees, a Masked Tityra Tityra semifasciata
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.77431" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260909" page_num="87" year="" vol="">
ROLES - COSTA RICA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998255" page_id="56260909"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
87
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998332071428572" page_id="56260909"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
flashed overhead as our guide identified the sound of toucans calling nearby.
Anyone who has kept toucans for any length of time would have recognised
the familiar, montononous (and endless) "kronking" sound and, sure enough,
there were three Chestnut-mandibled Toucans Ramphastos swainsonii
looking strangely unnatural to me, posed on the perimeter of a tall tree.
Vividly coloured, they looked like mechanical toys, with their jerky
movements and odd posturing and I had some difficulty absorbing that they
were truly wild birds.
We had not travelled more than 10ft (approx. 3m) into the forest when
we saw a flawless pair of Rufous Motmots Baryphthengus martii, just a
short distance away. What a privilege it was to see them. Calm and still,
apart from the 'ticking' of their tails, they watched quietly as we passed by.
The only other species we observed below the canopy was a pair of Slaty-
tailed Trogons Trogon massena. In the gloom of the forest, I could not get
a really good look at them, which was frustrating for a possibly once in a
lifetime experience, but I did see them, though mostly in silhouette. Beneath
them a wild agouti Dasyprocta sp. was feeding on fruits the birds had either
discarded or knocked down.
One other once in a lifetime experience was being shown an incredibly
rare species of palm tree. Rare because its developed buttress roots are
anatomically correct, phallus-like structures, which are harvested for their
supposed aphrodisiac properties!
A little disappointed in the number of species I had seen, I did have one
lovely experience in store as I headed back to the bus. It was getting gloomy
as I detected a repeated "squeaking" sound and, looking around, spied a
male Blue-black Grassquit Volatinia jacarini repeatedly leaping into the air
from the top of a fence post. His white pectoral tufts flashed in the gloom
and he "squeaked" as he hit the high point of his 1ft (30cm) leap into the air.
That cute little creature (hey, I can say cute!) was an absolute delight to see.
Saving the most thrilling experience until last, on my final afternoon I
headed for the La Paz Waterfall gardens. They were supposed to be only
45km (approx. 28 miles) away, but it took me a nerve-wracking lV 2 -hours
to get there. It is a beautiful modem park, way out in the sticks, which I
visited because the advertising blurb said - "27 species of hummingbirds".
Okay, I read it, and should have been prepared, but I was not. I do not know
if anything could have prepared me for what was the closest I have come to
a spiritual experience. I was blinded by the colour, activity, noise and the
sheer diversity of species. I quickly gave up trying to identify the different
species and just watched, both numbed and uplifted by the glory of the
spectacle. There were so many birds: Purple-crowned Fairies Heliothryx
harroti , Green Thomtails Popelairia conversii, Purple-throated Mountain
Gems Lampornis cinereicauda , Violet Sabrewings Campylopterus
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.945886" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260910" page_num="88" year="" vol="">
ROLES - COSTA RICA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.949418473684211" page_id="56260910"  page_num="88" year="" vol="">
hemileucurus and many, many more. I felt breathless, drained and a little
sick - kind of like I feel after I have pigged out on ice cream and chocolate
cake. I never knew you could have a surfeit of joy!
The most singular vision in my mind from that time is of two Violet
Sabrewings, which are quite large hummers - totally glittering violet/ruby/
amethyst with mostly pure white tails - twirling slowly around each other
about 2ft (60cm) in front of my face with their tails spread, each giving vent
to their "sizzling" call, before disappearing in a flash.
My second most wonderful experience lay a little further along the path,
where a buffet of fruit was staked out on an accumulation of deadfall. The
sight of so many tanagers was less overwhelming, but still oh, oh, so
awesome. They were mostly the exquisitely elegant Silver-throated Tangara
icterocephala, given a perfect foil by the presence of the superabundant
Blue-grey species. Then there was a sudden flush of Golden-hooded T.
larvata, with some punctuation by Scarlet-rumped Ramphoceluspasserinii
and a single Palm Tanager Thraupispalmamm. With so many Clay-coloured
Robins also in the mix, I almost missed a single Common Bush Tanager
Chlorospingus ophthalmicus and the (duller) local subspecies of the
Bananaquit Coereba flaveola.
I still had one more magical experience to come - duty bound I went to
look at a magnificent waterfall and completed the tour at an 'early settler's'
house, where you could sample homemade cheese and suchlike. Wandering
outside afterwards into the little valley I heard shrill screaming, screeching
approaching. Hurtling in my direction, about 50ft (approx. 5m) up, was a
flock of about 30 huge, White-collared Swifts Streptoprocne zonaris.
Screaming like banshees, they passed overhead like a whirlwind and I could
feel the rush of the disturbed air - it was quite incredible.
On my day of departure, I took a walk down the street to a couple of
small ponds and some nice Australian flowering Bottlebush Trees. There
was nothing exceptional there, but it was still satisfying to see 40 or more
Black-bellied Whistling Ducks Dendrocygna autumnalis , numerous Northern
Orioles Icterus galbula, a Chestnut-naped Wren Campylorhynchus rufinucha
and a 'swarm' of Tennessee Warblers Vermivora peregrina.
To help me identify the birds, I took with me A Guide to the Birds of
Costa Rica by Stiles, Skutch and Gardner, published by Cornell University
Press in the USA and by Helm in the UK.
D. Grenville Roles is Animal Operations Manager/Curator of Birds at
Disney's Animal Kingdom, PO Box 10,000, Lake Buena Vista, Florida 32830-
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.340458" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56260910" page_num="88" year="" vol="">
1000, USA .
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997297" page_id="56260911"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
89
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993955" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260911" page_num="89" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
SEVENTH EDITION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998675789473684" page_id="56260911"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
First published in 1940, Austin Roberts's Birds of South Africa has been
in print continuously ever since and is said to have sold well over 300,000
copies, in the process undergoing changes of title, first to Roberts Birds of
South Africa and then Roberts ' Birds of Southern Africa. The latest edition,
the seventh, now restyled Roberts - Birds of Southern Africa , is quite unlike
any of the previous editions. For a start, it is far bigger, it measures 9V2in x
12 3 /4in (24cm x 32.5cm), it is almost 2 3 /4in (7cm) thick and as a consequence
is far too weighty to take out into the field.
The text has been completely rewritten, with contributions from more
than 50 authors, drawn from the best of southern Africa's ornithologists,
coordinated by an editorial team of three experts - Phil Hockey, Richard
Dean and Peter Ryan - of the Percy Fitzpatrick Institute of African
Ornithology at the University of Cape Town. Similarly, it has 80 brand-new
colour plates painted by leading southern African bird artists Graeme Amott,
Chris van Rooyen, Ingrid Weiersbye, Penny Meakin, Ronald Cook, A.
Barlow and A. Clarkson. The best known of these being Graeme Amott,
whose paintings in Shrikes of Southern Africa (1988) and Robins of Africa
(1998), will be familiar to many members. All that seems to remain from
the previous editions is Norman Lighton's original frontispiece.
The Tmstees of the John Voelcker Bird Book Fund, say that the old
format, a combination of a field guide and a handbook, was inadequate to
accommodate the wealth of information that is now available, besides which
southern Africa is now well served by excellent field guides, therefore the
decision was taken to change the format, scope and intent of this work. It
certainly contains a mass of information on the 951 species recorded in the
region, namely South Africa, Lesotho, Swaziland, Namibia, Botswana,
Zimbabwe and Mozambique south of the Zambezi.
The modem taxonomy that is followed is also very different from that
which has gone before and will take some getting used to. It is surprising,
for example, to find the penguins towards the middle of the book and the
shearwaters coming immediately before the African Pitta and the broadbills.
The sequence adopted is said to be broadly based on Sibley and Ahlquisf s
'tapestry of avian evolution', with modifications where there is clear evidence
that this is flawed.
The changes to this classic work have not been to everyone's liking. A
letter to a South African newspaper complained that its price puts it beyond
the reach of the average birdwatcher and the libraries of all but a few private
schools. He helpfully pointed out that weighing as it does, 5.5kg (approx.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.992458" page_id="56260912"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
90
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.96062" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260912" page_num="90" year="" vol="">
BOOK REVIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991714846153846" page_id="56260912"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
12 V2lbs), an 11-year old schoolboy is likely to suffer a hernia carrying it
from the library to his classroom. He also complained that whereas the
previous artwork had been chosen to aid identification, the new paintings
seem to have been chosen for their artistic value. His advice was to buy a
copy of one of the earlier editions, something which I gather a lot of South
Africans have been doing. He might have asked, why when this present
volume is so different from Roberts's original format, has the name been
retained?
Despite the letter writer's forebodings and a price tag of R800, this latest
edition has proved an amazing success in South Africa. The first print run
of 10,000 copies quickly sold out and a second print run of a further 5,000
copies is awaited. Some more copies may be available shortly here in the
UK - price #110 (according to one advert).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.56188">
Roberts - Birds of Southern Africa Vllth Edition, 1,296 pages, 81 colour
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.807398333333333" page_id="56260912"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
plates, numerous distribution maps, etc., edited by P.A.R. Hockey, W.R.J.
Dean and P.G. Ryan, was published in 2005 by the Trustees of the John
Voelcker Book Fund, Cape Town.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.928009" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56260912" page_num="90" year="" vol="">
AVIAN MISCELLANY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.951907363636364" page_id="56260912"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
Described as "The perfect gift for birdwatchers and literary ornithologists
everywhere", The Bedside Book of Birds - An Avian Miscellany , is a collection
of writings about birds and the relationship between humans and birds by,
among others, Aristotle, Henry Walter Bates, William Beebe, The Venerable
Bede, Lewis Carroll, Bruce Chatwin, Charles Darwin, T.S. Eliot, Thomas
Hardy, W. H. Hudson, Peter Matthiessen, Edgar Allan Poe, Siegfried Sassoon,
Walter Scott, Henry David Thoreau, Laurens van der Post, Alfred Russel
Wallace, John Wesley and Gilbert White. The writings were collected over
a period of 15 years by Graeme Gibson, an acclaimed novelist and avid
birdwatcher living in Toronto, Canada, who has travelled around the world
in search of birds.
Over 100 illustrations, most of them in colour, decorate the pages of this
most attractively designed book. They range from early cave paintings to
Inuit folk art and other art from around the world, to paintings by Audubon,
Elizabeth Gould, Joseph Wolf and H. C. Richter (who illustrated works by
John Gould), J. G. Keulemans and others. There are sketches by J. Fenwick
Lansdowne, a line drawing of the extinct Stephens Island Wren by David
Reid-Henry, and a Red Bird of Paradise by T. W. Wood, illustrates Wallace's
account of his unsuccessful attempts to keep this species alive in captivity.
The Bedside Book of Birds - An Avian Miscellany , 370 pages, more than
100 illustrations, collected together by Graeme Gibson, is published in the
UK by Bloomsbury. Price #20.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.268286">
Malcolm Ellis
</subsectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995992" page_id="56260913"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
91
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.975329" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260913" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
ENCOURAGING NEWS ON THE GOULDIAN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.8488258" page_id="56260913"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
In northern Australia Gouldian Finches Erythrura gouldiae have
reappeared in flocks of hundreds in places they had not been seen for up to
15 years. The highest number of sightings in years have been reported in
Kakadu, Arnhem Land and Cape York. It may be a result of better fire
management.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.987027" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260913" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
CHOOSING A PARTNER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9908082" page_id="56260913"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
The young male Spix's Macaw Cyanopsitta spixii , which with its parents,
was imported into Germany from Switzerland last year (see News &amp; Views
Vol.l 12, No.l, p.44 (2006)), has been transferred from Berlin to the Loro
Parque Fundacion's breeding station on Tenerife in the Canary Islands. The
young male underwent veterinary examinations, virus tests and several
months' quarantine while in Germany, which meant that on arrival there it
could immediately be placed in a newly equipped 11m (approx. 36ft) long
aviary with Loro Parque's two females that were hatched there in 2004.
The male will be allowed to choose which of the two females he will
eventually be paired with.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.752541" page_id="56260913"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.770368" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260913" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
CONVINCED BY THE EVIDENCE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.665082333333333" page_id="56260913"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
Scientists at Cornell Laboratory of Ornithology have completed a second
in-depth analysis of David Luneau's woodpecker videotape shot on April
25th 2004, in eastern Arkansas, USA, and are sure that it shows an Ivory-
billed Woodpecker Campephilusprincipalis in flight. To judge for yourself
you can visit the Cornell website:www.birds.comell.edu/ivory/rediscovery/
support
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.53109" page_id="56260913"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.648508" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260913" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
EFFECTIVE AND HARMLESS ALTERNATIVE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9945532" page_id="56260913"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
The Indian Government has ordered a halt to the production and sale of
the veterinary drug diclofenac. The deaths of millions of vultures were
traced to diclofenac, a veterinary drug used widely in south Asian countries
to treat domestic cattle and buffalo for a variety of illnesses. During treatment
and for a short period afterwards the tissues of the treated animals contain
the drug and if treated animals subsequently die during this time the carcasses
can be toxic to vultures and have fatal consequences. The phasing out of
diclofenac came shortly after a team of scientists at the University of Pretoria,
South Africa, reported that the drug meloxicam is an effective and harmless
alternative to diclofenac.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995129" page_id="56260914"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
92
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.979913" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260914" page_num="92" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
ESTABLISHING MADAGASCAN BIRDS IN CAPTIVITY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.971045625" page_id="56260914"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
It seems that prior to 2004 the Madagascar Blue Pigeon Alectroenas
madagascariensis had never been kept in captivity. That year VogelPark
Walsrode, Germany, imported seven. Six had been caught in mist nets and
the other had been taken from the nest and hand-reared. In March 2005, the
hand-reared bird, a female, paired with one of the males and they incubated
a single egg in half of a coconut. Incubation took 17 days and the chick
fledged after another 17 days. The squab resembled those of Ptilinopus
fruit doves. At Walsrode the Madagascar Blue Pigeons receive the mixed
fruit and pellet diet for frugivores fed to all its fruit doves and cotingas.
Together with the pigeons, Walsrode received nine (7.2) Blue Coua Coua
caerulea. So far, one pair has produced three eggs, which is the usual size
clutch, from which three chicks hatched but, unfortunately, only one of them
was reared. Luckily it is a female.
In 2004 Walsrode also imported 10 Madagascar Pond Herons Ardeola
idae, a species that is becoming increasingly rare due to habitat changes and
replacement by the rapidly increasing Squacco Heron A. ralloides. The two
species may hybridize and, indeed, one of the 10 looks as so it may be a
hybrid. In 2005 Walsrode received a further 10 Madagascar Pond Herons
and hopes to establish a captive breeding population. It also imported 20
young Madagascar Sacred Ibis Threskiornis bernieri, a blue-eyed species
that is listed as Endangered because of destruction of its mangrove habitat,
the hunting of the adults and the collecting of juveniles and eggs for food.
Between 1998-2001 Walsrode imported 11 Madagascar Crested Ibis
Lophotibis cristata. Since the first captive breeding there in 2001, the
population has increased to 39 birds, 27 of which were bred in captivity.
Birds hand-reared at Walsrode have also bred successfully at Zurich Zoo
and San Diego. This species has also bred at Parc Botanique et Zoologique
Tsimbazaza (PBZT) on Madagascar.
Walsrode's efforts to establish Madagascan species in captivity are part
of a cooperative endeavour between the German bird park, PSZT and the
Madagascan Ministry of Higher Education. Called Project Tsimbazaza, it
is now in its seventh year.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.38652" page_id="56260914"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.982147" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260914" page_num="92" year="" vol="">
BRED IN THE USA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.954074" page_id="56260914"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
Dallas Zoo, Texas, the first zoo in the world to breed the Saddle-billed
Stork Ephippiorhynchus senegalensis - it has produced hand-reared and
parent-reared young that have been raised successfully to adulthood - has
opened a new exhibit in which visitors can see these birds flying.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700202" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260915" page_num="93" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.989515" page_id="56260915"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
93
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993076" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260915" page_num="93" year="" vol="">
IMPRESSIVE LIST OF BREEDINGS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.728718576923077" page_id="56260915"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
The 2005 Zoological Society of San Diego Physical Inventory included
an (as always) impressive list of birds bred in the two collections. Two
Superb Birds of Paradise Lophorina superba (subspecies unknown) and
three Raggiana Paradisaea raggiana (subspecies unknown) were raised at
San Diego Zoo and two Magnificent Diphyllodes magnificus hunsteini at
the Wild Animal Park. Micronesian Kingfisher Todiramphus c. cinnamomina
bred in both collections and White-fronted Bee-eater Merops bullockoides,
European Coracias garrulus and Blue-bellied Roller C. cyanogaster bred
at the Wild Animal Park, as did both ground hombills Bucorvus abyssinicus
and B. leadbeateri , Great Hombill Buceros bicornis , Red-knobbed Aceros
cassidix and Yellow-casqued Ceratogymna elata; Southern Sulawesi Tarictic
Hombill Penelopides exarhatus sanfordi bred in both collections. Two
Golden-headed Manakins Pipra e. erythrocephala were hatched at the Wild
Animal Park, one of which survived. Other species bred at San Diego Zoo
included five Collared Finchbills Spizixos semitorques , a Yellow-throated
Laughingthrush Garrulax galbanus simaoensis , four Fukien Niltavas Niltava
davidi, two Orange-billed Sparrows Arremon aurantiirostris and a Black-
striped Sparrow Arremonops conirostris richmondi.
Fifteen Social Weavers Philetairus socius , 19 Reichenow's Weavers
Ploceus baglafecht reichenowi, 26 New Guinea Metallic Starlings Aplonis
metallica , 10 Grosbeak Starlings Scissirostrum dubium and 10 White-
breasted Wood Swallows Artamus leucorhynchus amydrus were also among
the birds bred at San Diego Zoo. Other species bred in the collections
included Turquoise Tanager Tangara mexicana , Spotted Tanager T. punctata ,
Blue-necked T. cyanicollis caeruleucephala, Swallow Tanager Tersina viridis
occidental(TM), Double-eyed Fig Parrot Cyclopsitta d. diophthalma, Edwards's
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.95800425" page_id="56260915"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
Fig Parrot Psittaculirostris edwardii, Blue-eared Lory Eos semilarvata,
Papuan Mountain Pigeon Gymnophaps a. albertisii , imperial pigeons Ducula
spp., fruit doves Ptilinopus spp. and crowned pigeons Goura spp.
* * *
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.713749" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260915" page_num="93" year="" vol="">
AUSTRALIAN PIED IMPERIALS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.687966" page_id="56260915"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
Several resident urban breeding populations of the Pied Imperial
Pigeon Ducula bicolor have been discovered recently in Australia, including
one at Darwin and another at Caims. It is believed that over 100 pairs nest
at Caims, mainly in palms, some of which grow adjacent to busy streets.
Robert M. Alison, writing in the Birds Australia quarterly publication
Wingspan Vol.16, No.2, pp.30-33, June 2006, described the return of this
familiar avicultural subject, which used to occur in immense flocks in
Australia, until a widepread population collapse in the nineteenth century,
due to hunting and habitat destmction.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998276" page_id="56260916"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
94
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.981613" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260916" page_num="94" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
TWELVE SPIX'S MACAWS BRED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.992832416666667" page_id="56260916"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
In a Press Release dated June 6th 2006, A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation
announced that it has to date this year, bred seven Spix's Macaws Cyanopsitta
spixii. These represent almost 10% of the known world population. Together
with offspring reared in 2004 and 2005, it has now successfully reared 12
Spix's Macaws. All of the chicks have been hand-reared by specialist staff
at A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation, owned by Sheikh Saoud Bin Mohammad
Bin Ali Al-Thani in Qatar. It is hoped that further clutches will follow shortly
and that eventually pairs will be allowed to rear some of their own young.
The aim is to one day re-establish this species back in the wild in Brazil. If
you would like to learn more about A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation and its
efforts to save Spix's Macaw and other rare and endangered species, you
are invited to visit its website:awwp.alwabra.com
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.878465105263158" page_id="56260916"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
* * *
ANDEAN COCK-OF-THE-ROCK REARED
In 2005 Wuppertal Zoo in Germany, succeeded in rearing a male Andean
Cock-of-the-Rock Rupicolaperuviana. The zoo also bred two Hooded Pittas
Pitta sordida, two Bam Swallows Hirundo rustica, two Southern House
Wrens Troglodytes musculus, two Pale-legged Homeros Furnarius leucopus,
four Painted Finches Emblema picta, 10 Bali Starlings Leucopsar rothschildi
and four Ravens Corvus corax. Other noteworthy breedings included two
King Penguins Aptenodytes patagonicus, 22 Elegant Crested Tinamous
Eudromia elegans, two Magpie Geese Anseranas semipalmata, four
Madagascar Teal Anas bernieri , a Barrow's Goldeneye Bucephala islandica ,
16 Common Goldeneye B. clangula , 19 Hooded Merganser Lophodytes
cucullatus , a Smew Mergellus albellus , three Goosander Mergus merganser ,
13 European Eider Somateria m. mollissima , two Pacific Eider A m. v-nigra,
10 Spectacled Eider S. fischeri , three Black-headed Ruddy Ducks Oxyura
jamaicensis, a Black Vulture Aegypius monachus , two Bateleurs Terathopius
ecaudatus , a Red-legged Seriema Cariama cristata , an East African Crowned
Crane Balearica regulorum gibbericeps , a White-naped Crane Grus vipio,
22 Avocets Recurvirostra avosetta, seven Northern Lapwings Vanellus
</table>
<reference confidence="0.388066555555556">
vanellus, nine Stock Doves Columba oenas , a Kookaburra Dacelo
novaeguineae, four White-cheeked Turacos Tauraco leucotis and a Guira
Cuckoo Guira guira. A number of new birds were added to the collection,
the most important of which included a male Harpy Eagle Harpia harpyja ,
a female Red-crowned Crane Grus japonensis, a pair of Kagu Rhynochetos
jubatus (a gift from the Zoo Supporters' Association in celebration of the
association's 50th anniversary (2005)), two male Horned Parakeets
Eunymphicus cornutus and a male King Bird of Paradise Cicinnurus regius
(bred at VogelPark, Walsrode).
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.693624" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260917" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.970162" page_id="56260917"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
95
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.966193" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260917" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
GUEST SPEAKER
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.78149425" page_id="56260917"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
The Bird Keeping in Australia Newsletter , July 2006 Edition, Vol.5, Issue
7, official publication of The Avicultural Society of South Australia Inc.,
advertised that the guest speaker at its next meeting would be Tim Nielsen,
Adelaide Zoo's Head Birdkeeper, who would be talking about the Orange-
bellied Parrot Neophema chrysogaster and how the zoo is progressing with
the breeding of this species. Apparently it has been breeding the Orange-
bellied Parrot for some time now and has overcome many of the problems
associated with breeding it.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.789282" page_id="56260917"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.934009" genericHeader="method" page_id="56260917" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE GOLDEN ORIOLE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.958583133333333" page_id="56260917"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
A few years back, John Lovett sought information on whether the Golden
Oriole Oriolus oriolus had been bred in captivity and whether any breeding
accounts had been published. No record seemed to exist (and still does not)
of it ever having been bred in captivity in the UK and no articles about the
breeding of it seemed to have been published in the magazine. Following
Dr Herbert Schifter's correspondence on the breeding of the Black-naped
Oriole O. chinensis in captivity (see Avicultural Magazine Vol.l 11, No.3,
p.144 (2005)), I asked him if he knew of any records of the Golden Oriole
having been bred in captivity in Europe?
Dr Schifter has written to say that Helmut Kramer in his very detailed
compilation Bruten europdischer Vogelarten in Gefangenschaft (Breeding
of European bird species in captivity), published in Zoologischer Garten N.
F. Vol.50, pp.89-137 (1980), listed (p.90) the Golden Oriole among the
species of European birds that had not been bred in captivity. In Das gross e
Lexikon der Vogelpflege, published in 2003 by Verlag Ulmer, Stuttgart,
Germany, Dr Franz Robiller recorded that shortly afterwards in 1982, it had
been bred for the first time by Rudiger Neff of Fichtenberg, Germany, and
had been bred again later by him. Unfortunately Neff had obviously not
published an account of his success, as the German avicultural journal
Gefiederte Welt Vol.l 14, pp.363-364 (1990), published a paper by Heinz
Graff, Mannheim, Germany, entitled Welterstzucht des Pirols Oriolus oriolus
(L.) hei Hermann Greulich, Rauenberg gegliickt? (First successful breeding
of the Golden Oriole by Hermann Greulich, Reuenberg?), who had reared
three young. In 1991 two more Golden Orioles were bred by the same man.
This was recorded by Graff in Pirolzucht erneut gegliickt (Golden Oriole
bred again), published in Gefiederte Welt Vol.l 15, p.365 (1991). It was not,
of course, the first success, as it had been bred earlier by Rudiger Neff. It
was not until 2003, that Neff published a paper entitled DerPirol - ein Exot
in unserer Vogelwelt (The Golden Oriole -an exotic bird in our avifauna) in
Gefiederte Welt Vol.l27, pp.326-329 &amp; 366-368 (2003). Unfortunately it
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995633" page_id="56260918"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
96
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.927888" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260918" page_num="96" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99807535" page_id="56260918"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
lacked detailed information about his first breeding and subsequent successes,
but he did mention a male hatched on June 16th 1982, that was hand-reared
by him from the eighth day, after the breeding female died. This male was
kept by Neff for almost 19 years, until it died suddenly on May 21st 2001.
The male and the female with whom he had been paired since 1986, had the
year before (2000) produced a clutch of fertile eggs. In an earlier paper
entitled Zum Alter von Kdflgvogeln by Zarth in Geflederte WeltV ol.92, p. 140
(1968), the best longevity record was that of a hand-reared male Golden
Oriole that was stated to have lived for 20 years. Neff suggested that Golden
Orioles may reach 25 years of age in captivity but provided no records.
In his account mentioned above, Neff described how his Golden Orioles
were kept and bred in aviaries 10m x 5m x 3.5m high (approx. 32ft 6in x
16ft 3in x 11 ft 6in high). Unfortunately the birds were unable to build suitable
nests with the materials he offered them, but finally bred successfully using
artificial nests, one of which was shown on p. 327 of his paper. Neff made
notes on 18 breeding efforts when young were hatched. Usually three or
four eggs were laid and the female was observed sitting on the nest for 14-
15 days after the second egg had been laid. The nestlings were fed on moths,
mealworms, ant pupae, locusts and other livefood. Neff also hand-reared
some of the young, when the parents failed to do so.
There are relatively few records of orioles having been bred captivity.
One of the African species, the Black-headed Oriole O. larvata, was bred in
1964 in the Edward Marshall Boehm Aviaries, Trenton, New Jersey, USA
(.AviculturalMagazine Vol.71, No.2, pp.50-51 (1965); see also Vol.71, No. 1,
pp. 10-13 (1965)). The species most often bred has probably been the Black-
naped. According to the breeding records that used to be listed in the
International Zoo Yearbook , it was bred at Jurong Bird Garden, Singapore,
in 1977 and again later. This species was also bred at Harewood Bird Garden,
near Leeds, here in the UK, in 1985 (see News &amp; Views Vol.lll, No.3,
p.144 (2005)). The Crimson-breasted Oriole O. cruentus was listed in The
Foreign Bird Federation Register of Birds Bred in the UK under Controlled
Conditions for the Years 1999-2002, as having been bred in 2000, but no
further details or the name of the breeder have been forthcoming. The Olive-
backed Oriole O. sagittatus bred in 1986 at Taronga Zoo, Sydney, Australia,
but the youngster was not reared. In 1990, four young were hatched there,
one of which was reared. The Southern Figbird Sphecotheres viridis vieilloti
nested there in 1973, when two young were hatched, but were not reared. In
1989 this species bred at the Currumbin Bird Sanctuary in Queensland and
the same year, the Timor Figbird S. v. viridis , bred for the first time at Adelaide
Zoo, which later succeeded in breeding a second generation of this species.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.868537" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260919" page_num="" year="" vol="">
GEORGE A. SMITH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9897931875" page_id="56260919"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
It is with great sadness that I report to death on June 22nd 2006 of George
Smith of Peterborough. George joined the Avicultural Society in 1960 and
for many years was an active member.
As a veterinarian and as a writer he greatly advanced our knowledge of
parrots, especially during the 1970s and 1980s. He was unique among
avicultural writers in making important contributions to peer reviewed
ornithological literature, his special interests being parrot taxonomy,
systematics and morphology. Many members will recall his excellent articles
in the Avicultural Magazine, especially those on what were at the time little-
known species that he was breeding. These included the Long-tailed
Parakeet, Red-capped Parrot, vasa parrots and caiques. His Encyclopedia
of Cockatiels and Lovebirds and Related Parrots , both published in 1978,
were important contributions to parrot literature. He carried out extensive
research into parrot incubation and donated countless skin and skeleton
specimens to The Natural History Museum collection at Tring. Unlike most
aviculturists, he realised the value to science of dead birds.
He had an exceptionally deep and wide knowledge, although birds and
botany were his primary interests. The value of his articles and books lay in
the fact that he was an original thinker with an enquiring mind and had an
extraordinary ability to propose ideas no one had previously entertained.
This original thinking was especially evident in his letters which encapsulated
his humour and his knowledge. Often outspoken and sometimes deliberately
provocative, with a wicked sense of humour, he could be misunderstood by
those who did not know him well. In fact he was one of the most generous
people I have ever encountered in aviculture, carrying out hundreds of post
mortems free of charge, lending or giving parrots to countless breeders and
helping many parrot people in other ways. His wit was legendary (though
sometimes acerbic!). He was a rare personality in the world of aviculture.
George had travelled widely overseas speaking at conventions and
observing parrots in their natural habitat. He will be greatly missed by his
friends and family, especially his widow Olive and his daughter Kathryn.
Donations in memory of George Smith may be made to Cambridge
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.689681125">
University Botanical Gardens, Cory Lodge, Bateman Road, Cambridge CB2
1JF, UK. Cheques should be made payable to University of Cambridge and
you should state "In Memory of George Smith".
Rosemary Low
DIANA HOLLOWAY
The council was saddened to learn of the death of Avicultural Society
Vice President Diana Holloway. It is hoped to include an obituary in the
next issue of the magazine.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.766807" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56260920" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.9320863125" page_id="56260920"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
3 9088 01174 4513
Breeding the White-browed Coucal Centropus superciliosus
at Exmoor Zoological Park
by Derek Gibson.49
Some notes on our experiences of keeping and breeding the
Yellow-throated Laughingthrush Garrulax galbanus courtoisi
by Martina Reul-Schneider and Holger Schneider.53
Yellow-throated Laughingthrush.57
On The Edge
by Jo Gregson. 60
Breeding the White-bellied Go-away Bird
Corythaixoides leucogaster at Waddesdon Manor
by Andrew Owen.62
Breeding the Greater Flamingo - the first success in 15 years
by Walter Mangold.71
Breeding and diet of the Croaking Ground Dove
</table>
<figure confidence="0.856909090909091" page_id="56260920"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Columbina cruziana
by Jack Clinton Eitniear.75
A flying visit to Costa Rica
by D. Grenville Roles.84
Book Reviews
Roberts - Birds of Southern Africa.89
The Bedside Book of Birds - An Avian Miscellany.90
News &amp; Views
91
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</figure>
</algorithms>
