<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.867494" page_id="56255188"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
#7f
, f\ L wr
6MV\
VICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990762" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255189" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.96126375" page_id="56255189"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2012: British Isles #21.00:
Overseas #24.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the
Society later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of
the AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE.
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.701188333333333" page_id="56255189"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE HON. SECRETARY AND TREASURER, THE AVICULTURAL
SOCIETY, SHERATON LODGE, STATION ROAD, SOUTHMINSTER,
ESSEX CM0 7EW, UK.
</construct>
<bodyText confidence="0.91745" page_id="56255189"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Barclays Bank, Southminster Branch. Please quote
Account No. 13296954, Sort Code 20 54 30, and ensure you send your
name as the account reference, or else we cannot match payments. In case
of difficulty please contact the Hon. Secretary and Treasurer at the address
above, or e-mail: otusscops@talktalk.net
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have not
been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of a
particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history. Articles
should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the scientific
names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given. References
cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line drawings,
black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular point in
the article will be used where possible and should be clearly captioned. If
authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when submitting the
article and write their name on the back of each photograph. Tables and
graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be aware of
the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of the page
which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997594" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56255189" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982475333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.769262" genericHeader="method" page_id="56255190" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.584148" page_id="56255190"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol 118-No. 2 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2012
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.489397">
The Avicultural Society
</subsectionHeader>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.989741333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56255190" page_num="" year="" vol="">
FOR THE STUDY OF BRITISH AND FOREIGN BIRDS
IN THE WILD AND CAPTIVITY
OFFICERS AND COUNCIL
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.244672" page_id="56255190"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
As from May 19th 2012
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.488242681818182" page_id="56255190"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
President
C. J. S. Marler
Vice Presidents
F. Bamicoat (South Africa)
S. Bmslund (Spain)
M. Curzon MBE (UK)
Dr H. Quinque (France)
R. L. Restall (Venezuela)
Dr R. Wilkinson (UK)
Dr W. Grammt (Germany)
Honorary Editor
M. Ellis
Honorary Secretary - Treasurer
P. Stocks
Members of Council
P. Convy
Mrs L. Gardner
R. B. Girling
N. R. Hewston
G. Masson
S. Matthews
A. Owen
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.8129">
R. G. Piper
P. G. Schofield
J. G. Thurlow
J. Trollope
Ms R. Wiseman
Chairman N. R. Hewston
</reference>
<page confidence="0.896788" page_id="56255191"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
50
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.3264185" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255191" page_num="50" year="" vol="">
PAULTONS PARK - 2011
by Geoff Masson
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999692189189189" page_id="56255191"  page_num="50" year="" vol="">
As far as the bird collection was concerned, last year turned out to be
an average year here at Paultons Park in Hampshire. It was full of highs
and lows, with the weather as usual playing a part, which resulted in birds
coming into condition in February and going out of condition again in March,
when the weather changed.
We started off the year having our pair of Green-winged Macaws Ara
chloroptera stolen. Luckily the police managed to retrieve the pair following
a tip-off but, unfortunately, the male has had some serious health problems
ever since.
Our group of Pink-backed Pelicans Pelecanus rufescens went into its
winter breeding quarters again in October 2010, but for some reason none of
the six eggs which were laid were fertile. This was even after we borrowed
two extra males from Longleat Safari Park. The previous year the group
produced two young.
Anew pair of Von der Decken's Hombills Tockus deckeni was collected
from Colchester Zoo in February. The pair was placed in quarantine and a
nest box with a camera inside was put in with the pair just on the off-chance
something might happen. This proved to be the case and, by April 11th, the
female was completely walled-in and being fed by the male. On April 16th
the camera revealed that one egg had been laid and on April 25th a second
egg was seen in the nest. Regrettably, a few weeks later on May 15th, the
female broke out of the nest and no sign of the eggs could be found. The
pair was transferred to an outside aviary on June 1 st.
Our pair of Violet Turacos Musophaga violacea in the large mixed Garden
Aviary again did us proud by producing six parent-reared young. In addition,
very late in the year when the weather was beginning to turn, in an attempt to
stop the pair from nesting again, the pair's two eggs were removed and placed
in an incubator and one chick was hatched and hand-reared. Unfortunately,
removing the eggs failed to discourage the female from laying again and
she went on to produce a further two healthy youngsters, making an overall
total of seven young for the year.
The pair of White-throated Magpie-Jays Calocitta f formosa produced
two chicks which hatched on May 15th and luckily turned out to be one of
each sex. Our young male was paired with a young female from Phil Lewis
on the Isle of Wight and sent to Raymond Sawyer at Cobham.
For the first time the Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus ruber produced fertile eggs
and two chicks were hatched by the same pair. They grew well for the first
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.872019" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255192" page_num="51" year="" vol="">
MASSON - PAULTONS PARK 2011
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996873" page_id="56255192"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
51
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.954937733333333" page_id="56255192"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
10 days, but then the pair nesting next to them decided to take over their
nest one night and built a new nest on top of the chicks, which were found
buried beneath the new nest the next morning. This year the first clutch of
eggs will be removed and artificially incubated. The number of Scarlet Ibis
appear to be dwindling here in the UK.
On March 23rd, we found that the Turkey Vultures Cathartes aura had
two eggs in their nest chamber, which the pair was taking turns to incubate.
Only one chick was produced, but even for this one bird, we spent a great
deal of time collecting sufficient road kill to ensure that a healthy youngster
finally emerged. Once it was folly independent it was sent to join the
demonstration team at the Hawk Conservancy at Andover.
A number of birds either attempted to breed, laid eggs which did not
hatch, or their chicks failed to survive. These included: Greater Necklaced
Laughingthrash Garrulax p. pec torahs, White-throated Laughingthrush G.
albogularis, Humboldt Penguin Spheniscus humboldti , Blue and yellow
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.948121916666667" page_id="56255192"  page_num="51" year="" vol="">
Macaw Ara ararauna , Red-crested Turaco Tauraco erythrolophus and
Black-casqued Wattled Hombill Ceratogymna atrata.
Birds bred during 2011
1 Luzon Bleeding-heart Gallicolumba luzonica
2 Laughing Kookaburras Dacelo novaeguineae
1 Violet Turacos Musophaga violacea
5 White-cheeked Turacos Tauraco leucotis
3 Hahn's Macaws Diopsittaca n. nobilis
2 White-throated Magpie-Jays Calocitta f formosa
1 Turkey Vulture Cathartes aura
1 Southern Screamer Chauna torquata
2 Sacred Ibis Threskiornis aethiopicus
3 Ringed Teal Callonetta leucophrys
4 Pagoda Starlings Sturnus pagodarum
4 Mountain Bamboo Partridges Bambusicola fytchii
4 Chinese Bamboo Partridges Bambusicola thoracicus
3 Speckled Mousebirds Colius striatus
New arrivals during 2011
1 Blue-crowned Laughingthrash Dryonastes courtoisi
2 Sun Conures Araiinga solstitialis
1 Blue-and yellow Macaw Ara ararauna
5 Humboldt Penguins Spheniscus humboldti
2 Ternminck&amp;apos;s Tragopans Tragopan temminckii
6 Helmeted Guineafowl Numida meleagris
</figure>
<page confidence="0.939678" page_id="56255193"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
52
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.538018" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255193" page_num="52" year="" vol="">
MASSON - PAULTONS PARK 2011
</sectionHeader>
<figure confidence="0.950068882352941" page_id="56255193"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
1 Brown-breasted Barbet Lybius melanopterus
1 Luzon Bleeding-heart Gallicolumba luzonica
2 Timor Zebra Finches Tceniopygia g. guttata
2 Red-winged Starlings Onychognathus morio
1 Greater Rhea Rhea americana
Departures during 2011
3 Pagoda Starlings Sturnus pagodarum
7 Violet Turacos Musophaga violacea
1 Southern Screamer Chauna torquata
1 White-bellied Go-away Bird Corythaixoides leucogaster
1 Southern Pied Hombill Anthracoceros albirostris convexus
1 Javan Hill Mynah Gracula r. religiosa
1 Black-casqued Wattled Hombill Ceratogymna atrata
1 Blue-and-yellow Macaw Ara ararauna
4 Mountain Bamboo Partridges Bambusicola fytchii
4 Chinese Bamboo Partridges Bambusicola thoracicus
Geoff Masson is Livestock Manager at Paultons Park, Ower, The New
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.452023" page_id="56255193"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
Forest, Hampshire S051 6AL, UK. He is an Avicultural Society Council
Member and coordinates the Special Interest Groups for corvids, hornbills
and African starlings. E-mail:geoffmasson@paultons. co. uk
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.450961" page_id="56255193"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
* * *
BELIEVED TO BE A WORLD FIRST
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.984617222222222" page_id="56255193"  page_num="52" year="" vol="">
World of Birds Wildlife Sanctuary, Hout Bay, near Cape Town, believes it
is probably the first zoological institution in the world to succeed in breeding
the African Black Oystercatcher Haematopus moquini. One of the parents
which has been there for more than 18 years, paired with a two or three years
old bird. Two eggs were laid in January (the peak of the holiday season in
South Africa) next to the path everybody walks along. Although the female
sat most of the time, because of the risk of the eggs being taken or broken,
they were removed and placed in an incubator. One of the eggs hatched and
the chick was reared by staff at the sanctuary.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998471" page_id="56255194"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
53
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.82325" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255194" page_num="53" year="" vol="">
LONG-LIVED LORIES
by Rosemary Low
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996755837837838" page_id="56255194"  page_num="53" year="" vol="">
Like most medium-sized parrots, lories and lorikeets have the potential
to be long-lived. One reason why there are so few documented records
of their longevity in captivity is because few people are so committed to
lories that they keep a bird until the end of its life. Because keeping the
accommodation of these liquid-feeding birds clean takes up a lot of time,
they are more time-consuming to look after than other parrots. However,
the rewards of keeping these colourful, active, intelligent and cheeky parrots
fully compensate for the necessity to feed them at least twice a day and to
keep their perches and accommodation thoroughly clean.
As with other parrots, few owners keep records and usually the only
evidence regarding their longevity is anecdotal. This is almost invariably
greatly exaggerated, as in the case of "Winston Churchill's macaw." Several
years ago the claim was made that it was 100 years old. However, the bird
claimed to have become a centenarian was a Blue-and-yellow Macaw Ara
ararauna and was not even the same species that Churchill had kept, which
was a Scarlet Macaw A. macao . The fact is that large parrots very rarely,
if ever, live beyond their late sixties. Medium-sized parrots may live to be
40 years of age.
I have kept record cards for individual parrots since the 1960s. I know,
therefore, that my oldest bird is a Yellow-streaked Lory Chalcopsitta
sintillata acquired in December 1975 and that he has been with me for
more than 35 years. Four years ago he became afraid of his mate of the
previous 12 years, so I gave her to Paradise Park at Hayle, in Cornwall, and
pensioned him off. He was moved to my outdoor birdroom with access to
an outdoor cage in good weather. I should emphasise that old birds feel
the cold and need a heat lamp to ease them through the UK winter. For the
past four years an infrared ceramic bulb (in a reflective holder) was kept
on day and night and at night he always perched close to it. One of three
tubular heaters in the birdroom was behind his cage but this did not provide
adequate heating for him.
Last summer he showed increased signs of ageing. He was no longer
able to fly or to grip strongly with his feet and it was evident that his wings
and feet were affected by arthritis. As the November days became colder I
watched over him and became increasingly worried and, finally, just before
the big freeze commenced, I brought him into the house. As the freeze
got worse and, despite the tubular heaters, the temperature in the birdroom
dropped below freezing, I knew I had taken the right decision. He would
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994567" page_id="56255195"  page_num="54" year="" vol="">
54
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.680502" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255195" page_num="54" year="" vol="">
LOW - LONG-LIVED LORIES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997700261904762" page_id="56255195"  page_num="54" year="" vol="">
never have survived out in the birdroom.
This Yellow-streaked Lory has now become, by a year, my longest-lived
lory. The previous record was held by a female Duivenbode's Lory C.
duivenhodei acquired in October 1973. She died 34 years later, in August
2007, when she had two eight week old chicks in the nest. I mention this to
show that lories can not only live a long time but that some birds can breed
right up until the end of their lives. This female bred with the same male
from 1982 to her death, that is, for 25 years. It was the most wonderful pair
of birds I ever kept.
I would suggest that lory longevity depends mainly on them being fed the
correct diet (some commercial lory foods are only suitable for Trichoglossus
spp.) and good management. I never let my lories sleep in the outside part
of the aviary at night. Too many parrots die as a result of being frightened
at night or from being attacked by nocturnal predators.
I also had a long-lived pair of Dusky Lories Pseudeos fuscata. The pair
was imported from Singapore by a friend in 1973.1 remember how thrilled
I was to have the pair for the species was then rare in aviculture. (Alas, the
species is again rare in Europe.) The male of this prolific breeding pair lived
to at least 29 years of age and died in December 2002, having outlived the
female by about one year.
Two species of lorikeets which have proved to be long-lived with me
are the Iris Psitteuteles iris and Musschenbroek's Lorikeet Neopsittacus
musschenbroekii. Last year my previous record for the Iris Lorikeet, of 22
years, was broken by a female who lived for one year longer. Interestingly,
when she died there was nothing about her appearance to suggest that she
was old. The oldest male to produce a young one was 17 years of age. The
age of 23 years had also been attained by a male Musschenbroek's Lorikeet
when I gave him to a friend who had a female. This bird fertilized an egg
some months later but, alas, is probably now too old to produce offspring.
Perhaps the most commonly kept lorikeet is the Rainbow Trichoglossus
haematodus moluccanus. Ten years ago when I visited Hans Walser, a very
skilled lory breeder in Switzerland, he showed me a Rainbow Lorikeet that
was 26 years of age and in excellent condition. It had flown at liberty for
20 years until the female disappeared. In 2001, when I visited my Swedish
friends Inge and Nancy Forsberg they had several Rainbow Lorikeets in
their mid-twenties, including the bird shown on the front cover of my book
Lories and Lorikeets published by Paul Elek in 1977. The Trichoglossus spp.
are among the toughest of the lorikeets and the least sensitive to incorrect
feeding and poorly formulated commercial lory foods.
To sum up: if your lorikeets are not living into their early twenties and
your lories into their late twenties, there might be something wrong with
your management.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.989793333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56255196" page_num="55" year="" vol="">
THE HAND-REARING OF THREE
DUSKY LORY Pseudeosfascata CHICKS AT
WELTVOGELPARK WALSRODE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996653" page_id="56255196"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
55
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.970911555555556" page_id="56255196"  page_num="55" year="" vol="">
by Wolfgang Magnus, Janina Gerbatsch and Anne Hoppmann
The Dusky Lory Pseudeos fascata is found on the island of New Guinea
and on nearby Japen Island and the island of Salawati. It inhabits rainforest
up to 2,400m (approx. 7,875ft), but can also be seen in suburban parks and
occasionally even in plantations and on the savannah. It is a highly gregarious
species and sometimes forms roosts of several thousand birds. Like other
species of lories, it feeds mainly on nectar and also takes pollen, coconut
blossoms and feeds on fruits such as mangos.
Weltvogelpark Walsrode
Dusky Lory chicks at four weeks old.
In the wild, the offspring are reared in hollows in tall, montane trees.
Normally two white eggs are laid between November-April, which are
incubated for 24 days. The young fledge after about 70 days. On the Red
List of Threatened Species the Dusky Lory is considered to be of Least
Concern.
In Germany it can be found in a few zoological institutions. It can be
distinguished from the many colourful species of lories by its reddish-brown
plumage and creamy to white lower back and rump. For most of the time the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.988551" page_id="56255197"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
56
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.618019" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255197" page_num="56" year="" vol="">
HOPPMANN ET AL - DUSKY LORY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.969265428571429" page_id="56255197"  page_num="56" year="" vol="">
Five weeks old.
Weltvogelpark Walsrode
latter are hidden by the wings and are seen only by the most patient visitors,
when the birds are flying or during courtship.
Weltvogelpark Walsrode houses a breeding pair of this species in an
enclosure in the Lory Atrium. The pair is extremely territorial and the nest
box is vehemently defended. The female regularly lays a clutch of two
eggs in the nest box and, although the eggs have a high rate of fertilty, the
pair had failed to rear any of the young, which either vanished shortly after
hatching or were found dead in or outside the nest box.
Therefore, in 2011 it was decided to remove the young and hand-rear
them. Three chicks were hand-reared. The first two, which were hatched by
the parents in the nest box at the end of May, were removed at approximately
two days old and transferred to the hand-rearing section. The chicks were
very small and the pink coloured skin was covered with white fluffy down and
the eyes were still closed. The chicks weighed about 5g. They were placed
in a heated rearing box in which, during the first six days, the temperature
was maintained at 37.1*C (98.8*F) with 65% humidity. Both chicks still
had food remaining in their crop from the first feeds they had been given
by their parents, so were at first given only fluids (Ringer's solution) and
lactobacilli.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.455674" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255198" page_num="57" year="" vol="">
HOPPMANN ET AL - DUSKY LORY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.975291" page_id="56255198"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
57
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.921769" page_id="56255198"  page_num="57" year="" vol="">
The breeding pair of Dusky Lories.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.427506">
Weltvogelpark Walsrode
</subsectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996106" page_id="56255199"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
58
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.654236" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255199" page_num="58" year="" vol="">
HOPPMANN ET AL - DUSKY LORY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.96431912" page_id="56255199"  page_num="58" year="" vol="">
The chicks were initially fed five to six times a day. They received a 1:1
mixture of a powder especially developed for lories and A19 High Energy
powder made into a mush to which was added lactobacilli and dextrose.
Within one week the weight of the chicks had increased from 5g to 14.5g.
The number of feeds was reduced to four or five a day, depending on how
quickly the young digested the food. On day six the temperature in the
rearing box was reduced to 36.9*C (98.4*F) and during the following days
was reduced step by step 0.1 *C (0.18*F) at a time. An experienced keeper
controlled the temperature and ensured the well-being of the young lories.
As they were developing well and steadily gaining weight, from mid-
June onwards the number of feeds was reduced to three a day. At this stage
the food mixture was changed to a 2:1 ratio, that is two parts lory powder to
one part A19 High Energy. At three weeks of age, the young lories weighed
about 50g and, in addition to the daily feeds, were feeding by themselves
from a dish of food placed in the rearing cage. After six weeks they weighed
1 lOg and fledged at about 70 days.
After the parents had incubated the second clutch of eggs for a short time,
the eggs were removed from the nest box and transferred to an incubator.
The temperature was set at 37.2*C (99.0*F) and the humidity at 55%. Only
one of the eggs was fertile. The newly-hatched chick was fed for the first
time during the following 24 hours, to ensure that it had enough energy to
start its life. Following the successful rearing of the first two young, we
experienced no problems rearing the third young lory.
Product mentioned in the text
Nutribird A19 High Energy Parrot Hand-Rearing Food: Versele-Laga nv, Kappellestraat 70,
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.926692111111111">
9800 Deinze, Belgium. Website:www.versele-laga.com
Bibliography
BirdLife International. 2009. Pseudeos fuscata. In: IUCN 2011. Red List of Threatened Species.
Version 2011.2. Website:www.iucnredlist.org (accessed December 15th 2011).
del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A. and Sargatal, J. (eds.). 1997. Handbook of the Birds of the World.
Volume 4 - Sandgrouse to Cuckoos. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona.
Weltvogelpark Walsrode opened in 1962 and this year is celebrating its
50th Anniversary. Website:www. weltvogelpark. de/E-mail:anne. hoppmann@
weltvogelpark. de
</reference>
<page confidence="0.996789" page_id="56255200"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
59
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.95746725" genericHeader="method" page_id="56255200" page_num="59" year="" vol="">
THE ARTIFICIAL INCUBATION OF THE EGGS AND
THE HAND-REARING OF THE CHICKS OF THE
CAPUCHINRIRB Perissocephalus tricolor .
AT DALLAS WORLD AQUARIUM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990229947368421" page_id="56255200"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
by Carolina M. A mala
The Capuchinbird Perissocephalus tricolor is a member of the family
Cotingidae (Cotingas) and is placed in the moeotypic genus Perissocephalus.
It is a monomorphic species found in humid forests in north-east South
America, where it eats mainly fruits and large insects. In this article, I discuss
the incubation of four Capuchinbird eggs and the hand-rearing of the four
chicks at Dallas World Aquarium in 2011.
Incubation and hatching
The eggs were laid in an exhibit housing two male and one female
Capuchinbirds The eggs were laid, one per clutch, between February and
July. Because the birds had a tendency to break the eggs, the eggs were
removed and placed in an incubator. They were incubated at a temperature
of 99*F (37.2*C) and 54%-56% humidity. The incubation period varied
from 26-27 days. Prior to hatching, the eggs were moved to a hatcher set at
97*F (36.1*C) and 70% humidity, in which the chicks remained until they
were folly dry. A small rubber mat in their bowl gave the chicks something
to grab hold of with their feet and made them more comfortable, and proved
to be very efficient in avoiding foot and leg problems, such as malformations
of the bones, as the chicks grew.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.515757">
Feeding and housing
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989805416666667" page_id="56255200"  page_num="59" year="" vol="">
Their initial diet, until the first few faeces had been passed, consisted
mainly of soaked pellets. Sound stimulation was used to obtain the feeding
response. Capuchinbird chicks pass faeces immediately after the first
beakfol of food at every feed, at which time their weight was determined
and recorded (see Fig.l).
In order to provide heat until the chicks were able to thermoregulate, they
were kept in a brooder. Temperature and humidity parameters are shown in
Table 1, At approximately one month of age, perches were provided inside
the brooder and chicks were moved to a larger cage after that.
Days one to seven the chicks were fed every two hours; days eight to 14
they were fed every three hours and, from then on, were fed ad lib. Their
daily food intake is shown in Table 2.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.894329" page_id="56255201"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
60
</page>
<table confidence="0.470081" page_id="56255201"  page_num="60" year="" vol="">
ARRUBA - CAPUCHIMBIRD
Two weeks old.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.627719" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255202" page_num="61" year="" vol="">
ARRUDA - CAPUCHINBIRD
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.974148" page_id="56255202"  page_num="61" year="" vol="">
61
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.616899">
One month old.
Fig. 1. Growth rates of Capuchinbird chicks determined immediately after
the first beakful of food at every feed.
</figureCaption>
<page confidence="0.991305" page_id="56255203"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
62
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.472957" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255203" page_num="62" year="" vol="">
ARRUDA - CAPUCHINBIRD
</sectionHeader>
<tableCaption confidence="0.955679">
Table 1. Brooder parameters according to the age of the chicks.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.766836166666667" page_id="56255203"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
Days
Temperature
Humidity
1-3
94*F-92*F (34.4*C-33.3*C)
65%
</figure>
<page confidence="0.607199" page_id="56255203"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
4-6
</page>
<equation confidence="0.90520675" page_id="56255203"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
90*F-88*F (32.2*C-31.1*C)
60%
7-15
86*F-84*F (30*C-28.9*C)
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.9724955" page_id="56255203"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
After this each chick was kept at room temperature and the door of the
brooder was replaced with an open front in order to provide better air
circulation.
At each feed they received a portion of pellets, a portion of fruit and a
small amount of protein. Mazuri Low Iron Pellets were soaked in a drinking
water/apple cider vinegar solution (5ml of vinegar per 250ml of water); the
fruit included chopped papaya and blueberries, with chopped waxworms,
butterworms and pinkies providing the protein. The protein intake was
gradually decreased as the young Capuchinbirds began eating on their own.
They learned to do this when they were about one-and-a-half months old.
This was done by simply offering them a bowl of food with their favourite
items on top.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.924924">
Table 2. Percentage of daily food intake in comparison to body weight (first
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.905293428571429" page_id="56255203"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
weight of the day) spread throughout daily feeds. _____
Day
Intake
1
20%-25%
2
25%-30%
</figure>
<page confidence="0.952055" page_id="56255203"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
3
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.98142" page_id="56255203"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
30%-35% and so on
After two weeks each bird received at least 40% of its body weight per day,
fed ad lib and not force fed.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.868272" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56255203" page_num="62" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.974656166666667" page_id="56255203"  page_num="62" year="" vol="">
Special thanks to Daryl Richardson, founder and Director of The Dallas
World Aquarium, without whose successful breeding and conservation
programmes we would not be able to work with this and many other
incredible species. Special thanks also to other members of the Nursery
Staff, namely Susan Schmidt, Nikki Gomas and Breanna Cestari, for their
great team work raising so many young birds.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.29904" genericHeader="references" page_id="56255203" page_num="62" year="" vol="">
Bibliography
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.8770814">
Snow, D. W. 2004. Family Cotingidae (Cotingas). In: del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A. and Christie, D.
A. (eds.). Handbook of the Birds of the World. Volume 9 - Cotingas to Pipits and Wagtails.
Lynx Edicions, Barcelona.
Carolina M. Arruda is a biologist from Brazil, who has been working at
The Dallas World Aquarium since 2009. E-mail:carolina@dwazoo.com
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.635799" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255204" page_num="63" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE BLUE-CROWNED MOTMOT
Momotus momota IN FRANCE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998921" page_id="56255204"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
63
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.970562222222222" page_id="56255204"  page_num="63" year="" vol="">
by Patrick Chartier and Cedric Libert
The Blue-crowned Motmot is a medium-sized arboreal bird living in
Central and South America, where it can be found in many different habitats,
ranging from tropical rainforests to arid regions. It measures 38cm-43cm
(1 Sin-1 Tin) in length and weighs from 50g-160g (M m. exiguus , for example,
weighs 77g-102g and M. m. momota 120g-160g). Twenty subspecies are
recognised based on size and plumage variations, but can also differ in their
vocalisations. This has led numerous authorities to call for a taxonomic
revision of the species. Molecular genetic studies may provide justification
for giving full species status to some current subspecies, especially M. m.
bahamensis which has long been isolated on the islands of Trinidad and
Tobago.
The specimens which one of the authors (P.C.) owns were obtained from
the Netherlands, having been imported originally from Ecuador. Our contact
for exportation from Ecuador was an Ecuadorian veterinarian, well-known
for his knowledge of birds and the birds reached us in perfect condition,
I sent Dr D. W. Snow at The Natural History Museum at Tring photos
of each of my specimens and, in answer to my inquiry concerning the
identification of subspecies, he stated that it is virtually impossible to
accurately identify them as individual variation within each subspecies is so
great. One of my specimens has much more rufous on the breast and belly
and another has a reddish spot behind the crown.
Description
A predominantly green bird with a blue edged black crown and a long tail
with the two central rectrices adorned with the characteristic racket-shaped
tips. It has a slightly curved bill with serrations along most of the length of
the cutting edges of both mandibles. The plumage of the sexes is identical
but slight sexual dimorphism, such as differences in bill size and head width,
etc., can be observed in Coraciiformes. Males are generally larger and
weigh more, but the most reliable criteria is the length of the tarsus, which
is usually longer in the case of the male and easily measurable. Both sexes
of the nominate subspecies have a black crown, edged with turquoise, blue
and violet. A black mask runs through the red eye and terminates in a thin
line, bordered above and below with turquoise. The nape is reddish and
the back is green. The breast and belly are green, often more-or-less tinged
with cinnamon, depending on the subspecies. There are two black spots
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995894" page_id="56255205"  page_num="64" year="" vol="">
64
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.455002" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255205" page_num="64" year="" vol="">
CHARTIER &amp; LIBERT - BLUE-CROWNED MOTMOT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999061333333333" page_id="56255205"  page_num="64" year="" vol="">
Entrance to the artificial nest burrow. The stone was placed on the right-hand side of
the entrance to stop the birds from digging a new entrance by the side of the original
entrance the width of which it should be noted, is greater than the height.
on the breast. The tail is composed of twelve rectrices, two of which have
black-edged violet-blue racket-like tips, which are not always symmetrical.
The so-called rackets are often wider than the actual rectrices. Apparently,
motmots use their racket-like tail feathers, which they swing pendulum-like
from side to side, to send out signals or as a sign of their mood, and I have
often witnessed this in captivity when a bird seems alarmed by an unusual
presence (Chartier pers. obs.). The legs and feet are black and typical of
birds of the order Coraciiformes, have the outer toe fused to the middle toe
for most of its length. They have forest-bird type, short, rounded wings, and
are not great fliers. They make quick, brief flights, and show remarkable
agility when moving through dense vegetation.
On leaving the nest hole, the juveniles are almost the same size as the
adults, but are a little slimmer in build. Their coloration, especially the
coloration of the green parts, is duller and the black areas are less extensive
and they lack the two black spots on the breast and the two central rectrices,
which are already longer and wider, are also differently coloured to the others.
The racket-like tips are not acquired until after the first moult. These special
adornments are, according to some authors, acquired as a result of the birds
removing the barbs of the subterminal sections of the two central rectrices.
This seems perfectly feasible to me (P. C.), although I have never succeeded
in witnessing it happening.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.253757" page_id="56255206"  page_num="65" year="" vol="">
CHARTIER &amp; LIBERT - BLUE-CROWNED MOTMOT
</equation>
<page confidence="0.997204" page_id="56255206"  page_num="65" year="" vol="">
65
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9696263" page_id="56255206"  page_num="65" year="" vol="">
Nest chamber with the top removed to show the clutch of three white eggs.
The back of the nesting chamber.
Voice
This species is usually silent and inconspicuous and moves about mostly
when hunting for food. The vocalizations consist of a deep and soft, far-
carrying, double "hoot", which can also be translated as "whoo-hoop" or
"hoot-hoot". (The name motmot is said to come from the call, in this instance
translated as "moat-moat".) At my (P. C's) home in Pays Basque, south-
western France, it could be heard from May, mostly at sunrise and sunset,
prior to breeding commencing. The male gives a double "hoot-hoot" and the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.9718" page_id="56255207"  page_num="66" year="" vol="">
66
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.453785" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255207" page_num="66" year="" vol="">
CHARTIER &amp; LIBERT - BLUE-CROWNED MOTMOT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.968660289473684" page_id="56255207"  page_num="66" year="" vol="">
female answers with a single "hoot-hoot". This is accompanied by a breeding
display involving the male presenting twigs and leaves to the female, none
of which were found in the nesting chamber after the young fledged.
Habitat
Seasonally or permanently humid tropical rainforest, arid and semi-
arid areas, as well as montane areas up to 2,000m (approx. 6,500ft). Also
gardens and cultivated areas, close to human activity. It usually favours
areas with banks and gentle slopes and along roadsides. It has the most
adaptable habitat requirements of all the Momotidae, It enjoys dust-bathing
and rain-bathing.
Feeding
It takes a great variety of different foods for a Coraciiformes. Any
appropriate-sized insect or invertebrate is swallowed whole. It hunts from a
perch or by probing around on the ground, turning over leaves and twigs and
digging in the earth to find snails, earthworms, frogs (including the highly
toxic poison dart frogs, such as Dendrohates auratus in Costa Rica), reptiles
(snakes and lizards), scorpions, the chicks of small birds, and mammals. It
often dives down onto its prey from a perch on which it had been sitting
motionless and kills the prey by beating it on the ground or returns to the
perch with it and beats it against the branch. Fruits, including those of
palms, along with figs, also constitute a high proportion of the bird's diet.
No seeds have been found amongst the stomach contents. It Is thought that
the chicks are fed on a similar diet to that described above, but that items
of food are, at the beginning, usually dismembered by the parents, before
being fed to the nestlings. Later, the nestlings swallow the food whole. No
fruits are given to them during the first two weeks.
Breeding
It nests in a burrow excavated in a bank of earth or the bank of a river,
including sometimes at archeological sites. The burrow consists of a tunnel
0.6m-5m (approx. 2ft-16ft) in length and with an oval-shaped entrance
(the width being greater than the height), which is characteristic of this
species and easily distinguishes it from burrows dug by other birds and
mammals. The tunnel is not always straight and may turn at an angle of up
to ninety degrees, depending on obstacles met during the digging process.
The entrance is usually inconspicuous and hidden by fallen leaves and
other debris. Areas with tree roots are often favoured as they offer better
possiblities for concealing the entrance of the nest. Both sexes excavate the
tunnel, digging rapidly using both feet alternatively and kicking the earth
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.39867" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255208" page_num="67" year="" vol="">
CHART) ER &amp; LIBERT - BLUE-CROWNED MOTMOT
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998818" page_id="56255208"  page_num="67" year="" vol="">
67
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.973384179487179" page_id="56255208"  page_num="67" year="" vol="">
backwards. Construction can take several weeks and usually commences up
to a few months before the start of the breeding season, which in the wild is
usually in September or October, at the end of the rainy season. Breeding
occurs during the dry season some four or five months later, once the soil
has become harder. Burrows are almost never used for a second time and
only for breeding purposes, an exception being M m. bahamensis, which has
been seen roosting in its burrow at night. A burrow which is currently in use
can be recognised by the two parallel grooves left in the earth by the bird's
legs and feet. Usually two to five oval-shaped white eggs are laid, which is
typical of hole-nesting Coraciiformes. Incubation, which is undertaken by
both the male and female, commences following the laying of the last egg.
The incubation period is usually 21 days. The last egg hatches 24 hours
after the first egg. The nestlings are bom naked. The flight feather quills
usually begin to appear after nine days.
Both parents take an equal share of the feeding duties. Skutch noted that
the Turquoise-browed Motmot Eumomota superciliosa and the Broad-billed
Motmot Electron platyrhynclum basically have no nest sanitation and the
floor of the nest chamber is often covered with the remains of all kinds of
larvae and droppings. In the case of our captive Blue-crowned Motmots, we
can testify that the nest chamber remained perfectly clean until the juveniles
finally fledged, which is very surprising for a Coraciiformes.
The chicks usually remain in the nest for up to 32 days. Usually only
a single clutch of eggs is laid each year, but Snow recorded replacement
clutches being laid usually 21 days later, which is something we have never
observed.
Captivity
The Blue-crowned Motmot was bred at Winged World in 1970 (see
Avicultural Magazine Vol.76, No.5, pp. 188-189 (1970)) and at Kilverstone
Wildlife Park, also in the UK, for the first time in 1985, with a total of 13
young being reared over a period of four years (see Vol.97, No.l, pp.38-40
(1991)). Since then private breeders - particularly Gerald Morisseau in
France - and some zoos have succeeded in breeding this species in Europe.
On January 1st 2011, the ISIS database listed six males and 16 females in
Europe, with only one breeding success having been recorded during the
previous 12 months. This occurred at Parc Zoologique de Montpellier, which
also seems to have been the only zoo to have bred this species in 2009. This
species has apparently become extremely rare in private collections. The
situation looks better in the USA, with a captive population of 58 males, 60
females, 16 specimens of unknown sex and 22 young produced in 2010.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996584" page_id="56255209"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
68
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.454832" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255209" page_num="68" year="" vol="">
CHARTIER &amp; LIBERT - BLUE-CROWNED MOTMOT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99711548" page_id="56255209"  page_num="68" year="" vol="">
Four days old. The third chick has died.
Aviary structure and landscaping
Each pair in my private collection was housed singly in aviaries
measuring 6m long x 2.5m wide x 2.5m high (approx. 19ft 6in long x 8ft
wide x 8ft high) with two access doors (one on each side) and a small shelter
2m x 1.5m (approx. 6ft 6in x 5ft) in which the food was placed on metal
structures, so that it could not be reached by small rodents. Each aviary was
planted with rich and dense vegetation, amongst which the birds disappeared
whenever they felt the need to.
Two-thirds of the roof of each aviary was covered with polycarbonate
sheeting. The sides of the aviaries were protected with the same material
during wintertime. The birds were rather more sensitive to wind and rain,
than to low temperatures. However, in the shelters I always used IR and
ceramic lamps in order to maintain the temperature above freezing.
The aviaries were covered with 13mm x 13mm (&amp;apos;Ain x Viin) wire mesh
and rather than use a double layer of wire as protection against raptors, I
had wires 15cm (approx. 6in) apart loosely attached to the structure and
about 40cm (approx. 1ft 4in) clear of the aviaries, to deter raptors without
injuring them.
The ground was covered with sand, which was regularly raked over. Most
of the ground vegetation was left in the aviary, except for under the perches,
from where it was removed in order to make cleaning a good deal easier.
The breeding pair at Parc Zoologique de Montpellier, consisting of my
(P. C's) breeding male and a female hatched at Zurich Zoo, has since the
summer of 2007 been exhibited in an aviary of similar dimensions to that
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.254413" page_id="56255210"  page_num="69" year="" vol="">
CHARTIER &amp; LIBERT - BLUE-CROWNED MOTMOT
</equation>
<page confidence="0.996426" page_id="56255210"  page_num="69" year="" vol="">
69
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.995079166666667" page_id="56255210"  page_num="69" year="" vol="">
Eight days old.
Twelve days old.
described above. The aviary is in the Amazonian Tropical Hall, in which the
temperature hardly ever varies and, therefore, there is no need for a shelter. A
small, but very leafy tree Gustavia gracilima, has been planted in the aviary
and the birds often shelter or hide among the foliage of this tree if they feel
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.988307" page_id="56255211"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
70
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.449742" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255211" page_num="70" year="" vol="">
CHARTIER &amp; LIBERT - BLUE-CROWNED MOTMOT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97873082051282" page_id="56255211"  page_num="70" year="" vol="">
at all stressed. Most of the top of the aviary is covered by a climber/vine
Aristolochia sp. and at the back there is a wall, which provides the birds with
a peaceful area in which to rest, when there are lots of visitors to the Tropical
Hall. Five or six times a day fine sprays of water are directed towards the
back of the exhibit, but without soaking the aviary itself.
Behaviour
In captivity these birds remain physically and mentally healthy so long
as they can keep their distance and hide away from visitors whenever they
feel the need to. Rather than take fright and crash against the wire, they
prefer to quickly slip away into dense vegetation, showing how well this
species is adapted to forest habitat.
During the first few weeks after fledging, juveniles are very nervous and
great care must be taken when approaching them and they should always be
given sufficient time to quietly slip away.
I (R C.) have kept mostly males in my breeding station and have
succeeded in keeping young males together in a single aviary without
witnessing any aggressive behaviour. I kept two brothers together in the
same aviary for three years without any problems. I must stress, of course,
that there were no females in the aviaries or nearby.
Juveniles become independent fairly rapidly and the females were usually
separated from their parents after eight weeks.
I (R C.) do not know how this species would behave if housed in a mixed
species exhibit, as I have always housed my breeding pairs separately in order
to avoid any trouble which might lead to the failure of a breeding attempt,
which I suspect might happen unless they are housed in an especially large
exhibit. Observations at Parc Zoologique de Montpellier show that when
young males reach four months of age, tensions begin to surface between
them and their father, leading to concern over the safety of the young
males.
Feeding
They are mostly given suitable livefood, as well as various different
kinds of fruit (see Table 1). I (P. C.) personally favour whole cherries
and fruits such as blueberries and elderberries, etc., which deteriorate less
rapidly. Nutribird T16, a low iron complete maintenance and breeding food
specially formulated for toucans, turacos and other fruit-eating birds, is
also provided, but the birds do not usually eat much of this. Other softbill
foods may be accepted in time, but may have to be moistened, which is
likely to cause them to deteriorate in quality fairly quickly. Insectivorous
mixtures, if given alone, usually prove to be unsuitable, as the birds often
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.253807" page_id="56255212"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
CHARTIER &amp; LIBERT - BLUE-CROWNED MOTMOT
</equation>
<page confidence="0.997248" page_id="56255212"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
71
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99745005" page_id="56255212"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
toss them about looking for cherries and other fruits, and make a mess in
the aviary. Pieces of meat, mice and quail chicks (always dead of course)
are also given. In my outside aviaries, I hardly ever found lizards and the
mouse traps were usually empty, which was probably a sign of opportunistic
predation by the birds.
The mouse traps were the small mechanical type which I kept in place
permanently. I never used poison in and around my aviaries, as I felt there
was a risk of the motmots eating rodents that had ingested the poison. My
concern though may have been misplaced, as Eric Bureau, veterinarian and
Deputy Director of Parc de Oiseaux Villars les Dombes and my co-author
(C. L.), have confirmed that using poison as a means of pest control is not
a major issue, as it has usually been completely metabolised by the liver by
the time the animal dies. Prophylactic treatment with vitamin K is always
possible. What must be avoided, however, is a massive pest control effort
which generates large quantities of dead rodents.
It is essential to dust the above diet with a good vitamin/mineral
supplement daily throughout the breeding season and on a regular basis
outside of the breeding season (I (P. C.) used Quiko Forte).
The birds are fed twice a day. Half of fresh fruit, vegetables and proteins
in the morning and the remainder in the afternoon.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.954747">
Table 1. Typical daily diet for each motmot at Parc Zoologique de
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.947349407407407" page_id="56255212"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
Montpellier.
Ingredients
Preparation
T16 low iron pellets
Available at all times
lOg Apples/pears
Cut into small cubes
lOg Banana
Cut into small cubes
lOg Carrots
Cut into small cubes
lOg Melon/grapes/figs/peaches
Cut into small cubes
cherries (during summer)
lOg Insectivore patee
Placed on fruit
5 Pieces of dog food with
Soaked in tea overnight
maximum iron content of
150ppm
1 Day old mouse (pinkie)
Previously fed on reptile
2-3 Morio worms and
croquettes/pellets
mealworms
(manufactured specially for reptiles)
2-3 Locusts and crickets
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.981078" page_id="56255212"  page_num="71" year="" vol="">
in order to achieve the correct
calcium to phosphorus ratio
Vitamin/mineral supplement: a small amount of Olivitasol on the tip of a
knife each day for the first 10 days of each month.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.993194" page_id="56255213"  page_num="72" year="" vol="">
72
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.303289" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255213" page_num="72" year="" vol="">
CHARTIER &amp; LIBERT - BLUE-CROWNED MOTMOT
Diseases
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999611951219512" page_id="56255213"  page_num="72" year="" vol="">
Motmots are very resistant to pathogens and very few publications
are available on specifically motmot-related diseases. In 2007, however,
a specific parasite Circumvitellatrema motmota was described, first from
Audubon Zoo and then from other zoological institutions in the USA. This
parasite, which is confined to motmots, develops in snails and passes to the
bird when the bird eats the snails. The larvae migrate to the bird's air sacs
where they can develop into 5mm long parasites. Up to 50 of these can be
found in the air sacs of a single bird and, one can easily imagine, how this
must affect the bird.
In the autumn (fall) of 2010, this parasite was identified in a young
motmot hatched at Parc Zoologique de Montpellier, showing that this parasite
is capable of completing its life cycle here in Europe. The hypothesis we
came up with is that the male parent, although he appeared perfectly healthy,
was probably carrying the parasite when he was imported from Ecuador.
The parasite had then completed its development in the small snails living
in the aviary, which is similar to what happened in the USA. Drugs such as
Prazinquantel (at five times higher than the usual dose), which are used in the
USA, did not provide very satisfactory results. Infected birds can, however,
live to a fairly old age, so long as they are maintained in good conditions.
The main problem is that young birds can become infected through their
parents excreting the parasite's eggs in their saliva and faeces. So far, the
only solution seems to be to remove the eggs for artificial incubation and
hand-rear the chicks.
Parasites such as coccidia, giardia and capillaria are frequently
encountered. Avian tuberculosis Mycobacterium avium , which is known to
cause important losses in captive populations of passerines, is also known
to affect motmots. Other diseases such as aspergillosis, yersiniosis and
chlamydophilosis can have a negative effect on these birds. E. coli is mostly
found in very sick birds suffering from terminal septicemia. Hypovitaminosis
A, which can occur due to a lack of whole prey items in the diet (vitamin
A being stored in the liver), emphasises the importance of using a good
vitamin/mineral supplement.
The effects of hemosiderosis (iron storage disease) are well known.
Therefore, we feed our birds low iron pellets and dog food which has
been soaked in tea, relying on the tannin in the tea to limit iron absorption.
Fruits with a high vitamin C content should be fed to birds only sparingly,
as ascorbic acid is known to aid iron absorption. Osteodystrophia, which
can lead to broken bones or the excessive mineralization of the bones, can
occur if there is an imbalance of calcium and phosphorus in the diet. It is
important, therefore, to feed the birds whole prey items rather than just meat
and to feed them livefood which has previously been fed on, for example,
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.253758" page_id="56255214"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
CHARTIER &amp; LIBERT - BLUE-CROWNED MOTMOT
</equation>
<page confidence="0.997909" page_id="56255214"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
73
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9992095" page_id="56255214"  page_num="73" year="" vol="">
Juvenile two weeks after emerging from the burrow. The bird already has the
two black spots on the breast.
reptile croquettes/pellets in order to achieve a good ratio of calcium to
phosphorus.
Foods with a high fat content and other foods which may lead to obesity
should be avoided.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995267" page_id="56255215"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
74
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.355598" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255215" page_num="74" year="" vol="">
CHARTIER &amp; LIBERT - BLUE-CROWNED MOTMOT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.973440658536585" page_id="56255215"  page_num="74" year="" vol="">
Breeding
I (P. C.) created a nesting burrow in my aviary, which the birds had no
choice but to use, as I had placed wire mesh beneath the sandy soil most of
which was sheltered from the rain and was, therefore, also very hard.
The burrow was basically a 1 Ocm (4in) diameter cardboard tube filled
with a mixture of peat and sand, which was attached to the nest chamber - a
wooden box which had originally held 12 bottles of wine - with a substrate
consisting of a mixture of compost and sand. The entire structure was then
boxed-in and coated with an adhesive, to which sand, earth, leaves and
branches were attached in order to give it a more naturalistic appearance.
It was then placed beneath a small tree.
By using such a structure, the nest chamber can easily be checked to
determine what is happening and, at the appropriate time, the chicks can be
ringed (banded). I never had any problems ringing (banding) the birds, but
did take the precaution of putting a black or brown covering on the rings
(bands) at the beginning.
At Parc Zoologique de Montpellier the breeding pair is housed in an
exhibit in which the ground is covered with a 40cm (approx. 1 ft 4in) deep
layer of well packed mulch. The birds have access to an artificial burrow
similar to that described above, which the pair sometimes explore and work
on after keepers have blocked the entrance by adding earth at the end of the
winter. However, in both 2009 and 2010, the pair nested in a burrow which
the two birds had excavated themselves. This was approximately lm (3ft Sin)
in length and had an oval-shaped opening which was 14cm (SVfin) wide and
12cm (4%in) high. It was discretely dug by the pair in February but it was
not until May that the pair was observed regularly going in and out of it.
Raising the chicks
During the first 12 days only livefood was given. Then we progressively
added fruit and berries. Amongst the preferred items of food were day old
mice (pinkies), pieces of quail chick, thin slices of heart or other meat,
dog food (max. 150ppm of iron, soaked in tea for 24 hours), beetles and
mealworms, etc. A single chick can eat up to six one day old mice (pinkies)
and a great many morio worms each day during the first two weeks of its
life.
Livefood for feeding to the chicks needs to be especially well fed
beforehand on a good varied diet that provides as many nutritional elements
as possible for the chicks. Mealworms can eat almost anything as soon
as their mandibles are able to crush the food items they are given. These
can include, as mentioned earlier, reptile croquettes/pellets (manufactured
specially for reptiles), which will help achieve a better calcium to phosphorus
ratio.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.254722" page_id="56255216"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
CHARTIER &amp; LIBERT - BLUE-CROWNED MOTMOT
</equation>
<page confidence="0.992956" page_id="56255216"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
75
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.8584964" page_id="56255216"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
Diary of events in 2005 when the pair used an artificial burrow:
15.06.05. Both birds, working alternatively, began to dig out earth blocking access
to the artificial tunnel.
22.06.05. When both birds were visible in the aviary, the nest chamber was checked,
but no eggs had been laid.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.728052823529412">
26.06.05. Female remained in burrow.
28.06.05. On inspecting the nest chamber, three eggs were found (see photo
P-65).
29.06.05. Both birds spent an equal amount of time in the nest chamber.
06.07.05. The female barely ever left the nest chamber.
09.07.05. The female was seen again while the male was in the nest chamber.
14.07.05. Three fertile eggs were present in the nest chamber.
16.07.05. Both parents were out in the aviary and continually going back and forth
to the nest chamber.
20.07.05. One of the three chicks was found dead in the nest.
24.07.05. The quills of the flight feathers were beginning to appear, but it had not
yet been possible to ring (band) the chicks.
27.07.05. It was still not possible to ring (band) the chicks. The nest chamber was
very clean.
29.07.05. The two chicks were ringed (banded), afterwhich it was decided not to
make any further checks of the nest chamber.
16.08.05. The two juveniles emerged from the nest. They were relatively agile
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.965817173913043" page_id="56255216"  page_num="75" year="" vol="">
in flight, very similar to their parents. They were easily frightened but
given the size of the aviary and the vegetation, this was not a problem as
they hid whenever they saw me approaching. They fledged very quickly
and were almost independent once they left the nest chamber.
Two weeks after the two juveniles fledged, the adult pair began to moult.
Diary of events in 2010 when the pair used a natural burrow:
04.02.10. Pair dug a new burrow.
27.05.10. Male spent most of the day in the nest chamber. Keepers were told to
increase the amount of livefood and not go into the aviary anymore.
Feeding was done via a pivoting platform.
30.05.10. Both members of the pair went into the nest chamber together, afterwhich
one of them almost always remained in the nest chamber. This is thought
to have been the date egg laying commenced.
05.06.10. The male remained in the nest chamber most of the day.
15.06.10. The female remained in the nest chamber most of the day.
19.06.10. The pair was in the nest chamber during the morning, which is thought
to have been the hatching date.
22.06.10. The male was seen going into the nest with a morio worm.
12.07.10. The male took morio worms, mealworms and artificial food into the
nest.
17.07.10. Two juveniles flew out of the nest hole.
30.11.10. Tension involving young male was observed during feeding.
01.12.10. Juveniles are separated in quarantine.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.971524" page_id="56255217"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
76
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.6146785" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255217" page_num="76" year="" vol="">
CHARTIER &amp; LIBERT - BLUE-CROWNED MOTMOT
Conclusion
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.910706818181818" page_id="56255217"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
These birds should be kept only by highly motivated and knowledgeable
aviculturists, who have a wide experience of keeping such birds and are
able to bring a scientific approach to bird breeding. If these criteria can be
met, a good case can be made for allowing the further importation of wild
specimens and significant progress made in conserving this species both in
situ and ex situ. Given the very small number of captive birds in Europe,
we are actively looking for specimens and aviculturists who currently have
or have kept this species in their collection. For details of how to contact
us please see below.
Bibliography
Dutton, C J. 2003. Coraciiformes. In: Fowler, M. E. and. Miller, R. E. (eds.). Zoo and Wild
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.892543142857143">
Animal Medicine, 5th Edition. W. B. Saunders, Saint Louis, Missouri.
Hilty, S. L , Brown, W. L. 1986. A Guide to the Birds of Colombia. Princeton University
Press, Princeton, New Jersey.
Prouse, E. and Hardy, A. 2007. Motmots. In: Encyclopedia of Aviculture. Hancock House
Publishers Ltd., Surrey, B. C., Canada &amp; Blaine, USA.
Ridgely, R. S., Gwynne, J. A. 1989. A Guide to the Birds of Panama, with Costa Rica,
Nicaragua, and Honduras. Second Edition. Princeton University Press, Princeton, New
</reference>
<bodyText confidence="0.869233" page_id="56255217"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
Jersey.
Snow, D. W. 2001. Momotidae. In: del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A., Sargatal, J. (eds.). Handbook of
the Birds of the World. Volume 6 - Mousebirds to Hombills. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona
Patrick Chartier is a private breeder and holder of a Certificate of
Competency for the class Aves. E-mail:patrick. chartier. aves@gmail. com/
Tel: 00 33 6 15 26 40 40 (Parc Zoologique de Montpellier).
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.6154385" page_id="56255217"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
Cedric Libert is the Veterinarian at Parc Zoologique de Montpellier,
50 Avenue Agropolis, 34090 Montpellier, France. E-mail:zoocheptel@
ville-montpellier.fr
Hon. Editor's Acknowledgements
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.87195925" page_id="56255217"  page_num="76" year="" vol="">
I would like to thank Pierre de Chabannes for translating the above
article from French to English, apart from a few sentences here and there
and one particular paragraph on which I received assistance from Gregory
Guida, to whom I am also most grateful.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.858546" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255218" page_num="77" year="" vol="">
THE SUCCESSFUL BREEDING OF THE SUNBITTERN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.657241" page_id="56255218"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
Eurypyga h. helias AT TWYCROSS ZOO
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.991261" page_id="56255218"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
77
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9006604375" page_id="56255218"  page_num="77" year="" vol="">
by Christopher Dunn
The Sunbittern Eurypyga helias is the sole member of the Central
and South American family Eurypygidae. Its closest relative is the Kagu
Rhynochetos jubatus of New Caledonia, although exactly how these two
birds fit in taxonomically with other species remains a matter of dispute.
The Sunbittern inhabits tropical rainforest, where it lives near water and
hunts small vertebrate and invertebrate prey. This consists largely of small
amphibians, fish, very small mammals and insects/aquatic insect larvae.
Female Sunbittern with a single egg.
It is usually found singly or in pairs. Breeding pairs use mud and plant
materials to construct an open nest in a tree, and usually lay one or two
mottled eggs, which both birds take turns to incubate and both parents rear
the young. The chicks are semi-precocial and hatch out covered in downy
feathering and with both eyes open. Although soon capable of moving
around within the nest, they remain in the nest until they fledge aged about
16-20 days. They continue to be fed by both parents until they are weaned
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996457" page_id="56255219"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
78
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.853138" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255219" page_num="78" year="" vol="">
DUNN - SUNBITTERN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.872322878048781" page_id="56255219"  page_num="78" year="" vol="">
at eight to nine weeks of age.
The Sunbittem gets its common name, of course, on account of the
sunset-like markings, which are revealed when it spreads its wings. When
threatened, Sunbittems open both wings, which they arch and direct forward
towards the perceived threat while hissing. Should the threat persist, they
will often flick the wings forward and continue to make clicking/hissing
vocalisations in an attempt to intimidate whatever it is that they perceive to
be a threat to them. Presumably, the sunset-like markings imitate the eyes
of a large predator and are intended to fool other creatures into believing
that the Sunbittem is much larger and more ferocious than it actually is.
However, in the event of the creature threatening them not backing down,
Sunbittems are relatively harmless and will usually turn tail and fly away.
There are apparently no visual differences between the sexes and, currently,
the only accurate means of distinguishing between the sexes is by DNA or
surgical sexing, or by carefully observing their behaviour.
At Twycross Zoo the Sunbittems live in the Tropical House, which is a
small walk-through mixed species exhibit housing free-roaming Cotton-eared
Marmosets Callithrixjacchus , Linne's Two-toed Sloth Choloepus didactylus ,
Seba's Short-tailed Bats Camilla perspicillata , Roulroul or Crested Wood
Partridge Rollulus rouloul , Ringed Teal Callonetta leucophrys. Striated
Heron Butorides virescens and Montserrat Oriole Icterus oberi. The exhibit
imitates a tropical rainforest setting and is planted throughout, although
nearly all of the plant growth and cover is at ground level. A sprinkler system
directly above the pond creates an artificial thunderstorm, which works on a
timer roughly every 15-20 minutes. It mns for a short duration and the birds
seem to enjoy the opportunities to bathe which it provides, whereas upon
hearing the thunder soundtrack, the marmosets leave the pond area. This
may well be why the Sunbittems have continuously chosen to nest directly
above the pond or very nearby as, given the opportunity, the marmosets
would steal the eggs or take the chicks. In all previous nesting attempts the
Sunbittems had nested directly above the pond or on the bank. The path
which visitors follow goes all of the way around this area, except that the
pond forms a barrier near the entrance and a barrier of plants on the opposite
side provided sufficient cover/distance for the birds to nest and feel secure.
The average relative humidity in the exhibit ranges from 60%-80% and the
average spring-autumn temperature is 25*C-27*C (77*F-80.6*F).
The Sunbittems at Twycross Zoo receive the following diet:
75g Freshwater smelt (defrosted from frozen)
60g Soaked ibis diet
75g Finely chopped fruit (taken from apple, pear, orange, banana,
grapes, tomato, sultanas, mixed with Haith's softbill food at a rate
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.471823" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255220" page_num="79" year="" vol="">
DUNN - SUNBITTERN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997686" page_id="56255220"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
79
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998660609756097" page_id="56255220"  page_num="79" year="" vol="">
of roughly 750ml softbill food to 2 litres of chopped fruit)
lOOg Minced (ground) meat diet (taken from approx. 5kg minced
(ground) red meat, mixed with 1kg chick crumbs and 1kg Haith's
softbill food)
6-8 Pinkie mice (increased to 12 when a chick is present)
The food is then lightly dusted with Mazuri carnivore supplement, before
being offered to the birds. Scatter feeds of live food - crickets, locusts,
waxworms and mealworms - dusted with a calcium balancer are offered
during the day, with the frequency being increased when chicks are present
or breeding behaviour has been observed.
The Sunbittems appear to ignore the soaked ibis diet and the chopped fruit
and feed mainly on whole vertebrate items and some of the minced (ground)
meat, along with the scattered livefood. When rearing chicks only livefood
and whole vertebrates are offered to the chicks by the parents.
Sunbittems are believed to take roughly one-and-a-half years to two
years to reach sexual maturity. Those at Twycross first started showing
signs of breeding behaviour around June/July 2010, following a series of late
aftemoon/evening displays and vocalisations by the pair. Whether through
inexperience or to avoid the marmosets, the first nesting attempts were at
ground level on the bank at the rear of the pond. Leaves were collected and
placed on the ground at the chosen nest site, however, no eggs were laid
and the pair was later discovered to be incubating a large pebble of roughly
the same colour and with roughly the same markings as a Sunbittem egg.
Such behaviour has been observed in gulls, with nesting birds attempting to
incubate large pebbles or artificial eggs with similar coloration and patterning
to their own eggs, with the largest 'egg' (object) producing the strongest
brooding responses. As a result the pebble was removed to avoid potential
problems in the future.
Several months later the pair nested again in the same spot and within
a week an egg was laid. However, due to the poorly constmcted nest, the
egg rolled out and down the bank on several occasions. It came to a stop
almost 2ft (0.6m) away and was quickly retrieved and placed back beneath
the brooding bird. To everyone's amazement the egg hatched about 30 days
later. At this point the marmosets were closed off in their off-show area
to avoid any chance of them predating the chick, and remained closed off
until after the chick had fledged approximately 18 days later. The chick was
more-or-less weaned at about 60 days and was surgically sexed and found
to be a male. The young bird remained with its parents for several weeks.
When the adults decided to nest again they started to drive it away, but due
to the layout of the tropical house and dense ground cover there were plenty
of hiding places for it.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.989407" page_id="56255221"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
80
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.872447" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255221" page_num="80" year="" vol="">
DUNN - SUNBITTERN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999450571428571" page_id="56255221"  page_num="80" year="" vol="">
Threat display by female Sunbittern while on the nest.
The third nesting attempt was a failure. This time the pair chose a branch
overhanging the pond and attempted to build on it, but the nesting materials
the pair collected simply fell off the branch. An egg was laid which was
found at the bottom of the pond. This was recovered for possible artificial
incubation, but was found to have a hairline crack.
By then it had become apparent that the nesting materials available in
the tropical house were unsuitable. The soil was largely humus and silt and
crumbled and did not therefore bind the nesting materials together. To solve
the problem, moss and dry grass/plant fibres were collected from around
the site and sterilised in boiling water and Safe4 disinfectant. Some of the
nesting material was then lightly rubbed with modelling clay and some was
heavily rubbed with modelling clay, so that the birds had a choice. The
pair had been observed collecting nesting material from near the water's
edge, so the nesting material which had been mixed with clay was scattered
loosely around the edge of the pond. Both birds took an immediate interest
in this and initially seemed to prefer long fibrous materials. These were
collected and placed on a branch in a rough oval shape to construct a base
to support the rest of the nest. Once the base had been built up sufficiently,
the pair collected more moss, which was placed on top and gently trod in
and manipulated with the beak. A lot of nesting material fell into the pond,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.464445" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255222" page_num="81" year="" vol="">
DUNN - SUNBITTERN
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.981909" page_id="56255222"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
81
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.576824" page_id="56255222"  page_num="81" year="" vol="">
Twelve days old.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99506" page_id="56255223"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
82
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.867414" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255223" page_num="82" year="" vol="">
DUNN - SUNBITTERN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999220761904762" page_id="56255223"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
but not enough to prevent them from virtually completing the nest within
24 hours. More moss was collected the following day to provide additional
material to line the nest.
The fourth breeding attempt was the most successful so far. An egg
was laid on June 23rd, which hatched 27 days later on July 20th. The chick
developed rapidly and fledged at 16 days old and by eight to nine weeks of
age had been weaned onto mealworms and smelt. Furthermore, with the
existing nest already in place the interval between clutches was drastically
reduced and the fourth egg was laid on October 7th, roughly nine weeks
after chick number two had fledged. This further nesting attempt again
resulted in the adult pair, especially the male, showing some aggression
towards the young Sunbittem. However, this was minimal and amounted to
driving the youngster away from the nest site, with the odd lunge towards it,
if it landed within lm (approx. 3ft 3in) or so of the nest site. Oddly, when
the male was incubating the egg, the female rarely showed any aggression
towards the youngster and, at times, all three Sunbittems could be seen on
the same nesting branch. The fourth egg hatched on November 4th after
28 days incubation. The presence of the chick in the nest did not lead to
increased aggression towards the juvenile Sunbittem. In fact the parents
showed less interest in the juvenile, as they concentrated on providing food
for the growing chick.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.833373" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56255223" page_num="82" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.886871333333333" page_id="56255223"  page_num="82" year="" vol="">
Special thanks to Tropical House keepers Nick Rowley, Jamie Brown and
Paul Round, without whose help we may not have succeeded in successfully
breeding these birds.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.324223">
Bibliography
</subsectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.847494444444445">
del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A. and Sargatal, J. (eds.). 1996. Handbook of the Birds of the World.
Volume 3 - Hoatzin to Auks. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona.
Thomas, B T., Strahl, S. D. 1990. Nesting Behavior of Sunbittems (Eurypyga helms&amp;apos;) in
Venezuela. The Condor 92,3:576-581. The Cooper Ornithological Society, University of
California Press.
Christopher Dunn BSc Hons Zoology, was at the time of the breeding,
Birds &amp; Tropical Keeper, Twycross Zoo, Atherstone, Warwickshire CV9 3PX,
UK. He now works at Birdworld, Holt Pound, Farnham, Surrey GUI 0 4LD,
UK. E-mail: Chrisdunnl987@hotmail.co.uk/Tel: 07413 522485.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.797109" genericHeader="method" page_id="56255224" page_num="83" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE MARABOU STORK
Leptoptilos crumeniferus
AT PAIGNTON ZOO ENVIRONMENTAL PARK
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.995244" page_id="56255224"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
83
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.963057" page_id="56255224"  page_num="83" year="" vol="">
by Peter Smallbones
The Marabou Leptoptilos crumeniferus is the largest member of the
Ciconiidae family. It stands from 115cm-152cm (approx. 3ft 10in-5ft tall),
has a wingspan of225cm-287cm (approx. 7ft 4in-9ft 4in) and weighs from
4kg-8.9kg (approx. 81bs 8ozs-191bs 6ozs). It is found in tropical Africa,
where it frequents open savannah, grassland and swamps and is also found
around fishing villages and rubbish dumps and abattoirs in towns and
cities.
The Marabou's diet consists of various small items of prey such as
locusts, snakes, fish and rats. However it is also capable of sometimes taking
adult Lesser Flamingos Phoenicopterus minor and even Greater Flamingos
P. roseus. It will also sometimes join vultures at kills. Carrion and waste
from the human population often makes up the majority of its diet and its
increasing numbers in the wild may be due to its willingness to exploit
rubbish dumped by humans.
The Marabou is bred in only a small number of EAZA (European
Association of Zoos and Aquaria) collections. The first recorded breeding
in the UK was at Blackbrook Zoological Park in 1999, which was described
by Malcolm Mycock in the Avicultural Magazine Vol. 106, No.4, pp.182-
184 (2000). In 2011 it was bred for the first time here at Paignton Zoo
Environmental Park.
Paignton's group consists of 2.2 Marabous. A male of approximately 26
years of age who was paired with a mature female of unknown age, which
first formed a pair bond in 2009 and had been observed mating. A younger
mature male of unknown age and a three years of age female make up the
group.
The group is housed in a new purpose-built aviary measuring
approximately 18m x 16m x 5m high (60ft x 52ft 6in x 16ft 6in high). The
roof of the aviary is 10cm (4in) gauge netting and the back of the aviary
incorporates part of the zoo's main lake. The aviary has several perches and
platforms at different heights which may be important in reducing aggression,
as dominant birds usually choose the highest perches. The grass roof of
the building (see below) also provides an elevated position on which the
birds can perch. Several large logs on the aviary floor provide perches for
pinioned birds and a tall evergreen Lonicera nitida enables a bird to quickly
put a barrier between itself and an aggressor - if necessary.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996396" page_id="56255225"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
84
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.919956" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255225" page_num="84" year="" vol="">
SMALLBONES - MARABOU STORK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994532375" page_id="56255225"  page_num="84" year="" vol="">
Forty days old.
The grass-roofed building has four doors and four stalls each measuring
2.25m x 2.4m (approx. 7ft Sin x 7ft 9in) divided by double mesh. These
dividers can, if need be, be removed to make the stalls larger. The four stalls
enable the Marabous to be housed separately at night during cold weather
and also enables them to be fed separately. The floor of each stall is covered
with wood shavings and has two bales of straw on which the birds roost.
The lighting in the building is controlled by a timer so that the birds can
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.737731" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255226" page_num="85" year="" vol="">
SMALLBONES - MARABOU STORK
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.973059" page_id="56255226"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
85
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.752419">
Young Marabou (on the right) at 89 days.
Fig. 1. Growth rate of Marabou chick measured at approximately weekly
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.923885166666667" page_id="56255226"  page_num="85" year="" vol="">
intervals.
have extra light and, in addition, a heat lamp in each stall provides heating
during the winter. Two air vents at the back of the building help ventilate
it when the birds are shut in.
Each bird is fed separately and gets half-a-dozen (6) day old, deyolked
chicks, 15-20 Sprats Sprattus sprattus and two chunks of meat cut into
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994076" page_id="56255227"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
86
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.922296" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255227" page_num="86" year="" vol="">
SMALLBONES - MARABOU STORK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998706097560976" page_id="56255227"  page_num="86" year="" vol="">
approximately 4cm x 4cm x 4cm (VAin x VAin x VAin) cubes. By feeding the
birds separately in the stalls keepers are able monitor their food consumption
and prevent a dominant bird from monopolising the choicest items of food.
This may also help to keep aggression levels down. Each bird quickly
chooses a favoured stall in which to roost and we have very few problems
when it comes to shutting them in at night.
The original pair was moved to the new aviary in the autumn (fall) of
2010. Both birds settled in well but at night were housed in separate stalls
due to the oncoming cold weather and to get them into a routine. At about
the same time, the young male and female were introduced to each other in
the zoo's off-show purpose-built stork/crane pairing aviary. This consists of
a house divided into two by a mesh divide and with an approximately 16m
x 15m x 4m high (52ft 6in x 50ft x 13ft high) outside aviary. The birds were
initially kept in separate stalls and allowed out separately. Windows in the
building allowed them to have constant visual contact with each other. After
a couple of weeks the birds were released together into the outside aviary
and monitored by a keeper during the day and housed in separate stalls at
night. The slow nature of the introduction seemed to lessen any aggression
which might have occurred between the two birds.
At the end of 2010 the new pair was moved to the new on-show aviary
but continued to be shut into separate stalls at night. The two pairs of
Marabous were then allowed out on alternative days. This enabled the new
pair to familiarize itself with the new surroundings at its own pace prior to
being introduced to the original pair.
In January 2011 the two pairs were slowly introduced to each other and,
although the introduction went well, they continued to be monitored. The
young female being the least dominant bird kept her distance from the other
three. The two males were, as expected, the dominant birds and would often
show slight signs of aggression, when they would occasionally snap at each
other, but this was to be expected.
In February 2011, however, the mature female began to show an interest
in the younger male and his aggression then increased towards the older male.
This aggression continued and the older male, who is pinioned, was unable
to manoeuvre quickly enough to stay out of harm's way and, therefore, for
his own safety the decision was taken to remove him from the aviary.
The newly dominant male was caught and one wing was clipped slightly
to slow him down and allow the females to stay one jump ahead of him as
he became increasingly more confident. He and the older female would
often bill-clap in unison and make high-pitched squealing calls affirming
their partnership. An assortment of different sized sticks were provided as
nesting material and, as the night-time temperature was rising, the pair was
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.751069" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255228" page_num="87" year="" vol="">
SMALLBONES - MARABOU STORK
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998425" page_id="56255228"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
87
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999075951219512" page_id="56255228"  page_num="87" year="" vol="">
allowed to remain together in the aviary throughout the day and night. The
young female, however, continued to be shut in her stall at night.
The male and the older female chose the top of the two bales of straw on
which to construct a nest measuring 100cm x 80cm x 20cm (approx. 3ft 3in
x 2ft IVi in x 8in), to which green leafy material was often added. One of the
partitions was removed to allow the pair more space and the following day,
April 5th 2011, an egg was laid on the nest. A second egg was recorded on
April 9th. Incubation was shared between the sexes, with the male possibly
spending slightly more time on the nest during the day. On the afternoon
of May 10th a chick was heard calling extremely loudly from inside one of
the eggs and, by May 11th, a chick had hatched.
Due to the young female's inquisitive behaviour and because it was
uncertain how much hostility would be shown towards her by the pair now
that the chick had hatched, the decision was taken on May 14th to remove
the young female from the aviary and house her with the original male.
When the chick was first hatched the pair was given chopped Sprats,
strips of meat, pinkie mice, strips of filleted Roach Rutilus rutilus , chopped
and skinned deyolked chicks with the legs and feet removed and chopped
whitebait, sprinkled with Witte Molen Calcicare 40+ supplement. Mice
fluffs were chopped up and added to the diet as the chick grew bigger and
the number of pinkies was reduced and replaced with skinned, crushed mice,
with the tail and feet removed. Nestlings cannot caste until approximately
20 days old, which is why the food was skinned, but after that the amount
of skin was slowly increased to prevent proventricular impaction.
Two bowls of food were placed in the house at 8.45am each day and a
third was placed there at approximately 4.30pm (16.30hrs). As the chick's
size increased the amount of food was increased to take account of this.
Whitebait, pinkies and mice fluffs were gradually phased out and the
amount of meat and mice was increased. Eventually all of the food was
fed whole.
Metabolic bone disease is a serious concern when rearing this species.
Therefore, as the chick was being reared inside the house, where exposure
to sunlight was minimal and it could not be detemined whether the parents
were feeding the chick the food to which the supplement had been added and
were not washing it off or eating the food themselves, on May 28th when
the chick was 17 days old, it was decided to weigh it once a week and hand-
feed it each day and also give it Mazuri(TM) Fish Eater Tablets and a pinch of
Nutrobal. It was given the recommended number of tablets according to its
weight using the guidelines on the website: www.mazuri.eu The chick was
quite feisty and would lunge at keepers during this process.
On the final occasion the chick was weighed, which was on July 16th,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.952562" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255229" page_num="88" year="" vol="">
SMALLBONES - MARABOU STORK
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999465" page_id="56255229"  page_num="88" year="" vol="">
it weighed 8kg (approx. 17lbs 6ozs) and was hand-fed fish eater tablets in
mice. At the same time six feathers were removed from its breast and sent
for DNA sexing. As keepers suspected, on account of the bird's large size,
this confirmed that it is a male. Thereafter the young Marabou caught food
thrown to it, to which the supplements had been added.
Although the female spent the greater amount of time rearing the chick,
both parents were very attentive towards it and both fed it and covered it.
Neither parent showed any aggression towards the keepers.
The chick was first seen standing on the nest at 40 days and fledged at
88 days. After having learned valuable social skills from its parents, the
young Marabou was removed from the aviary on December 7th 2011 when
it was aged 210 days. It was housed in the off-show pairing aviary with
the young female. They were, however, separated by a mesh divider. The
pairing process was about to begin again and, hopefully, the two will become
a second breeding pair.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.882429" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56255229" page_num="88" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.725487833333333" page_id="56255229"  page_num="88" year="" vol="">
I wish to thank Jo Gregson, Curator of Birds and the bird keeping staff
at Paignton, with a special mention for Head Keeper Ian Grant, Rob Peters
and Sam Gray, without whose efforts caring for these birds this success
would never have been achieved.
Products mentioned in the text
Nutrobal multivitamin powder: Vetark Professional, PO Box 60, Winchester, Hants S023 9XN,
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.897416666666667" page_id="56255229"  page_num="88" year="" vol="">
UK. Website: www.vetark.co.uk
Mazuri(TM) Zoo Foods Fish Eater Tablets: Mazuri(TM) Zoo Foods UK, PO Box 705, Witham, Essex
CM8 3TH, UK. E-mail: info@mazurifoods.com/Website:www.mazuri.eu
Witte Molen Calcicare 40+: Witte Molen, Moleneind 2, 4268 Meeuwen, Postbus 25, 4260 A
A Wijk en Aalburg, the Netherlands. Website: www.wittemolen.nl
Bibliography
</table>
<reference confidence="0.994548555555556">
Coles, D. 2001. Additions and Corrections to UK First Breeding Records. Avicultural
Magazine 107,3:125-135.
del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A., Sargatal, J. (eds.). 1992. Handbook of the Birds of the World, Vol.l
- Ostrich to Ducks. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona.
Mycock, M. 2000. The probable first UK breeding of the Marabou. Avicultural Magazine
106,4:182-184.
Peter Smallbones is Senior Head Bird Keeper at Paignton Zoo
Environmental Park, Totnes Road, Paignton, Devon TQ4 7EU, UK. E-mail:
Peter Smallbones@paigntonzoo. org. uk
</reference>
<page confidence="0.997311" page_id="56255230"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
89
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.899172" genericHeader="method" page_id="56255230" page_num="89" year="" vol="">
THE OPENING OF ANEW HUMMINGBIRD BREEDING
CENTRE TO MARK THE FIFTIETH ANNIVERSARY OF
WELTVOGELPARK WALSRODE
by Anne Hoppmann
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999235771428571" page_id="56255230"  page_num="89" year="" vol="">
At the end of 2011, thanks to the cooperation of a hummingbird breeding
centre at Trieste, in Italy, we received two species of hummingbirds for
our newly-designed hummingbird breeding centre here at Weltvogelpark
Walsrode. At the moment we have the Amazilia Hummingbird Amazilia
amazilia , which prefers habitats with scrub, xerophytic steppe, thorn forest
and desert areas and is also common even in parks and gardens in cities. The
male and female closely resemble each other in appearance.
The second species is the Green-tailed Trainbearer Leshia nuna , which
like the Amazilia Hummingbird is found in western South America, where
it lives in the Andean region at altitudes of up to 3,800m (approx. 12,500ft).
The male can be distinguished from the female (which otherwise looks very
similar) by his 10cm-12cm (approx. 4in-4%in) long, forked tail. This species
is rarely seen in zoos and in Germany can be seen only at Weltvogelpark
Walsrode.
To satisfy the special requirements of these birds, much thought went
into planning their housing. It is, for example, kept as sterile as possible,
as pathogens can pose a serious danger to hummingbirds. The temperature
and lighting are constantly controlled and the water used is specially filtered
and a sprinkler system has been adapted to the needs of the humingbirds
and helps regulate the humidity. The daytime temperature is maintained at
26*C (78.8*F). This is reduced to 17*C-20*C (62.6*F-68*F) at night. The
humidity is maintained at 60%-7Q%. The lighting is controlled automatically
and, to give the birds a good start to the day, shortly after 8.00am the basic
lighting is slowly increased and half-an-hour later UV daylight lamps are
turned on as well. Twelve hours later, shortly after 8.00pm (20.00hrs), the
lighting is gradually reduced over a period of one hour. During the night
the enclosures housing the birds are in complete darkness to ensure that the
birds get the necessary period of rest.
The birds are cared for all day by dedicated keepers who, because
scientific work and documentation are an important part of the work at
Weltvogelpark Walsrode, observe and record the behaviour of each bird. The
specially formulated nectar, which contains proteins, fats and carbohydrates,
plus vitamins, is prepared fresh twice daily. It is given to the birds in
free-hanging feeding tubes, which are filled with fresh nectar twice a day.
Hummingbirds need to feed on nectar every 45 minutes. During the breeding
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.992846" page_id="56255231"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
90
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.883369" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255231" page_num="90" year="" vol="">
HOPPMANN - HUMMINGBIRD BREEDING CENTRE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999270682926829" page_id="56255231"  page_num="90" year="" vol="">
season the hummingbirds are also offered fruit flies which they prefer for
feeding their offspring.
The breeding enclosures are densely planted and offer numerous hiding
places for these very sensitive birds. Fibres from the plants may be used for
nest building. In addition, silk and cotton threads are provided as nesting
material. It is important that none of the nesting material has been treated
with chemicals and that only clean, natural fibres are given to the birds.
The nests of the various species can differ a lot - in the wild the Amazilia
Hummingbird builds a cup-shaped nest made of plant wool and cobwebs
which it places on the upperside of a branch, whereas the nest of the Green-
tailed Trainbearer is made of mosses and rootlets and placed beneath an
overhang on a slope.
Most hummingbirds are very territorial and males and females are not
normally kept together. Some species, such as the Amazilia Hummingbird,
seem to be hardier and easier to keep than others. Consequently the Amazilia
Hummingbird is kept in some European zoos. The Green-tailed Trainbearer,
however, is more delicate and sensitive to changes in its environment. The
enclosures in the breeding centre have been designed so that each female
has her own enclosure and the males are housed in adjacent areas. The
male is only allowed to enter the female's enclosure when she is actively
building a nest. Following a successful pairing, the male is immediately
separated again and the female is left to concentrate on incubating the eggs
and caring for the young.
Following the opening in March 2012, visitors are able to experience the
exciting world of hummingbirds as well as visit our Kolibri-Haus beneath
the breeding centre. New educational signs and short films can be seen
and visitors can observe the birds at close quarters in enclosures specially
designed to resemble the hummingbird's natural habitat. If visitors watch
patiently for a while they may see a hummingbird hovering in front of a
feeding tube and sipping the nectar. When they are breeding, live images
from the breeding centre (which is located above the heads of the visitors)
show females building their nests, incubating their eggs or caring for their
young. A member of staff is always on hand to answer questions and tell
visitors interesting anecdotes and facts about the world of hummingbirds.
Our hummingbirds have now settled in quite well and the breeding season
has begun. At the moment one female is building a nest, while another is
incubating eggs. A chick hatched in mid-May in the nest of our hardest-
working female, who cares for her offspring very well. The staff are very
happy with the progress we are making and are looking forward to more
chicks hatching during the present breeding season.
Website :www. weltvogelpark. de/E~mail:anne. hoppmann@weltvogelpark. de
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996599" page_id="56255232"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
91
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9063504" genericHeader="method" page_id="56255232" page_num="91" year="" vol="">
FIRST RECORDED CASE OF ACTIVE NESTS OF THE
SCARLET MACAW Ara macao AND GREAT GREEN
MACAW Ara ambiguus IN THE SAME TREE IN TROPICAL
RAINFOREST IN CENTRAL AMERICA
by David Waugh
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994132470588235" page_id="56255232"  page_num="91" year="" vol="">
The tropical rainforest of the heterogeneous landscape of northern Costa
Rica has suffered major fragmentation and its ecological connectivity has
been seriously reduced. The National Mixed Wildlife Refuge Maquenque is
the last redoubt of the native range of the Endangered Great Green Macaw
Ara ambiguus in this northern zone. For several years Loro Parque Fundacion
(LPF) has been supporting the conservation of the Great Green Macaw,
through a project which is being conducted in Costa Rica and Nicaragua by
the Tropical Science Centre and El Rio Foundation. The Scarlet Macaw A.
macao remains relatively common and widespread in South America, but
capture, loss and fragmentation of its habitat have contributed to its decline
in Central America.
The populations of the Scarlet Macaw in Costa Rica are fragmented
and the species is considered to have disappeared from the Caribbean slope
in the 1950s. Only two Costa Rican populations are described, one in the
Osa Conservation Area which is estimated to number approximately 700
individuals and the other in the Central Pacific Conservation Area which
is estimated to number approximately 330 individuals. Observations,
however, indicate that the Scarlet Macaw population has experienced a
significant increase since 2003. The Great Green Macaw is limited to the
humid lowlands, where the project census conducted in 2009 in the San
Juan River basin, indicated a population increase in recent years, with the
average number of Great Green Macaws counted in Costa Rica being 302
individuals and a population of 532 individuals in Nicaragua.
The National Mixed Wildlife Refuge Maquenque is mostly tropical
rainforest with 3,000mm-3,600mm (approx. 118in-140in) of rainfall
distributed throughout the year. It has large trees such as the Almendro
Dipteryxpanamensis, which are up to 60m (approx. 196ft) tall, the Kapok
Ceiba pentandra and other trees that emerge above the canopy and provide
suitable cavities for nesting parrots. It is the only site in Costa Rica where
the two populations of macaws occur alongside each other. Sometimes
during the nesting season competition for nesting cavities in Almendro trees
is observed between pairs of both species, with the outcome usually being
that the Scarlet Macaws take ownership of the cavity.
In January 2011, however, Adolfo Gonzalez, manager of Laguna del
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994943" page_id="56255233"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
92
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.7006090625" page_id="56255233"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
WAUGH - SCARLET &amp; GREAT GREEN MACAWS
Lagarto Lodge, discovered an Almendro tree 100m (approx. 330ft) from the
edge of the forest in a clearing approximately 1,000m (3,280ft) in diameter,
with two active nests belonging to pairs of Great Green Macaws and an
active nest belonging to a pair of Scarlet Macaws. The project's researchers
reported (Chassot et al. 2011) that they visited the site in April 2011 and
confirmed the above findings. They found the tree, approximately 45m
(147ft) tall, in a state of deterioration, with many cavities in which several
pairs of Crimson-fronted Conures Aratinga finschi nested. The two nests
of the Great Green Macaws were at heights of 23m (approx. 75ft) and 24m
(approx. 78ft) and the Scarlet Macaw nest was at a height of 21m (approx.
68ft). The behaviour of the birds indicated that the pair of Scarlet Macaws
was rearing young, one of the pairs of Great Green Macaws had young and
the other pair was incubating eggs. The pairs showed no hostility towards
each other. Researchers had previously observed Almendro trees with several
active nests belonging to Great Green Macaws, but never one with pairs of
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.232579875" page_id="56255233"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
Great Green Macaws and a pair of Scarlet Macaws.
Reference
Chassot, O., Monge-Arias, G., Aleman-Zelaya, I. and Gonzalez-Tellez, A. 2011. Primer reporte
de un arbol con nidos activos de Guacamayo rojo {Am macao) y Guacamayo verde mayor (Am
ambiguus) en bosque muy humdeo tropical de Centroamerica. Zeledonia 15 (2).
Dr David Waugh is Director of Loro Parque Fundacion, Loro Parque, Tenerife, Canary
Islands, Spain. Website:www.loroparque-fundacion.org
* * *
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.625395" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255233" page_num="92" year="" vol="">
PEKIN ROBINS SEIZED IN BELGIUM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.968685125" page_id="56255233"  page_num="92" year="" vol="">
According to a report in a newspaper called The Journal May 31 st 2012,
p.37, sent to me by my good friend Richard Meyer who lives in north Devon,
154 Pekin Robins Leiothrix lutea and 54 chameleons seized from a dealer
by the Belgium authorities were sent to the UK and have been distributed
among several BIAZA (British &amp; Irish Association of Zoos &amp; Aquaria)
collections. Eight of the Pekin Robins and seven of the chameleons have
gone to Exmoor Zoo, north Devon, which also houses a number of the waders
which belonged to our late President, Raymond Sawyer.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997227" page_id="56255234"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
93
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9821565" genericHeader="method" page_id="56255234" page_num="93" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
TAKING OVER TOUCANS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.954583571428571" page_id="56255234"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
Following the death of John Ellis (see Obituary pp.95-96), Laura Gardner
is taking over as Coordinator of the Special Interest Group for toucans,
toucanets and ara 9 aris. In addition, Laura will continue as Coordinator for
the Special Interest Group for the Blue-crowned Laughingthrush Dryonastes
courtoisi. Please note that Laura's new e-mail address is:toucan 1 @hotmail.
co.uk. The full list of Special Interest Groups and the Coordinators can be
viewed on the society's website:www.avisoc.co.uk
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.763778" page_id="56255234"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.961755" genericHeader="method" page_id="56255234" page_num="93" year="" vol="">
SAVING THE BLACK-THROATED FINCH
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.972133423076923" page_id="56255234"  page_num="93" year="" vol="">
We are all aware of the threats to the Gouldian Finch Ery thrum gouldiae
(see Vol. 117, No. 1, pp.2-6 (2010)), but how many of us I wonder are aware
of the plight of the Black-throated Finch Poephila cincta - sometimes,
particularly in the past, also known as the Parson Finch on account of its
black bib (it also has a black bill)?
Its plight is highlighted in the latest issue of Australian birdlife Vol.l,
No.2, June 2012. There are two distinct subspecies, the northern black-
rumped subspecies P, c. atropygialis (Diggles's Finch) and the southern
white-ramped nominate subspecies P. c. cincta. The latter has disappeared
from up to 80% of its former range and apparently is no longer to be found
in New South Wales and has largely disappeared from southern and central
Queensland. This dramatic decline has been linked to large scale landscape
changes associated with agriculture and pastoralism. The latest threat,
however, comes from a proposed coal mining development, one of the largest
in the world covering almost 700,000 hectares (approx. 1,730,000 acres), in
the Galilee Basin in central Queensland, right in the middle of which is the
Bimblebox Nature Refuge, where the Black-throated Finch was discovered
recently - the most southerly record of the nominate subspecies in many years.
Urban expansion around Townsville threatens remaining key habitat.
Further information about the Black-throated Finch, management of its
habitat and the work of the Black-throated Finch Recovery Team can be
found by visiting the website:www.blackthroatedfinch.com
The annual Gouldian Finch census will take place at Wyndham, in the
eastern Kimberley region of Western Australia, during the first week of
September. Those taking part in the census will have a unique opportunity
to see Gouldian Finches in the wild, as well as Star Finches Neochmia
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.935709666666667">
ruficauda, Crimson Finches N. phaeton , Long-tailed P acuticauda and
Masked Grassfinches P. personata. Yellow-ramped Lonchura flaviprymna
and Chestnut-breasted Mannikins L. castaneothorax , Bicheno or Double-
</reference>
<page confidence="0.989392" page_id="56255235"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
94
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.667572" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255235" page_num="94" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.53483" page_id="56255235"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
barred Finches Taeniopygia bichenovii , Zebra Finches T. guttata and
Pectorella Finches Heteromuniapectoralis. Less than an hour's drive away
they may also succeed in seeing the lovely Painted Finch or Painted Firetail
Emblema pictum.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.54137" page_id="56255235"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.723693" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56255235" page_num="94" year="" vol="">
GRATIFYING SUCCESSES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987677714285714" page_id="56255235"  page_num="94" year="" vol="">
By April the breeding season was in full swing for many of the parrots
at Loro Parque, Tenerife. Amongst the first species to begin breeding is
always the Red-browed Amazon Amazona rhodocorytha. It is a species
whose breeding behaviour has been studied there for many years. Pairs kept
separately have never laid eggs, they only breed when housed in a group. Its
present group consists of four experienced breeding pairs (thought to be the
ideal number), which began breeding in early spring. The first eggs were
placed in an incubator and the first three chicks had hatched. Three of the
four females had already laid a second clutch of eggs, which the parents
were being left to incubate and rear the young. A second potential breeding
group, made up of Loro Parque-bred birds, is being established in a second
large aviary and it hopes to develop a long-term breeding programme for
this species, which is becoming increasingly rare in the wild. A pair of
Yellow-faced Amazons Alipiopsitta xanthops was raising a chick and a trio,
consisting of a male and two females, was getting along well and one of the
females was incubating a clutch of eggs.
During the past 10 years, the Blue-crowned Lorikeet Vini australis has
bred regularly at Loro Parque, which now has six pairs. However, some
of the pairs had repeatedly been producing infertile eggs, especially those
which could see other pairs in nearby aviaries. As soon as these aviaries
were screened from each other, two pairs promptly produced fertile eggs
and each of the pairs was rearing a chick.
A pair of Green-winged Macaws Ara chloropterus transferred from
public exhibition to the breeding station had raised two young. Three of the
parque's Poicephalus spp., the Senegal Parrot P senegalus , Brown-necked
Parrot P robustus fuscicollis and Brown-headed Parrot P. cryptoxyanthus
had reared young. The first two species have bred there regularly for many
years, but the Brown-headed Parrots had not bred for a number of years, so
this was a particularly gratifying success.
With the objective of getting the White-eared Conures Pyrrhura leucotis
emma breeding again, the three remaining birds, two males and a female,
were placed together in a new aviary. This seemed to do the trick, as five
young were being fed by all three adults. Also by May, a pair of Gang-gang
Cockatoos Callocephallon fimbriatum was incubating two eggs as was a pair
of Hyacinth Macaws Anodorhynchus hyacinthinus .
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994887" page_id="56255236"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
95
</page>
<author confidence="0.95964">
John Ellis, Senior Curator of Higher Vertebrates and Horticulture at the
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.818705">
Zoological Society of London (ZSL) - and an Avicultural Society Council
</affiliation>
<bodyText confidence="0.96969175" page_id="56255236"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
Member - collapsed during his presentation at the European Association
of Zoos and Aquaria (EAZA) workshop on zoo involvement in avian
conservation held at Weltvogelpark Walsrode in Germany. He was rushed
to hospital but died later. John was just 53 years of age.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9950885" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255236" page_num="95" year="" vol="">
OBITUARY
JOHN ELLIS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9970571" page_id="56255236"  page_num="95" year="" vol="">
Any attempt to classify John would be a taxonomic enigma, but I think,
the closest we might come to a parallel taxon would be that of the Shoebill
- big, bold, beautiful (in the eye of the beholder), something every aviculturist
wants and evolutionary distinct! It is also somewhat apt that it just happened
to be one of John's favourite birds.
John had a passion for birds, birdwatching, aviculture and almost
everything avian that was perhaps rivalled only by the late Jean Delacour and
Raymond Sawyer. It is not unreasonable to mention John's name amongst
some of these avian greats, as John was certainly one of the best modem
bird curators and aviculturists of our generation.
John's legacy is immense. He developed some wonderful avian
experiences with Penguin Beach at London Zoo encapsulating his vision
of combining spectacular displays of birds underpinned by solid mission
objectives and advanced welfare. John's brilliant animal training and
presentational skills ensured that his audiences left his animal demonstrations
with an inspired and increased appreciation of animals and nature. John
was a committed conservationist and his recent work with the Corncrake
and Asian vultures was an integral part of the success of these collaborative
projects.
Colleagues on these projects expressed their great admiration and respect
for his knowledge and skills. Perhaps one of John's greatest attributes was
his ability to inspire, teach and enthuse others. He had a willingness to share
his vast knowledge of birds. Many of us in the profession today valued the
mentoring and support that John provided. His teams and colleagues at ZSL
are greatly indebted to him.
John's career spanned some 37 years beginning as a bird keeper at Chester
Zoo in 1975, where he primed his talent for incubation and hand-rearing.
In April 1979, John moved to Jersey Wildlife Preservation Trust, which
gave him the chance to become involved in many of the breeding projects
for endangered species. Later, at Dr Henry Quinque's collection in France,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996361" page_id="56255237"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
96
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.979179" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255237" page_num="96" year="" vol="">
OBITUARY - JOHN ELLIS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998039096774194" page_id="56255237"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
John had the wonderful opportunity to work with Kagu and it was there that
he developed a lifelong love of hummingbirds, which led to his ambition to
establish a self-sustaining population of hummingbirds in EAZA zoos.
From France, John moved to Kelling Park Aviaries in Norfolk and then
in 1985 to Ocean World Rhyl. There John was able to indulge two of his
other passions, horticulture and sealions. Following a dalliance with the
commercial pet world, John moved to Chessington World of Adventures as
Senior Keeper in 1994. It was there that John honed his art of presentation
and produced one of the best zoo sealion demonstrations.
In December 2000, John became Curator of Birds at ZSL. He was
immensely proud to be following in the footsteps of some of the zoo's
previous avian experts. Under John's leadership it became a centre of
excellence for toucans and the recent breeding of sunbirds was of great pride
to John, who in 2006, was promoted to Senior Curator and also became
responsible for horticulture. This reflected another expert side to John whose
ability to blend aviculture and horticulture was remarkable.
John took on many roles in his career, including Studbook Keeper for the
Toco Toucan and various TAG (Taxon Advisory Group) chairs. He was also
an enthusiastic EAZA and BIAZA (British &amp; Irish Association of Zoos &amp;
Aquaria) colleague. For a period in the late 1990s he was chair of ABWAK
(Association of British Wild Animal Keepers). John was also a committed
supporter and member of the Avicultural Society.
All of us who knew John, who worked with him or who just shared
a few glorious moments of laughter with him will miss him deeply. Our
heartfelt thoughts go out to his wonderful family, his brilliant boys and his
devoted partner.
John's family have set up a charity page in memory of John on which
you can donate to one of his favourite projects - The Asian Vulture Recovery
Project in Nepal. Website:justgiving.com/In-Memory-of-John-Ellis
We have lost a giant of the bird world way too soon. Let us hope that
he is up there enjoying a G&amp;T with Raymond.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.929832666666667" page_id="56255237"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
David Field
Zoological Director
Zoological Society of London
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.594156" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56255237" page_num="96" year="" vol="">
IN MEMORY OF JOHN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.610505" page_id="56255237"  page_num="96" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society has made a donation of #200 (approx. US$300)
to the Asian Vulture Recovery Project in Nepal in memory of John Ellis.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997878" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56255238" page_num="" year="" vol="">
LONGEST LIVED PARROTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.925129375" page_id="56255238"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
In an attempt to overcome some of the difficulties scientists encounter
when trying to study the lifespans of wild parrots, Anna Young and her team
turned to ISIS (International Species Information System) and analysed the
records of more than 80,000 captive parrots on its global database, to see
what they could learn about the lifespans of these birds.
Their findings were published in PsittaScene, pp.12-15, May 2012.
The longest lived parrot they found was a Moluccan Cockatoo Cacatua
moluccensis that lived to be 92 years old. On the whole, however, parrots
were not as long-lived in captivity as Anna and her team expected. The
records of 260 species were analysed and only 11 other species besides the
Moluccan Cockatoo included an individual which lived longer than 50 years
in a zoo. Over half of the parrot species lacked an individual which lived
more than 22 years. Cockatoos had the highest average maximum lifespan,
but macaws and Amazons had higher average median lifespans. This means
that although cockatoos have the potential to live longer, many are not as
long-lived on average as some individual macaws and Amazons.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.928039" page_id="56255238"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
* The longest lived captive parrots (based on ISIS records), each with
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.987396166666667" page_id="56255238"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
an individual living 50 years or longer, are: Moluccan Cockatoo Cacatua
moluccensis , Leadbeater's or Major Mitchell's Cockatoo Lophocroa
leadbeateri , Sulphur-crested Cockatoo C. galerita , Roseate Cockatoo or
Galah Eolophus roseicapilla, Yellow-naped Amazon Amazona ochrocephala ,
Green-winged Macaw Ara chloroptera , Golden Conure Guaruba guarouba,
Ducorp's Corella C. ducorpsii , Red-tailed Black Cockatoo Calyptorhynchus
banksii , Military Macaw A. militaris, Hyacinth Macaw Anodorhynchus
hyacinthinus and Kea Nestor notablilis.
The current trend is for present day parrots to outlive those of previous
generations, indicating that the care of captive parrots is improving.
Unsurprisingly perhaps, the larger species of parrots generally live longer
than the smaller species.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.92055775" page_id="56255239"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Paultons Park -2011
by Geoff Masson.50
Long-lived Lories
by Rosemary Low.53
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.85873675" page_id="56255239"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The hand-rearing of three Dusky Lory Pseudeos fascata chicks
by Wolfgang Magnus, Janina Gerbatsch and Anne Hoppmann 55
The artificial incubation of the eggs and the hand-rearing of the
chicks of the Capuchinbird Perissocephalus tricolor
by Carolina M. Arruda.59
Breeding the Blue-crowned Motmot Momotus momota in France
by Patrick Chattier and Cedric Libert.63
The successful breeding of the Sunbittem Eurypyga h. helias
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.5382314" page_id="56255239"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Christopher Dunn.77
Breeding the Marabou Stork Leptoptilos crumeniferus
at Paignton Zoo Environmental Park
by Peter Smallbones.83
The opening of a new hummingbird breeding centre to mark the
Fiftieth Anniversary of Weltvogelpark Walsrode
by Anne Hoppmann.89
First recorded case of active nests of the Scarlet Macaw Ara macao
and Great Green Macaw Ara ambiguus in the same tree in tropical
rainforest in Central America
by David Waugh.91
News &amp; Views.93
Obituary
John Ellis.95
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
</figure>
</algorithms>
