<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<figure confidence="0.914060333333333" page_id="56500658"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
(o~7 I
A*lST
AVICULTURAL
MAGAZINE
VOLUME 109
No. 1
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990763" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500659" page_num="" year="" vol="">
THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991894571428571" page_id="56500659"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
The Avicultural Society was founded in 1894 for the study of British and
foreign birds in the wild and in captivity. The Society is international in
character, having members throughout the world.
Membership subscription rates per annum for 2003 as for 2002: British Isles
#18.00: Overseas #21.00 (plus #6.00 for airmail). (U.K. funds please). The
subscription is due on 1st January of each year and those joining the Society
later in the year will receive back numbers of the current volume of the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.583919" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500659" page_num="" year="" vol="">
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE..
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.966923181818182" page_id="56500659"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Enquiries regarding membership should be sent to:
THE MEMBERSHIP SECRETARY, Stewart Pyper, 21, Primrose Hill,
Nunney, Frome, Somerset BA11 4NP. Tel: 01373 836293
Subscriptions and other payments can be made direct to The Avicultural
Society Account, Lloyds TSB Bank PLC, 83 High Street, Sevenoaks, Kent
TN13 1LG, UK. Please quote Account No. 00003950; Sort Code:30 97 49;
and ensure you send your name as the account reference, or else we cannot
match payments.
Website: http://www.avisoc.co.uk
THE AVICULTURAL MAGAZINE welcomes original articles that have
not been published elsewhere and that essentially concern the aviculture of
a particular bird or group of birds, or that describe their natural history.
Articles should be preferably typewritten, with double spacing, and the
scientific names as well as the vernacular names of birds should be given.
References cited in the text should be listed at the end of the article. Line
drawings, black and white or colour photographs which illustrate a particular
point in the article will be used where possible and should be clearly
captioned. If authors wish their eventual return, they must say so when
submitting the article and write their name on the back of each photograph.
Tables and graphs will also be used wherever possible but authors should be
aware of the constraints of reproduction, particularly regarding the width of
the page which is 105mm.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998476" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500659" page_num="" year="" vol="">
ADDRESS OF THE EDITOR
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982477333333333">
Malcolm Ellis, Hon. Editor, The Avicultural Magazine, The Chalet, Hay
Farm, St. Breock, Wadebridge, Cornwall PL27 7LL, England.
E-mail: editor@avisoc.co.uk
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.819171" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500660" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Avicultural Magazine
THE JOURNAL OF THE AVICULTURAL SOCIETY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.396936" page_id="56500660"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Vol. 109 - No. 1 All rights reserved ISSN 0005 2256 2003
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.951098" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500660" page_num="" year="" vol="">
MANAGEMENT OF BUSTARDS IN CAPTIVITY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9738207" page_id="56500660"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
by Tom Bailey and Sara Hallager
Introduction
This article presents key facts for aviculturists who are working with
bustards maintained in breeding projects or zoological collections. Further
information on how to manage bustards in captivity may be found in the
publications listed in the references at the end of this article.
Bustards
The bustard family is made up of 25 species in 11 genera. Four species,
including the Great Indian Bustard Ardeotis nigriceps, are listed by the IUCN
(International Union for Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources)
Red List of Threatened Animals as Endangered. One species is listed as
vulnerable and an additional six are listed as near-threatened (del Hoyo et
al. 1996). Bustards are medium-sized to large terrestrial birds, inhabiting
chiefly open plains in arid or seasonally dry regions of the Old World.
Agricultural changes, overgrazing, hunting, trapping, habitat loss, droughts
and wars are the main threats to bustards (del Hoyo et al. 1996). In recent
years, there has been a surge of interest in the propagation of bustards in
captivity, in particular, the Houbara Bustard Chlamydotis undulata in the
Middle East and North Africa (Saint Jaime and Van Heezik, 1996). Similar
programmes for vulnerable and threatened species of bustards such as the
Great Bustard Otis tarda have been established in Europe and the former
Soviet Union as well as for the Kori Bustard A. kori in the USA. Programmes
with threatened bustard species aim to produce surplus birds for release into
protected areas, thereby supplementing declining wild populations, while
Houbara Bustard projects in the Middle East and North Africa aim to provide
surplus birds for sustainable hunting using falcons (Bailey et al. 1996).
Captive breeding programmes in the USA for Kori Bustards and the Buff-
crested Bustard Lophotis gindiana aim to maintain populations that are
genetically and demographically self-sustaining and do not rely on continued
imports from the wild (Hallager and Ballou, 2001).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.324724" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500661" page_num="2" year="" vol="">
BAILEY &amp; HALLAGER - BUSTARDS
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.4121385">
Husbandry
Housing
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995758913043478" page_id="56500661"  page_num="2" year="" vol="">
Differences exist in the housing of bustards both between and within
species and according to the region in which the birds are maintained in
captivity. In the Middle East, captive Houbara Bustards are managed in an
extreme climate outside of their natural breeding range, and they are
maintained in environmentally controlled buildings. In North Africa, where
captive Houbara are bred within their natural breeding range, birds are
maintained in outdoor aviaries. In the USA, Kori Bustards are maintained
in outdoor pens, which are equipped with heated sheds in which the birds
are housed in during periods of inclement winter weather. Smaller species
T. Bailey
Large natural-like aviary for Houbara Bustard.
such as the Buff-crested Bustard and White-bellied Bustard E. senegalensis
are kept in both indoor and outdoor aviaries and provided with supplemental
heat during the winter months if housed outdoors and/or moved into winter
holding facilities. The provision of shade and shelter are important for birds
managed outdoors in tropical and temperate climates respectively, as is the
use of predator-proof fencing. All species of bustard are susceptible to
frostbite and supplemental heat must be supplied when temperatures drop
below 4 Q C (39.2*F). Outdoor aviaries may have alfalfa beds in addition to
natural vegetation. This provides birds with cover in which to hide and also
encourages foraging for invertebrates attracted to the vegetation. Trauma is
an important cause of morbidity and mortality of all captive bustards, so
great attention is paid to using soft materials when pens are constructed. In
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.265768" page_id="56500662"  page_num="3" year="" vol="">
BAILEY &amp; HALLAGER - BUSTARDS
</equation>
<page confidence="0.961511" page_id="56500662"  page_num="3" year="" vol="">
3
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.989765487804878" page_id="56500662"  page_num="3" year="" vol="">
addition, pinioning of chicks or feather cutting (of the primaries) of adults
are important management tools to reduce the potential for self-inflicted
injuries. Pinioning of chicks is preferred as this eliminates the need to
routinely catch adults for feather-clipping. Strict biosecurity of large captive
breeding projects is an important issue. Smaller bustard species can be
exhibited in mixed aviaries. Kori Bustards should preferably be housed by
themselves to facilitate breeding, but if necessary, can be maintained in mixed
species exhibits with non-aggressive hoofstock (e.g. Gerenuk Litocranius
walleri or dik dik Madoqua spp.).
Diet and feeding
Bustards are opportunistic omnivores and in the wild the diet reflects
the local and seasonal abundance of plants and small animals, including
invertebrates and small vertebrates. Studies of gut contents have shown
that vegetation constitutes a significant proportion of the diet of some free-
living bustards (del Hoyo et al. 1996). However, studies of the gut contents
of Kori Bustards in Namibia have revealed mostly insects and very little
plant material (T. Osborne pers. comm.). In captivity, bustards are fed mice,
mealworms, crickets, apple, cabbage, chopped greens and either bustard
pellets, game bird pellets or a mixture of crane and ratite pellets (Sleigh and
Samour, 1996). Minced or ground beef can be used to replace mice or
mealworms if either component is unavailable. Kori Bustards in US zoos
are fed horsemeat in addition to mice and- the meat is supplemented with
either crane and ratite pellets or game bird pellets. The mixture is made into
small meatballs and hand-tossed to each bird. This method of feeding
facilitates close inspection of each bird as well as helping form a trust bond
between the keeper and each bird. Pinkie mice are fed to smaller species of
bustards, while fuzzie or adult mice are fed to the larger species such as
Kori Bustards.
Calcium carbonate may be added to the fresh food mixture to compensate
for the calcium imbalance that is caused by the addition of livefood/mince.
Multivitamin supplements (e.g. SA37 at Ig per 10kg body weight) are
provided to birds maintained in the Middle East (Sleigh and Samour, 1996).
Maintenance pellets (15% protein) are fed to birds outside the breeding season
and productioner pellets (20.5% protein) are fed during the breeding season
(Anderson, 1998; Sleigh and Samour, 1996).
Food is presented in plastic or aluminium food dishes either once or
twice a day. Water is provided ad lib. Additional livefood such as mealworms
or crickets may be supplemented as part of taming protocols to reduce keeper-
induced stress. To encourage natural foraging behaviour, supplement the
daily diet and provide a form of enrichment, chopped green beans, cherry
tomatoes, hard-boiled egg and blueberries are given twice a week to Kori
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.446773" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500663" page_num="4" year="" vol="">
BAILEY &amp; HALLAGER - BUSTARDS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.969478727272727" page_id="56500663"  page_num="4" year="" vol="">
Bustards.
Medication may be given to specific birds within favoured items such as
mice. Bustard chicks, like those of other long-legged species, are susceptible
to long-bone disorders and chick-rearing diets must be supplemented with
Vitamin D 3 (e.g. Neutrobal, Vetark). Angel wing is a common occurrence
with hand-reared Kori Bustard chicks, typically occurring at day 11-14.
Taping the affected primaries in a natural position at the first sign of the
outward turning will permanently correct the deformity. A definitive cause
of the problem has not been determined (Boylan et al. 2001).
A suitable way of holding smaller species such as the Buff-crested Bustard.
Capture
To avoid injuries correct methods must be used to catch and handle
bustards. For birds maintained in outside aviaries in the Middle East, as
well as North American zoos in the south-west, catching is carried out early
in the morning to reduce the risk of heat stress. In the Middle East
multivitamin solutions are given in the water before large catches to reduce
the potential for capture-related myopathies. The specific methods for
catching birds depend on the species, aviary size and the reason for catching
them (translocation, medication, artificial insemination). Single small to
medium-sized birds in small outside aviaries are caught with catching nets.
Single tame bustards in small indoor aviaries are caught by hand, after herding
the bird into a comer. Flocks of birds in large aviaries can be captured using
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.272356" page_id="56500664"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
BAILEY &amp; HALLAGER - BUSTARDS
</equation>
<page confidence="0.92035" page_id="56500664"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
5
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.960475368421052" page_id="56500664"  page_num="5" year="" vol="">
a catching corral. This is a blind-ended funnel with a wide mouth and a
circular catching area at the blind end. Small and medium-sized bustards
can be caught using nets in the blind end, while larger species like Kori
Bustards are caught by guiding them slowly into a darkened small shed,
cornering them and grabbing them by hand. Nets should not be used for
Kori Bustards.
Handling
Bustards should be held firmly against the handler's body, the wings
should be fully closed and the legs held together and prevented from rubbing
against each other by positioning one of the handler's fingers between the
legs. They can be held so that the legs are bent at the tibiotarsal joint. Some
movement of the leg is allowed without letting the bird kick uncontrollably.
Falcon hoods or cloth bags with holes for the nares can be used to calm
birds down although hand-reared birds may be more comfortable without
hoods. Birds should be kept as sternal as possible while being held as this
reduces stress levels.
Falcon hoods can be used to calm birds down.
Positioning a Finger between the legs prevents the
legs rubbing against each other.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.954005" page_id="56500665"  page_num="6" year="" vol="">
6
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.656533" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500665" page_num="6" year="" vol="">
BAILEY &amp; HALLAGER - BUSTARDS
Transportation
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985264269230769" page_id="56500665"  page_num="6" year="" vol="">
Small bustards (up to 2 kg) can be transported in commercial pet carriers
or cardboard boxes. Larger bustards, such as Kori Bustards can be transported
individually in transport crates. Crate requirements for all bustard species
can be found in the International Air Transport Association manual (IATA,
1998).
Individual identification
Bustards in captivity can be individually identified by using coloured
plastic rings with engraved coding attached above the tibiotarsal joint for
visual identification of individuals in pens. Birds are also identifiable by
means of a subcutaneous passive induced transponder (PIT), which is placed
in the inner crural region of the leg.
Routine health care
Bustards in the Middle East have succumbed to a variety of diseases,
notably trichomoniasis, Newcastle disease and avian pox. Preventive
medicine programmes include annual vaccination with inactivated Newcastle
disease vaccine, live canary pox vaccine and regular (two to three times a
year dependant on risk) anthelmintic and antiprotozoal medication given in
the water or food. Vaccines are given during health assessment catches held
one to two months before the breeding season and during the cool season in
the Middle East. In the USA, internal parasites are seen occasionally and
avian pox has been reported in two chicks. Vaccines are not routinely
administered in the USA. Kori Bustards in zoo settings need to be monitored
carefully for signs of impaction and zinc toxicity as they have a particular
tendency to consume items thrown into their enclosures by visitors (e.g.
coins, camera batteries, nails, etc). Daily inspection of pees and the removal
of foreign material are very important.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.9039385">
Breeding Management
Sexing
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997473444444445" page_id="56500665"  page_num="6" year="" vol="">
Bustards show sexual dimorphism (see Table 1). Some smaller species
such as the White-bellied Bustard can be sexed by differences in head and
throat plumage. Larger species, such as the Kori Bustard, are easily sexed
at one year of age, for although the plumage of both sexes is similar, males
are considerably larger. Juvenile bustards can also be sexed using endoscopy
after about six months of age. Genetic sexing offers many advantages, being
non- invasive and if done from feathers or blood collected from freshly
hatched chicks, it can allow different sexes to be reared under different
protocols.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.269991" page_id="56500666"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
BAILEY &amp; HALLAGER - BUSTARDS
</equation>
<page confidence="0.989531" page_id="56500666"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
7
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.98671">
Table 1. Adult body weight of bustards.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.952099603773585" page_id="56500666"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
Species
a* (kg)
9 (kg)
Great Bustard Otis tarda
6-8.5
3.8-4.5
Kori Bustard Ardeotis kori struthinuculus 1
10-18
6-7
Kori Bustard Ardeotis kori kori 2
7-14
3-6
Houbara Bustard Chlamydotis undulata
1.5-2.5
0.8-1.4
White-bellied Bustard Eupodotis senegalensis
1.0-1.3
0.9-1.1
Buff-crested Bustard Lophotis gindiana
0.4-0.8
0.4-0.6
1 subspecies maintained in US zoos
2 subspecies maintained in the Middle East
Breeding strategies
Bustards are K-selected species - long-lived and with a low reproductive
output (del Hoyo et al 1996). Management strategies for breeding vary
according to the species but there are basically three regimes (see Table 2).
Table 2. Examples of breeding strategies.
Strategy
Species
Age
Social Grouping
Isolated for artificial
insemination
Houbara
Adult
Juvenile
Singles
Small groups (&lt;5)
Pairs
White-bellied
Adult
Juvenile
Pairs
Small groups (&lt;5)
Heterosexual groups
Kori
Adult
Adult
Juvenile
Large group (~25)
Trio or 2.3
Large group (--15)
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.9953751" page_id="56500666"  page_num="7" year="" vol="">
In most species, males and females do not establish a true pair-bond,
and depend instead on a dispersed lek breeding system in which the males
advertise themselves in traditional areas. Male bustards perform elaborate
displays to attract females and maintain a dominance hierarchy. The females
are left alone to undertake the nesting, incubation and rearing of the young.
In captivity, Houbara Bustards managed as pairs or as mixed sex groups
rarely, if ever, breed. Similarly, Houbara Bustards caught as adults remain
sensitive to stress and in most cases fail to breed. Successful Houbara Bustard
breeding projects use hand-reared birds, which are more suitable for intensive
production efforts utilizing artificial insemination. White-bellied Bustards
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.548111" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500667" page_num="8" year="" vol="">
BAILEY &amp; HALLAGER - BUSTARDS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9669111875" page_id="56500667"  page_num="8" year="" vol="">
are monogamous and adults are maintained in pairs. Kori Bustards are
managed in mixed-sex flocks, but can be managed as trios. Intraspecific
aggression can occur between pairs of Buff-crested Bustards (cf-9) and male
Kori Bustards (cf-cf) in the breeding season so care needs to be taken when
there are changes to group structure. Adult male Kori Bustards may require
physical and visual separation during the breeding season to prevent
aggression and physical injuries (Boylan et al. 2001).
End-piece
Species such as the Houbara are in the early stages of domestication, with
the objective to produce large numbers for managed hunting. Other species,
e.g. Great Bustard and Kori Bustard, are maintained in captivity for
conservation objectives. The successful breeding of all species is being
held back because of the poor understanding of nutritional requirements
and high levels of infertility and chick mortality. An expansion of the
knowledge base is needed if advances in the husbandry and medical
management of these birds are to be made.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.897009" genericHeader="references" page_id="56500667" page_num="8" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.852184428571429">
Anderson, S. 1998. Captive management and breeding of the kori bustard, white-bellied bustard
and rufous-crested bustard at the National Avian Research Center. External Report No. 3.
Bailey, T.A., Samour, J.H., Cooper, J.E. and Cromie, R.L. 1996. Veterinary considerations of
houbara bustard captive breeding and restoration programs in the Middle East. Journal of
Avian Medicine and Surgery 10: 268-277.
Boylan, J., Hallager, S. and Cramm, A. 2001. Update on Husbandry Guidelines for Kori Bustards
(.Ardeotis kori). 2001 AZA Conference Proceedings.
del Hoyo, J., Elliott, A. &amp; Sargatal, J. 1996. Handbook of Birds of the World. Vol. 3 Hoatzin to
Auks. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona.
Hallager, S. and Ballou, J. 2001. 2001 North American Population Management Plan for the
kori bustard. Smithsonian National Zoological Park.
IATA 1998. Live animal regulations, 25th Edition, International Air Transport Association,
Geneva. Webpage:http://www.iata.org/index.asp
Saint Jaime, M. &amp; Van Heezik, Y. 1996. Propagation of the houbara bustard. Kegan Paul
International, London.
Sleigh, I. &amp; Samour, J.S. 1996. The National Avian Research Center Bird Care Manual National
Avian Research Center Internal Research Report No. 41. Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates.
Dr Tom Bailey has returned recently to the United Arab Emirates.
E-mail: drtombailey@hotmail.com
Sara Hallager is at the Smithsonian National Zoological Park,
Washington DC 20008-2598, USA. E-mail: shallager@nzp.si.edu
</reference>
<page confidence="0.967075" page_id="56500668"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
9
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.867062" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500668" page_num="9" year="" vol="">
WONGA SUCCESS
by Louise Peat
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994394842105263" page_id="56500668"  page_num="9" year="" vol="">
The Wonga Pigeon Leucosarcia melanoleuca is endemic to Australia,
where it is found mainly on the east coast. A plump bird that spends a lot of
time on the ground where it forages for fruits, seeds and insects, it is renowned
for its far-carrying and monotonous call.
At the Cots wold Wildlife Park, Oxon., UK, we have kept Wonga or
Wonga Wonga Pigeons (as they are also known) since 1998. A pair was
kept initially in our walk-through aviary, in which the pair made a wonderful
display, but failed to breed. Several months later we lost the female to a
Stoat Mustela erminea , after which the male was moved to a more secure
aviary while the Stoat problem was resolved.
We decided that more birds and a change of aviary could prove fruitful,
so in October 2000 five more Wonga Pigeons arrived. The old male and the
five new birds were placed together in an aviary on the Pheasant Section.
They mixed together well without any aggression being shown by any of
the six birds. A choice of nesting places was offered including baskets,
roofed boxes and open-roofed boxes. The open-roofed boxes were favoured,
as the birds seemed more secure in these. Nest material in the form of long
slender twigs were eagerly snatched up as soon as they were placed on the
aviary floor.
Our first egg was laid in June 2001 but it was clear, as were those of the
first three clutches; then in August, after sitting for the full incubation period,
both adults were seen away from the nest and made no attempt to return.
The nest was checked and two eggs were found, one was clear, the other
had a chick half way out of the shell. The chick was warmed up and helped
out of the shell. Hand-rearing was attempted but the chick survived for
only three days. Eggs continued to come, but were abandoned and with bad
weather on the way, it was decided to try foster-rearing using Barbary Doves
Streptopelia roseogrisea (dom.). These had been set up for our pair of Pink
Pigeons Nesoenas mayeri and, at that time, had successfully reared both
Pink Pigeons and Crested Pigeons Ocyphaps lophotes. Wonga Pigeon eggs
are slightly larger than Pink Pigeon eggs, so initially there was concern that
they might be unable to turn the Wonga Pigeon eggs, however, this concern
proved unjustified. The Barbary Doves did a wonderful job, but most of the
eggs proved to be clear, until in October when the first chick hatched.
Unfortunately, I had set up the Barbary Doves to synchronise with the 16-
18 day incubation period given by Gibbs et al. (2001). The chick hatched
on the 19th day and therefore missed the crucial first three days of crop
milk. As a result the chick was very small and died 10 days later. The
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.990321" page_id="56500669"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
10
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.749004" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500669" page_num="10" year="" vol="">
PEAT - WONGA PIGEON
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.970529894736842" page_id="56500669"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
majority of chicks which followed hatched after a 19 day incubation period,
with just one hatching after 18 days.
Our luck changed with the third chick, which hatched February 28th, for
this was the first to be successfully reared by foster parents. Two more
chicks hatched, one of which died a few days later. Hatched on April 17th,
the sixth chick, was found abandoned and almost dead 10 days later. The
chick was warmed in an incubator and after some liquid food its head was
up and its breathing was back to normal, so the decision was taken to
introduce it back to the Barbary Doves. The foster parents went straight
back to it and all seemed well. However, the following morning the chick
was again alone on the nest and had an empty crop, therefore we were left
with little choice but to attempt to hand-rear it.
Hand-rearing pigeons from day one is notoriously difficult, and few
attempts are successful. Although we had tried this with several species, we
had succeeded only once, when we managed to hand-rear a Pied Imperial
Pigeon Ducula bicolor. The situation with the Wonga Pigeon was very
different; at 11 days old it had already got past the most difficult stage and,
providing it did not have an infection, we felt we had a good chance of
pulling it through.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.95589">
Table 1. Diet covering the period day 11 - day 62.
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.9809233" page_id="56500669"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
Day
Weight
Diet
11
72g
Very watery Milupa, thickened through the day.
A pinch of Nutrobal added to each feed.
12
73g
Boiled egg yolk and crushed soaked millet.
Probiotic added every other feed.
16
110g
Soaked super com pellets added.
19
138g
Feeds reduced to six a day.
30
236g
Chick fledged.
</figure>
<page confidence="0.932728" page_id="56500669"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
31
</page>
<table confidence="0.2906385" page_id="56500669"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
244g
Barbary Dove introduced to encourage self-feeding.
</table>
<page confidence="0.80499" page_id="56500669"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
33
</page>
<figure confidence="0.833159823529412" page_id="56500669"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
259g
Seen pecking at food. Feeds reduced to five a day.
40
292g
Feeds reduced to four a day.
41
299g
Seen eating for the first time.
45
306g
Feeds reduced to three a day. Eating much more by himself.
52
327g
Feeds reduced to two a day
56
335g
Feeds reduced to one a day
</figure>
<page confidence="0.568603" page_id="56500669"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
62
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.924266857142857" page_id="56500669"  page_num="10" year="" vol="">
348g
Feeds stopped. Bird putting on weight by himself.
The chick was fed at two to three hourly intervals, receiving seven feeds
a day between 6.00am - 10.00pm. Many attempts were made to feed the
chick with a spoon, but this resulted in a huge mess and very little food
going down into the crop. Even though the chick looked keen, at no stage
did it attempt to gape for food (in hindsight I believe this may have been the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.403959" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500670" page_num="11" year="" vol="">
PEAT - WONGA PIGEON
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999162" page_id="56500670"  page_num="11" year="" vol="">
11
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998858235294118" page_id="56500670"  page_num="11" year="" vol="">
reason why the chick was rejected by the foster parents).
The syringe was placed at the side of the beak and a small amount of
food was squeezed into the mouth, then the syringe was withdrawn to allow
the chick to swallow the food. The chick grew steadily and fledged at 30
days old. The following day, to try to encourage weaning, a Barbary Dove
was placed with the chick. I also began to reduce the feeds in order to keep
the chick keen. Weaning was a slow process and the chick was 62 days old
before it was fully weaned.
After rearing, the chicks were all kept together in a creche along with
two Crested Pigeons reared by foster parents. All were later placed with
other collections, apart from the hand-reared Wonga Pigeon which has been
placed in our mixed group so that we can monitor its behaviour and find out
if having been hand-reared affects its ability to breed successfully.
On May 15th the adults sat on two eggs for the 19 days incubation period,
but unfortunately both were found to be infertile. They laid their tenth clutch
on May 27th and sat tight throughout the incubation period. A week later
they were still sitting tight but with no sighting of a chick I started to lose
hope. Then on June 19th I was thrilled to see a squab being fed on the nest.
The chick fledged on June 30th. In immaculate condition, it had taken 17
days to fledge and had done so at a much earlier age than those reared by
foster parents. At the time of writing (early September 2002) they are rearing
a second chick, bringing the total to five chicks bred so far this year. The
hope now is that the adult birds will continue to rear their own young.
It has been a wonderful experience having the opportunity to observe all
three methods of rearing in the space of one year, especially as with the
exception of the one we are keeping, the others were all snapped up by other
collections, which makes all the hard work even more worthwhile. The
Wonga Pigeon is a delightful species and although not endangered the
experience gained breeding it may prove helpful when breeding more
vulnerable pigeon species. I cannot express how thrilling it is to see a chick
hatch under a foster parent, and to everyone who keeps pigeons, I would
recommend always having a few pairs of Barbary Doves on standby. They
have proved their worth over and over again here at the Cotswold Wildlife
Park and, I am sure, will continue to do so.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.983328" genericHeader="references" page_id="56500670" page_num="11" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.982505428571429">
Gibbs, D., Bames, E. and Cox, J. 2001 . Pigeons and Doves - A Guide to Pigeons and Doves of
the World. Pica Press, East Sussex, UK.
del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A. and Sargatal, J. (eds.). 1997. Handbook of the Birds of the World. Vol.
4. Sandgrouse to Cuckoos. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona, Spain.
Louise Peat is a bird keeper at the Cotswold Wildlife Park, Burford,
Oxon., 0X18 4JW, UK. Tel:01993 823006/Fax: 01993 823807/Website: www.
cotswoldwildlifepark.co.uk
</reference>
<page confidence="0.991818" page_id="56500671"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
12
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.980573" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500671" page_num="12" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE CHESTNUT-TAILED MINLA
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.965824820512821" page_id="56500671"  page_num="12" year="" vol="">
Minla strigula
by Neil Owen
The Chestnut-tailed Minla is a very lively and attractive babbler,
approximately 15cm (6in) long, found from the north-western Himalayas,
eastwards through countries including Myanmar (Burma), Malaysia,
Thailand and Laos, to western China (King, Dickinson &amp; Woodcock, 1975).
Its crown is a bright chestnut colour and can be raised to form a small crest
when the bird is excited (which is most of the time). There is a bright
yellow spot under the beak and the throat has black and white scaly markings.
The underparts are yellow, which can vary in brightness from bird to bird.
The back and rump are greenish grey and the wings are a colourful mix of
orange and black stripes. The tail is bright chestnut with yellow and black
on the edges.
I bought what I hoped was a pair in March 1998, choosing the brightest
and the dullest coloured birds in the hope this might be a sexual difference.
They were in excellent condition and as the weather was mild I decided to
put them straight into a large planted flight. It has a shelter with a night
light, and can be heated, but the birds preferred to roost out in the flight.
This is approximately 6m x 2.5m x 2m (20ft x 8ft x 6ft 6in). The roof has
clear Perspex (Plexiglas) sheeting along most of its length and also along
one side, to protect the occupants from strong winds and driving rain. The
flight is planted with various small conifers as well as climbing plants such
as honeysuckle and ivy. As the birds are keen bathers, there is a small
concrete pool at one end. The aviary also housed a pair of White-collared
Yuhinas Yuhina diademata and a pair of Omei Shan Liocichlas Liocichla
omeiensis. All six birds seemed to get on well and would come down together
to fresh bath water or to investigate a new perch.
They were fed the same diet I give all small softbills, this consists of a
fine grade universal mixture, to which is added finely chopped pear, grapes,
tomato, banana, etc. Occasionally other items were added such as mashed
hard-boiled egg or brown breadcrumbs. Half an orange spiked on a perch
was also popular. A few small mealworms or crickets were added to the
mixture and the minlas were always first to investigate these. I placed various
nest-boxes in different parts of the aviary and as I did this the minlas followed
me around watching with interest. In late March, I was surprised to see a
small nest had been made entirely from coconut fibre inside a wicker basket
low down in a conifer bush. A couple of days later when I went to change
the bath water, one of the minlas hopped out of the bush and I could see two
bright blue eggs with dark spots at one end. On April 15th there were three
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.497181" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500672" page_num="13" year="" vol="">
OWEN - CHESTNUT-TAILED MINLA
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999276" page_id="56500672"  page_num="13" year="" vol="">
13
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999210942857143" page_id="56500672"  page_num="13" year="" vol="">
eggs and, despite a heavy snowfall, the birds sat tight. All three eggs hatched
and the birds seemed model parents, taking it in turns to brood the young
and chasing away any other birds which came too close.
The chicks were being fed on small waxworms and white mealworms.
The weather was too cold to find much livefood in the garden. When they
were a week old all three chicks were found dead on the floor beneath the
nest. I suspected one of the other birds might have been responsible, so I
decided to move the yuhinas and liocichlas to another aviary.
The minlas set about re-lining the nest and were soon sitting on two
more eggs. Unfortunately, on the day they were due to hatch, both eggs
were thrown out. The pair spent the rest of the summer half-heartedly
carrying bits of nest material but nothing more came of it.
The following year, 1999, began in a similar fashion. A nest was built in
the same place early in April. One egg was thrown out but then three more
were laid and after about 14 days all three hatched. The weather was warmer
than it had been the previous year and I was able to gather a variety of
livefood from the garden, including spiders and greenfly (aphids), which I
used to supplement the mealworms and crickets. Sadly, this was still not
enough and two of the chicks were found dead on the floor. The third chick
was still alive, so I took it indoors and attempted to hand-rear it, but it died
the first night.
Although I was getting more and more frustrated, the minlas did not
seem bothered and in mid-June went to nest again. Three eggs were laid,
and all three hatched, but two of the chicks were ejected. For some unknown
reason the pair decided to do the job properly and, to my great relief, the
third chick was reared to independence.
On leaving the nest, it was a duller version of the adults, being mainly
grey/green but with the distinctive bright chestnut and yellow tail. When I
was sure it could feed itself, the youngster was moved to another flight and
housed with some other young softbills.
The adult pair went on to have yet another clutch, but just when I thought
I had 'cracked it', the two chicks were found dead in the nest. They were 10
days old.
I found Chestnut-tailed Minlas fascinating and lovely birds to keep, but
breeding them successfully is certainly a challenge.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.61904" genericHeader="keywords" page_id="56500672" page_num="13" year="" vol="">
Reference
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.996555">
King, B. F., Dickinson, E. C., Woodcock, M. W. 1975. A Field Guide to the Birds of South-
East Asia. Collins, London.
Neil Owen lives in Carmarthenshire, Wales. Tel: 01558 668336.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998927" page_id="56500673"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
14
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.86439825" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500673" page_num="14" year="" vol="">
BREEDING AND HAND-REARING THE BLUE-WINGED
LEAFBIRD Chloropsis cochinchinensis AT THE
RIVERBANKS ZOO AND GARDEN
by Angela Hardy
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991412942857143" page_id="56500673"  page_num="14" year="" vol="">
Leafbirds are fairly common in the wild, inhabiting India and south-east
Asia, including Sumatra, Java, Borneo and the Philippines. All eight species
are varying shades of green with medium-sized wings and tails. Throughout
their range, these beautiful songbirds often frequent orchards and gardens,
searching for an easy source of soft fruits and nectar-filled blooms. Leafbirds
also spend a lot of time searching branches and acrobatically peering under
leaves for insects and larvae. Even though they are common in the wild,
leafbirds are rare in captivity (in the USA), and are almost never bred
successfully.
Aviary
The Blue-winged Leafbirds at the Riverbanks Zoo are housed in one of
several large, mixed-species aviaries within the new Bird House. The
leafbirds' aviary is 25ft long x 15ft wide x 30ft high (approx. 7.6m long x
4.5m wide x 9m high). All of the exhibits are covered by a glass roof allowing
them to be brightly lit with natural light. In addition, the exhibits are equipped
with metal halide and fluorescent lights to supplement the natural light on
cloudy days. Some of these are also used after dark as night lights.
The exhibit is thickly planted with species, such as the Golden Rain
Tree Koelreuteria paniculata. West Indian Cedar Cedrela odomta and a
variety of Ficus spp. commonly found in Asian rainforests. Many of the
trees are at least 20ft (6m) tall and provide excellent nest sites for small
passerines such as leafbirds. The exhibit floor is covered with natural mulch
that is both aesthetically pleasing and ideal for the terrestrial birds such as
the Hooded Pittas Pitta sordida and Indian Pygmy Geese Nettapus
coromandelianus. The exhibit features a shallow pool surrounded by leafy
plants and overhanging branches which the leafbirds regularly use when
bathing. The aviary offers plenty of privacy, as only the bottom 7ft (2.1m)
of the front is exposed to the public. Viewing is through a fine, stainless
steel mesh (ZooMesh(TM)) which is almost invisible when painted black.
Other inhabitants of the exhibit include Fairy Bluebirds Irena puella,
Lesser Green Broadbills Calyptomena viridis, Pin-tailed Nonpareil Parrot
Finches Erythrura prasina , Dhyal Thrushes or Magpie Robins Copsychus
saularis and a Luzon Bleeding Heart Gallicolumba luzonica. All of these
species coexist very well. In fact, the Fairy Bluebirds, Hooded Pittas and
Blue-winged Leafbirds breed simultaneously without any problems. The
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.428002" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500674" page_num="15" year="" vol="">
HARDY - BLUE-WINGED LEAFBIRD
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.988882" page_id="56500674"  page_num="15" year="" vol="">
15
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.990483775" page_id="56500674"  page_num="15" year="" vol="">
leafbirds, however, are very protective of their nesting area and will
aggressively chase away other birds.
Diet
By volume, the diet consists of 55% chopped fruit, 25 % Tropical Bits
and 20% Red Apple Jungle pellets that are softened briefly in water. All
three ingredients are mixed together and offered in the same dish. A
proprietary nectar - Nekton Lory(TM) - is offered in a separate dish. Waxworms
(waxmoth larvae), small mealworms, and lin (25mm) crickets are also
provided. To make the insects more nutritious, the crickets and mealworms
are fed romaine lettuce, carrots, sweet potato and Layena poultry meal for
several days before use. The high calcium content of the poultry meal helps
to correct the inverted c.ak tum-to phosphorous ratio. If left uncorrected,
the high level of phosphorous could lead to a calcium deficiency, especially
in chicks which live almost entirely on insects for the first few days of life.
In addition, all insects are lightly dusted before use with laboratory grade
calcium.
Orange slices are skewered onto perches for the birds to eat during the
day. Normally, these hold little interest for the leafbirds but are eaten
consistently during the breeding season. Indeed, the increased consumption
of orange seems to precede breeding activity and is followed by courtship
behaviour. We have also noticed this phenomenon in our Crested
Oropendolas Psarocolius decumanus and Troupials Icterus icterus. Perhaps
these birds are unable to manufacture vitamin C and not only need regular
amounts of dietary vitamin C, but need it in increased levels in order to
achieve breeding condition. Avieulturists traditionally shy away from feeding
orange due to its acidic content and its implicated role in promoting iron
storage disease. While feeding an excess of any natural food is risky (since
no natural food is a complete diet) it is reasonable to feed a small amount of
most fruits to all fruit-eating birds. Occasionally, an interesting observation
will result such as this apparent correlation between the increased
consumption of orange and increased breeding activity.
Nest site
The Blue-winged Leafbirds built small cup-shaped nests. While the
outer dimensions varied depending on the chosen nest site and materials
used, the inner dimensions were fairly constant, being 5.5cm (approx.
2 74no across and 3.5cm (not quite 1 Am) deep. The female chose the nest
sites and did most of the building. Materials included burlap strings, sisal
rope fibres and palm fibres. We cut the sisal rope into 12in (approx 30cm)
lengths and separated it into loose fibres. This was the female&amp;apos;s favourite
material and was used to line the nests. To encourage nesting behaviour
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.982323" page_id="56500675"  page_num="16" year="" vol="">
16
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.468871" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500675" page_num="16" year="" vol="">
HARDY - BLUE-WINGED LEAFBIRD
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.366649">
Martin Vince
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999438916666667" page_id="56500675"  page_num="16" year="" vol="">
The nest is well camouflaged and constructed of plant fibres,
burlap strings and sisal rope.
these materials were placed in an old cup nest. The female quickly 'stole'
the materials from this site. If the materials were simply scattered around
the aviary perches, she ignored them.
The pair nested in thick foliage 10- 14ft (approx 3m-4m) above the ground.
They almost always built in the West Indian Cedar in the centre of the exhibit,
where the top of the tree was in the direct airflow from a vent. This caused
the leaves to move in the breeze. As this tree had no real branches, only
long branch-like leaves, it was too weak to support even a tiny nest. The
female tried several times to build a nest, but each time the leaves collapsed.
When a small, wicker canary nest cup was added at her chosen site, she
immediately built her nest inside it. The male was very excited during the
building process. He called constantly and frequently would sit in the nest
while she was away. When he did this, however, the female became very
agitated and quickly returned to the nest, whereupon the male left. The
female worked diligently on the nest, but would stop to solicit copulations.
She did this by landing near the male, singing and shaking vigorously. They
copulated multiple times during the three days it took her to build the nest.
Most of these copulations appeared to be false, as the birds did not properly
align their vents. In retrospect, they were probably just part of the courtship.
Within two days of finishing the nest, the female laid two eggs and began
incubating alone. The male sat nearby and chased off any onlookers that
came too close, most often the female Lesser Green Broadbill. The male
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.429441" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500676" page_num="17" year="" vol="">
HARDY - BLUE-WINGED LEAFBIRD
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998975" page_id="56500676"  page_num="17" year="" vol="">
17
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998159166666667" page_id="56500676"  page_num="17" year="" vol="">
leafbird brought food for the incubating female, but she always left the nest
to accept it. Whenever she left to eat, he would become very agitated. He
would fly to the nest, call, and if she did not quickly return, he would sit on
the eggs. This always attracted her attention and she would immediately
chase him away. The male never tried to damage the eggs or chicks, and
eventually was allowed more contact with the young.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.575445">
Eggs and Chicks
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.988479" page_id="56500676"  page_num="17" year="" vol="">
In a total of six clutches, two eggs were laid in every clutch. The eggs
are a glossy cream colour, wreathed with purplish scrawls around the air
cell line (at the blunt end). Dimensions are as follows: 24mm long x 15mm
at the widest point. Each is laid on consecutive days, with incubation starting
after the second egg. The incubation period is about 13.5 days. The chicks
are fed mostly waxworms for the first three days. On day four the parents
start to include nectar. They accomplish this by drinking nectar, then taking
a wax worm, mashing it, and feeding the nectar-worm puree to the chicks.
On day five pieces of grape are added, but even then waxworms remain the
favourite food. Chicks go from eating a worm per feeding on day one, to
six or seven worms per feeding on day eight. For the first four days, the
chicks produce tiny faeces which are eaten by the parents. On day five,
they start producing faecal sacs which are removed by the parents and
dropped in a far comer of the aviary.
Hand-rearing
Unfortunately the nest was located directly in the airflow from a heating/
air conditioning vent, and at the top of the exhibit where it is hottest. This
environment appeared to cause the chicks to become dehydrated. The female
attempted to correct this by wetting her feathers before brooding, but it did
not help. Four consecutive clutches were lost between day six and day nine,
leading to our decision to remove further clutches on day five for hand-
rearing.
After being removed from the nest, the chicks were placed in a Gmmbach
incubator to provide a constant temperature and humidity; they weighed
approximately 5g. The chicks had no body fat, and were visibly dehydrated
with very pale and slightly wrinkled skin. After a few hours in a humid
incubator, however, the wrinkles had gone and the skin tone was a strong,
dark pink. The chicks were very temperature-sensitive and shivered if the
temperature dropped below 100*F (37.8*C). To prevent dehydration the
incubator was kept at a constant 80% Relative Humidity.
The diet fed was Kaytee Exact Original hand-rearing formula. There
were no problems adjusting from the livefood to the formula. The first feed
was one part Kaytee Exact mixed with four parts water (1:4). Thereafter,
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.952973" page_id="56500677"  page_num="18" year="" vol="">
18
</page>
<table confidence="0.38855075" page_id="56500677"  page_num="18" year="" vol="">
HARDY - BLUE-WINGED LEAFBIRD
Martin Vince
The eyes start to open at nine days of age.
Martin Vince
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.512956" page_id="56500677"  page_num="18" year="" vol="">
By 11 days of age the eyes are completely open and green feathers are starting to
emerge. Enkamat (the black plastic mesh) provides ideal footing, and is easy to
disinfect. It is an erosion control material used extensively by horticulturists.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.370214" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500678" page_num="19" year="" vol="">
HARDY - BLUE-WINGED LEAFBIRD
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.850255" page_id="56500678"  page_num="19" year="" vol="">
19
</page>
<table confidence="0.3440785" page_id="56500678"  page_num="19" year="" vol="">
Martin Vince
At 12 days the feathers are looking great, thanks to lots of preening.
Martin Vince
At 19 days, three days after fledging, chicks can perch and fly but are clumsy.
</table>
<page confidence="0.924423" page_id="56500679"  page_num="20" year="" vol="">
20
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.437882" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500679" page_num="20" year="" vol="">
HARDY - BLUE-WINGED LEAFBIRD
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.34421">
Martin Vince
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99091712" page_id="56500679"  page_num="20" year="" vol="">
At 12 days chicks respond well to vibration. We tap on the table near the chick to
solicit a feeding response. When excited the chicks can shake like an electric
toothbrush.
the food was mixed to a ratio of 1:3 until day 10. From day 10 until weaning,
the food was thickened and mixed at a ratio of 1:2.
The chicks were fed with a flexible syringe tip cannula on the end of a
1 .Occ tuberculin syringe. A syringe tip cannula is normally used for the
treatment of cattle teats, but the lin (25mm) long, thin flexible tip is also
ideal for feeding small passerines. It fits easily onto the syringe and can be
disinfected between feedings. All of the hand-feeding implements were
disinfected daily with a diluted chlorhexidine solution.
Tapping the table next to the chicks elicited a strong feeding response.
For the first ten days, the chicks were fed 14 times a day from 8.00am -
10.00pm, with the late feeding being particularly important to prevent
dehydration.
In addition to syringe feeding, we began to use tweezers on day 10 to
feed small pieces of Red Apple Jungle pellets and grapes soaked in the
hand-rearing formula. Small amounts of Nekton Lory nectar were gradually
added to the diet to allow the chicks' digestive systems to adjust. At day 16
the chicks fledged and were no longer fed after 5.00pm. They were fully
feathered and a shade darker green than their parents. At this point we
began feeding them entirely with tweezers, including more fruit and pellets
in the diet. Each piece of food was first soaked in the Kaytee/nectar mixture.
Once they had fledged, the chicks were occasionally offered nectar or water
with a spoon to encourage self-feeding. Being nectar drinkers, the chicks
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.429569" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500680" page_num="21" year="" vol="">
HARDY - BLUE-WINGED LEAFBIRD
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997934" page_id="56500680"  page_num="21" year="" vol="">
21
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.960076444444444" page_id="56500680"  page_num="21" year="" vol="">
had no problems drinking nectar and water from the spoon, and would
sometimes consume as much as one teaspoon of this.
Hand-feeding became difficult once the chicks fledged because they were
more interested in flying than eating. However, tapping on the perch quickly
caught their attention and encouraged a feeding response. Food and water
dishes were added to the brooder on day 21 to encourage self-feeding, and
on day 30 the chicks were moved to a small indoor aviary. The hand-feedings
were reduced gradually, and by day 36 the birds were reliably feeding
themselves. The chicks moulted into their light green adult plumage within
two months of weaning, and were then indistinguishable from the adults.
For Riverbanks Zoo and Garden's complete hand-rearing notes, please
e-mail: ahardy@riverbanks.org
In 2002 we successfully raised three Blue-winged Leafbirds. All were
DNA sexed as females. One bird has gone to the North Carolina Zoo to
enter its breeding programme. The other two females will remain at
Riverbanks to be paired with unrelated males and perpetuate our leafbird
breeding programme. We believe that this is a world first breeding. Any
member knowing otherwise are asked to contact the author or the Hon. Editor
of the Avicultural Magazine.
Products mentioned
Red Apple Jungle pellets: extruded, cylindrically-shaped pellets nearly
lin (25mm) long and 5 /i6in (9mm) in diameter and bright red in colour.
Manufactured by Marion Zoological, Wayzata, Minnesota, USA.
Tropical Bits: with the same nutritional content as the above, but only
the size of finch seed and normally marketed for finches and canaries.
Manufactured by Marion Zoological, Wayzata, Minnesota, USA. Several
manufacturers, such as Pretty Bird and Kay tee, produce equivalent products.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.408444" page_id="56500680"  page_num="21" year="" vol="">
Angela Hardy is Primary Bird House Keeper, Riverbanks Zoo &amp; Garden ,
PO . Box 1060, Columbia, South Carolina 29202-1060, USA. Website:
www.riverbanks .org
</figure>
<page confidence="0.997198" page_id="56500681"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
22
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.820787333333333" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500681" page_num="22" year="" vol="">
BREEDING THE HOOPOE Upupa epops AT DISNEY'S
ANIMAL KINGDOM
by Paul Schutz
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.991913111111111" page_id="56500681"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
The Hoopoe Upupa epops is one of the most distinctive birds in the
world. A migratory species, it is found in season throughout much of Europe,
Africa and Asia and cannot be mistaken for any other bird within that range.
The Hoopoe has traditionally been treated as a single species within the
order Coraciiformes. Recently, however, various authors have suggested
separating the Hoopoe into two or more species and even its own order,
Upupiformes (del Hoyo et al. 2001). In the wild the Hoopoe is almost
completely insectivorous and uses its long beak to probe in the ground for
grubs and other invertebrates (del Hoyo et al. 2001).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.354824">
Paul Schutz
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.542294" page_id="56500681"  page_num="22" year="" vol="">
Adult pair of Hoopoes. The female is the one reaching out of the nest-box.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.447869" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500682" page_num="23" year="" vol="">
SCHUTZ - HOOPOE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998751" page_id="56500682"  page_num="23" year="" vol="">
23
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.980982976190476" page_id="56500682"  page_num="23" year="" vol="">
Disney's Animal Kingdom received a pair of captive bred Eurasian
Hoopoes in September 1998. After a 30 day quarantine period, the pair was
moved into an acclimation pen in the walk-through Africa aviary. This is a
heavily planted enclosure, that features a large waterfall and pool at one
end, and houses 20 species of African birds. Upon release, the Hoopoes did
well but their activity decreased gradually over a two month period. This
culminated in both being injured, though how this happened remains
unknown. Both were removed from the aviary and an infection led to surgery
and the subsequent removal of one of the female's eyes, after which both
birds spent approximately seven months off-exhibit while they were
recuperating. When the birds were finally given a clean bill of health, the
decision was made to introduce them into the Asia aviary.
This is situated along the Maharajah Jungle Trail at Disney's Animal
Kingdom, along which guests (visitors) can view Komodo Dragons Varanus
komodensis , Malayan Tapirs Tapirus indicus , Tigers Panther a tigris , fruit
bats and two species of hoofed stock, as well as many species of birds. The
aviary measures approximately 120ft long x 65ft wide x 40ft high (36m
long x 20m wide x 12m high). It is terraced, so that the aviary is on three
levels, with the majority of the exhibit at ground level. It too is heavily
planted, with fig trees, banana plants and bamboo, to name just a few. In
addition to the Hoopoes, a myriad of other avian species can be encountered,
including Great Argus Pheasants Argusianus argus, Indian Blue Rollers
Coracias benghalensis, Amboina King Parrots Alisterus amboinensis,
Golden-crested Mynahs Ampeliceps coronatus , Golden-backed Wood-
peckers Dinopium javanense. Crested Wood Partridges Rollulus roulroul
and Timor Sparrows Padda fuscata. Food is placed at approximately 15
different locations. Diets vary, they include chopped mixed fruits, soaked
Mazuri(TM) brand parrot breeder pellets, chopped greens, seed, Millikin Meats(TM)
brand carnivore diet (mixed with the aforementioned parrot pellets) and
pinky mice. Mealworms, waxworms and crickets are also provided, in
addition to which a variety of wild invertebrates occur in the aviary. A
simple exclusion feeder has been developed for the Hoopoes. This is simply
a shallow pan of insect larvae covered with a piece of peg-board. The
Hoopoes can fit their beaks through the holes in the peg-board and extract
the insect larvae, but other birds are unable to do so. This allows a large
supply of livefood to be provided specifically for the Hoopoes without
skewing the diets of the other residents of the aviary.
After a two day acclimation period, the male was released into the aviary
on July 8th 1999, followed the next day by the female. Both birds seemed
to adjust well. They initially stayed in the vicinity of the acclimation pen,
but within a week they were moving throughout the aviary. Most of their
time was spent probing in the ground for insects, grubs and worms. Although
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997756" page_id="56500683"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
24
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.840919" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500683" page_num="24" year="" vol="">
SCHUTZ - HOOPOE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998651357142857" page_id="56500683"  page_num="24" year="" vol="">
the Hoopoes were fairly visible, they remained wary and timid, never
approaching keepers and retreating when they were approached.
The pair remained shy and unobtrusive for several months before any
change in behaviour was observed. That occurred in mid-January 2000,
when the pair seemed to become more confident and was seen in the open
more often, even venturing out onto the pathway. On January 16th, the
male was heard for the first time giving his distinctive three-note "hoop-
poo-poo". Fry et al. (1988) referred to this as his "advertisement call". Two
days later, the male was observed pursuing the female throughout the aviary,
another behaviour that had not been observed previously. They flew above
the highest trees, coming to rest occasionally before beginning again. The
next day, the male was observed entering the nest-box, approximately 20ft
(6m) above the ground. The female then investigated the same nest-box for
a few seconds before she entered it. Constructed of plywood, the box was
1ft 1 lin tall x 8in wide x 9in deep (approx. 58cm tall x 20cm wide x 23cm
deep) with a 2in (5cm) in diameter entrance hole. The distance from the
bottom of the entrance hole to the bottom of the box was 19in (48cm).
Starting on January 20th 2000, the male spent most mornings calling.
He chose a high and exposed perch and called, sometimes for hours, with
only a few seconds between each set of vocalizations. He also made frequent
visits to the nest-box he had selected, calling sometimes from inside or on
the top of the box. Two days later, the male began to defend the box from
other birds. He routinely chased off Goldie's Lorikeets Trichoglossus goldiei
when they attempted to investigate the box. Besides the advertisement call,
two different vocalizations were heard. One was a hoarse rasping call, often
heard during the male's pursuit of the female. The second was a high-pitched
trill, similar to a cricket's chirp. The trilling call was heard only three times
and also accompanied the male's pursuit of the female.
Throughout January, the male continued his courtship: advertisement
calling, pursuing the female and entering his chosen nest-box. As February
began, the male seemed to intensify his efforts to persuade the female to
enter the nest-box. He was heard advertisement calling while seen holding
a mealworm in his beak for the first time on February 1 st. At this point, he
most often called from on top of the nest-box or from inside it, rather than
from an open location. The next day the male was observed feeding the
female for the first time. Later that day, the female was on top of the nest-
box while the male was inside. In his attempts to coax her in, he even
reached out and pulled her tail. Courtship feeding and pursuit continued
over the next week. On February 5th, the female was in the nest-box and
for the first time was observed altering the interior. Over a 20 minute period,
she steadily threw out of the box beakfuls of nest substrate (pine shavings).
The male periodically flew to the opening and fed her.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.442799" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500684" page_num="25" year="" vol="">
SCHUTZ - HOOPOE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.983293" page_id="56500684"  page_num="25" year="" vol="">
25
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.994336428571428" page_id="56500684"  page_num="25" year="" vol="">
On February 7th, one of the Hoopoes was observed threatening a female
Green Junglefowl Callus varius that approached the box. The Hoopoe
extended its neck and swayed it back and forth, like a snake threatening to
strike. This was seen several times over the next few weeks in response to
the approach of other birds. Normally timid, the Hoopoes adopted a more
aggressive character when defending their nest. On at least one occasion,
the male violently confronted a Goldie's Lorikeet and slammed into it with
his body to drive the lorikeet away from the nest-box.
By the second week of February, the calling of the male began to wane
and both adults were seen going in and out of the nest-box. On the 9th, what
seemed to be pre-copulatory behaviour was observed. The male walked up
behind the female and pecked lightly at her nape, and she occasionally turned
her head and pecked back at him. It seemed as if he was about to mount her,
but she flew off after about 20 seconds of this interaction. This sort of
courtship was repeated often over the next three days, with copulation always
seeming imminent but never observed. Courtship feeding seemed to change
as well. While not passing food items back and forth, the male would hold
an item of food in and out of the female's beak repeatedly before finally
relinquishing it.
By February 13th, the female was seen in or around the nest-box more
often than not, with the male bringing her food. A note was made on the
17th that the female was "rarely visible." From February 17th-28th, she
was seen only briefly leaving the box, but on the 29th, an increase in the
female's activity and journeys from the box was noted. That day the male
was seen to make five feeding trips to the box within 15 minutes. On March
3rd, for the first time in about a month, the male was heard advertising
again. An observation made on March 7th seemed to confirm the presence
of chicks: a Golden-backed Woodpecker that was foraging on the wall next
to the nest-box, suddenly cocked his head and then jumped to the side of the
box and tapped on it lightly; the woodpecker then looked into the entrance
of the box, at which point the female Hoopoe emerged and chased him off.
The woodpecker certainly seemed to have heard something and indeed both
the male and female Hoopoe were making frequent trips to the nest-box
with food. The next day, after the female exited the box, keepers were able
to check inside by using a mirror on a pole. At least two chicks were present.
The height of the nest-box (about 20ft (6m) up) made it difficult to see the
exact number.
The parents continued to diligently feed their young. Other institutions
had warned us that the nest-box might become quite dirty. Therefore, on
the morning of the 15th, using a ladder we accessed the nest-box in order to
clean it out and at the same time examine and band the chicks. A total of
four chicks were present, along with two olive green eggs. Two of the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.992326" page_id="56500685"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
26
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.839939" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500685" page_num="26" year="" vol="">
SCHUTZ - HOOPOE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999841125" page_id="56500685"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
chicks were significantly larger (67g and 63.9g vs 49.lg and 44.9g) and it
was assumed that the two unhatched eggs were the third and fourth. All
four chicks were covered in brown-grey down and pin feathers. The pin
feathers of the crest were arranged in two parallel rows on the top of the
chicks' heads and the chicks' fleshly gape flanges were bright white. The
smallest chick seemed developmentally behind the other three: its legs were
more splayed and it was not as active as its siblings. Several small twigs
were added to the pine shavings to give this bird something more substantial
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.681572">
Paul Schutz
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987330222222222" page_id="56500685"  page_num="26" year="" vol="">
Approximately 14 days old.
to grip, but all of the twigs were thrown out over the next few days. Despite
the stories of a filthy nest, the substrate seemed to be in good shape. Although
the box and its contents were malodorous, overall it appeared fairly tidy but
some of the substrate was replaced. When handled the chicks excreted a
foul smelling liquid from their uropygial gland. Within about 10 minutes of
the completion of the nest check, the parents returned to the nest-box and
continued caring for the chicks.
One week later, the chicks underwent a brief medical examination at the
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.44799" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500686" page_num="27" year="" vol="">
SCHUTZ - HOOPOE
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997495" page_id="56500686"  page_num="27" year="" vol="">
27
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999445690476191" page_id="56500686"  page_num="27" year="" vol="">
nest and the smallest of the clutch now appeared normal, with no sign of the
splayed legs witnessed earlier. Their weights were 69.9g, 84. lg, 70.7g and
72.8g. At this time, the female was observed to be undergoing a moult.
Several of her primaries were missing and as the moult progressed she began
to lose her tail feathers, to a point where she had great difficulty accessing
the nest-box. The male seemed to pick up the slack and took over the majority
of the feeding of the chicks. He also began advertisement calling again and
investigating nest sites.
On March 29th, the male was observed on top of the nest-box, holding a
mealworm and uttering his rasping call. A chick was looking out of the
opening and begging. The male tapped the chick&amp;apos;s beak with the mealworm,
then resumed calling. This behaviour was repeated several times before the
chick was finally fed. The next day, two of the chicks had fledged. Their
beaks were about half the length of their parents' beaks, they had a few tufts
of down on their crest feathers and the remnants of the white gape flanges
were barely visible. Otherwise, the chicks were difficult to distinguish from
their parents. A third chick left the box the next day and the fourth left three
days after that.
From the beginning, the fledglings were curious and pecked at just about
everything. They were seen to investigate items of food and were observed
eating ants just five days after fledging. Despite feeding themselves, the
fledglings continued to beg from the parents, especially the male. On
numerous occasions, all four fledglings were seen chasing the male
throughout the aviary, begging for food. The male continued feed them for
some time and was last seen to feed them on May 8th, 39 days after the first
chick fledged.
Only a week after the first chick fledged, the adults began pre-copuiatory
behaviour again. The male was observed to feed his mate and call from the
nest-box with food in his beak. On April 27th, the female was observed
aggressively displacing a juvenile from the vicinity of the nest-box. By
May 6th, the female was throwing shavings out of the box and by the 27th,
a second clutch of eggs had been laid. Five chicks hatched of which three
survived to fledging. Despite some notations about cooperative breeding
behaviour (Fry et ai. 1988), the juvenile Hoopoes were not seen to assist
their parents with their new clutch.
Some time after the chicks of the second clutch fledged, the adult male
Hoopoe was discovered with a broken beak. It was so severely broken that
only about one-third of its length remained intact. Several procedures were
performed in an attempt to save the broken section, but proved unsuccessful.
The male, along with Ms mate, was moved to our off-exhibit Avian Research
Center, in which we could more closely monitor his health and progress.
Despite his obvious impairment, the pair has gone on to raise several more
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996757" page_id="56500687"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
28
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.804708" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500687" page_num="28" year="" vol="">
SCHUTZ - HOOPOE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.963728714285714" page_id="56500687"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
successful broods in its new enclosure. Our success with this species can
probably be attributed first, and probably foremost, to the birds being such
attentive and protective parents that have given remarkable care to their
chicks. Secondly, every effort has been made to provide the Hoopoes with
a large supply of livefood, which makes up the vast majority of the chicks'
diet, especially in the early days. The male's beak injury has not seemed to
hinder his parenting ability.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.885224" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56500687" page_num="28" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.988220833333333" page_id="56500687"  page_num="28" year="" vol="">
I would like to thank the staff of the Aviary Department at Disney's
Animal Kingdom, including Curator Grenville Roles and zoological
managers Chelle Plasse and Scott Barton. I would especially like to thank
the entire keeper staff, including Jennifer Carney, Marci Cody and Jeremy
Taylor and former staff members Ron Fry and Josef Lindholm III, whose
hours of diligent observations helped make this paper possible.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.957647" genericHeader="references" page_id="56500687" page_num="28" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.992709428571429">
Fry, C. H., Keith, S. and Urban, E. K. 1988. Birds of Africa. Vol.III, Parrots to Woodpeckers.
Academic Press, San Diego and London.
del Hoyo, J., Elliot, A. and Sargatal, J. 2001. Handbook of the Birds of the World. Vol.VI,
Mousebirds to Hombills. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona.
Paul Schutz is Zoological Manager, Disney's Animal Kingdom, PO. Box
10,000, Lake Buena Vista, Florida 32830-1000, USA. Tel: 407-938-6383/
Fax:502-333-3966.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9620265" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500688" page_num="29" year="" vol="">
THE FESTIVE AMAZON Amazona festiva festiva IN THE
WILD AND IN CAPTIVITY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996412" page_id="56500688"  page_num="29" year="" vol="">
29
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.935112666666667" page_id="56500688"  page_num="29" year="" vol="">
by Lars Lepperhoff
The Festive Amazon appears to be common in the wild, mainly near
rivers, yet it is rarely found in captivity. There are few reports about how it
lives in the wild and very little is known about its breeding biology. In the
aviaries of the Association Hyacmthinus here in Switzerland we are fortunate
in having two pairs of Festive Amazons. Because it is a most beautiful
species with a very strong personality I was very keen to observe it in the
wild, which I did in April 2002 in the Amazonian rainforest.
History
This species was given its scientific name by Carl von Linne (1707-
1778) in 1758 - /estiva coming from the Latin language and meaning -
festive, magnificent, pretty. The nominate form first came to Europe, to
London Zoo in 1865. The subspecies A.f. bodini was first seen here in 1872
at Berlin Zoo.
Description
The basic colour is a wonderful green; the lores and a narrow frontal
band are dark red. There is a nice blue colour above and behind the eyes;
there is also a little blue under the lower mandible which gives this species
its German name Blaubartamazone (Blue-bearded Amazon). The lower
back and ramp are a beautiful scarlet, which can be seen when the birds are
flying or when they are preening each other.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.563826">
Subspecies
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.969738666666667" page_id="56500688"  page_num="29" year="" vol="">
The only subspecies, Bodiei's Amazon, is a different more yellow shade
of green. The head coloration is also different. There is more blue around
the eyes and the blue on the cheeks is more extensive. Bodiei's Amazon
comes only from central Venezuela along the Orinoco River and from parts
of Guyana.
Calls
The contact calls of the Festive Amazon are loud and typically Amazon-
like and are heard when birds are flying in a flock or, in captivity, before
feeding and during mornings and evenings. The calls often remind me of
laughter. Often the birds fluff out their feathers and dilate their pupils. If
disturbed when breeding, they call in the same way very loudly. When they
are preening each other or after a shower, they call more quietly and
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.958428" page_id="56500689"  page_num="30" year="" vol="">
30
</page>
<table confidence="0.6862204" page_id="56500689"  page_num="30" year="" vol="">
LEPPERHOFF - FESTIVE AMAZON
Lars Lepperhoff
Bird with red and yellow colouring owned by a woman at Alencar.
Lars Lepperhoff
Old pair of Festive Amazons at Swiss breeding centre.
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.398445" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500690" page_num="31" year="" vol="">
LEPPERHOFF - FESTIVE AMAZON
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999283" page_id="56500690"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
31
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.718819">
Lars Lepperhoff
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9912265" page_id="56500690"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
The longest surviving 2000 chick at about 69 days old. Shortly afterwards the decision
was taken to euthanase it.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.757941">
Lars Lepperhoff
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.940967" page_id="56500690"  page_num="31" year="" vol="">
Food for pairs with young.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997572" page_id="56500691"  page_num="32" year="" vol="">
32
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.736719" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500691" page_num="32" year="" vol="">
LEPPERHOFF - FESTIVE AMAZON
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99537575" page_id="56500691"  page_num="32" year="" vol="">
contentedly in gutteral tones. They have a variety of carolling notes when
they are perched. A flock of five I observed after heavy rain on the top a
Cecropia tree had very distinctive and variable calls.
Distribution
It is found over a large area along the upper Amazon and its tributaries
principally in Brazil, west to Rio Branco and Rio Negro and into parts of
Colombia, Peru and even Ecuador. It is also known from the upper Rio
Orinoco in Venezuela.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.381785">
Status
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990782433333333" page_id="56500691"  page_num="32" year="" vol="">
This Amazon seems not to be endangered and in many places occurs
still in untouched flooded forest. The Mamiraua reserve and the adjoining
reserves of Jau and Amana combined are as large as Costa Rica! This is a
wonderful place for the Festive Amazon.
In Brazil
I flew from Manaus via Tabatinga to Tefe. I enjoyed the flight because
I was fascinated to see the endless green sea of the Amazonian rainforest
and the rivers (which were carrying a lot of sediment) like enormous snakes
floating through the vegetation. I saw the Amazon with its numerous
tributaries and the flooded parts of the forest. From Tefe, a typical Brazilian
jungle town, it took two hours by boat to reach the Mamiraua Sustainable
Development Reserve located between two rivers, the Japura and Solimoes
(which becomes the Amazon). I stayed on the Parana do Mamiraua in a
floating house built on two trunks of Assacu trees.
On my first excursion a Kabokloman took me by canoe through the
flooded forest - a unique environment. In April the water level was very
high so we were close to the treetops. Back at Mamiraua Lodge in the late
afternoon I suddenly heard typical Amazon calls and saw quite close by five
Festive Amazons sitting on the top of a Cecropia tree. The birds were
preening their feathers and 'talking' together. Some flew from the top of
one branch to another and behaved very socially. After about 20 minutes,
they flew off over the greyish brown water and disappeared among the
vegetation.
The annual cycle of the varzea (seasonally flooded forest) is variable.
Some parts are flooded only during some weeks in June and July, others,
such as the Mamiraua, are flooded for more than six months. There is a
difference of 12m (approx. 39ft) between June (flooded) and October (dry
season). The climate is hot and humid throughout the year. Rain usually
falls in relatively short but very heavy tropical showers often accompanied
by spectacular thunderstorms. The average temperature ranges from 23*C-
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.39837" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500692" page_num="33" year="" vol="">
LEPPERHOFF - FESTIVE AMAZON
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998759" page_id="56500692"  page_num="33" year="" vol="">
33
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.996151166666667" page_id="56500692"  page_num="33" year="" vol="">
33*C (approx.74*F-91*F) and the humidity was, according to my hygrometer,
about 70%-80% during the day and about 100% at night.
Because of their preference for flooded forests, Festive Amazons have a
large range. According to Olafita, a parrot lover who lives in the flooded
forest, the breeding season is in June when the water level is high (over 12m
(39ft)). At this time the trees have a lot of seeds and fruits. Despite the fact
that many mammals must move to terra firma, many of those able to climb,
such as sloths, monkeys and the Jaguar Panthem onca , remain. Some toucans
and snakes take eggs from nest cavities. When my guide was showing me
the Amazons from the canoe, it sometimes took me a long time to identify
these green birds sitting amongst the leaves. They are very active during
the early morning when they prefer to sit in the sun. Until 11.00am it was
possible to observe them flying and sitting on branches, calling and preening
each other. By the early afternoon they were mainly silent, but if there were
clouds and a thunderstorm could be heard in the distance, they remained
active. In the evenings before the sun set I often saw them moving about
again. I never observed them in the company of any other species of Amazon,
but often there were Short-tailed Parrots Graydidasculus brachyurus nearby.
The Mamiraua reserve is a sustainable development reserve which means
that income from tourists helps support the local people and the reserve.
The local people receive the profits from the lodge, not a tourist company.
This works well for it gives them an added incentive to protect the forest
and its inhabitants.
I had the opportunity to visit a local village. I was told that some people
in Alencar keep Festive Amazons. Our boat found its way through channels,
swamps and thick vegetation to a small place with wooden houses on stilts
which was not flooded. I liked this little village of some 60 or so inhabitants
- a civilisation without cars! As I was walking through the village I suddenly
stopped in front of a house with two Festive Amazons in the window and
afterwards saw another two in a tree in the neighbourhood. I was allowed to
go into the house and spoke with the owner, an elderly woman. One of the
Amazons had red and yellow feathers all over its body. It had, she said,
been living with her for more than five years. The other bird which was
normal in colour had been with her for only one and a half years. The birds
had been taken from the nest and hand-reared on a diet of maniok, maize
and fruit. Thinking about the bird with red and yellow feathering I was
suddenly reminded of an observation of Alfred Russel Wallace, who reported
that Festive Amazons were fed by the Indians with fat from a fish that caused
their green feathers to turn partially red and yellow. I do not think that the
abnormal colouration of the bird at Alencar was produced on purpose, but
assume that it was a result of malnutrition, as the younger birds were normal
in colour. I was told by other travellers that Festive Amazons are kept as
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997374" page_id="56500693"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
34
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.667618" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500693" page_num="34" year="" vol="">
LEPPERHOFF - FESTIVE AMAZON
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.876586" page_id="56500693"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
companions by people in many villages and towns along the Amazon.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.736452">
In Switzerland
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99777441025641" page_id="56500693"  page_num="34" year="" vol="">
Our parrot collection is privately owned. We can only keep birds in
indoor aviaries. Therefore it is important to enrich the world around them
with natural things. The Amazon aviaries are located on the first floor of
the building. They are about 2.5m long x 1.3m wide x 2.5m high (approx.
9ft long x 4ft 6in wide x 9ft high). There are walls on three sides, with wire
elsewhere. I have painted the walls green (leaves/plants), blue (sky) and
yellow (sun), three dominant colours in nature. These help avoid the
appearance of comers and make the room look bigger. They also make the
birds more relaxed than they were before when all the walls were white. As
we cannot get sufficient daylight through the windows in the roof the birds
are in artificial light all day. We use neon lights (Trulight) which give about
95% of the natural light spectrum. On the advice of the Curator at Zurich
Zoo we have also installed a special lamp of the kind that is often used by
gardeners. It gives UV-light as well, and is like the sun sending its warm
light down on the earth. Visitors often believe that the light is coming from
the sun through a window. Just one lamp gives enough light for eight Amazon
aviaries. It is on for eight hours a day, from late morning and into the
afternoon and therefore helps simulate the natural environment. It also makes
it possible to grow plants in the parrot house.
I give the birds fresh branches at least once a week. The Festive Amazons
like to gnaw the wood and remove the leaves. Branches of fir trees and pine
trees are provided during the winter, even though the birds do not gnaw
them or the cones. Because plants are so important in the wild, I try to use
them to create a naturalistic environment for our Amazons. The building is
quite high, so I put branches over the aviaries and over the path and fix them
in place with chains. On these branches I cultivate epiphytic plants, such as
species of Bromelia and Til lands ia. I also grow Platycerium mdAsplenium
ferns. Other easily-grown tropical plants such as Monster a. Philodendron
and Chlorophytum are grown in pots standing on the top of the aviaries.
These enrich the lives of our birds and create a more sympathetic atmosphere
in the house. During the summer when the temperature often reaches 25*C
(77 *F) I spray the plants every second day. During the winter we maintain
the temperate at 10*C (50*F) and I spray them just once a week. Without
the special lamp the plants would not grow so well.
As the floor is tiled, I offer the birds sand in a separate tray. During the
warm weather the aviaries are cleaned daily and are cleaned every second
day during the winter. This is done with water and they are kept very clean
and to date we have never had any diseases. In each aviary there is a shower
and a round bowl in which the Amazons can bathe. They prefer the shower,
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.398424" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500694" page_num="35" year="" vol="">
LEPPERHOFF - FESTIVE AMAZON
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.996593" page_id="56500694"  page_num="35" year="" vol="">
35
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.98253075" page_id="56500694"  page_num="35" year="" vol="">
and when I turn on the water, it 'rains' throughout the building and the
sound of it stimulates the birds. Normally I spray them twice a week, but in
the summer only once a week.
Feeding
Each day the birds are given a variety of fruits and vegetables which I
cut into small pieces. From spring to autumn they also receive sprouted
seeds. I also use CeOe Eggfood for Parrots and sometimes feed eggs with
it. In addition, I regularly give vitamins and trace elements. I use different
products, such as Totalin, Vitakalk, Biotopic and Eiverdin, in a rotation
system. When the birds have chicks I also offer them cheese and dry seed.
Each day during the winter the birds get fruit and vegetables, plus dry seed
and one peanut per bird. I usually feed the birds once a day in the late
afternoon.
Breeding
Made from birch wood, the nest-boxes measure 58cm x 39cm x 50cm
(approx. 1ft 11 in x 1ft 3 72 m x 1ft 7 3 Ain). The entrance hole is 12cm (4 3 Ain)
in diameter. Wood shavings are placed in the bottom of the boxes and in the
spring I add rotten wood, which I collect from the forest. The Amazons like
to gnaw this prior to laying. It is possible to inspect the inside of the nest-
boxes from behind the wall.
We keep two pairs of Festive Amazons. One is an unrelated pair bred in
Switzerland by Peter Buser, Altdorf UR and David Rothlisberger, Rohrbach
BE. Peter Buser was, in 1991, the first person to breed this Amazon in
Switzerland. The male of our pair was parent reared in 1994 and the female
was parent reared in 1995. They have been together here since autumn
1995. In summer 2000 this pair for the first time showed an interest in the
nest-box; they also displayed.
The other pair are imported birds and have been living here since 1984.
They get very excited when they hear children's voices. They have damaged
wings, so cannot fly. I believe and so does Peter Buser, that these Amazons
need to be several years old before they start to breed.
This older second pair first had eggs in 1992. All three were infertile. In
1994 the female laid two infertile eggs. In 1999 she again laid three eggs
that were infertile. It was not until 2000 that two chicks were hatched by
this pair, after it had been together for 16 years! This shows how patient
you must be. My philosophy is to remain patient if the pair is compatible.
Before the female lays the pair become very aggressive towards people.
The male hangs on the wire at the front of the aviary, dilating his pupils,
calling loudly and trying to bite me. At this time of the year, mainly June-
July, I have to use a board to protect my hands from the risk of injury, when
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994738" page_id="56500695"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
36
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.73399" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500695" page_num="36" year="" vol="">
LEPPERHOFF - FESTIVE AMAZON
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997648928571429" page_id="56500695"  page_num="36" year="" vol="">
I put them into the aviary to change the food. The female normally runs
towards the nest-box calling, and then suddenly runs to the wire and joins
the male in his attack. After some weeks of this behaviour the female usually
lays two to three eggs, at two day intervals. It is difficult to inspect inside
the nest-box, despite the fact that this can be done from behind so that the
birds cannot see me. Whenever the two birds are feeding - the female always
comes out for a short time to eat - and I attempt to approach the nest-box,
both birds always run back to it. I approach it very quietly but somehow
they always seem to know exactly what is going on. There is dark glass
through which I can just see inside the nest-box. When both are inside, they
look suspiciously at the dark glass, dilating their pupils and making very
little noise. Sometimes they show aggression towards the glass.
2000 breeding season
On July 5th I found an egg in the nest-box. On July 9th there was still
only one egg. On July 20th there were three eggs! On July 29th when
someone was talking to the birds at the front of the aviary and they were
busy defending their territory, I took the opportunity to check the eggs. Two
were fertile but the third was damaged. One chick hatched August 10th and
the other on August 12th. Through the dark glass I could see that the chicks
were always lying on their backs and this continued to be the case during
the following days and weeks. On August 22nd I tried to put the chicks on
their feet but they fell straight back. On September 5th their feathers started
to grow and the following day the older chick looked at me. Two days later
the youngest chick was dead in the nest-box. By September 10th the
remaining youngster had feathers on its head (I could see red on its forehead),
cheeks and back, and the parents were spending more time outside the nest-
box. The youngster was fully feathered September 24th.
On several occasions I observed it on its belly near the entrance and
could see that it had a problem. Therefore, on October 18th I decided to
remove the chick from the nest-box. It appeared to be paralysed and on the
following day when I was hand-feeding it, the youngster was quite tame but
incapable of standing. I constructed a bed for it in which it appeared quite
comfortable. I consulted two veterinarians, Willy Hafeli and Peter Sandmeier,
who specialise in parrots. It was confirmed that the youngster was paralysed
and the decision was taken to euthanase it. Dr Sandmeier found that its
skeleton was normal and it remains unclear why it was paralysed. Another
Amazon breeder, Hans Butler, Miihlau AG, has had the same problem with
young Tucuman Amazons A. tucumana. Later I consulted many other
breeders, particularly Amazon breeders, but most of them had never
encountered this problem. I was sad that after such a long time what looked
like being our first breeding success with this remarkable pair ended in the
way it did.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.398357" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500696" page_num="37" year="" vol="">
LEPPERHOFF - FESTIVE AMAZON
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997529" page_id="56500696"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
37
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9944512" page_id="56500696"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
2001 breeding season
I observed a much higher degree of aggression on July 1st . On July
21st the female went into the nest-box but stayed only a short time. On July
23rd she remained inside for a long time. Then from July 25th the female
left the box only if there was a disturbance in the house. On July 28th I
found two eggs and a few days later there was a third. Unfortunately, all
were infertile. They measured: 36mm x 28mm, 36mm x 27mm and 35mm
x 28mm.
Postscript: 2002 breeding season
The female of the old pair laid three infertile eggs. The female of the
young pair laid for the first time. She laid two eggs, both were fertile and
two chicks hatched and were raised successfully. The male did not feed the
female in the nest-box during the breeding time, including when the female
was raising the two chicks. Interestingly, the latter do not yet (at the time of
writing) have the red rump. They flew from the box at 64 days of age. At
present they are quite tame with me but are very shy with strangers. After
the two young flew the male became aggressive towards the female.
Therefore I placed it in a separate cage from which it can see the rest of the
family. We are very pleased about this success with a species of Amazon
which is very rarely bred.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.849356" genericHeader="acknowledgments" page_id="56500696" page_num="37" year="" vol="">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.973115" page_id="56500696"  page_num="37" year="" vol="">
The Swiss breeding centre of the Association Hyacinthinus is funded by
Mr Walter and Mrs Esther Squindo, whose generosity in running this centre
is very much appreciated. Many thanks also to Rosemary Low who helped
me put the above article into proper English.
Bibliography
George, U. 1987. Regenwald, Geo, Hamburg.
Juniper, T. and Parr, M. 1998. Parrots. A guide to the Parrots of the World. Pica Press,
Sussex.
Lepperhoff, L. 2000. Die Blaubartamazone (Amazona festiva). DieVoliere 10:311-314.
Robiller, F. 1990. Papageien Band 3. Eugen Ulmer Verlag, Stuttgart.
Seibert, P. 1996. Farhatlas Sudamerika. Eugen Ulmer Verlag, Stuttgart.
Stranden, H. 1984. Papageien einst und jetzt. Horst Muller Verlag, Walsrode.
The main purpose of Association Hyacinthinus is to observe, describe
and breed endangered parrots, especially Neotropical species. The breeding
centre is normally not open to the public but members may visit it by
appointment. If you wish to know more you should write to: Lars Lepperhoff,
Association Hyacinthinus, Lutschenstrasse 15, 3063 Ittigen, Switzerland.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998436" page_id="56500697"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
38
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9067335" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500697" page_num="38" year="" vol="">
COTSWOLD WILDLIFE PARK REVIEW OF 2002
by Louise Peat
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995321535714286" page_id="56500697"  page_num="38" year="" vol="">
Last year was a hectic year for the Bird Department, with several high
points and one or two disappointments. Among the highs was the successful
breeding of five species that had not previously been bred at the park. The
first of these was the Black-faced Ibis Theristicus melanopis, of which two
chicks were hand-reared by Jamie Graham (see Avicultural Magazine
Vol.108, No.2, pp. 110-112 (2002)), who also hand-reared four Demoiselle
Cranes Anthropoides virgo, though unfortunately despite all our research
and efforts only one survived. We did, however, learn much from the
experience and will be better prepared this year. Jamie also hand-reared our
first Red-crested Turaco Tauraco erythrolophus .
As described earlier (pp. 9-11), after several years of trying we were
finally successful with our Wonga Pigeons Leucosarcia melanoleuca,
eventually raising six chicks, three of which were reared by Barbary Doves
Streptopelia risoria dom., two were parent reared and one, ('Willy Wonga')
was reared by my own fair hands. The fifth species to be bred here for the
first time was the Red-winged Starling Onychognathus mono, again a species
kept at the park for many years. In this instance, we were forced to remove
two chicks from the nest after the female attacked and killed the male. Nathan
Crockford used an enormous number of crickets to rear the chicks. We
have since obtained another nine Red-winged Starlings and are studying the
group in the hope that the birds may remain together and become a breeding
colony.
We bred two Humboldt Penguins Spheniscus humboldti and two White
Storks Ciconia ciconia; our Black Storks C. nigra laid two fertile eggs but
disappointingly, these failed to hatch. All our four species of ibis bred:
Scarlet Eudocimus ruber , Waldrapp Geronticus eremita , Sacred Threskiornis
aethiopicus and the aforementioned Black-faced. Other species we were
successful with included Chilean Flamingo Phoenicopterus chilensis (5),
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.7959357">
Eyton's Tree Duck Dendrocygna eytoni , Ringed Teal Callonetta leucophiys,
Lesser Magellan Goose Chloephaga picta, European Eider Somateria
mollis sima, Striated Caracara Phalcoboenus australis , Vietnamese Pheasant
Lophura hatinhensis, Green Imperial Pigeon Ducula aenea, Red Turtle Dove
S. tranquebarica and Crested Pigeon Ocyphaps lophotes. The last species
produced a stunning total of 10 young. Violaceous Turaco Musophaga
violacea and White-cheeked Turaco Tauraco leucotis (our female is 28 and
still going strong) bred, as did Burrowing Owl Athene cunicularia , White-
faced Scops Owl Otus leucotis , Spectacled Owl Pulsatrix perspicillata and
Great Grey Owl Strix nebulosa lapponica , though unfortunately in the case
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.180534" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500698" page_num="39" year="" vol="">
PEAT - COTSWOLD WILDLIFE PARK REVIEW OF 2002
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998514" page_id="56500698"  page_num="39" year="" vol="">
39
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.993023861111111" page_id="56500698"  page_num="39" year="" vol="">
of the latter, the two chicks did not survive. We also bred Speckled Mousebird
Colius striatus , Olive Thrash Turdus olivaceus , Blue-winged Minla Minla
cyanouroptera and Black-headed Weaver Ploceus cucullatus bohndorffi.
In all a total of 81 birds of 29 species were bred.
There were also several new additions to the collection, including six
Little Egrets Egretta garzetta , which have been placed in our large Stork
Aviary. Other additions include a pair of Spix's Guan Penelope jacquacu , a
group of White-shouldered Starlings Sturnus sinensis , Citron-crested
Cockatoos Cacatua sulphured citrinocristata and a pair of Blue Magpies
Urocissa erythrorhyncha. We also obtained two Blue and Yellow Macaws
Am ararauna and two Scarlet Macaws A . macao, which are housed on our
new Macaw Island and are being trained by Senior Keeper Darren Fellowes
for educational parrot displays. Darren's enthusiasm to educate the public
about the plight of parrots is highly commendable, and I am sure that the
displays will be a big success.
Work also started on relocating the pheasant aviaries. Built shortly after
the park opened in 1970 this row of aviaries is now in a state of disrepair.
Although wonderful aviaries in their time they were somewhat out of the
way and even on busy days only a handful of visitors would wander down
to see them. Much thought went into ways to improve the existing site, but
it was decided that moving the aviaries into the heart of the park would
provoke more interest. A wooded area behind the large Stork Aviary provided
the inspiration for a themed area through which visitors will be able to walk.
In the summer the foliage of the trees lets in dappled light which along with
the bird song gives the area a relaxing atmosphere. It will be left as natural
as possible, with a walk-way and aviaries scattered about the area, which
will be enclosed within a perimeter fence that will also allow us to have a
few free-range pheasants roaming amongst the public.
This year we would love to breed Great Hombills Buceros bicornis again.
The present female arrived in 2001 following the death of our old female,
which was a parent of the first of these hombills bred in the UK (which is
now paired-up at Chester Zoo). The new female spent 2002 bonding with
our male, and the signs are looking good. We also hope to breed our Black
Storks again, and have better luck with our Demoiselle Cranes. I am sure
that whatever happens it will be another season of challenges, hard work
and lots of excitement, after all is that not what being a bird keeper is all
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.82519275">
about?
Louise Peat is a keeper at the Cotswold Wildlife Park, Burford, Oxon.
0X18 4JW, UK. Tel:01993 823006/ Fax:01993 823807/ Website:
www. cotswoldwi Idlifepark. co.uk
</reference>
<page confidence="0.984155" page_id="56500699"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
40
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.572316" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500699" page_num="40" year="" vol="">
PRESIDENT'S GARDEN PARTY 2002
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.957052529411765" page_id="56500699"  page_num="40" year="" vol="">
by Nigel Hewston
On Sunday, July 14th over 100 members and guests gathered in glorious
sunshine at Chestnut Lodge, the home of our President Ruth Ezra and Vice
President Raymond Sawyer.
The gardens as always looked wonderful with their sweeping lawns,
magnificent mature trees and interesting borders. In particular the many
hemerocallis in full bloom made a brilliant display and a recently planted
scree garden added fascinating detail.
The giant tortoises shone in the sun and took a shine to some of the
visitors - particularly those with handbags - while the white wallabies
watched warily from their basking area. Can Koi possibly grow bigger than
this?
Among the birds themselves there were as usual old favourites and new
delights. Red-billed Choughs were present in some numbers having bred
well in recent years, and there were waders in variety: stilts, avocets, ja#anas
and at least four species of plover, though early broods of waders had been
lost in poor weather. A colony of 20 Carmine Bee-eaters made a spectacular
show in the waterfall aviary and no doubt give rise to a spectacular bill for
mealworms, which they are adept at catching on the wing.
Spangled Cotingas still graced the tropical house but had made no further
nesting attempts since the previous year. The small covered aviaries housed
a wide variety of smaller gems including Golden Bush Robins and Large
Niltavas, and were also home to a pair of Pompadour Cotingas. New to me
were some impressive south-east Asian woodpeckers, which I think were
the Greater Yellownape and the Checker-throated Woodpecker.
There are always so many rare and beautiful birds at Chestnut Lodge
that many which would be noteworthy elsewhere escape mention here, not
only in the aviaries but among the waterfowl, cranes and flamingos which
roam the grounds.
Members and their guests enjoyed a splendid tea and the superb weather
made it easy to linger and exchange avicultural news and views. The event
raised a record #800 (approx. US$1,280) which was generously donated by
our hosts to the society. This year's garden party will be held in July. Details
are included with this magazine.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998296" page_id="56500700"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
41
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.466311666666667" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500700" page_num="41" year="" vol="">
A BRIEF NOTE ON THE FEEDING BEHAVIOUR OF TWO
Agapomis SPECIES
by Luigi Racheli
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999489866666667" page_id="56500700"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
Studies on the behaviour in captivity of species of the Afrotropical genus
Agapornis have been extensively conducted by Dilger (1960, 1962). Nine
species are currently recognised within this genus (e.g. Juniper &amp; Parr, 1998).
Both Moreau (1948) and Dilger (1960) stressed the close relationship
between the Black-winged Lovebird A. taranta and the Red-faced Lovebird
A. pullarius. More recently, phylogenetic analyses of the genus Agapornis
confirmed this hypothesis (Eberhard, 1998; Racheli, 1999). Here I describe
preliminary observations on an unusual shared behaviour by these two
species, briefly described elsewhere (Racheli, 2002).
During the past five years, we have had the opportunity to study several
pairs of captive-bred Black-winged Lovebirds and wild-caught Red-faced
Lovebirds. A wide range of vegetables and fruits were offered to both species.
When a vegetable is swaying on an unstable support, both species use their
feet to grasp it and then to feed on it. Although the use of feet when feeding
is common in medium and large parrots, it was not previously recorded for
Agapornis species. Furthermore, it has been noticed that Black-winged
Lovebirds bite off a small piece of chicory and hold it firmly between the
foot and the perch. Only when this small piece of food is firmly held, do
they feed&amp;apos;on it.
Other Agapornis species (except perhaps A. swindernianus which is not
available in captivity and has not been studied) use their feet but not for
feeding behaviour. For example, the species of the 'eye-ringed group' (A.
fischeri, A. personatus, A, lilianae and A, nigrigenis ) use their feet in order
to obtain materials for nest construction. This behaviour does not seem so
well developed though and often the material is lost before the bird goes
back to the nest.
Although the unusual shared behaviour described above has been
observed only in captivity, it further corroborates the close relationship
between these two species. It would be of interest should this evolutionary
trait be confirmed in the field.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.924406" genericHeader="references" page_id="56500700" page_num="41" year="" vol="">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.776350666666667" page_id="56500700"  page_num="41" year="" vol="">
Dilger, W. C. 1960. The comparative ethology of the African parrot genus Agapornis. Zeitschrift
fur Tierpsychologie 17: 649-685.
Dilger, W. C. 1962. The behaviour of Lovebirds. Scientific American 206: 88-98.
Eberhard, J. R. 1998. Evolution of nest-building behaviour in Agapornis parrots. The Auk
115,2:455-464.
Juniper, 1 T.&amp; Parr, M. 1998. Parrots - A guide to the Parrots of the World. Pica Press, Sussex.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.999296" page_id="56500701"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
42
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.908255" page_id="56500701"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
Moreau, R. E. 1948. Aspects of evolution in the parrot genus Agapornis. Ibis 90: 206-239 &amp;
449-490.
Racheli, L. 1999. A cladistic analysis of the African genus Agapornis. Papageienkunde 3,1:9-
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.441511" page_id="56500701"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
19.
</page>
<construct confidence="0.43285625" page_id="56500701"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
Racheli, L. 2002. Uso delle zampe per fini alimentari in due specie del genere Agapornis.
Uccelli 41, 12:44.
Luigi Racheli, Via G. Valmarana 66, 1-00139 Rome, Italy or E-mail:
racheli@tiscalinet.it
</construct>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8650815" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500701" page_num="42" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
MOST NOTEWORTHY BREEDING
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985505" page_id="56500701"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
The most noteworthy breeding during 2002 at San Diego Zoo was the
hatching of a Fawn-breasted Bowerbird Chlamydera ceiwiniventris, a species
that had never previously been bred in North America.
Other species bred during 2002 at San Diego Zoo and San Diego Wild
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.896118363636364" page_id="56500701"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
Animal Park included Kori Bustard Ardeotis kori , Secretary Bird Sagittarius
serpentarius, Crowned Eagle Stephanoaetus coronatus , Indian Cotton Teal
or Pygmy Goose Nettapus coromandelianus, Hyacinth Macaw
Anodorhynchus hyacinthinus, Pesquet's Parrot Psittrichas fulgidus, Great
Hombill Buceros bicornis and Long-tailed Broadbill Psarisomus dalhousiae.
* * *
BIRDS OF PARADISE AND PARROTS IN THE DESERT
Writing in International Zoo News Vol. 49/8 (No. 321), pp. 482-486
about His Excellency Sheikh Saoud Bin Mohammed Bin Ali A1 Thani's
private facility, A1 Wabra Wildlife Preservation, in Qatar, Catrin and Sven
Hammer provide a full list of the species kept there. The birds include Greater
</table>
<reference confidence="0.689114625">
Paradisaea apoda. Lesser P. minor , Red P. rubra , King Cicinnurus regius.
Magnificent C. magnificus and Twelve-wired Bird of Paradise Seleucidis
melanoleuca. Flamed Bowerbird Sericulus aureus ardens , Bulwer's Pheasant
Lophura bulweri , Red-tailed Cockatoo Calyptorhynchus hanksii. Yellow-
tailed Cockatoo C.funereus , Blue-headed Macaw Am couloni , Blue-throated
Macaw A. glaucogularis, Hyacinth Macaw Anodorhynchus hyacinthinus ,
Spix's Macaw Cyanopsitta spixii , Pesquet's Parrot Psittrichas fulgidus and
Long-wattled Umbrellabird Cephalopterus penduliger.
</reference>
<bodyText confidence="0.822663" page_id="56500701"  page_num="42" year="" vol="">
Some of the birds, such as birds of paradise, macaws, cockatoos,
umbrellabirds and pheasants, are housed in huge aviaries with air-conditioned
indoor rooms and computer-controlled irrigation systems, connected to a
freshwater osmosis unit. A large walk-through free-flight aviary (75m x
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.700155" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500702" page_num="43" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.999799" page_id="56500702"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
43
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9922" page_id="56500702"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
30m x 7m (approx. 246ft x 98ft x 23ft)), with a rainforest-like atmosphere,
has recently been completed. It accommodates male birds of paradise,
starlings, pheasant pigeons, turacos and cranes. Another is under
construction, in which it is planned to keep flamingos, Scarlet Ibis Eudocimus
ruber and macaws.
The four species listed as having been bred there so far are, Greater and
King Bird of Paradise, Green-naped Pheasant Pigeon Otidiphaps n . nobilis
and Chestnut-bellied Sandgrouse Pterocles exustus ellioti. In the important,
but still young, collection of parrots, the first pairs had just started to lay.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.83965" page_id="56500702"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.796755" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56500702" page_num="43" year="" vol="">
SAVING SUMATRA'S RAINFOREST
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.989272095238095" page_id="56500702"  page_num="43" year="" vol="">
BirdLife International is appealing for help to save the lowland rainforests
of Indonesia, home to birds such as the Rufous-collared Kingfisher Halcyon
concreta. Rhinoceros Hombill Buceros rhinoceros , Critically Endangered
Sumatran Ground-cuckoo Carpococcyx viridis and Endangered Storm's
Stork Ciconia stormi. Logging, much of it illegal, is destroying Indonesia's
rainforests at the rate of almost 2 million hectares (something like 5 million
acres) per year. Over 15 million hectares (38 million acres) were logged
between 1985 and 1997, an area equal in size to England and Wales. Much
of the timber is pulped and used to make paper and the land is then used for
oil palm plantations.
Indonesia has 117 globally threatened bird species, more than any other
country. The crisis is most severe on Sumatra, where 90 species are listed
as globally threatened or near threatened - three times more than in 1994.
Unless action is taken now, virtually all of Sumatra's lowland rainforest
could be logged-out by 2005.
BirdLife International wants to secure the lease on a large intact area
containing lowland rainforest and has identified on Sumatra, a 61,000 hectare
(roughly 150,000 acre) logging concession of mainly secondary rainforest,
with some primary rainforest remaining. One of the last remaining pieces
of lowland rainforest on the island, it is known to be home to many threatened
bird species and more are expected to be found by a survey currently being
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.914946142857143">
conducted by BirdLife International. It also supports an important population
of Sumatran Tiger Panthera tigris sumatrae, estimated at 15-20 individuals,
Malayan Tapir Tapirus indicus. Sun Bear Helarctos malayanus, Agile Gibbon
Hylobates agilis and Siamang H. syndactylus.
Donations can be sent to: Sumatra Appeal, BirdLife International,
Wellbrook Court, Girton Road, Cambridge CB3 ONA, UK. Tel: +44 (0)1223
279853/Website:www.birdlife.org/sumatra.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.997861" page_id="56500703"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
44
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.980811" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500703" page_num="44" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
HELP FOR THE ST VINCENT PARROT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.990477738095238" page_id="56500703"  page_num="44" year="" vol="">
Last year, with the support of several international organisations, St
Vincent Forestry Department took a number of positive steps towards the
conservation of the St Vincent Parrot Amazona guildingii -- the national
bird of St Vincent &amp; the Grenadines. In support of these conservation
initiatives, Roger Sweeney, Associate Director, Graeme Hall Nature
Sanctuary, Worthing, Christ Church, Barbados, made several visits to St
Vincent on behalf of the sanctuary, with partial funding of his travel expenses
provided by the Loro Parque Fundacion.
The year began with major structural renovation work being carried out
at the Calvin Nicholls Wildlife Complex, where a large captive population
of St Vincent Parrots is housed. The first major renovation since the initial
construction over 16 years ago, it has significantly improved the physical
environment of the captive population. Funding for this work was provided
by the Graeme Hall Nature Sanctuary and Zoologische Gesellschaft fuer
Arten-und Populationsschutz e. V. (ZGAP) in Germany.
At the same time as the work was being carried out, the Forestry
Department was preparing to undertake the latest census of the wild
population. This was made possible thanks to the World Parrot Trust (WPT)
which donated field equipment worth approximately US$1,500 (#950). The
census was completed during the months March - April and suggested that
the wild population numbers about 550 birds and therefore remains stable,
though there is some concern about the distribution of the population and
patterns of disturbance to its primary habitat across its range.
Following the completion of the renovation work to the Calvin Nicholls
Wildlife Complex, the next area of husbandry that was identified for review
was the diet of the captive population. The captive birds had been receiving
a diet mainly of fruits and vegetables, supplemented with crushed calcium
carbonate tablets and poultry pellets. It was decided it would be beneficial
to replace the poultry pellets with good quality parrot pellets and a broad
spectrum vitamin, mineral and amino acid supplement. Mark Hagen of
Rolf C. Hagen, pet food and care products, generously offered a free supply
of food products for the captive populations present on St Vincent and
Barbados. The three products being supplied on an on-going basis are:
Tropican - pellet diet for parrots.
Tropi-mix -- a low fat diet made from the above pellets, dried fruits and
low fat cereals, etc. for obesity-prone parrots.
Prime -- vitamin, mineral and amino acid supplement powder.
All interested parties involved with the conservation management of the
St Vincent Parrot were consulted to ensure that there was general agreement
that these products are suitable and will be of benefit to the birds. The costs
of shipping them to the West Indies will be borne by the Graeme Hall Nature
Sanctuary.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.70009" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500704" page_num="45" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.997314" page_id="56500704"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
45
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.988026382352941" page_id="56500704"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
There was also the need to provide improved information for visitors to
the wildlife complex, which is in the National Botanical Gardens in
Kingstown. This was made possible by the Education Department of Chester
Zoo, England, which generously donated individual signs providing basic
information about the species exhibited in each enclosure. These include
the Red-footed Tortoise Geochelone carhonaria, Green Vervet Monkey
Cercopithecus aethiops pygerythrus and Agouti Dasyprocta punctata , as
well as the St Vincent Parrot and others.
A two week veterinary workshop was conducted in July by the field
veterinary programme of the Wildlife Conservation Society (WCS). Dr
Sharon Deems and Emily Ladwig, a senior keeper at Bronx Zoo, conducted
a thorough health review of all the St Vincent Parrots on the island, examining
those at the wildlife complex, as well as specimens held by private custodians.
Emily also spent a significant amount of time working with the aviary staff
and reviewed their husbandry routines and the practical implementation of
the dietary changes. The staff greatly enjoyed the opportunity to interact
with other animal care professionals and plans have been made to send some
of the staff abroad to receive additional training. At the invitation of the
Loro Parque Fundacion, the Principal Government Veterinarian, Dr
Hachshaw, is to travel to Tenerife to participate in practical training in avian
surgery techniques at the veterinary clinic there and, at the invitation of the
World Parrot Trust (WPT), some of the aviary staff will undertake training
at Paradise Park, Cornwall, England.
Later in the year some additional signs were installed. The first is a
renovated version of the old sign that describes the St Vincent Parrot and its
role, and the need to protect this species. The second is a newly
commissioned sign illustrating a wide variety of the unique forms of wildlife
found on St Vincent, with a message about the need to protect the island's
unique biodiversity. Work on both signs was funded by the Graeme Hall
Nature Sanctuary.
In the next issue of the magazine, Roger Sweeney, the author of the
above report, will describe the hand-rearing of a St Vincent Parrot and
illustrate his account with photos of the chick at one day old, 15 days old, 33
days old and aged three months.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.624796" page_id="56500704"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.882548" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors" page_id="56500704" page_num="45" year="" vol="">
HELPING SAVE HORNBILLS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.622323666666667" page_id="56500704"  page_num="45" year="" vol="">
In an attempt to dissuade indigeous people from killing hombills for
their tail feathers (see News &amp; Views Vol.108, No.l, p.47 (2002)), the first
400 hornbill feathers collected from US collections by Bronx Zoo
Ornithology Curator Christine Sheppard, have been handed over to the
District Chief of West Kutai District in East Kalimantan, Indonesia, for use
in traditional dances.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99679" page_id="56500705"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
46
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9817655" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500705" page_num="46" year="" vol="">
NEWS &amp; VIEWS
ALBINO PENGUIN
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99157725" page_id="56500705"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
What is believed to be the first albino penguin hatched in captivity,
hatched at Bristol Zoo Gardens in November 2002, and was hand-reared
there. The African Penguin Spheniscus demersus is a true albino, with a
pale coloured beak, pink eyes, pink feet and entirely white plumage.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.805642" page_id="56500705"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.877797" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500705" page_num="46" year="" vol="">
LONG LOST SPIX'S MACAW REPATRIATED
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997510277777778" page_id="56500705"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
Rumours of the existence of a Spix's Macaw Cyanopsitta spixii
somewhere in Colorado, USA, proved to be true when the bird's owner
living in a Denver suburb phoned a vet's surgery to seek advice about caring
for the bird, after its long time companion, an Amazon parrot Amazona spp.
died, and the macaw became listless.
The owner, who told authorities that the Spix's Macaw was left with her
in the late 1970s, was put in touch with the World Parrot Trust (WPT).
Director, James Gilardi, pushed for the macaw, identified as a male following
DNA tests on some feathers and a blood sample at San Diego Zoo, to be
repatriated to Brazil. Eventually arrangements were made to return it and it
was flown from Denver to Miami, where it was handed over to a Brazilian
official, who took it back to Brazil where it will join a breeding programme.
In a letter to the Editor of Cage &amp; Aviary Birds (March 22,2003), former
dealer Gordon Cooke, wrote saying he is certain that this bird is one of a
young pair he exported to Colorado in the mid-1970s. Apparently the buyer's
whole family came to England and resided in Leicester for the required 90
days which allowed the birds to be carried to the USA. Gordon Cooke
thinks the bird must now be about 28 years old.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.609807" page_id="56500705"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
* * *
</equation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.79061" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500705" page_num="46" year="" vol="">
RON OXLEY
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997535" page_id="56500705"  page_num="46" year="" vol="">
The death of Ron Oxley, aged 62, on March 8th following two brain
hemorrhages, came as a great shock. I leamt of his sudden illness on February
15th, when I tried to phone him at Cage &amp; Aviary Birds.
A first class aviculturist, Ron had kept birds most of his life. He joined
the Avicultural Society in 1960 and in 1967 became a Life Member - back
when this cost the princely sum of #25 (approx. US$40). Ron was elected
onto the council in 1980 and had remained a member of the council ever
since. In recent years Ron invariably drove his close friend, fellow Council
Member, the late Bob Grantham, to council and social meetings and pushed
him around in a wheelchair, when Bob was no longer able to walk.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.75646" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500706" page_num="47" year="" vol="">
RON OXLEY
</sectionHeader>
<page confidence="0.998561" page_id="56500706"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
47
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.932733176470588" page_id="56500706"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
Ron kept a varied selection of birds, specialising in his early days in
softbills and nectar feeders. At one time he kept a quetzal and in recent
years kept birds such as peacock pheasants, Red-winged Starlings and Black-
naped Fruit Doves, and bred the last three. In 1975, he succeeded in breeding
the Chinese Bulbul (see Avicultural Magazine Vol. 82. No.3, pp. 124-126
(1976)), but does not appear to have been awarded the society's medal.
Bryan Peck was also successful with this species that year and this may be
the reason why.
Ron had been a top showman, whose birds were always meticulously
staged in large clean cages. He, in partnership with his first wife Linda, in
1973 at the National Exhibition of Cage and Aviary Birds, then staged at
Alexandra Palace, won the award for the Best Foreign. The bird, a Spangled
Tanager, went on to be judged Best in Show, the only occasion a tanager has
won this award at the UK's top show. Ron was also an excellent judge, who
used to be very much in demand. On numerous occasions he judged at the
National Exhibition and was selected as a judge to place the Supreme Award
for Best in Show.
Ron joined the Foreign Bird League in 1956 and last year was made an
Hon. Life Member. He was one of the last remaining founder members of
the Southern Foreign Bird Club. In 1984, Ron was elected Chairman of the
Foreign Bird Federation, a position he held for nearly a decade. Later he
was FBF Breeding Registrar and was responsible for collating the FBF
Breeding Register. Ron was also an active member of the International
Touraco Society.
He started his working life as a compositor in the print trade but, when
he became redundant, made the transition to journalism. He joined the
editorial staff of the UK weekly magazine Cage &amp; Aviary Birds , where his
knowledge of birdkeeping and contacts with individual birdkeepers and
avicultural organisations quickly made him an indispensable member of
staff. At the time of his death, Ron was Assistant Editor.
Universally liked and described as a "nice person" and a first rate
aviculturist, Ron will be greatly missed by his many friends and colleagues,
and the large silent majority of aviculturists.
Our deepest sympathy go to his widow, Shirley, and family.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.757439" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500706" page_num="47" year="" vol="">
Stewart Pyper
AVICULTURAL MAGAZINES BACK ISSUES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.943202333333333" page_id="56500706"  page_num="47" year="" vol="">
A large stock is available including some early issues. Further details
are available from: The Membership Secretary, Stewart Pyper, 21, Primrose
Hill, Nunney, Frome, Somerset BA11 4NP, UK. Tel: 01373 836293
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997586" page_id="56500707"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
48
</page>
<table confidence="0.986232033333333" page_id="56500707"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
Straights
Aniseed #5.50 kg
Brown Perilla #2.50 kg #11.50 5kg
Black Lettuce #5.50 kg #12.00 2.5kg
Blue Maw #2.50 kg #11.50 5kg
Buckwheat #1.50 kg #4.95 5kg
Chicory Seed #3.50 kg #15.00 5kg
Chillies #2.50 500g
Evening Primrose #5.50 kg
Fonio Paddy #6.95 500g #13.00 kg
Fresh Water Shrimps #5.00 500g #9.50 kg
German Thistle #4.50 kg #8.50 2.5kg
Groats #1.50 kg #5.00 5kg
Juniper Berries #4.00 500g#15 2.5kg
M. Sprays Chinese #3 kg #14.00 5kg
M. Sprays French #3.50 kg #16.00 5kg
Mountain Ash #3.25 500g #12.50 2.5kg
Mung Beans #2.00 kg #8.00 5kg
Niger Seed #2.50 kg #9.50 5kg
Paddy Rice #1.50 kg #4.95 5kg
Pine Seed Medium #3.50 500g
Plantain #4.00 500g #8.00 kg
Safflower #1.50 kg #4.95 5kg
Seasame Seed #2.50 kg #10.00 5kg
Sunflower Striped #1.95 kg #6.00 5kg
Sunflower Kemals #2.95 kg #10.00 5kg
Teasel Seed #4.50 500g #9.00 kg
White Lettuce Seed #6.95 kg
White Perilla Seed #3.00 kg #13.50 5kg
Whole Rosehips #2.50 500g #5.00 kg
</table>
<figure confidence="0.88066135" page_id="56500707"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
Vitamins &amp; Minerals
Sunbird Nectars
Livefoods
Soak Mixes
Nuts
Eggfoods
Softbill Diets
Straights
Seed Mixtures
Parrot Mixes
Frozen Foods
Lorikeet Nectars
Supplements
Handrearing
Formulas
Mynah Pellets
Dried Fruits
Berries
Moist Eggfood
WITTE MOLEN Eggfood is a
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.662921">
complimentary food enjoyed by all seed-
eating birds. This food contains the
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.875566888888889" page_id="56500707"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
correct amount of vitamins, minerals and
the essential amino and fatty acids to keep
your birds in good health.
Witte Molen Eggfood is composed of
light digestable egg products, bakery
products and various seeds. This food is
made from the highest quality products to
ensure your birds are maintained at their
optimal standard.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.47413475" page_id="56500707"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
5kg Tub #16.95 2 Tubs 10kg #28.50
25kg Sack #39.95 Prices include Delivery
Softfood With Fruit
WITTE MOLEN Softfood with fruit is a
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.982601916666667" page_id="56500707"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
complete food for insectivorous and fruit
eating birds such as thrushes, blackbirds,
starlings, turacos, toucans, green magpies,
birds of paradise and jays. This ideal,
balanced diet has a uniquely low iron
content of less than 70ppm. It contains
the right proportion of proteins, vitamins,
minerals and all the essential amino acids
and fatty acids. This food is enriched
with berries and pieces of papaya,
pineapple, figs and apricots. It also
contains honey, brewers yeast and vitamin C.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.431490142857143" page_id="56500707"  page_num="48" year="" vol="">
5kg Tub # 19.95 2 Tubs 10 kg #34.95
25kg Sack #53.95 Prices include Delivery
P&amp;P only #4.95 up to 45kg unless included in price (for most postcodes). Rob Harvey Specialist
Feeds, Kookaburra House, Gravel Hill Road, Holt Pound, Famham, Surrey, GU10 4LG.
Tel: 01420 23986 Fax: 01420 23078 E-mail: rob@robharvey.com
Website: www:robharvey.com
Sole UK agent for Witte Molen &amp; Avi-Plus All major CC taken
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996083" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500708" page_num="" year="" vol="">
WORLD'S MOST SUCCESSFUL RELEASE PROJECT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9438143125" page_id="56500708"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
During the 2002 breeding season, 16 captive pairs of San Clemente
Loggerhead Shrikes Lanius ludovicianus mearnsi produced 55 young, 11
of which were hand-reared, while the remaining 44 were raised by their
parents. Of the 55, 39 were later released onto this fog-shrouded island
about 50 miles (80km) off the coast of San Diego, California. It was part of
the cooperative effort by the Zoological Society of San Diego, US Navy,
PRBO Conservation Science and the Institute for Wildlife Studies (IWS) to
save this shrike from extinction.
In 1991, fewer than 20 remained in the wild. Thankfully, the population
has increased dramatically since 1999, when the present release effort began.
Since the beginning of that breeding season, when just 19 remained in the
wild, 122 chicks have been successfully hand-reared in the zoological
society's captive-rearing facility on the island and 184 have been raised by
the shrikes themselves. By the end of2002 there were more than 80 breeding
birds, two-thirds of them captive-bred.
fYenYen\
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.5038155" genericHeader="method" page_id="56500708" page_num="" year="" vol="">
Ackroyd's Australian Avitours
RAY ACKROYD&amp;apos;S AUSTRALIAN BIRDWATCHING AND NATURALHISTORYTOURS
</sectionHeader>
<footnote confidence="0.974175833333333">
* We offer adventure tours of the highest standard led by Ray Ackroyd a knowledgeable
and enthusiastic bush guide with 50 years outback experience.
* Our tours are well priced and we travel with small groups for that exclusive personalised
service that is so hard to find in today's tourist industry.
* Everybody has a window seat and our accommodation is modern and spacious.
* So come down and discover Australia's unique fauna and flora, the tour of a life time:
</footnote>
<reference confidence="0.535324666666667">
Cockatoos, Parrots, Reptiles, Waterfowl, Kangaroos, Koalas, Wildflowers, Landscapes.
Many overseas aviculturists have travelled with us to date, all completely satisfied.
So please join Ray and our Hostess Beryl on the Australian Outback Tour of a Lifetime.
Enquiries for itineraries:
Ray Ackroyd's Australian Avitours, PO Box 44, Bringelly N.S.W., Australia.
Tel: 0247 748471 Email: cockatoosgalore@hotmail.com Fax: 029 8261639
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.987891" genericHeader="abstract" page_id="56500709" page_num="" year="" vol="">
CONTENTS
SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION LIBRARIES
</sectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.970230521739131" page_id="56500709"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
3 9088 01769 6493
Management of bustards in captivity
by Tom Bailey and Sara Hallager.1
Wonga success
by Louise Peat...9
Breeding the Chestnut-tailed Minla Minla strigula
by Neil Owen.12
Breeding and hand-rearing the Blue-winged Leafbird Chloropsis
cochinchinensis at the Riverbanks Zoo and Garden
by Angela Hardy.14
Breeding the Hoopoe Upupa epops at Disney's Animal Kingdom
by Paul Schutz.22
The Festive Amazon Amazonafestiva festiva in the wild and in
captivity
by Lars Lepperhoff. 29
Cotswold Wildlife Park Review of 2002
by Louise Peat.38
President's Garden Party 2002
by Nigel Hewston.40
A brief note on the feeding behaviour of two Agapornis species
by Luigi Racheli. 41
News &amp; Views.42
Obituary - Ron Oxley
</table>
<page confidence="0.810103" page_id="56500709"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
46
</page>
<figure confidence="0.6028875" page_id="56500709"  page_num="" year="" vol="">
Published by the Avicultural Society, England.
Produced by Data Publishing Service, Cheddar.
</figure>
</algorithms>
